[
  {
    "id": "4sIot5QGUtwc9g6c",
    "question": "During dehydration of alcohols to alkenes by heating with conc. H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> the initiation step is",
    "options": [
      "formation of carbocation",
      "elimination of water",
      "formation of an ester",
      "protonation of alcohol molecule"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "protonation of alcohol molecule"
  },
  {
    "id": "wD7xPfbcf8ctAFRK",
    "question": "Acetyl bromide reacts with excess of CH<sub>3</sub>MgI followed by treatment with a saturated solution\nof NH<sub>4</sub>Cl given ",
    "options": [
      "acetone",
      "acetyl iodide ",
      "2- methyl -2- propanol ",
      "acetamide "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "2- methyl -2- propanol "
  },
  {
    "id": "2nHqBAvmBhJ6Guml",
    "question": "Acid catalyzed hydration of alkenes except ethene leads to the formation of ",
    "options": [
      "primary alcohol ",
      "secondary or tertiary alcohol ",
      "mixture of primary and secondary alcohols ",
      "mixture of secondary and tertiary alcohols "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "mixture of secondary and tertiary alcohols "
  },
  {
    "id": "M7I9T2V8qoOi1qGw",
    "question": "The best reagent to convert pent -3- en-2-ol into pent -3-en-2-one is",
    "options": [
      "Acidic permanganate",
      "Acidic dichromate",
      "Chromic anhydride in glacial acetic acid ",
      "Pyridinium chloro – chromate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "Pyridinium chloro – chromate"
  },
  {
    "id": "TI4fYt2BBabwcPlc",
    "question": "In the following sequence of reactions, <br/>\nCH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OH $$\\buildrel {P + {I_2}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ A $$\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{ether}^{Mg}} $$ B $$\\buildrel {HCHO} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ C $$\\buildrel {{H_2}O} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ D<br/>\nthe compound ‘D’ is ",
    "options": [
      "butanal",
      "n-butyl alcohol ",
      "n-propyl alcohol ",
      "propanal "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "n-propyl alcohol "
  },
  {
    "id": "F20jceMYLocIsmNj",
    "question": "From amongst the following alcohols the one that would react fastest with conc. HCl and anhydrous\nZnCl<sub>2</sub>, is",
    "options": [
      "2–Butanol",
      "2–Methylpropan–2–ol",
      "2–Methylpropanol",
      "1–Butanol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "2–Methylpropan–2–ol"
  },
  {
    "id": "OF4fQ69S9QNL7Qbo",
    "question": "An unknown alcohol is treated with the “Lucas reagent” to determine whether the alcohol is primary,\nsecondary or tertiary. Which alcohol reacts fastest and by what mechanism: ",
    "options": [
      "tertiary alcohol by S<sub>N</sub>1",
      "secondary alcohol by S<sub>N</sub>2",
      "tertiary alcohol by S<sub>N</sub>2",
      "secondary alcohol by S<sub>N</sub>1 "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "tertiary alcohol by S<sub>N</sub>1"
  },
  {
    "id": "jIFtaNeZrGrvSnIr",
    "question": "The most suitable reagent for the conversion of R - CH<sub>2</sub> - OH $$\\to$$ R - CHO is:",
    "options": [
      "CrO<sub>3</sub>",
      "PCC (Pyridinium Chlorochromate)",
      "KMnO<sub>4</sub>",
      "K<sub>2</sub>Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "PCC (Pyridinium Chlorochromate)"
  },
  {
    "id": "tdjhEQYgwwe1qxvNtV9Ih",
    "question": "The gas evolved on heating CH<sub>3</sub>MgBr in methanol is :",
    "options": [
      "HBr",
      "Methane",
      "Ethane",
      "Propane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "Methane"
  },
  {
    "id": "0xVdcFmwK7EJXT4nkWYJI",
    "question": "Bouveault-Blanc reduction reaction involves :",
    "options": [
      "Reduction of an acyl halide with  H<sub>2</sub>/Pd.",
      "Reduction of an ester with Na/C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH.",
      "Reduction of a carbonyl compound with Na/Hg and HCl.",
      "Reduction of an anhydride with LiAlH<sub>4</sub>."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "Reduction of an ester with Na/C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH."
  },
  {
    "id": "0T30OIGXiLWPby3zBj4re",
    "question": "The major product of the following reaction is :<br/>\n$${\\rm{C}}{{\\rm{H}}_3}{\\rm{CH =  CHC}}{{\\rm{O}}_2}{\\rm{CH_3 }}\\buildrel {LiAl{H_4}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CHO",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH = CHCH<sub>2</sub>OH",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>CH = CHCH<sub>2</sub>OH"
  },
  {
    "id": "3S1G0WJPmCpX2z10Ng1klurc923",
    "question": "Ceric ammonium nitrate and CHCl<sub>3</sub>/alc. KOH are used for the identification of functional groups present in __________ and _______ respectively.",
    "options": [
      "amine, alcohol",
      "alcohol, phenol",
      "alcohol, amine",
      "amine, phenol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "alcohol, amine"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq60bl7",
    "question": "In the given reaction \n<br/><br/>3-Bromo-2, 2-dimethyl butane $$\\buildrel {{C_2}{H_5}OH} \\over\n \\longrightarrow \\mathop {'A'}\\limits_{(Major\\,\\Pr oduct)} $$ <br/><br/>Product A is :",
    "options": [
      "2-Ethoxy-3, 3-dimethyl butane",
      "1-Ethoxy-3, 3-dimethyl butane",
      "2-Ethoxy-2, 3-dimethyl butane",
      "2-Hydroxy-3, 3-dimethyl butane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "2-Ethoxy-2, 3-dimethyl butane"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktiauoy6",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R). <br/><br/>Assertion (A) : Treatment of bromine water with propene yields 1-bromopropan-2-ol.<br/><br/>Reason (R) : Attack of water on bromonium ion follows Markovnikov rule and results in 1-bromopropan-2-ol.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bdivfj",
    "question": "<p>Hex-4-ene-2-ol on treatment with PCC gives 'A'. 'A' on reaction with sodium hypoiodite gives 'B', which on further heating with soda lime gives 'C'. The compound 'C' is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2-pentene",
      "proponaldehyde",
      "2-butene",
      "4-methylpent-2-ene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "2-butene"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6e1u9l1",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : On heating with $$\\mathrm{KHSO}_{4}$$, glycerol is dehydrated and acrolein is formed.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Acrolein has fruity odour and can be used to test glycerol's presence.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct option.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rkwll0",
    "question": "<p>When ethanol is heated with conc. $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$$, a gas is produced. The compound formed, when this gas is treated with cold dilute aqueous solution of Baeyer's reagent, is</p>",
    "options": [
      "formaldehyde",
      "formic acid",
      "glycol",
      "ethanoic acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "glycol"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsc9ica",
    "question": "<p>A solution of $$\\mathrm{Cr O_5}$$ in amyl alcohol has a __________ colour.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Yellow",
      "Orange-Red",
      "Green",
      "Blue"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "Blue"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvurueq",
    "question": "<p>Incorrect method of preparation for alcohols from the following is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Hydroboration-oxidation of alkene.",
      "Reaction of Ketone with $$\\mathrm{RMgBr}$$ followed by hydrolysis.",
      "Ozonolysis of alkene.",
      "Reaction of alkyl halide with aqueous $$\\mathrm{NaOH}$$."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "Ozonolysis of alkene."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh02rkk8",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A: Butan -1- ol has higher boiling point than ethoxyethane.</p>\n<p>Reason R: Extensive hydrogen bonding leads to stronger association of molecules.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true but R is not the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh03g9az",
    "question": "<p>The water gas on reacting with cobalt as a catalyst forms</p>",
    "options": [
      "Methanoic acid",
      "Methanol",
      "Methanal",
      "Ethanol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "Methanol"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7anlk",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R:</p>\n<p>Assertion A: Alcohols react both as nucleophiles and electrophiles.</p>\n<p>Reason R: Alcohols react with active metals such as sodium, potassium and aluminum to yield corresponding alkoxides and liberate hydrogen.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$A$$ is false but $$R$$ is true.\n",
      "Both $$A$$ and $$R$$ are true but $$R$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$A$$.\n",
      "Both $$A$$ and $$R$$ are true and $$R$$ is the correct explanation of $$A$$.\n",
      "$$A$$ is true but $$R$$ is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-alcohols",
    "solution": "Both $$A$$ and $$R$$ are true but $$R$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$A$$.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "rKpvjN3h9RhkMatE",
    "question": "An ethar is more volatile than an alcohol having the same molecular formula. This is due to",
    "options": [
      "alcohols having resonance structures",
      "inter-molecular hydrogen bonding in ethers",
      "inter-molecular hydrogen bonding in alcohols",
      "dipole characters of ethers"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-ethers",
    "solution": "inter-molecular hydrogen bonding in alcohols"
  },
  {
    "id": "plPnh9m4gar6Qxf5",
    "question": "HBr reacts with CH<sub>2</sub> = CH – OCH<sub>3</sub> under anhydrous conditions at room temperature to give ",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CHO and CH<sub>3</sub>Br ",
      "BrCH<sub>2</sub>CHO and CH<sub>3</sub>OH",
      "BrCH<sub>2</sub> – CH<sub>2</sub> – OCH<sub>3</sub> ",
      "H<sub>3</sub>C – CHBr – OCH<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-ethers",
    "solution": "H<sub>3</sub>C – CHBr – OCH<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kteci83s",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R). <br/><br/>Assertion (A) : Synthesis of ethyl phenyl ether may be achieved by Williamson synthesis.<br/><br/>Reason (R) : Reaction of bromobenzene with sodium ethoxide yields ethyl phenyl ether.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-ethers",
    "solution": "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq4gt4t",
    "question": "<p>2-Methyl propyl bromide reacts with $$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{H}_{5} \\mathrm{O}^{-}$$ and gives 'A' whereas on reaction with $$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{H}_{5} \\mathrm{OH}$$ it gives 'B'. The mechanism followed in these reactions and the products 'A' and 'B' respectively are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{S}_{N} 1, A=$$ tert-butyl ethyl ether; $$\\mathrm{S}_{N} 2, B=$$ iso-butyl ethyl ether",
      "$$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 1, \\mathrm{~A}=$$ tert-butyl ethyl ether; $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 1, \\mathrm{~B}=$$ 2-butyl ethyl ether",
      "$$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2, \\mathrm{~A}=$$ iso-butyl ethyl ether; $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 1, \\mathrm{~B}=$$ tert-butyl ethyl ether",
      "$$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2, \\mathrm{~A}=$$ 2-butyl ethyl ether; $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2, \\mathrm{~B}=$$ iso-butyl ethyl ether"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-ethers",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2, \\mathrm{~A}=$$ iso-butyl ethyl ether; $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 1, \\mathrm{~B}=$$ tert-butyl ethyl ether"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyh8qi0",
    "question": "<p>Suitable reaction condition for preparation of Methyl phenyl ether is</p>",
    "options": [
      "Benzene, MeBr",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ph{O^\\Theta }N{a^ \\oplus }}$$, MeBr",
      "Ph - Br, $$\\mathrm{Me{O^\\Theta }N{a^ \\oplus }}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ph{O^\\Theta }N{a^ \\oplus }}$$, MeOH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-ethers",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Ph{O^\\Theta }N{a^ \\oplus }}$$, MeBr"
  },
  {
    "id": "7Mv4P7zHHsSe0WjW",
    "question": "Phenyl magnesium bromide reacts with methanol to give ",
    "options": [
      "a mixture of anisole and Mg(OH)Br",
      "a mixture of benzene and Mg(OMe)Br ",
      "a mixture of toluene and Mg(OH)Br",
      "a mixture of phenol and Mg(Me)Br"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "a mixture of benzene and Mg(OMe)Br "
  },
  {
    "id": "CNnkpxmvwOadc5tt",
    "question": "Phenol, when it first reacts with concentrated sulphuric acid and then with concentrated nitric acid,\ngives",
    "options": [
      "2,4,6-trinitrobenzene",
      "o-nitrophenol ",
      "p-nitrophenol ",
      "nitrobenzene "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "o-nitrophenol "
  },
  {
    "id": "4HLMIyteMTWXUX9g",
    "question": "The major product obtained on interaction of phenol with sodium hydroxide and carbon dioxide is : ",
    "options": [
      "benzoic acid ",
      "salicylaldehyde ",
      "salicylic acid",
      "phthalic acid "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "salicylic acid"
  },
  {
    "id": "RRpobofkpARvU8XC",
    "question": "Phenol is heated with a solution of mixture of KBr and KBrO<sub>3</sub>. The major product obtained in the above\nreaction is ",
    "options": [
      "3-Bromophenol",
      "4-Bromophenol",
      "2, 4, 6- Tribromophenol ",
      "2-Bromophenol "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "2, 4, 6- Tribromophenol "
  },
  {
    "id": "nzFCxAyY4jwP8rrB",
    "question": "Ortho–Nitrophenol is less soluble in water than p– and m– Nitrophenols because :",
    "options": [
      "o–Nitrophenol is more volatile in steam than those of m – and p–isomers",
      "o–Nitrophenol shows Intramolecular H–bonding",
      "o–Nitrophenol shows Intermolecular H–bonding",
      "Melting point of o–Nitrophenol is lower than those of m–and p–isomers."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "o–Nitrophenol shows Intramolecular H–bonding"
  },
  {
    "id": "3G6dabpylT237sDCoJ7k9k2k5h0ozpj",
    "question": "Arrange the following compounds in increasing order of C–OH bond length : <br/>methanol, phenol,\np-ethoxyphenol",
    "options": [
      "phenol &lt; methanol &lt; p-ethoxyphenol",
      "methanol &lt; p-ethoxyphenol &lt; phenol",
      "methanol &lt; phenol &lt; p-ethoxyphenol",
      "phenol &lt; p-ethoxyphenol &lt; methanol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "phenol &lt; p-ethoxyphenol &lt; methanol"
  },
  {
    "id": "NKOpVAGoGWm7IuwX5F1kludvp91",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : <br/><br/>Statement I : o-Nitrophenol is steam volatile due to intramolecular hydrogen bonding.<br/><br/>Statement II : o-Nitrophenol has high melting due to hydrogen bonding.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l549ulcc",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Phenols are weakly acidic.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Therefore they are freely soluble in NaOH solution and are weaker acids than alcohols and water.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate option :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gqp075",
    "question": "<p>The difference in the reaction of phenol with bromine in chloroform and bromine in water medium is due to :</p>\n",
    "options": [
      "Hyperconjugation in substrate",
      "Polarity of solvent",
      "Free radical formation",
      "Electromeric effect the substrate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "Polarity of solvent"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i5icdc",
    "question": "<p>Hydrolysis of which compound will give carbolic acid?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Cumene",
      "Benzenediazonium chloride",
      "Benzal chloride",
      "Ethylene glycol ketal"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "Benzenediazonium chloride"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsruan5",
    "question": "<p>The increasing order of $$\\mathrm{pK_a}$$ for the following phenols is</p>\n<p>(A) 2, 4 - Dinitrophenol</p>\n<p>(B) 4 - Nitrophenol</p>\n<p>(C) 2, 4, 5 - Trimethylphenol</p>\n<p>(D) Phenol</p>\n<p>(E) 3-Chlorophenol</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the option given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A), (E), (B), (D), (C)",
      "(C), (E), (D), (B), (A)",
      "(C), (D), (E), (B), (A)",
      "(A), (B), (E), (D), (C)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "(A), (B), (E), (D), (C)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu1ahil",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements, one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Butylated hydroxy anisole when added to butter increases its shelf life.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Butylated hydroxy anisole is more reactive towards oxygen than food.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is not correct but R is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldukx6yj",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R :</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Acetal / Ketal is stable in basic medium.</p>\n<p>Reason R : The high leaving tendency of alkoxide ion gives the stability to acetal/ketal in basic medium.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is false but R is true.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "A is true but R is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaokiln",
    "question": "Match <b>List - I</b> with <b>List - II</b>.\n<br/><br/>\n<style>\n  table {\n    border-collapse: collapse;\n    width: 100%;\n  }\n  th, td {\n    border: 1px solid black;\n    padding: 8px;\n    text-align: left;\n  }\n  th {\n    background-color: #0000FF;\n    color: white;\n  }\n</style>\n<table>\n<tr>\n<th>List I (Reactants)</th>\n<th>List II (Product)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(A) Phenol, Zn/Δ</td>\n<td>(I) Salicylaldehyde</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(B) Phenol, CHCl<sub>3</sub>, NaOH, HCl</td>\n<td>(II) Salicylic acid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(C) Phenol, CO<sub>2</sub>, NaOH, HCl</td>\n<td>(III) Benzene</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(D) Phenol, Conc. HNO<sub>3</sub></td>\n<td>(IV) Picric acid</td>\n</tr>\n</table>\n<br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(II), (C)-(I), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(IV)"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc5fpk2",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p><b>Statement (I)</b> : p-nitrophenol is more acidic than m-nitrophenol and o-nitrophenol.</p>\n<p><b>Statement (II)</b> : Ethanol will give immediate turbidity with Lucas reagent.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscrdfwx",
    "question": "<p>Phenolic group can be identified by a positive:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Tollen's test\n",
      "Phthalein dye test\n",
      "Carbylamine test\n",
      "Lucas test"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "Phthalein dye test\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7rplh",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R:</p>\n<p>Assertion A: $$\\mathrm{pK}_{\\mathrm{a}}$$ value of phenol is 10.0 while that of ethanol is 15.9 .</p>\n<p>Reason R: Ethanol is stronger acid than phenol.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is false but R is true.\n",
      "Both $$A$$ and $$R$$ are true but $$R$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$A$$.\n",
      "Both $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathrm{A}$$.\n",
      "$$A$$ is true but $$R$$ is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "$$A$$ is true but $$R$$ is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfpbasr",
    "question": "<p>Phenol treated with chloroform in presence of sodium hydroxide, which further hydrolyzed in presence of an acid results</p>",
    "options": [
      "Salicylic acid\n",
      "Benzene-1,2-diol\n",
      "2-Hydroxybenzaldehyde\n",
      "Benzene-1,3-diol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "2-Hydroxybenzaldehyde\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfpdgky",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 523px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 70px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 184px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 94px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 175px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - I<br/>(Compound)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - II<br/>($$\\mathrm{pK_a}$$ value)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ethanol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">10.0</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Phenol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">15.9</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">m-Nitrophenol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">7.1</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">p-Nitrophenol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">8.3</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV\n",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III\n",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III\n",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erzhd",
    "question": "<p>Common name of Benzene - 1,2 - diol is -</p>",
    "options": [
      "catechol\n",
      "quinol\n",
      "o-cresol\n",
      "resorcinol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "catechol\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmax0",
    "question": "<p>Which one the following compounds will readily react with dilute $$\\mathrm{NaOH}$$ ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_5 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{OH}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_2 \\mathrm{H}_5 \\mathrm{OH}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_5 \\mathrm{OH}$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\mathrm{CH}_3\\right)_3 \\mathrm{COH}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_5 \\mathrm{OH}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v49oe",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statement :</p>\n<p>Statements I : Bromination of phenol in solvent with low polarity such as $$\\mathrm{CHCl}_3$$ or $$\\mathrm{CS}_2$$ requires Lewis acid catalyst.</p>\n<p>Statements II : The Lewis acid catalyst polarises the bromine to generate $$\\mathrm{Br}^{+}$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alcohols-phenols-and-ethers",
    "topic": "properties,-preparation-and-uses-of-phenols",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "0Bv6DPFm7zDrQND5",
    "question": "Which one of the following reduced with zinc and hydrochloric acid to give the corresponding\nhydrocarbon? ",
    "options": [
      "Ethyl acetate ",
      "Butan -2-one ",
      "Acetamide",
      "Acetic acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "chemical-reactions-for-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "Butan -2-one "
  },
  {
    "id": "oEYSqKy4Jhv50vE1",
    "question": "Trichloroacetaldehyde was subjected to Cannizzaro’s reaction by using NaOH. The mixture of the\nproducts contains sodium trichloroacetate and another compound. The other compound is :",
    "options": [
      "Trichloromethanol",
      "2, 2, 2-Trichloropropanol",
      "Chloroform",
      "2, 2, 2-Trichloroethanol "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "chemical-reactions-for-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "2, 2, 2-Trichloroethanol "
  },
  {
    "id": "vrPW5hzwZvj1eZf3axXNC",
    "question": "Which of the following compounds will most readily be dehydrated to give alkene under acidic condition ? ",
    "options": [
      "1- Pentanol ",
      "4-Hydroxypentan - 2-one",
      "3-Hydroxypentan - 2-one",
      "2-Hydroxycyclopentanone"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "chemical-reactions-for-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "4-Hydroxypentan - 2-one"
  },
  {
    "id": "Y4rUeNIEPtXtMeYCjysPe",
    "question": "In the following reaction : \n<br/><br/> Aldehyde + Alcohol   $$\\buildrel {HCl} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$  Acetal \n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border:none;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:0px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:0px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-pjk9{font-size:22px;text-align:left}\n.tg .tg-cyim{font-size:22px;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-pjk9\"><b>Aldehyde</b></th>\n<th class=\"tg-cyim\">          </th>\n<th class=\"tg-pjk9\">       </th>\n<th class=\"tg-pjk9\"><b>Alcohol</b></th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-pjk9\">HCHO</td>\n<td class=\"tg-cyim\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-pjk9\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-pjk9\">t<sub>BuOH</sub></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-pjk9\">CH<sub>3</sub>CHO</td>\n<td class=\"tg-cyim\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-pjk9\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-pjk9\">MeOH</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>\n<br/>The best combination is ",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CHO and MeOH",
      "HCHO and MeOH",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CHO and tBuOH",
      "HCHO and tBuOH "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "chemical-reactions-for-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "HCHO and MeOH"
  },
  {
    "id": "J5jOWF2pEgg7ZkxWJNjgy2xukf3lmbbq",
    "question": "The increasing order of the reactivity of the\nfollowing compound in nucleophilic addition\nreaction is :\n<br/><br/>Propanal, Benzaldehyde, Propanone, Butanone",
    "options": [
      "Butanone &lt; Propanone &lt; Benzaldehyde &lt;\nPropanal",
      "Benzaldehyde &lt; Butanone &lt; Propanone &lt;\nPropanal",
      "Propanal &lt; Propanone &lt; Butanone &lt;\nBenzaldehyde",
      "Benzaldehyde &lt; Propanal &lt; Propanone &lt;\nButanone"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "chemical-reactions-for-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "Butanone &lt; Propanone &lt; Benzaldehyde &lt;\nPropanal"
  },
  {
    "id": "j4e8FzqKoN8xZ8DFKE1kmht1tzs",
    "question": "Assertion A : Enol form of acetone [CH<sub>3</sub>COCH<sub>3</sub>] exists in &lt; 0.1% quantity. However, the enol form of acetyl acetone [CH<sub>3</sub>COCH<sub>2</sub>OCCH<sub>3</sub>] exists in approximately 15% quantity.<br/><br/>Reason R : Enol form of acetyl acetone is stabilized by intramolecular hydrogen bonding, which is not possible in enol form of acetone.<br/><br/>Choose the correct statement :",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true but R is not the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "chemical-reactions-for-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn03hi6",
    "question": "Experimentally reducing a functional group cannot be done by which one of the following reagents?",
    "options": [
      "Pt-C/H<sub>2</sub>",
      "Na/H<sub>2</sub>",
      "Pd-C/H<sub>2</sub>",
      "Zn/H<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "chemical-reactions-for-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "Na/H<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn1d14v",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : The nucleophilic addition of sodium hydrogen sulphite to an aldehyde or a ketone involves proton transfer to form a stable ion.<br/><br/>Statement II : The nucleophilic addition of hydrogen cyanide to an aldehyde or a ketone yields amine as final product.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement are true.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but  Statement II is true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "chemical-reactions-for-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vy3rc",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statements I : Acidity of $$\\alpha$$-hydrogens of aldehydes and ketones is responsible for Aldol reaction.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Reaction between benzaldehyde and ethanal will NOT give Cross - Aldol product.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect\n",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct\n",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "chemical-reactions-for-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lzFvSWBY3RV0kYkv",
    "question": "Reaction of cyclohexanone with dimethylamine in the presence of catalytic amount of\nan acid forms a compound if water during the reaction is continuously removed. The\ncompound formed is generally known as",
    "options": [
      "a Schiff’s base",
      "an enamine ",
      "an imine",
      "an amine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "method-of-preparation-for-aldehydes",
    "solution": "an enamine "
  },
  {
    "id": "9zA5MqQEK36Q5vtUAfjgy2xukg3ed3ul",
    "question": "The correct match between Item-I (starting\nmaterial) and Item-II (reagent) for the\npreparation of benzaldehyde is :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\"><b>Item-I</b></th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\"><b>Item-II</b></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(I) Benzene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(P) HCl and SnCl<sub>2</sub>,\nH<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(II) Benzonitrile</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(Q) H<sub>2</sub>, Pd-BaSO<sub>4</sub>, S\nand quinoline</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(III) Benzoyl Chloride</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(R) CO, HCl and AlCl<sub>3</sub></td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "(I) - (R), (II) - (P) and (III) - (Q)",
      "(I) - (P), (II) - (Q) and (III) - (R)",
      "(I) - (Q), (II) - (R) and (III) - (P)",
      "(I) - (R), (II) - (Q) and (III) - (P)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "method-of-preparation-for-aldehydes",
    "solution": "(I) - (R), (II) - (P) and (III) - (Q)"
  },
  {
    "id": "fuctW6ydtkJWkjVJSe1kls809rh",
    "question": "Which one of the following reactions will not form acetaldehyde?",
    "options": [
      "$$C{H_3}C{H_2}OH\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{573K}^{Cu}} $$",
      "$$C{H_3}C{H_2}OH\\buildrel {Cr{O_3} - {H_2}S{O_4}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$",
      "$$C{H_2} = C{H_2} + {O_2}\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{{H_2}O}^{Pd(II)/Cu(II)}} $$",
      "$$C{H_3}CN\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{ii)\\,{H_2}O}^{i)\\,DIBAL - H}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "method-of-preparation-for-aldehydes",
    "solution": "$$C{H_3}C{H_2}OH\\buildrel {Cr{O_3} - {H_2}S{O_4}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "tdYf5JdeW3TWpUa1",
    "question": "One mole of a symmetrical alkene on ozonolysis gives two moles of an aldehyde having a molecular\nmass of 44 u. The alkene is",
    "options": [
      "propene ",
      "1–butene",
      "2–butene",
      "ethene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation-methods-for-both-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "2–butene"
  },
  {
    "id": "qGR0YViDBf55nYiAIp7k9k2k5h38lx6",
    "question": "The predominant intermolecular forces present in ethyl acetate, a liquid, are:",
    "options": [
      "Dipole-dipole and hydrogen bonding",
      "hydrogen bonding and London dispersion",
      "London dispersion, dipole-dipole and hydrogen bonding",
      "London dispersion and dipole-dipole"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation-methods-for-both-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "London dispersion and dipole-dipole"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZjcfHEUzV3Q33VCX4S1klrdqcd3",
    "question": "Which of the following reagent is used for the following reaction ?<br/><br/>\n$$\n\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_3 \\stackrel{?}{\\longrightarrow} \\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CHO}\n$$",
    "options": [
      "Molybdenum oxide",
      "Manganese acetate",
      "Copper at high temperature and pressure",
      "Potassium permanganate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation-methods-for-both-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "Molybdenum oxide"
  },
  {
    "id": "07HBNTV4FkzqfYabzM1kmj7v421",
    "question": "Mesityl oxide is a common name of :",
    "options": [
      "3-Methyl cyclohexane carbaldehyde",
      "4-Methyl pent-3-en-2-one",
      "2,4-Dimethyl pentan-3-one",
      "2-Methyl cyclohexanone"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation-methods-for-both-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "4-Methyl pent-3-en-2-one"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58jpzbj",
    "question": "<p>Oxidation of toluene to benzaldehyde can be easily carried out with which of the following reagents?</p>",
    "options": [
      "CrO<sub>3</sub>/acetic acid, H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>",
      "CrO<sub>3</sub>/acetic anhydride, H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>",
      "KMnO<sub>4</sub>/HCl, H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>",
      "CO/HCl, anhydrous AlCl<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation-methods-for-both-aldehydes-and-ketones",
    "solution": "CrO<sub>3</sub>/acetic anhydride, H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1GwY3CoPZQJCcxz1",
    "question": "The compound formed as a result of oxidation of ethyl benzene by KMnO<sub>4 </sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "benzophenone",
      "acetophenone",
      "benzoic acid",
      "benzyl alcohol "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation,-properties-and-uses-of-carboxylic-acids",
    "solution": "benzoic acid"
  },
  {
    "id": "06w76bwLAiXnjlNr",
    "question": "A liquid was mixed with ethanol and a drop of concentrated H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> was added. A compound with a\nfruity smell was formed. The liquid was : ",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>OH ",
      "HCHO",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CO CH<sub>3</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COOH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation,-properties-and-uses-of-carboxylic-acids",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>COOH"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktb5fie5",
    "question": "The correct sequential addition of reagents in the preparation of 3-nitrobenzoic acid from benzene is :",
    "options": [
      "Br<sub>2</sub>/AlBr<sub>3</sub>, HNO<sub>3</sub>/H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, Mg/ether, CO<sub>2</sub>, H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>",
      "Br<sub>2</sub>/AlBr<sup>3</sup>, NaCN, H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>, HNO<sub>3</sub>/H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>",
      "Br<sub>2</sub>/AlBr<sub>3</sub>, HNO<sub>3</sub>/H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, NaCN, H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>",
      "HNO<sub>3</sub>/H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, Br<sub>2</sub>/AlBr<sub>3</sub>, Mg/ether, CO<sub>2</sub>, H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation,-properties-and-uses-of-carboxylic-acids",
    "solution": "HNO<sub>3</sub>/H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, Br<sub>2</sub>/AlBr<sub>3</sub>, Mg/ether, CO<sub>2</sub>, H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfrnvnw",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : Ethyl pent-4-yn-oate on reaction with CH<sub>3</sub>MgBr gives a 3$$^\\circ$$-alcohol.<br/><br/>Statement II : In this reaction one mole of ethyl pent-4-yn-oate utilizes two moles of CH<sub>3</sub>MgBr.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation,-properties-and-uses-of-carboxylic-acids",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfs3rzv",
    "question": "Which one of the following reactions will not yield propionic acid?",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COCH<sub>3</sub> + OI<sup>$$-$$</sup>/H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>3</sub> + KMnO<sub>4</sub>(Heat), OH<sup>$$-$$</sup>/H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CCl<sub>3</sub> + OH<sup>$$-$$</sup>/H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>Br + Mg, CO<sub>2</sub> dry ether/H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation,-properties-and-uses-of-carboxylic-acids",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>Br + Mg, CO<sub>2</sub> dry ether/H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l549nouv",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The esterification of carboxylic acid with an alcohol is a nucleophilic acyl substitution.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Electron withdrawing groups in the carboxylic acid will increase the rate of esterification reaction.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate option :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation,-properties-and-uses-of-carboxylic-acids",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c6sbau",
    "question": "<p>Two statements are given below :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The melting point of monocarboxylic acid with even number of carbon atoms is higher than that of with odd number of carbon atoms acid immediately below and above it in the series.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The solubility of monocarboxylic acids in water decreases with increase in molar mass.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate option :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation,-properties-and-uses-of-carboxylic-acids",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsybj0x",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements, one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : A solution of the product obtained by heating a mole of glycine with a mole of chlorine in presence of red phosphorous generates chiral carbon atom.</p>\n<p>Reason R : A molecule with 2 chiral carbons is always optically active.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation,-properties-and-uses-of-carboxylic-acids",
    "solution": "A is true but R is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaouz79",
    "question": "Which among the followng has highest boiling point?",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2-\\mathrm{OH}$",
      "$\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_3$",
      "$\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CHO}$",
      "$\\mathrm{H}_5 \\mathrm{C}_2-\\mathrm{O}-\\mathrm{C}_2 \\mathrm{H}_5$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation,-properties-and-uses-of-carboxylic-acids",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2-\\mathrm{OH}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscrzydm",
    "question": "<p>The molecular formula of second homologue in the homologous series of mono carboxylic acids is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_2 \\mathrm{H}_4 \\mathrm{O}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_2 \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{O}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_3 \\mathrm{H}_6 \\mathrm{O}_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "preparation,-properties-and-uses-of-carboxylic-acids",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{C}_2 \\mathrm{H}_4 \\mathrm{O}_2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "IvmZis08k2VEIDknzsqs4",
    "question": "The correct statement about the synthesis of erythritol  (C(CH<sub>2</sub>OH)4) used in the preparation of PETN is : ",
    "options": [
      "The synthesis requires four aldol condensations between methanol\nand ethanol.",
      "The synthesis requires two aldol condensations and two Cannizzaro\nreactions.",
      "The synthesis requires three aldol condensations and one Cannizzaro\nreaction.",
      "Alpha hydrogens of ethanol and methanol are involved in this\nreaction."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "reactions-involving-aldehydes",
    "solution": "The synthesis requires three aldol condensations and one Cannizzaro\nreaction."
  },
  {
    "id": "dIa1d9uZ2yLupTxmYtU9q",
    "question": "The correct match between <b>Item I</b> and <b>Item II</b> is :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-wv9z{font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-de48{font-weight:bold;font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\" colspan=\"2\">Item - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\" colspan=\"2\">Item - II</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-de48\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Benzaldehyde</td>\n<td class=\"tg-de48\">(P)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Mobile phase</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-de48\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Alumina</td>\n<td class=\"tg-de48\">(Q)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Adsorbent</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-de48\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Acetonitrile</td>\n<td class=\"tg-de48\">(R)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Adsorbate</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "(A)  $$ \\to $$  (Q);  (B)  $$ \\to $$  (P);  (C)  $$ \\to $$  (R)",
      "(A)  $$ \\to $$  (R);  (B)  $$ \\to $$  (Q);  (C)  $$ \\to $$  (P)",
      "(A)  $$ \\to $$  (Q);  (B)  $$ \\to $$  (R);  (C)  $$ \\to $$  (P)",
      "(A)  $$ \\to $$  (P);  (B)  $$ \\to $$  (R);  (C)  $$ \\to $$  (Q)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "tests-for-aldehyde-and-ketones",
    "solution": "(A)  $$ \\to $$  (R);  (B)  $$ \\to $$  (Q);  (C)  $$ \\to $$  (P)"
  },
  {
    "id": "Cav9RjZYrYvXTKqtM51klus87ww",
    "question": "2, 4-DNP test can be used to identify :",
    "options": [
      "ether",
      "amine",
      "aldehyde",
      "halogens"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "tests-for-aldehyde-and-ketones",
    "solution": "aldehyde"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwdeto",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following compounds will give silver mirror with ammoniacal silver nitrate?</p>\n<p>A. Formic acid</p>\n<p>B. Formaldehyde</p>\n<p>C. Benzaldehyde</p>\n<p>D. Acetone</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "B and C only",
      "C and D only",
      "A, B and C only",
      "A only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "aldehydes-ketones-and-carboxylic-acids",
    "topic": "tests-for-aldehyde-and-ketones",
    "solution": "A, B and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "mo99S4jYeBTUH1NS",
    "question": "Consider the acidity of the carboxylic acids:<br/>\n(a)  PhCOOH <br/>\n(b) o – NO<sub>2</sub>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>4</sub>COOH <br/>\n(c) p – NO<sub>2</sub>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>4</sub>COOH<br/>\n(d) m – NO<sub>2</sub>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>4</sub>COOH <br/>\nWhich of the following order is correct?",
    "options": [
      "(b) &gt; (d) &gt; (a) &gt; (c)",
      "(b) &gt; (d) &gt; (c) &gt; (a)",
      "(a) &gt; (b) &gt; (c) &gt; (d)",
      "(b) &gt; (c) &gt; (d) &gt; (a)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "(b) &gt; (c) &gt; (d) &gt; (a)"
  },
  {
    "id": "2s7osUAKBUiwnugA",
    "question": "CH<sub>3</sub>Br + Nu<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$ CH<sub>3</sub> - Nu + Br<sup>-</sup> The decreasing order of the rate of the above reaction with nucleophiles (Nu<sup>–</sup>) A to D is<br/>\n[Nu<sup>–</sup> = (A) PhO<sup>–</sup>, (B) AcO<sup>–</sup>, (C) HO–, (D) CH<sub>3</sub>O<sup>–</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "A &gt; B &gt; C &gt; D",
      "B &gt; D &gt; C &gt; A",
      "D &gt; C &gt; A &gt; B",
      "D &gt; C &gt; B &gt; A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "D &gt; C &gt; A &gt; B"
  },
  {
    "id": "TFMhKOxWC28IA7Hv",
    "question": "The correct order of increasing basicity of the given conjugate bases (R = CH<sub>3</sub>) is",
    "options": [
      "$$RCO\\overline O$$ &lt; HC = $$\\overline C$$ &lt; $$\\overline R$$ &lt; $$\\overline NH_2$$",
      "$$\\overline R$$ &lt; HC = $$\\overline C$$ &lt; $$RCO\\overline O$$ &lt; $$\\overline NH_2$$",
      "$$RCO\\overline O$$ &lt; $$\\overline NH_2$$ &lt; HC = $$\\overline C$$ &lt; $$\\overline R$$",
      "$$RCO\\overline O$$ &lt; HC = $$\\overline C$$ &lt; $$\\overline NH_2$$ &lt; $$\\overline R$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "$$RCO\\overline O$$ &lt; HC = $$\\overline C$$ &lt; $$\\overline NH_2$$ &lt; $$\\overline R$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1YtMkBtgrsBLvP9IjTJCZ",
    "question": "Which amongst the following is the strongest acid ? ",
    "options": [
      "CHBr<sub>3</sub>",
      "CHI<sub>3</sub> ",
      "CH(CN)<sub>3</sub>",
      "CHCl<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "CH(CN)<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "igT4LNZm5lKrhipeNg9bR",
    "question": "The correct decreasing order for acid strength is : ",
    "options": [
      "NO<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; FCH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; CNCH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; ClCH<sub>2</sub>COOH",
      "FCH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; NCCH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; NO<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; ClCH<sub>2</sub>COOH",
      "CNCH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; O<sub>2</sub>NCH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; FCH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; ClCH<sub>2</sub>COOH",
      "NO<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; NCCH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; FCH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; ClCH<sub>2</sub>COOH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "NO<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; NCCH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; FCH<sub>2</sub>COOH &gt; ClCH<sub>2</sub>COOH"
  },
  {
    "id": "8fiCCKECwzPVdw8D820jz",
    "question": "In the following compounds, the decreasing order of basic strength will be :",
    "options": [
      "(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub>NH &gt; NH<sub>3</sub> &gt; C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>",
      "NH<sub>3</sub> &gt; C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>NH<sub>2</sub> &gt; (C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub>NH",
      "(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub>NH &gt; C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>NH<sub>2</sub> &gt; NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>NH<sub>2</sub> &gt; NH<sub>3</sub> &gt; (C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub>NH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub>NH &gt; C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>NH<sub>2</sub> &gt; NH<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "RD5MP4FbaOfiAqWiBdvRs",
    "question": "Which of the following compounds will show\nthe maximum 'enol' content?",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COCH<sub>3</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COCH<sub>2</sub>COCH<sub>3</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COCH<sub>2</sub>COOC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COCH<sub>2</sub>CONH<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>COCH<sub>2</sub>COCH<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "cPaHSS3QEbMXyIcOX43rsa0w2w9jx10umoz",
    "question": "The increasing order of nucleophilicity of the following nucleophiles is :\n<br/>(a) CH<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub><sup>$$-$$</sup>           (b) H<sub>2</sub>O\n<br/>(c) CH<sub>3</sub>SO<sub>3</sub><sup>$$-$$</sup>           (d) $$\\mathop O\\limits^ -  H$$",
    "options": [
      "(b) &lt; (c) &lt; (a) &lt; (d)",
      "(b) &lt; (c) &lt; (d) &lt; (a)",
      "(a) &lt; (d) &lt; (c) &lt; (b)",
      "(d) &lt; (a) &lt; (c) &lt; (b)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "(b) &lt; (c) &lt; (a) &lt; (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldukzg76",
    "question": "<p>The correct order in aqueous medium of basic strength in case of methyl substituted amines is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{NH_3 > Me_3N > MeNH_2 > Me_2NH}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Me_3N > Me_2NH > MeNH_2 > NH_3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Me_2NH > MeNH_2 > Me_3N > NH_3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Me_2NH > Me_3N > MeNH_2 > NH_3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Me_2NH > MeNH_2 > Me_3N > NH_3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgysi9xv",
    "question": "<p>The descending order of acidity for the following carboxylic acid is-</p>\n<p>A. $$\\mathrm{CH}_{3} \\mathrm{COOH}$$</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{F}_{3} \\mathrm{C}-\\mathrm{COOH}$$</p>\n<p>C. $$\\mathrm{ClCH}_{2}-\\mathrm{COOH}$$</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{FCH}_{2}-\\mathrm{COOH}$$</p>\n<p>E. $$\\mathrm{BrCH}_{2}-\\mathrm{COOH}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "B > C > D > E > A",
      "D > B > A > E > C",
      "B > D > C > E > A",
      "E > D > B > A > C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "B > D > C > E > A"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vy3oe",
    "question": "<p>What will be the decreasing order of basic strength of the following conjugate bases? $${ }^{-} \\mathrm{OH}, \\mathrm{R} \\overline{\\mathrm{O}}, \\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CO} \\overline{\\mathrm{O}}, \\mathrm{Cl}$$\n\n</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{C} \\overline{\\mathrm{I}}>\\mathrm{R} \\overline{\\mathrm{O}}>{ }^{-} \\mathrm{OH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CO} \\overline{\\mathrm{O}}$$\n",
      "$${ }^{-} \\mathrm{OH}>\\mathrm{R} \\overline{\\mathrm{O}}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CO} \\overline{\\mathrm{O}}>\\mathrm{C} \\overline{1}$$\n\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{C} \\overline{\\mathrm{I}}>{ }^{-} \\mathrm{OH}>\\mathrm{R} \\overline{\\mathrm{O}}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CO} \\bar{O}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{R} \\overline{\\mathrm{O}}>{ }^{-} \\mathrm{OH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CO} \\overline{\\mathrm{O}}>\\mathrm{C} \\overline{1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{R} \\overline{\\mathrm{O}}>{ }^{-} \\mathrm{OH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CO} \\overline{\\mathrm{O}}>\\mathrm{C} \\overline{1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmadk",
    "question": "<p>The correct sequence of acidic strength of the following aliphatic acids in their decreasing order is:</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}, \\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{COOH}, \\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}, \\mathrm{HCOOH}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{HCOOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{COOH}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{HCOOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{HCOOH}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{HCOOH}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "acid-and-base-strength",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{HCOOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}>\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{COOH}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp2yz2n",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Tropolone is an aromatic compound and has $$8 \\pi$$ electrons.</p>\n<p>Statement II : $$\\pi$$ electrons of $$ &gt; \\mathrm{C}=\\mathrm{O}$$ group in tropolone is involved in aromaticity.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "aromaticity",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
  },
  {
    "id": "A9DlvJoYelzEnvRh",
    "question": "Arrangement of (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>C-, (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CH-, CH<sub>3</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>- when attached to benzyl or an unsaturated group in increasing order of inductive effect is",
    "options": [
      "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>C- &lt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CH- &lt; CH<sub>3</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-  &lt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CH- &lt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>C-",
      "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CH- &lt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>C- &lt; CH<sub>3</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>",
      "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>C- &lt; CH<sub>3</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-  &lt; CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CH-"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-  &lt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CH- &lt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>C-"
  },
  {
    "id": "3PR85jqfqrMNzZ1d",
    "question": "In the anion HCOO<sup>$$-$$</sup>\n the two carbon-oxygen bonds are found to be of equal length. What is the reason for it?",
    "options": [
      "The C = O bond is weaker than the C-O bond",
      "The anion HCOO-\n has two resonating structures",
      "The anion is obtained by removal of a proton from the acid molecule",
      "Electronic orbitals of carbon atom are hybridised"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "The anion HCOO-\n has two resonating structures"
  },
  {
    "id": "TGOQoIRLqWj8AIzQ",
    "question": "Presence of a nitro group in a benzene ring",
    "options": [
      "activates the ring towards electrophilic substitution ",
      "renders the ring basic ",
      "deactivates the ring towards nucleophilic substitution ",
      "deactivates the ring towards electrophilic substitution "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "deactivates the ring towards electrophilic substitution "
  },
  {
    "id": "OO0ptTctkbylzLMdE87k9k2k5ll2evo",
    "question": "Which of the following has the shortest C-Cl\nbond?",
    "options": [
      "Cl–CH=CH–CH<sub>3</sub>",
      "Cl–CH=CH–NO<sub>2</sub>",
      "Cl–CH=CH–OCH<sub>3</sub>",
      "Cl–CH=CH<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "Cl–CH=CH–NO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1hjric",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : Hyperconjugation is a permanent effect.<br/><br/>Statement II : Hyperconjugation in ethyl cation $$\\left( {C{H_3} - \\mathop C\\limits^ +  {H_2}} \\right)$$ involves the overlapping of $${C_{s{p^2}}} - {H_{1s}}$$ bond with empty 2p orbital of other carbon.<br/><br/>Choose the correct option :",
    "options": [
      "Both statement I and statement II are false",
      "Statement I is incorrect but statement II is true",
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is false",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nwslel",
    "question": "<p>Arrange the following in increasing order of reactivity towards nitration</p>\n<p>A. p-xylene</p>\n<p>B. bromobenzene</p>\n<p>C. mesitylene</p>\n<p>D. nitrobenzene</p>\n<p>E. benzene</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "C < D < E < A < B",
      "D < B < E < A < C",
      "D < C < E < A < B",
      "C < D < E < B < A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "D < B < E < A < C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwuj8se",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements, one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Benzene is more stable than hypothetical cyclohexatriene</p>\n<p>Reason R : The delocalised $$\\pi$$ electron cloud is attracted more strongly by nuclei of carbon atoms.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is true but R is false",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT  the correct explanation of A",
      "A is false but R is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaoaihn",
    "question": "The set of meta directing functional groups from the following sets is :",
    "options": [
      "$-\\mathrm{CN},-\\mathrm{NH}_2,-\\mathrm{NHR},-\\mathrm{OCH}_3$",
      "$-\\mathrm{CN},-\\mathrm{CHO},-\\mathrm{NHCOCH}_3,-\\mathrm{COOR}$",
      "$-\\mathrm{NO}_2,-\\mathrm{NH}_2,-\\mathrm{COOH},-\\mathrm{COOR} $",
      "$-\\mathrm{NO}_2,-\\mathrm{CHO},-\\mathrm{SO}_3 \\mathrm{H},-\\mathrm{COR}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "$-\\mathrm{NO}_2,-\\mathrm{CHO},-\\mathrm{SO}_3 \\mathrm{H},-\\mathrm{COR}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaosqy9",
    "question": "The functional group that shows negative resonance effect is :",
    "options": [
      "$-\\mathrm{OH}$",
      "$-\\mathrm{OR}$",
      "$-\\mathrm{COOH}$",
      "$-\\mathrm{NH}_2$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "$-\\mathrm{COOH}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbmamho",
    "question": "Ionic reactions with organic compounds proceed through :<br/><br/>\n(A) homolytic bond cleavage<br/><br/>\n(B) heterolytic bond cleavage<br/><br/>\n(C) free radical formation<br/><br/>\n(D) primary free radical<br/><br/>\n(E) secondary free radical\n<br/><br/>\nChoose the <b>correct</b> answer from the options given below :\n",
    "options": [
      "(A) only",
      "(B) only",
      "(C) only",
      "(D) and (E) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "(B) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjrkoo",
    "question": "<p>The interaction between $$\\pi$$ bond and lone pair of electrons present on an adjacent atom is responsible for</p>",
    "options": [
      "Resonance effect\n",
      "Electromeric effect\n",
      "Hyperconjugation",
      "Inductive effect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "Resonance effect\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vyqqy",
    "question": "<p>Which among the following is incorrect statement?</p>",
    "options": [
      "The electromeric effect is, temporary effect\n",
      "Hydrogen ion $$(\\mathrm{H}^{+})$$ shows negative electromeric effect\n",
      "The organic compound shows electromeric effect in the presence of the reagent only.\n",
      "Electromeric effect dominates over inductive effect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "electron-displacement-effect",
    "solution": "Hydrogen ion $$(\\mathrm{H}^{+})$$ shows negative electromeric effect\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "i6gxw6BpFeG6N8Pi",
    "question": "A similarity between optical and geometrical isomerism is that",
    "options": [
      "each forms equal number of isomers for a given compound",
      "if in a compound one is present then so is the other",
      "both are included in stereoisomerism",
      "they have no similarity"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "both are included in stereoisomerism"
  },
  {
    "id": "Sox4Ulfi8dSjN3z3",
    "question": "Racemic mixture is formed by mixing two",
    "options": [
      "isomeric compounds",
      "enantiomers with chiral compounds",
      "meso compounds",
      "optical isomers"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "enantiomers with chiral compounds"
  },
  {
    "id": "PlmdyG2bKwMy7oRx",
    "question": "Which of the following does not show geometrical isomerism?",
    "options": [
      "1,2-dichloro-1-pentene",
      "1,3-dichloro-2-pentene",
      "1,1-dichloro-1-pentene",
      "1,4-dichloro-2-pentene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "1,1-dichloro-1-pentene"
  },
  {
    "id": "Sa7GhXIlheTWb9S3",
    "question": "The general formula C<sub>n</sub>H<sub>2n</sub>O<sub>2</sub> could be for open chain",
    "options": [
      "carboxylic acids",
      "diols",
      "dialdehydes",
      "deketones"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "carboxylic acids"
  },
  {
    "id": "izv8S3XrstKy7Chw",
    "question": "Which of the following compound is not chiral? ",
    "options": [
      "1- chloropentane",
      "3-chloro-2- methyl pentane ",
      "1-chloro -2- methyl pentane ",
      "2- chloropentane "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "1- chloropentane"
  },
  {
    "id": "BZezXmoSqycP9JyI",
    "question": "Which of the following will have meso-isomer also? ",
    "options": [
      "2- chlorobutane",
      "2- hydroxyopanoic acid",
      "2,3 – dichloropentane",
      "2-3- dichlorobutane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "2-3- dichlorobutane"
  },
  {
    "id": "qPbuje4HOcvnmhYR",
    "question": "Increasing order of stability among the three main conformations (i.e. Eclipse, Anti, Gauche) of\n2-fluoroethanol is",
    "options": [
      "Eclipse, Gauche, Anti",
      "Gauche, Eclipse, Anti ",
      "Eclipse, Anti, Gauche ",
      "Anti, Gauche, Eclipse "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "Eclipse, Anti, Gauche "
  },
  {
    "id": "lljkZljWFfVyi6yR",
    "question": "Which one of the following conformation of cyclohexane is chiral? ",
    "options": [
      "Twist boat ",
      "Rigid ",
      "Chair ",
      "Boat"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "Twist boat "
  },
  {
    "id": "LFOgm6Efj1n4Epk5",
    "question": "The number of stereoisomers possible for a compound of the molecular formula\nCH<sub>3</sub> - CH = CH - CH(OH) - Me is :",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "4",
      "6",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "7XBcGDXQs3SxDCoz",
    "question": "The alkene that exhibits geometrical isomerism is :",
    "options": [
      "propene",
      "2-methyl propene ",
      "2-butene",
      "2- methyl -2- butene "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "2-butene"
  },
  {
    "id": "qPh4MSXo9J5fvwWF",
    "question": "Out of the following, the alkene that exhibits optical isomerism is",
    "options": [
      "3–methyl–2–pentene ",
      "4–methyl–1–pentene",
      "3–methyl–1–pentene",
      "2–methyl–2–pentene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "3–methyl–1–pentene"
  },
  {
    "id": "gph8uwPqaolDmbPq",
    "question": "Identify the compound that exhibits tautomerism.",
    "options": [
      "Lactic acid",
      "2-Pentanone",
      "Pheno",
      "2- Butene "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "2-Pentanone"
  },
  {
    "id": "RR1LJVrcIoDjJ04y",
    "question": "Which of the following compounds will exhibit geometrical isomerism?",
    "options": [
      "3-Phenyl-1-butene",
      "2-Phenyl-1-butene",
      "1,1-Diphenyl-1-propane",
      "1-Phenyl-2-butene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "1-Phenyl-2-butene"
  },
  {
    "id": "wpRnpNfDL5pMDeE5Av3rsa0w2w9jx0xrtwu",
    "question": "Which of these factors does not govern the stability of a conformation in acyclic compounds?",
    "options": [
      "Angle strain",
      "Torsional strain",
      "Electrostatic forces of interaction",
      "Steric interactions"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "Angle strain"
  },
  {
    "id": "yYFvPkWMGeTSJhccrmjgy2xukftckrep",
    "question": "Which of the following compounds shows\ngeometrical isomerism?",
    "options": [
      "2-methylpent-1-ene",
      "4-methylpent-1-ene",
      "2-methylpent-2-ene",
      "4-methylpent-2-ene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "4-methylpent-2-ene"
  },
  {
    "id": "3peIu40D9LGkXhBsHn1kmlmzdy7",
    "question": "Compound with molecular formula C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>6</sub>O can show :",
    "options": [
      "Positional isomerism",
      "Both positional isomerism and metamerism",
      "Metamerism",
      "Functional group isomerism"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "Functional group isomerism"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt4qro4",
    "question": "Which of the following molecules does not show stereo isomerism?",
    "options": [
      "3, 4-Dimethylhex-3-ene",
      "3-Methylhex-1-ene",
      "3-Ethylhex-3-ene",
      "4-Methylhex-1-ene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "3-Ethylhex-3-ene"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz1egjv",
    "question": "Staggered and eclipsed conformers of ethane are :",
    "options": [
      "Polymers",
      "Rotamers",
      "Enantiomers",
      "Mirror images"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "Rotamers"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktcrctpl",
    "question": "The number of stereoisomers possible for 1, 2-dimethyl cyclopropane is :",
    "options": [
      "One",
      "Four",
      "Two",
      "Three"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "Three"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscrvirz",
    "question": "<p>The incorrect statement regarding conformations of ethane is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "The dihedral angle in staggered conformation is $$60^{\\circ}$$.\n",
      "Ethane has infinite number of conformations.\n",
      "Eclipsed conformation is the most stable conformation.\n",
      "The conformations of ethane are inter-convertible to one-another."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "Eclipsed conformation is the most stable conformation.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3tyj",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : Cis form of alkene is found to be more polar than the trans form.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Dipole moment of trans isomer of 2-butene is zero.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true",
      "Both $$(\\mathbf{A})$$ and $$(\\mathbf{R})$$ are true and $$(\\mathbf{R})$$ is the correct explanation of $$(\\mathbf{A})$$",
      "Both $$(\\mathbf{A})$$ and $$(\\mathbf{R})$$ are true but $$(\\mathbf{R})$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$(\\mathbf{A})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "Both $$(\\mathbf{A})$$ and $$(\\mathbf{R})$$ are true and $$(\\mathbf{R})$$ is the correct explanation of $$(\\mathbf{A})$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s281y",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 703px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Pair of Compounds)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Isomerism)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">n-propanol and Isopropanol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Metamerism</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Methoxypropane and ethoxyethane</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Chain Isomerism</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Propanone and propanal</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Position Isomerism</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Neopentane and Isopentane</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Functional Isomerism</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(III)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(IV)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(III), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2a7zg",
    "question": "<p>The incorrect statement regarding the geometrical isomers of 2-butene is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "cis-2-butene and trans-2-butene are not interconvertible at room temperature.\n",
      "trans-2-butene is more stable than cis-2-butene.\n",
      "cis-2-butene has less dipole moment than trans-2-butene.\n",
      "cis-2-butene and trans-2-butene are stereoisomers."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "isomerism",
    "solution": "cis-2-butene has less dipole moment than trans-2-butene.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "RURpxpet0gEFQdga",
    "question": "The IUPAC name of CH<sub>3</sub>COCH(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> is",
    "options": [
      "2-methyl-3-butaone",
      "4-methylisopropyl 1 ketone",
      "3-methyl-2-butaone",
      "Isopropylmethyl ketone"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "iupac-nomenclature",
    "solution": "3-methyl-2-butaone"
  },
  {
    "id": "Mk5jgnA61bJlM8Yp",
    "question": "Which one the following does not have sp<sup>2</sup> hybridized carbon?",
    "options": [
      "Acetone",
      "Acetamide",
      "Acetonitrile",
      "Acetic acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "iupac-nomenclature",
    "solution": "Acetonitrile"
  },
  {
    "id": "5Qj5hVTScN0vBd92",
    "question": "The correct decreasing order of priority for the functional groups of organic compounds in the IUPAC\nsystem of nomenclature is",
    "options": [
      "−COOH, −SO<sub>3</sub>H, −CONH<sub>2</sub>, −CHO ",
      "−SO<sub>3</sub>H, −COOH, −CONH<sub>2</sub>, −CHO ",
      "−CHO, −COOH, −SO<sub>3</sub>H, −CONH<sub>2</sub> ",
      "−CONH<sub>2</sub>, −CHO, −SO<sub>3</sub>H, −COOH "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "iupac-nomenclature",
    "solution": "−COOH, −SO<sub>3</sub>H, −CONH<sub>2</sub>, −CHO "
  },
  {
    "id": "bqKDiHrqwPvKHh8M",
    "question": "The IUPAC name of neopentane is ",
    "options": [
      "2-methylbutane",
      "2, 2-dimethylpropane",
      "2-methylpropane ",
      "2,2-dimethylbutane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "iupac-nomenclature",
    "solution": "2, 2-dimethylpropane"
  },
  {
    "id": "X30jgEuwFky5NkuYFTGnb",
    "question": "The hydrocarbon with seven carbon atoms containing a neopentyl and a vinyl group\nis :",
    "options": [
      "2, 2-dimethyl-4-pentene ",
      "Isopropyl-2-butene",
      "4, 4-dimethylpentene",
      "2, 2-dimethyl-3-pentene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "iupac-nomenclature",
    "solution": "4, 4-dimethylpentene"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5am41p7",
    "question": "<p>The IUPAC name of ethylidene chloride is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1-Chloroethene",
      "1-Chloroethyne",
      "1,2-Dichloroethane",
      "1,1-Dichloroethane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "iupac-nomenclature",
    "solution": "1,1-Dichloroethane"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7tehh",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I: IUPAC name of $$\\mathrm{HO}-\\mathrm{CH}_2-\\left(\\mathrm{CH}_2\\right)_3-\\mathrm{CH}_2-\\mathrm{COCH}_3$$ is 7-hydroxyheptan-2-one.</p>\n<p>Statement II: 2-oxoheptan-7-ol is the correct IUPAC name for above compound. In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct.\n",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "iupac-nomenclature",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "o8BmFj9gQsddtygX",
    "question": "For the estimation of nitrogen, 1.4 g of organic compound was digested by Kjeldahl method and the\nevolved ammonia was absorbed in 60 mL of M/10 sulphuric acid. The unreacted acid required 20 ml of M/10\nsodium hydroxide for complete neutralization. The percentage of nitrogen in the compound is:",
    "options": [
      "3%",
      "5%",
      "6%",
      "10%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "10%"
  },
  {
    "id": "8aPlaiwmP4fkNkrG",
    "question": "In Carius method of estimation of halogens, 250 mg of an organic compound gave 141 mg of AgBr. The\npercentage of bromine in the compound is: (at. Mass Ag = 108; Br = 80)",
    "options": [
      "48",
      "60",
      "36",
      "24"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "24"
  },
  {
    "id": "UAvdtqeDjcJ5hPYW",
    "question": "The distillation technique most suited for separating glycerol from spent-lye in the soap industry is :",
    "options": [
      "Simple distillation",
      "Fractional distillation",
      "Steam distillation",
      "Distillation under reduced pressure"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Distillation under reduced pressure"
  },
  {
    "id": "mOFUQmvkIYxuqBaxsBxWQ",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is not true about partition chromatography?",
    "options": [
      "Mobile phase can be a gas",
      "Stationary phase is a finely divided solid adsorbent",
      "Separation depends upon equilibration of solute between a mobile and a stationary phase\n",
      "Paper chromatography is an example of partition chromatography"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Stationary phase is a finely divided solid adsorbent"
  },
  {
    "id": "sGb013VC8ZxZJ8QY5nLpC",
    "question": "Two compounds I and II are eluted by column chromatography (adsorption of I &gt; II). Which one of following is a correct statement ? ",
    "options": [
      "I moves faster and has higher R<sub>f</sub> value than II",
      "II movesfaster and has higher&nbsp; R<sub>f</sub>&nbsp; value than I",
      "I moves slower and has higher&nbsp; R<sub>f</sub>&nbsp; value than II",
      "II moves slower and has higher&nbsp; R<sub>f</sub> &nbsp;value than I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "II movesfaster and has higher&nbsp; R<sub>f</sub>&nbsp; value than I"
  },
  {
    "id": "FltkfgWFfsS8fciFtw8HF",
    "question": "The correct match between items of <b>List-I</b> and <b>List-II</b> is :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-13k7{font-size:20px;text-align:left}\n.tg .tg-p7ly{font-weight:bold;font-size:20px;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-p7ly\" colspan=\"2\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-p7ly\" colspan=\"2\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Coloured impurity</td>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(P)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Steam distilation</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Mixture of o-nitrophenol <br/>and p-nitrophenol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(Q)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Fractional distilation</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Crude Naphtha </td>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(R)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Charcoal treatment</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(d)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Mixture of glycerol <br/>and sugars</td>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(S)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Distillation under <br/>reduced pressure</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(R), (B)-(S), (C)-(P), (D)-(Q)",
      "(A)-(R), (B)-(P), (C)-(S), (D)-(Q)",
      "(A)-(R), (B)-(P), (C)-(Q), (D)-(S)",
      "(A)-(P), (B)-(S), (C)-(R), (D)-(Q)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "(A)-(R), (B)-(P), (C)-(Q), (D)-(S)"
  },
  {
    "id": "Tnkau2QUd25jR5XAj2ntT",
    "question": "If dichloromethane (DCM) and water (H<sub>2</sub>O) are used for differential extraction, which one of the following statements is correct ?",
    "options": [
      "DCM and H<sub>2</sub>O would stay as upper and lower layer respectively in the separating funnel (S.F.)",
      "DCM and H<sub>2</sub>O will make turbid/colloidal mixture",
      "DCM and H<sub>2</sub>O would stay as lower and upper layer respectively in the separating funnel(S.F).",
      "DCM and H<sub>2</sub>O will be miscible clearly "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "DCM and H<sub>2</sub>O would stay as lower and upper layer respectively in the separating funnel(S.F)."
  },
  {
    "id": "DNOMaghnBzJKuD76hPsAH",
    "question": "The correct match between items I and II is : \n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-wrg0{font-size:22px;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-wv9z{font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-de48{font-weight:bold;font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\" colspan=\"2\">Item-I (Mixture)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\" colspan=\"2\">Item-II (Seperation method)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">H<sub>2</sub>O : Sugar</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">(P)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Sublimation</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">H<sub>2</sub>O : Aniline</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(Q)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">Recrystallization</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">H<sub>2</sub>O : Toluene<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(R)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">Steam distillation</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(S)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">Differential extraction</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "A$$ \\to $$(R); (B)$$ \\to $$(P); (C)$$ \\to $$(S)",
      "A$$ \\to $$(Q); (B)$$ \\to $$(R); (C)$$ \\to $$(S)",
      "A$$ \\to $$(Q); (B)$$ \\to $$(P); (C)$$ \\to $$(R)",
      "A$$ \\to $$(S); (B)$$ \\to $$(R); (C)$$ \\to $$(P)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "A$$ \\to $$(Q); (B)$$ \\to $$(R); (C)$$ \\to $$(S)"
  },
  {
    "id": "q5tdJRSJHrKWKmX9wX3rsa0w2w9jwve0kga",
    "question": "The principle of column chromatography is :",
    "options": [
      "Gravitational force.",
      "Capillary action.",
      "Differential adsorption of the substances on the solid phase.",
      "Differential absorption of the substances on the solid phase. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Differential adsorption of the substances on the solid phase."
  },
  {
    "id": "fDVEXjpq8DCMIPKMDb3rsa0w2w9jx0v14co",
    "question": "In chromatography, which of the following statements is incorrect for R<sub>f</sub> ?",
    "options": [
      "R<sub>f</sub>  value depends on the type of chromatography.",
      "Higher R<sub>f</sub>\n value means higher adsorption.",
      "R<sub>f</sub>\n value is dependent on the mobile phase.",
      "The value of R<sub>f</sub>\n can not be more than one. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Higher R<sub>f</sub>\n value means higher adsorption."
  },
  {
    "id": "BRVJh4m9wYYt5bKNK97k9k2k5hl9t26",
    "question": "Kjeldahl's method cannot be used to estimate\nnitrogen for which of the following\ncompounds?",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>",
      "$${\\rm{N}}{{\\rm{H}}_2} - \\mathop C\\limits^{\\mathop \\parallel \\limits^O }  - {\\rm{N}}{{\\rm{H}}_2}$$",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-C $$ \\equiv $$ N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "q5oG6rGSA4bQHkIhuSjgy2xukf2b70jx",
    "question": "Glycerol is separated in soap industries by :",
    "options": [
      "Fractional distillation",
      "Distillation under reduced pressure",
      "Differential extraction",
      "Steam distillation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Distillation under reduced pressure"
  },
  {
    "id": "bkKIzgyVNxE2Xdmcgn7k9k2k5h3fkgm",
    "question": "A flask contains a mixture of isohexane and 3-methylpentane. One of the liquids boils at 63<sup>o</sup>C while the\nother boils at 60<sup>o</sup>C What is the best way to separate the two liquids and which one will be distilled out first ?",
    "options": [
      "fractional distillation, 3-methylpentane",
      "simple distillation, 3-methylpentane",
      "fractional distillation, isohexane",
      "simple distillation, isohexane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "fractional distillation, isohexane"
  },
  {
    "id": "GCy75AHnQ2I3vh5l357k9k2k5epxn0x",
    "question": "A chromatography column, packed with silica gel as stationary phase, was used to separate a\nmixture of compounds consisting of (A) benzanilide (B) aniline and (C) acetophenone. When the\ncolumn is eluted with a mixture of solvents, hexane : ethylacelate (20:80), the sequence of\nobtained compounds is :",
    "options": [
      "(A), (B) and (C)",
      "(B), (A) and (C)",
      "(C), (A) and (B)\n",
      "(B), (C) and (A) "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "(C), (A) and (B)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "yTKueDaZTjGERgKmFP1klucw2q7",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : A mixture of chloroform and aniline can be separated by simple distillation.<br/><br/>Statement II : When separating aniline from a mixture of aniline and water by steam distillation aniline boils below its boiling point.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "fY08CRP8mlUgZk3BNo1kmht5wqw",
    "question": "In chromotography technique, the purification of compound is independent of :",
    "options": [
      "Solubility of the compound",
      "Mobility or flow of solvent system",
      "Physical state of the pure compound",
      "Length of the column or TLC plate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Physical state of the pure compound"
  },
  {
    "id": "TRbgXhH7Da5NP2lHnv1kmj85yjg",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : Retardation factor (R<sub>f</sub>) can be measured in meter/centimeter.<br/><br/>Statement II : R<sub>f</sub> value of a compound remains constant in all solvents.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Both statement I and statement II are false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt37ftf",
    "question": "Which purification technique is used for high boiling organic liquid compound (decomposes near its boiling point)?",
    "options": [
      "Simple distillation",
      "Steam ditillation",
      "Fractional distillation",
      "Reduced pressure distillation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Reduced pressure distillation"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktiedge7",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R) :<br/><br/>Assertion (A) : A simple distillation can be used to separate a mixture of propanol and propanone.<br/><br/>Reason (R) : Two liquids with a difference of more than 20$$^\\circ$$ in their boiling points can be separated by simple distillations.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A) is false but (R) is true.",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56b0tm8",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following techniques is not used to spot components of a mixture separated on thin layer chromatographic plate?</p>",
    "options": [
      "I<sub>2</sub> (Solid)",
      "U.V. Light",
      "Visualisation agent as a component of mobile phase",
      "Spraying of an appropriate reagent"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Visualisation agent as a component of mobile phase"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59r6ck3",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : A mixture contains benzoic acid and napthalene. The pure benzoic acid can be separated out by the use of benzene.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Benzoic acid is soluble in hot water.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "A is false but R is true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5am1psg",
    "question": "<p>Phenol on reaction with dilute nitric acid, gives two products. Which method will be most efficient for large scale separation?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Chromatographic separation",
      "Fractional Crystallisation",
      "Steam distillation",
      "Sublimation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Steam distillation"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gqmtwh",
    "question": "<p>Which technique among the following, is most appropriate in separation of a mixture of $$100 \\,\\mathrm{mg}$$ of $$p$$-nitrophenol and picric acid ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Steam distillation",
      "2-5 ft long column of silica gel",
      "Sublimation",
      "Preparative TLC (Thin Layer Chromatography)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Preparative TLC (Thin Layer Chromatography)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kr4j7b",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 497px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 53px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 208px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 40px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 196px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - I<br/>(Mixture)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - II<br/>(Purification Process)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Chloroform &amp; Aniline</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Steam distillation</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Benzoic acid &amp; Napthalene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Sublimation</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Water &amp; Aniline</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Distillation</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Napthalene &amp; Sodium chloride</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Crystallisation</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - (IV), (B) - (III), (C) - (I), (D) - (II)",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (I), (C) - (IV), (D) - (II)",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (IV), (C) - (II), (D) - (I)",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (IV), (C) - (I), (D) - (II)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "(A) - (III), (B) - (IV), (C) - (I), (D) - (II)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nx7lkp",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Thin layer chromatography is an adsorption chromatography.</p>\n<p>Reason R : A thin layer of silica gel is spread over a glass plate of suitable size in thin layer chromatography which acts as an adsorbent.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options  given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqx9epg",
    "question": "<p>Match List <b>I</b> with List <b>II</b>:</p>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\" colspan=\"2\"> List I (Mixture) </th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\" colspan=\"2\"> List II (Separation Technique) </th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\mathrm{CHCl}_3+\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_5 \\mathrm{NH}_2$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Steam distillation</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_{14}+\\mathrm{C}_5 \\mathrm{H}_{12}$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Differential extraction</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_5 \\mathrm{NH}_2+\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Distillation</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\text { Organic compound in } \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Fractional distillation</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-II, B-I, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnzeywd",
    "question": "Which of the following statement is correct for paper chromatography?",
    "options": [
      "Water present in the mobile phase gets absorbed by the paper which then forms the stationary phase.",
      "Water present in the pores of the paper forms the stationary phase.",
      " Paper sheet forms the stationary phase.",
      "Paper and water present in its pores together form the stationary phase."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Water present in the pores of the paper forms the stationary phase."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgygjxi9",
    "question": "<p>Using column chromatography, mixture of two compounds 'A' and 'B' was separated. 'A' eluted first, this indicates 'B' has</p>",
    "options": [
      "high R<sub>f</sub>, weaker adsorption",
      "high R<sub>f</sub>, stronger adsorption",
      "low R<sub>f</sub>, weaker adsorption",
      "low R<sub>f</sub>, stronger adsorption"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "low R<sub>f</sub>, stronger adsorption"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaoomjj",
    "question": "Lassaigne's test is used for detection of :",
    "options": [
      "Phosphorous and halogens only",
      "Nitrogen, Sulphur and Phosphorous only",
      "Nitrogen, Sulphur, phosphorous and halogens",
      "Nitrogen and Sulphur only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Nitrogen, Sulphur, phosphorous and halogens"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg7bpxi",
    "question": "<p>Which among the following purification methods is based on the principle of \"Solubility\" in two different solvents?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Distillation\n",
      "Sublimation\n",
      "Column Chromatography\n",
      "Differential Extraction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "Differential Extraction"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2ustl",
    "question": "<p>Methods used for purification of organic compounds are based on :</p>",
    "options": [
      "neither on nature of compound nor on the impurity present.\n",
      "presence of impurity only.\n",
      "nature of compound and presence of impurity.\n",
      "nature of compound only."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "purification-of-organic-compounds",
    "solution": "nature of compound and presence of impurity.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "xrkqpl1CM0uRLmnP",
    "question": "Due to the presence of an unpaired electron, free radicals are: ",
    "options": [
      "Chemically reactive ",
      "Chemically inactive ",
      "Anions ",
      "Cations"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "stability-of-intermediate",
    "solution": "Chemically reactive "
  },
  {
    "id": "LjyyB60NMFGhtJWy",
    "question": "The increasing order of stability of the following free radicals is",
    "options": [
      "$${({C_6}{H_5})_2}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  H$$ &lt; $${({C_6}{H_5})_3}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet$$ &lt; $${(C{H_3})_3}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  $$  &lt; $${(C{H_3})_2}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet H$$",
      "$${(C{H_3})_2}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet H$$ &lt; $${(C{H_3})_3}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  $$ &lt; $${({C_6}{H_5})_2}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  H$$ &lt; $${({C_6}{H_5})_3}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet$$ ",
      "$${(C{H_3})_2}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet H$$ &lt; $${(C{H_3})_3}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  $$  &lt;  $${({C_6}{H_5})_3}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet$$  &lt; $${({C_6}{H_5})_2}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  H$$",
      "$${({C_6}{H_5})_3}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet$$ &lt; $${({C_6}{H_5})_2}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  H$$ &lt; $${(C{H_3})_3}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  $$ &lt; $${(C{H_3})_2}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet H$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "stability-of-intermediate",
    "solution": "$${(C{H_3})_2}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet H$$ &lt; $${(C{H_3})_3}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  $$ &lt; $${({C_6}{H_5})_2}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  H$$ &lt; $${({C_6}{H_5})_3}\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "eYGmt6Fl9kJkT01k",
    "question": "Arrange the carbanions, $${(C{H_3})_3}\\overline C $$,  $$\\overline C C{l_3}$$ , $${(C{H_3})_2}\\overline C H$$, $${C_6}{H_5}\\overline C H{}_2$$ in order of their decreasing stability : ",
    "options": [
      "$${(C{H_3})_2}\\overline C H$$ &gt; $$\\overline C C{l_3}$$ &gt; $${C_6}{H_5}\\overline C H{}_2$$ &gt; $${(C{H_3})_3}\\overline C $$",
      "$$\\overline C C{l_3}$$ &gt; $${C_6}{H_5}\\overline C H{}_2$$ &gt; $${(C{H_3})_2}\\overline C H$$ &gt; $${(C{H_3})_3}\\overline C $$",
      "$${(C{H_3})_3}\\overline C $$ &gt; $${(C{H_3})_2}\\overline C H$$ &gt; $${C_6}{H_5}\\overline C H{}_2$$ &gt; $$\\overline C C{l_3}$$",
      "$${C_6}{H_5}\\overline C H{}_2$$ &gt; $$\\overline C C{l_3}$$ &gt; $${(C{H_3})_3}\\overline C $$ &gt; $${(C{H_3})_2}\\overline C H$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "stability-of-intermediate",
    "solution": "$$\\overline C C{l_3}$$ &gt; $${C_6}{H_5}\\overline C H{}_2$$ &gt; $${(C{H_3})_2}\\overline C H$$ &gt; $${(C{H_3})_3}\\overline C $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse75vwi",
    "question": "<p>A species having carbon with sextet of electrons and can act as electrophile is called</p>",
    "options": [
      "pentavalent carbon\n",
      "carbon free radical\n",
      "carbanion\n",
      "carbocation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "basics-of-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "stability-of-intermediate",
    "solution": "carbocation"
  },
  {
    "id": "BuZAVzF2vqhRzkUr",
    "question": "Complete hydrolysis of cellulose gives",
    "options": [
      "D-ribose",
      "D-glucose",
      "L-glucose",
      "D-fructose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "D-glucose"
  },
  {
    "id": "ieUYfKfGPDdWCryW",
    "question": "The term anomers of glucose refers to ",
    "options": [
      "isomers of glucose that differ in configurations at carbons one and four (C-1 and C-4) ",
      "a mixture of (D)-glucose and (L)-glucose",
      "enantiomers of glucose",
      "isomers of glucose that differ in configuration at carbon one (C-1) "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "isomers of glucose that differ in configuration at carbon one (C-1) "
  },
  {
    "id": "dFYewtGhC4QqZPCA",
    "question": "$$\\alpha$$-D-(+)-glucose and $$\\beta$$-D-(+)-glucose are ",
    "options": [
      "conformers ",
      "epimers",
      "anomers",
      "enantiomers "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "anomers"
  },
  {
    "id": "tZaaI1PWKGd1MHzl",
    "question": "The two functional groups present in a typical carbohydrate are ",
    "options": [
      "-OH and -COOH ",
      "-CHO and -COOH ",
      "&gt; C = O and - OH ",
      "- OH and -CHO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "- OH and -CHO"
  },
  {
    "id": "kKFos6LA4lSK8VZN",
    "question": "Which of the following compounds can be detected by Molisch’s test ?",
    "options": [
      "Nitro compounds",
      "Sugars",
      "Amines ",
      "Primary alcohols"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Sugars"
  },
  {
    "id": "joVTXbxTEZBU5iAeTql4A",
    "question": "The <b>incorrect</b> statement among the following is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\alpha $$-D-glucose and $$\\beta $$-D-glucose are anomers.",
      "$$\\alpha $$-D-glucose and $$\\beta $$-D-glucose are enantiomers.\n",
      "Cellulose is a straight chain polysaccharide made up of only $$\\beta $$-D-glucose units.",
      "The penta acetate of glucose does not react with hydroxyl amine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha $$-D-glucose and $$\\beta $$-D-glucose are enantiomers.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "fbTtGOhzwsOJq36I",
    "question": "Glucose on prolonged heating with HI gives",
    "options": [
      "6-iodohexanal",
      "n-Hexane",
      "1-Hexene",
      "Hexanoic acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "n-Hexane"
  },
  {
    "id": "4dNqKkyWU49a4qqoijv8L",
    "question": "Among the following, the <b>incorrect</b> statement is : ",
    "options": [
      "Maltose and  lactose has 1, 4 - glycosidic linkage. ",
      "Sucrose and amylose has 1,  2 - glycosidic linkage",
      "Cellulose and amylose has 1, 4 - glycosidic linkage. ",
      "Lactose contains $$\\beta $$-D-galactose and $$\\beta $$-D-glucose. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Sucrose and amylose has 1,  2 - glycosidic linkage"
  },
  {
    "id": "vTKXe0D78GZlj8GoRkPWz",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is not true\nabout sucrose?",
    "options": [
      "The glycosidic linkage is present between\nC<sub>1 </sub>of $$\\alpha $$-glucose and C<sub>1</sub> of $$\\beta $$-fructose",
      "It is also named as invert sugar",
      "It is a non reducing sugar",
      "On hydrolysis, it produces glucose and\nfructose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "The glycosidic linkage is present between\nC<sub>1 </sub>of $$\\alpha $$-glucose and C<sub>1</sub> of $$\\beta $$-fructose"
  },
  {
    "id": "iJqmxfLizA998lW0mZ3rsa0w2w9jx8566pb",
    "question": "Which of the given statements is <b>INCORRECT</b> about glycogen? ",
    "options": [
      "It is a straight chain polymer similar to amylose",
      "It is present in animal cells",
      "It is present in some yeast and fungi",
      "Only $$\\alpha $$-linkages are present in the molecule"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "It is a straight chain polymer similar to amylose"
  },
  {
    "id": "YraQEL0Ofcu85dbCjs3rsa0w2w9jx4y5gk5",
    "question": "Glucose and Galactose are having identical configuration in all the positions except position",
    "options": [
      "C–5",
      "C–3",
      "C–2",
      "C–4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "C–4"
  },
  {
    "id": "6vtDB7CTzoMoJOL3oO3rsa0w2w9jx0uhb35",
    "question": "Number of stereo centers present in linear and cyclic structures of glucose are respectively :",
    "options": [
      "4 &amp; 4\n",
      "4 &amp; 5",
      "5 &amp; 4",
      "5 &amp; 5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "4 &amp; 5"
  },
  {
    "id": "NdGJwR0pyAPFLpqg3e3rsa0w2w9jwuoj7tc",
    "question": "Amylopectin is compound of :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\alpha $$-D-glucose, C<sub>1</sub> – C<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>1</sub> – C<sub>6</sub> linkages",
      "$$\\beta $$-D-glucose, C<sub>1</sub> – C<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>2</sub> – C<sub>6</sub> linkages",
      "$$\\beta $$-D-glucose, C<sub>1</sub> – C<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>1</sub> – C<sub>6</sub> linkages",
      "$$\\alpha $$-D-glucose, C<sub>1</sub> – C<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>2</sub> – C<sub>6</sub> linkages"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha $$-D-glucose, C<sub>1</sub> – C<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>1</sub> – C<sub>6</sub> linkages"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZaXj9ZOX5MNxtwNjw6lES",
    "question": "Fructose and glucose can be distinguished by :",
    "options": [
      "Barfoed's test",
      "Fehling's test",
      "Seliwanoff's test",
      "Benedict's test"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Seliwanoff's test"
  },
  {
    "id": "5rKtX9Wupmhw9vr0q7Mrk",
    "question": "Maltose on treatment with dilute HCI gives :",
    "options": [
      "D-Galactose",
      "D-Glucose and D-Fructose",
      "D-Glucose",
      "D-Fructose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "D-Glucose"
  },
  {
    "id": "xn9nIBoi2hl0RxspRb7k9k2k5h6f056",
    "question": "Which of the following statement is not true for glucose?",
    "options": [
      "Glucose gives Schiff's test for aldehyde",
      "Glucosse reacts with hydroxylamine to form oxime",
      "The pentaacetate of glucose does not react with hydroxylamine to give oxime",
      "Glucose exists in two crystalline forms $$\\alpha $$ and $$\\beta $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Glucose gives Schiff's test for aldehyde"
  },
  {
    "id": "TZIEsWcPSEVUXC603sjgy2xukg0ls23c",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is not\ntrue?",
    "options": [
      "Lactose contains $$\\alpha $$-glycosidic linkage\nbetween C<sub>1</sub> of galactose and C<sub>4</sub> of glucose",
      "Lactose is a reducing sugar and it gives\nFehling’s test",
      "On acid hydrolysis, lactose gives one\nmolecule of D(+)-glucose and one molecule\nof D(+)-galactose",
      "Lactose (C<sub>11</sub>H<sub>22</sub>O<sub>11</sub>) is a disaccharide and it\ncontains 8 hydroxyl groups"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Lactose contains $$\\alpha $$-glycosidic linkage\nbetween C<sub>1</sub> of galactose and C<sub>4</sub> of glucose"
  },
  {
    "id": "kmM8LnBf6Z55XpJT4ljgy2xukf7t0ok8",
    "question": "What are the functional groups present in the\nstructure of maltose?",
    "options": [
      "One acetal and one ketal",
      "One ketal and one hemiketal",
      "Two acetals",
      "One acetal and one hemiacetal"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "One acetal and one hemiacetal"
  },
  {
    "id": "931LtLVZBBbpfVSHyc7k9k2k5hlpczl",
    "question": "Two monomers in maltose are :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\alpha $$-D-glucose and $$\\alpha $$-D-galactose",
      "$$\\alpha $$-D-glucose and $$\\alpha $$-D-Fructose",
      "$$\\alpha $$-D-glucose and $$\\alpha $$-D-glucose",
      "$$\\alpha $$-D-glucose and $$\\beta $$-D-glucose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha $$-D-glucose and $$\\alpha $$-D-glucose"
  },
  {
    "id": "9N8KZ1rvROd8fj8T0Z7k9k2k5epzfsj",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct ?\n",
    "options": [
      "Gluconic acid can from cyclic (acteal/hemiacetal) structure",
      "Gluconic acid is a partial oxidation product of glucose",
      "Gluconic acid is obtained by oxidation of glucose with (HNO<sub>3</sub>)",
      "Gluconic acid is a dicarboxylic acid."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Gluconic acid is a partial oxidation product of glucose"
  },
  {
    "id": "GX3vCjablV4iSUWTmP1kls919p2",
    "question": "Which of the glycosidic linkage between galactose and glucose is present in lactose?",
    "options": [
      "C-1 of galactose and C-6 of glucose",
      "C-1 of glucose and C-6 of galactose",
      "C-1 of galactose and C-4 of glucose",
      "C-1 of glucose and C-4 of galactose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "C-1 of galactose and C-4 of glucose"
  },
  {
    "id": "QhI1shzNkBpOJbFhIg1kluslgus",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table style=\"width:100%\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I </th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Sucrose</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>$$\\beta $$-D-Galactose and $$\\beta $$-D-Glucose</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Lactose</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>$$\\alpha $$-D-Glucose and $$\\beta $$-D-Fructose</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Maltose</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>$$\\alpha $$-D-Glucose and $$\\alpha $$-D-Glucose</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (i)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (i), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (ii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (i), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (i), (c) $$ \\to $$ (ii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "(a) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (i), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "dFwKahA2nUbtH4lwFC1kmki21jj",
    "question": "$${C_{12}}{H_{22}}{O_{11}} + {H_2}O\\buildrel {Enzyme\\,A} \\over\n \\longrightarrow \\mathop {{C_6}{H_{12}}{O_6}}\\limits_{Glu\\cos e}  + \\mathop {{C_6}{H_{12}}{O_6}}\\limits_{Fructose} $$<br/><br/>$$\\mathop {{C_6}{H_{12}}{O_6}}\\limits_{Glu\\cos e} \\buildrel {Enzyme\\,B} \\over\n \\longrightarrow 2{C_2}{H_5}OH + 2C{O_2}$$<br/><br/>In the above reactions, the enzyme A and enzyme B respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "Zymase and Invertase",
      "Invertase and Amylase",
      "Amylase and Invertase",
      "Invertase and Zymase"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Invertase and Zymase"
  },
  {
    "id": "UACK82Cmm2rR7QsgIA1kmkj7wz5",
    "question": "Fructose is an example of :",
    "options": [
      "Heptose",
      "Pyranose",
      "Ketohexose",
      "Aldohexose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Ketohexose"
  },
  {
    "id": "8HAgYyyXLFIMJAalcd1kmlmg8x6",
    "question": "A non-reducing sugar \"A\" hydrolyses to give two reducing mono saccharides. Sugar A is ",
    "options": [
      "Fructose",
      "Galactose",
      "Glucose",
      "Sucrose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Sucrose"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq68vqf",
    "question": "Identify the incorrect statement from the following",
    "options": [
      "Amylose is a branched chain polymer of glucose",
      "Starch is a polymer of $$\\alpha$$-D glucose",
      "$$\\beta$$-Glycosidic linkage makes cellulose polymer",
      "Glycogen is called as animal starch"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Amylose is a branched chain polymer of glucose"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz0znag",
    "question": "Which one among the following chemical tests is used to distinguish monosaccharide from disaccharide?",
    "options": [
      "Seliwanoff's test",
      "Iodine test",
      "Barfoed test",
      "Tollen's test"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Barfoed test"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1i2aoh",
    "question": "Compound A gives D-Galactose and D-Glucose on hydrolysis. The compound A is :",
    "options": [
      "Amylose",
      "Sucrose",
      "Maltose",
      "Lactose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Lactose"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktco1160",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and other is labelled as Reason (R). <br/><br/>Assertion (A) : Sucrose is a disaccharide and a non-reducing sugar.<br/><br/>Reason (R) : Sucrose involves glycosidic linkage between C<sub>1</sub> of $$\\beta$$-glucose and C<sub>2</sub> of $$\\alpha$$-fructose.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the true explanation of (A).",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true.",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false.",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the true explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "(A) is true but (R) is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfsnmdl",
    "question": "Hydrolysis of sucrose gives :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\alpha$$-D-($$-$$)-Glucose and $$\\beta$$-D-($$-$$)-Fructose",
      "$$\\alpha$$-D-(+)-Glucose and $$\\alpha$$-D-($$-$$)-Fructose",
      "$$\\alpha$$-D-($$-$$)-Glucose and $$\\alpha$$-D-(+)-Fructose",
      "$$\\alpha$$-D-(+)-Glucose and $$\\beta$$-D-($$-$$)-Fructose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha$$-D-(+)-Glucose and $$\\beta$$-D-($$-$$)-Fructose"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktiab4nh",
    "question": "Which one of the following compounds contains $$\\beta$$-C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> glycosidic linkage?",
    "options": [
      "Lactose",
      "Sucrose",
      "Maltose",
      "Amylose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Lactose"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55nq14v",
    "question": "<p>When sugar 'X' is boiled with dilute H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> in alcoholic solution, two isomers 'A' and 'B' are formed. 'A' on oxidation with HNO<sub>3</sub> yields saccharic acid where as 'B' is laevorotatory. The compound 'X' is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Maltose",
      "Sucrose",
      "Lactose",
      "Starch"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Sucrose"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56y9in6",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements.</p>\n<p>Statement I : Maltose has two $$\\alpha$$-D-glucose units linked at C<sub>1</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> and is a reducing sugar.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Maltose has two monosaccharides : $$\\alpha$$-D-glucose and $$\\beta$$-D-glucose linked at C<sub>1</sub> and C<sub>6</sub> and it is a non-reducing sugar.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c6wjl4",
    "question": "<p>A polysaccharide 'X' on boiling with dil H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> at 393 K under 2-3 atm pressure yields 'Y'. 'Y' on treatment with bromine water gives gluconic acid. 'X' contains $$\\beta$$-glycosidic linkages only. Compound 'X' is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "starch",
      "cellulose",
      "amylose",
      "amylopectin"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "cellulose"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f7f5u7",
    "question": "<p>Glycosidic linkage between C<sub>1</sub> of $$\\alpha$$-glucose and C<sub>2</sub> of $$\\beta$$-fructose is found in</p>",
    "options": [
      "maltose",
      "sucrose",
      "lactose",
      "amylose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "sucrose"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i5nzqq",
    "question": "<p>Animal starch is the other name of</p>",
    "options": [
      "amylose.",
      "maltose.",
      "glycogen.",
      "amylopectin."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "glycogen."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jm1e8m",
    "question": "<p>A sugar 'X' dehydrates very slowly under acidic condition to give furfural which on further reaction with resorcinol gives the coloured product after sometime. Sugar 'X' is</p>",
    "options": [
      "Aldopentose",
      "Aldotetrose",
      "Oxalic acid",
      "Ketotetrose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Aldopentose"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kqzpez",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with Match List - II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 485px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 53px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 196px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 40px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 196px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Glucose + HI</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Gluconic acid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Glucose + Br$$_2$$ water</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Glucose pentacetate</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Glucose + acetic anhydride</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Saccharic acid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Glucose + HNO$$_3$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Hexane</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - (IV), (B) - (I), (C) -(II), (D) - (III)",
      "(A) - (IV), (B) - (III), (C) -(II), (D) - (I)",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (I), (C) -(IV), (D) - (II)",
      "(A) - (I), (B) - (III), (C) -(IV), (D) - (II)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "(A) - (IV), (B) - (I), (C) -(II), (D) - (III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rl2ubr",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements. One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A: Amylose is insoluble in water.</p>\n<p>Reason R: Amylose is a long linear molecule with more than 200 glucose units.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$.",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$.",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is not correct",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is not correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is not correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldojeb80",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 596px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 51px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 226px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 273px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-amwm\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-amwm\">Test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-amwm\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-amwm\">Functional group / Class of Compound</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Molisch's Test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Peptide</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Biuret Test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Carbohydrate</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Carbylamine Test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Primary amine</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Schiff's Test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Aldehyde</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - III, (B) - IV, (C) - II, (D) - I",
      "(A) - II, (B) - I, (C) - III, (D) - IV",
      "(A) - III, (B) - IV, (C) - I, (D) - II",
      "(A) - I, (B) - II, (C) - III, (D) - IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "(A) - II, (B) - I, (C) - III, (D) - IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr3hbj4",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : Ketoses give Seliwanoff's test faster than Aldoses.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Ketoses undergo $$\\beta$$-elimination followed by formation of furfural.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) is false but (R) is true",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "(A) is true but (R) is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7270g",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 523px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 70px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 184px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 94px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 175px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">Glucose/$$\\mathrm{NaHCO_3/\\Delta}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Gluconic acid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$$\\text { Glucose } / \\mathrm{HNO}_3$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">No reaction</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$$\\text { Glucose } / \\mathrm{HI} / \\Delta$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">n-hexane</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">Glucose/Bromine water</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Saccharic acid</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I",
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV\n",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II\n",
      "A-I, B-IV, C-III, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfmi0q1",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 523px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 70px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 184px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 94px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 175px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - I<br/>(Bio Polymer)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - II<br/>(Monomer)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Starch</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">nucleotide</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Cellulose</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\alpha$$-glucose</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Nucleic acid</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\beta$$-glucose</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Protein</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\alpha$$-amino acid</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-II, C-I, D-III\n",
      "A-I, B-III, C-IV, D-II\n",
      "A-II, B-I, C-III, D-IV\n",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgy8oql",
    "question": "<p>Sugar which does not give reddish brown precipitate with Fehling's reagent, is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Glucose\n",
      "Sucrose\n",
      "Lactose\n",
      "Maltose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Sucrose\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxzq693",
    "question": "<p>The incorrect statement about Glucose is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Glucose remains in multiple isomeric form in its aqueous solution\n",
      "Glucose is soluble in water because of having aldehyde functional group\n",
      "Glucose is an aldohexose\n",
      "Glucose is one of the monomer unit in sucrose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "Glucose is soluble in water because of having aldehyde functional group\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2eryxe",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 664px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 262px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\alpha$$ - Glucose and $$\\alpha$$ - Galactose</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Functional isomers</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\alpha \\text { - Glucose and } \\beta \\text { - Glucose }<br/>$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Homologous  </td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\alpha \\text { - Glucose and } \\alpha \\text { - Fructose }<br/>$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Anomers</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\alpha \\text { - Glucose and } \\alpha \\text { - Ribose }<br/>$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Epimers</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I\n",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "carbohydrates",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "3fVsM8OaomHwGegB",
    "question": "The functional group, which is found in amino acid is",
    "options": [
      "-COOH group",
      "-NH<sub>2</sub> group",
      "-CH<sub>3</sub> group",
      "both (a) and (b)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "both (a) and (b)"
  },
  {
    "id": "66NHlZF5ZVy4XoJz",
    "question": "Identify the correct statements regarding enzymes",
    "options": [
      "Enzymes are specific biological catalysts that can normally function at very high\ntemperature (T ~ 1000 K) ",
      "Enzymes are specific biological catalysts that the posses well – defined active sites ",
      "Enzymes are specific biological catalysts that can not be poisoned ",
      "Enzymes are normally heterogeneous catalysts that are very specific in their action "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Enzymes are specific biological catalysts that the posses well – defined active sites "
  },
  {
    "id": "MbSqitW9IUkfMgCz",
    "question": "Insulin production and its action in human body are responsible for the level of diabetes. This\ncompound belongs to which of the following categories? ",
    "options": [
      "A co- enzyme",
      "An antibiotic ",
      "An enzyme",
      "A hormone "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "A hormone "
  },
  {
    "id": "uBWnxySe3vx4UZKN",
    "question": "The secondary structure of a protein refers to ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\alpha$$-helical backbone",
      "hydrophobic interactions",
      "sequence of $$\\alpha$$-amino acids",
      "fixed configuration of the polypeptide backbone"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha$$-helical backbone"
  },
  {
    "id": "UjS12aJLafFvBDdT",
    "question": "Biuret test is <b>not</b> given by",
    "options": [
      "carbohydrates",
      "polypeptides",
      "urea",
      "proteins"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "carbohydrates"
  },
  {
    "id": "vGuKG40v1hU3iNIA",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is correct ?",
    "options": [
      "All amino acids except lysine are optically active",
      "All amino acids are optically active\n",
      "All amino acids except glycine are optically active",
      "All amino acids except glutamic acid are optically active\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "All amino acids except glycine are optically active"
  },
  {
    "id": "6451t5ZoWHeJvsVK",
    "question": "Synthesis of each molecule of glucose in photosynthesis involves: ",
    "options": [
      "10 molecules of ATP",
      "8 molecules of ATP ",
      "6 molecules of ATP ",
      "18 molecules of ATP"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "18 molecules of ATP"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ync0jVKYZTR6amAnjUMGZ",
    "question": "Observation of “Rhumann’s purple” is a confirmatory test for the presence of :\n",
    "options": [
      "Reducing sugar",
      "Cupric ion",
      "Protein",
      "Starch"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Protein"
  },
  {
    "id": "BH6tULGqrH8TBtOf",
    "question": "Thiol group is present in :",
    "options": [
      "Cytosine",
      "Cystine",
      "Cysteine ",
      "Methionine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Cysteine "
  },
  {
    "id": "qGVXiPGs5uKY8fUJN5smr",
    "question": "Among the following, the essential amino acid is :",
    "options": [
      "Alanine",
      "Valine",
      "Aspartic acid ",
      "Serine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Valine"
  },
  {
    "id": "RD0H7VIPO9MdGNYsrFqAs",
    "question": "The correct match between Item I and Item II is :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-nhda{font-size:22px;border-color:inherit;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-0xlv{font-weight:bold;font-size:22px;border-color:inherit;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-9d8n{font-size:22px;border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0xlv\" colspan=\"2\">Item I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0xlv\" colspan=\"2\">Item <span style=\"font-weight:700\">II</span></th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-nhda\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-nhda\">Ester test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-nhda\">(P)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-nhda\">Tyr</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">Carbylamine test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">(Q)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">Asp</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">Phthalein dye test<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">(R)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">Ser</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">(S)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">Lys</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "(A)$$ \\to $$(Q); (B)$$ \\to $$(S); (C)$$ \\to $$(P)",
      "(A)$$ \\to $$(R); (B)$$ \\to $$(S); (C)$$ \\to $$(Q)",
      "(A)$$ \\to $$(R); (B)$$ \\to $$(Q); (C)$$ \\to $$(P)",
      "(A)$$ \\to $$(Q); (B)$$ \\to $$(S); (C)$$ \\to $$(R)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "(A)$$ \\to $$(Q); (B)$$ \\to $$(S); (C)$$ \\to $$(P)"
  },
  {
    "id": "133K4VCn7QfsukBrIHsVK",
    "question": "The peptide that gives positive ceric\nammonium nitrate and carbylamine tests is :",
    "options": [
      "Ser-Lys",
      "Asp-Gln",
      "Gln-Asp",
      "Lys-Asp"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Ser-Lys"
  },
  {
    "id": "HW1ukj6b1j368xnL1Hg2d",
    "question": "The correct statement (s) among I to III with respect to potassium ions that are abundant within the cell fluid\nis /are \n<br/>I. They activate many enzymes \n<br/>II. They participate in the oxidation of glucose to produce ATP \n<br/>III. Along with sodium ions they are responsible for the transmission of nerve signals",
    "options": [
      "III only ",
      "I and II only ",
      "I and III only ",
      "I, II and III only "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "I, II and III only "
  },
  {
    "id": "v7XRrlKIMGrlUbverYrnU",
    "question": "Among the following compounds most basic amino acid is - ",
    "options": [
      "Lysine",
      "Asparagine ",
      "Histidine ",
      "Serine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Lysine"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ju7MKvcDmXaFE38YBqdM7",
    "question": "Which of the following tests cannot be used for identifying amino acids? ",
    "options": [
      "Ninhydrin test ",
      "Barfoed test \n",
      "Xanthoproteic test",
      "Biuret test \n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Barfoed test \n"
  },
  {
    "id": "DoVmhIIJy0ohCCmDVARNW",
    "question": "The increasing order of pka of the following amino acids in aqueous solution is : <br/><br>\nGly,  Asp, Lys,  Arg</br>",
    "options": [
      "Asp  &lt;  Gly  &lt; Arg  &lt; Lys",
      "Gly  &lt;  Asp   &lt;  Arg  &lt;  Lys",
      "Asp  &lt;  Gly  &lt;  Lys  &lt;  Arg",
      "Arg  &lt;  Lys  &lt; Gly  &lt;  Asp"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Asp  &lt;  Gly  &lt;  Lys  &lt;  Arg"
  },
  {
    "id": "iuqCHmH9eRV9JKc3g6jgy2xukfi6r5kv",
    "question": "Which of the following is not an essential\namino acid :",
    "options": [
      "Valine",
      "Leucine",
      "Lysine",
      "Tyrosine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Tyrosine"
  },
  {
    "id": "JOH5zQORaQTWcrss1O1klrecuw2",
    "question": "Out of the following, which type of interaction is reponsible for the stabilisation of $$\\alpha $$-helix structure of proteins ?",
    "options": [
      "Covalent bonding",
      "vander Waals forces",
      "Ionic bonding",
      "Hydrogen bonding"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Hydrogen bonding"
  },
  {
    "id": "dLhOspn1sdHgGaLu5z1kmitr5g6",
    "question": "The secondary structure of protein is stabilised by:",
    "options": [
      "Hydrogen bonding",
      "glycosidic bond",
      "Peptide bond",
      "van der Waals forces"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Hydrogen bonding"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krri516o",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is not true about enzymes?",
    "options": [
      "Enzymes are non-specific for a reaction and substrate.",
      "Almost all enzymes are proteins.",
      "Enzymes work as catalysts by lowering the activation energy of a biochemical reaction.",
      "The action of enzymes is temperature and pH specific."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Enzymes are non-specific for a reaction and substrate."
  },
  {
    "id": "1kruryaji",
    "question": "The water soluble protein is :",
    "options": [
      "Fibrin",
      "Albumin",
      "Myosin",
      "Collagen"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Albumin"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjvf3ck",
    "question": "Which of the following is not an example of fibrous protein?",
    "options": [
      "Keratin",
      "Albumin",
      "Collagen",
      "Myosin"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Albumin"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54yuu6n",
    "question": "<p>The structure of protein that is unaffected by heating is</p>",
    "options": [
      "secondary structure",
      "tertiary structure",
      "primary structure",
      "quaternary structure"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "primary structure"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56b8jyd",
    "question": "<p>Stability of $$\\alpha$$-Helix structure of proteins depends upon</p>",
    "options": [
      "dipolar interaction",
      "H-bonding interaction",
      "van der Waals forces",
      "$$\\pi$$-stacking interaction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "H-bonding interaction"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58iw1xa",
    "question": "<p>Match List-I with List-II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 545px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 44px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 202px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 42px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 257px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - I <br/>Enzyne</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - II<br/>Conversion of</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Invertase</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Starch into maltose</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Zymase</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Maltose into glucose</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Diastase</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Glucose into ethanol</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Maltase</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Cane sugar into glucose</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I",
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-III, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6e1qe0j",
    "question": "<p>During the denaturation of proteins, which of these structures will remain intact?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Primary",
      "Secondary",
      "Tertiary",
      "Quaternary"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Primary"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldo25rd6",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : $$\\alpha$$-halocarboxylic acid on reaction with dil. $$\\mathrm{NH_3}$$ gives good yield of $$\\alpha$$-amino carboxylic acid whereas the yield of amines is very low when prepared from alkyl halides.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Amino acids exist in zwitter ion form in aqueous medium.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct",
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsrecfw",
    "question": "<p>Number of cyclic tripeptides formed with 2 amino acids A and B is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "3",
      "5",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyg5fos",
    "question": "<p>The one that does not stabilize 2$$^\\circ$$ and 3$$^\\circ$$ structures of proteins is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$O $$-$$O $$-$$linkage",
      "$$-$$S $$-$$S $$-$$linkage",
      "van der Waals forces",
      "H-bonding"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "$$-$$O $$-$$O $$-$$linkage"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh03ehcq",
    "question": "<p>Sulphur (S) containing amino acids from the following are:</p>\n<p>(a) isoleucine (b) cysteine (c) lysine (d) methionine (e) glutamic acid</p>",
    "options": [
      "b, d",
      "a, d",
      "b, c, e",
      "a, b, c"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "b, d"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh28w6g2",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 616px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 258px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I <br/>Enzymatic reaction</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II <br/>Enzyme</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Sucrose $$\\to$$ Glocuse and Fructose</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Zymase</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Glucose $$\\to$$ ethyl alcohol and CO$$_2$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Pepsin</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Starch $$\\to$$ Maltose</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Invertase</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Proteins $$\\to$$ Amino acids</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Diastase</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-I, B-IV, C-III, D-II",
      "A-I, B-II, C-IV, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscqhxvw",
    "question": "<p>Which structure of protein remains intact after coagulation of egg white on boiling?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Quaternary\n",
      "Primary",
      "Secondary\n",
      "Tertiary"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Primary"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjihy9",
    "question": "<p>Type of amino acids obtained by hydrolysis of proteins is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\gamma$$\n",
      "$$\\beta$$\n",
      "$$\\alpha$$\n",
      "$$\\delta$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3yxk",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following gives a positive test with ninhydrin ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Polyvinyl chloride\n",
      "Cellulose\n",
      "Egg albumin\n",
      "Starch"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Egg albumin\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s2lk7",
    "question": "<p>Coagulation of egg, on heating is because of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Denaturation of protein occurs\n",
      "Biological property of protein remains unchanged\n",
      "Breaking of the peptide linkage in the primary structure of protein occurs\n",
      "The secondary structure of protein remains unchanged"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "Denaturation of protein occurs\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2a7u8",
    "question": "<p>The incorrect statements regarding enzymes are :</p>\n<p>(A) Enzymes are biocatalysts.</p>\n<p>(B) Enzymes are non-specific and can catalyse different kinds of reactions.</p>\n<p>(C) Most Enzymes are globular proteins.</p>\n<p>(D) Enzyme - oxidase catalyses the hydrolysis of maltose into glucose.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the option given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(B) and (D)\n",
      "(A), (B) and (C)\n",
      "(B) and (C)\n",
      "(B), (C) and (D)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "proteins-and-enzymes",
    "solution": "(B) and (D)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jLY8ENtJBMUyc3cU",
    "question": "RNA is different from DNA because RNA contains",
    "options": [
      "ribose sugar and thymine",
      "ribose sugar and uracil",
      "deoxyribose sugar and thymine",
      "deoxyribose sugar and uracil"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "ribose sugar and uracil"
  },
  {
    "id": "jL6YYBoCzBT9Mnuy",
    "question": "The reason for double helical structure of $$DNA$$ is operation of ",
    "options": [
      "dipole-dipole interaction",
      "hydrogen bonding",
      "electrostatic attractions ",
      "van der Waals' forces"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "hydrogen bonding"
  },
  {
    "id": "TBPo9VJBXPkzOCYZ",
    "question": "Which base is present in RNA but not in DNA? ",
    "options": [
      "Uracil ",
      "Thymine",
      "Guanine",
      "Cytosine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "Uracil "
  },
  {
    "id": "Ufmrx2EyxtqgD60p",
    "question": "In both DNA and RNA, heterocyclic base and phosphate ester linkages are at- ",
    "options": [
      "$$C_5^{'}$$ and $$C_2^{'}$$ respectively of the sugar molecule",
      "$$C_2^{'}$$ and $$C_5^{'}$$ respectively of the sugar molecule",
      "$$C_1^{'}$$ and $$C_5^{'}$$ respectively of the sugar molecule",
      "$$C_5^{'}$$ and $$C_1^{'}$$ respectively of the sugar molecule "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "$$C_1^{'}$$ and $$C_5^{'}$$ respectively of the sugar molecule"
  },
  {
    "id": "k4ew6C8Q43Mw3sAj",
    "question": "The pyrimidine bases present in DNA are ",
    "options": [
      "cytosine and adenine",
      "cytosine and guanine",
      "cytosine and thymine ",
      "cytosine and uracil "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "cytosine and thymine "
  },
  {
    "id": "ansyTTYSZi2QFdWS",
    "question": "The presence or absence of hydroxyl group on which carbon atom of sugar differentiates RNA and DNA ? ",
    "options": [
      "2<sup>nd</sup>",
      "3<sup>rd</sup> ",
      "4<sup>th</sup>",
      "1<sup>st</sup> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "2<sup>nd</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "bCoAkDQsvbeCdFkG",
    "question": "Which one of the following bases is <b>not</b> present in DNA?",
    "options": [
      "Cytosine",
      "Thymine",
      "Quinoline",
      "Adenine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "Quinoline"
  },
  {
    "id": "tt65GxVDHU4gGy2D",
    "question": "Which of the vitamins given below is water soluble?",
    "options": [
      "Vitamin D",
      "Vitamin E",
      "Vitamin K",
      "Vitamin C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "Vitamin C"
  },
  {
    "id": "4A8YA1GKIJUjMwmsAF3rsa0w2w9jx4yz9x9",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is not true about RNA?",
    "options": [
      "It controls the synthesis of protein",
      "It is present in the nucleus of the cell",
      "It usually does not replicate",
      "It has always double stranded $$\\alpha $$-helix structure"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "It has always double stranded $$\\alpha $$-helix structure"
  },
  {
    "id": "5mmfxVtbZtr0qF7NUE7k9k2k5dz920k",
    "question": "Match the following :<br/>\n(i) Riboflavin    (a) Beriberi<br/>\n(ii) Thiamine    (b) Scurvy<br/>\n(iii) Pyridoxine   (c) Cheliosis<br/>\n(iv) Ascorbic acid    (d) Convulsions<br/>",
    "options": [
      "(i)-(c), (ii)-(d), (iii)-(a), (iv)-(b)",
      "(i)-(d), (ii)-(b), (iii)-(a), (iv)-(c)",
      "(i)-c, (ii)-(a), (iii)-(d), (iv)-(b)",
      "(i)-(a), (ii)-(d), (iii)-(c), (iv)-(b)\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "(i)-c, (ii)-(a), (iii)-(d), (iv)-(b)"
  },
  {
    "id": "gV2GC1RoAGl8RiZOWyjgy2xukf7swod4",
    "question": "Which of the following will react with CHCl<sub>3</sub> +\nalc. KOH?",
    "options": [
      "Adenine and thymine",
      "Thymine and proline",
      "Adenine and lysine",
      "Adenine and proline"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "Adenine and lysine"
  },
  {
    "id": "tl6X7wPyrNZzx24GAB1klruo0a8",
    "question": "Match List - I and List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Valium</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Antifertility drug</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Morphine</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Pernicious anaemia</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Norethindrone</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Analgesic</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Vitamin $${B_{12}}$$</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Tranquilizer</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(iii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "KOHl5FYW6dAS5l09NH1kludzqls",
    "question": "Which of the following vitamin is helpful in delaying the blood clotting?",
    "options": [
      "Vitamin K",
      "Vitamin C",
      "Vitamin E",
      "Vitamin B"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "Vitamin K"
  },
  {
    "id": "eMkBQqrHHud2tzfoyx1kmhtnuq9",
    "question": "Which among the following pairs of Vitamins is stored in our body relatively for longer duration?",
    "options": [
      "Thiamine and Vitamin A",
      "Ascorbic acid and Vitamin D",
      "Thiamine and Ascorbic acid",
      "Vitamin A and Vitamin D"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "Vitamin A and Vitamin D"
  },
  {
    "id": "rrI6YXMGjiI2fxj2Qc1kmm0d75c",
    "question": "Deficiency of vitamin K causes :",
    "options": [
      "Cheilosis",
      "Decrease in blood clotting time",
      "Increase in blood clotting time",
      "Increase in fragility of RBC's"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "Increase in blood clotting time"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt57bdl",
    "question": "Thiamine and pyridoxine are also known respectively as :",
    "options": [
      "Vitamin B<sub>2</sub> and Vitamin E",
      "Vitamin E and Vitamin B<sub>2</sub>",
      "Vitamin B<sub>6</sub> and Vitamin B<sub>2</sub>",
      "Vitamin B<sub>1</sub> and Vitamin B<sub>6</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "Vitamin B<sub>1</sub> and Vitamin B<sub>6</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l549r7g9",
    "question": "<p>Sugar moiety in DNA and RNA molecules respectively are</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\beta$$-D-2-deoxyribose, $$\\beta$$-D-deoxyribose.",
      "$$\\beta$$-D-2-deoxyribose, $$\\beta$$-D-ribose",
      "$$\\beta$$-D-ribose, $$\\beta$$-D-2-deoxyribose.",
      "$$\\beta$$-D-deoxyribose, $$\\beta$$-D-2-deoxyribose."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "$$\\beta$$-D-2-deoxyribose, $$\\beta$$-D-ribose"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58jz7v2",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following is a water soluble vitamin, that is not excreted easily?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Vitamin B<sub>2</sub>",
      "Vitamin B<sub>1</sub>",
      "Vitamin B<sub>6</sub>",
      "Vitamin B<sub>12</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "Vitamin B<sub>12</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w6evbk",
    "question": "<p>The sugar produced after complete hydrolysis of DNA is</p>",
    "options": [
      "a pentose sugar.",
      "a hexose sugar.",
      "a polysaccharide.",
      "a disaccharide."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "a pentose sugar."
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnzgm5p",
    "question": "Which is not true for arginine?",
    "options": [
      "It has a fairly high melting point.",
      "It is associated with more than one $\\mathrm{pK}_{\\mathrm{a}}$ values.",
      "It has high solubility in benzene.",
      "It is a crystalline solid. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "It has high solubility in benzene."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp2jfq1",
    "question": "<p>The naturally occurring amino acid that contains only one basic functional group in its chemical structure is</p>",
    "options": [
      "asparagine",
      "arginine",
      "histidine",
      "lysine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "asparagine"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgysfdkf",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 658px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 300px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST I<br/>Natural amino acid</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST II<br/>One letter code</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Glutamic acid</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Q</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Glutamine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">W</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Tyrosine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">E</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Tryptophan</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Y</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh32d6j3",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 616px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 258px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I <br/>Natural Amino Acid</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II <br/>One Letter Code</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Arginine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Aspartic acid</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">N</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Asparagine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Alanine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">R</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - IV, (B) - I, (C) - III, (D) - II",
      "(A) - III, (B) - I, (C) - II, (D) - IV",
      "(A) - IV, (B) - I, (C) - II, (D) - III",
      "(A) - I, (B) - III, (C) - IV, (D) - II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "(A) - IV, (B) - I, (C) - II, (D) - III"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbmnxvx",
    "question": "If one strand of a DNA has the sequence ATGCTTCA, sequence of the bases in complementary strand is :",
    "options": [
      "CATTAGCT",
      "TACGAAGT",
      "ATGCGACT",
      "GTACTTAC"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "TACGAAGT"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc4rx0p",
    "question": "<p>Two nucleotides are joined together by a linkage known as :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Phosphodiester linkage\n",
      "Glycosidic linkage\n",
      "Disulphide linkage\n",
      "Peptide linkage"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "Phosphodiester linkage\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2uu5m",
    "question": "<p>The $$\\mathrm{F}^{-}$$ ions make the enamel on teeth much harder by converting hydroxyapatite (the enamel on the surface of teeth) into much harder fluoroapatite having the formula.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[3\\left(\\mathrm{Ca}_3\\left(\\mathrm{PO}_4\\right)_2\\right) \\cdot \\mathrm{CaF}_2\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[3\\left(\\mathrm{Ca}_3\\left(\\mathrm{PO}_4\\right)_2\\right) \\cdot \\mathrm{Ca}(\\mathrm{OH})_2\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[3\\left(\\mathrm{Ca}_3\\left(\\mathrm{PO}_4\\right)_3\\right) \\cdot \\mathrm{CaF}_2\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[3\\left(\\mathrm{Ca}_2\\left(\\mathrm{PO}_4\\right)_2\\right) \\cdot \\mathrm{Ca}(\\mathrm{OH})_2\\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "biomolecules",
    "topic": "vitamins-and-nucleic-acids",
    "solution": "$$\\left[3\\left(\\mathrm{Ca}_3\\left(\\mathrm{PO}_4\\right)_2\\right) \\cdot \\mathrm{CaF}_2\\right]$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "4cdlCNiVegCDNUzm",
    "question": "The bond dissociation energy of B - F in BF<sub>3</sub> is 646 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup> whereas that of C - F in CF<sub>4</sub> is 515 kj mol<sup>-1</sup>. The correct reason for higher B - F bond dissociation energy as compared to that of C - F is",
    "options": [
      "stronger $$\\sigma$$ bond between B and F in BF<sub>3</sub> as compared to that between C and F in CF<sub>4</sub>",
      "significant $$p\\pi - p\\pi$$ interaction between B and F in BF<sub>3</sub> whereas there is no possibility of such interaction between C and F in CF<sub>4</sub>",
      "lower degree of $$p\\pi - p\\pi$$ interaction between B and F in BF<sub>3</sub> than that between C and F in CF<sub>4</sub>",
      "smaller size of B - atom as compared to that of C- atom."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "back-bonding",
    "solution": "significant $$p\\pi - p\\pi$$ interaction between B and F in BF<sub>3</sub> whereas there is no possibility of such interaction between C and F in CF<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "hIKAVgpODAw47kWU",
    "question": "The correct order of bond angles (smallest first) in H<sub>2</sub>S, NH<sub>3</sub>, BF<sub>3 </sub> and SiH<sub>4</sub> is ",
    "options": [
      "H<sub>2</sub>S &lt; SiH<sub>4</sub> &lt; NH<sub>3</sub> &lt; BF<sub>3</sub> ",
      "H<sub>2</sub>S &lt; NH<sub>3</sub> &lt; BF<sub>3</sub> &lt; SiH<sub>4</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>S &lt; NH<sub>3</sub> &lt; SiH<sub>4</sub> &lt; BF<sub>3</sub> ",
      "NH<sub>3 </sub> &lt; H<sub>2</sub>S &lt; SiH<sub>4</sub> &lt; BF<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "bond-parameters",
    "solution": "H<sub>2</sub>S &lt; NH<sub>3</sub> &lt; SiH<sub>4</sub> &lt; BF<sub>3</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "JwF7qXS0mwqWGfITfQaAz",
    "question": "The bond angle H - X - H is the greatest in the compound :",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>4</sub>",
      "NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "PH<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "bond-parameters",
    "solution": "CH<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "UT37Bhz2pdWpjRRFSB7k9k2k5hlihae",
    "question": "Arrange the following bonds according to their\naverage bond energies in descending order :<br/>\nC–Cl, C–Br, C–F, C–I",
    "options": [
      "C–Br &gt; C–I &gt; C–Cl &gt; C–F",
      "C–Cl &gt; C–Br &gt; C–I &gt; C–F",
      "C–I &gt; C–Br &gt; C–Cl &gt; C–F",
      "C–F &gt; C–Cl &gt; C–Br &gt; C–I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "bond-parameters",
    "solution": "C–F &gt; C–Cl &gt; C–Br &gt; C–I"
  },
  {
    "id": "VSvDRTNVr5I8GcIzWg1kmhskjjf",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labeled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R :<br/><br/>Assertion A : The H$$-$$O$$-$$H bond angle in water molecule is 104.5$$^\\circ$$.<br/><br/>Reason R : The lone pair - lone pair repulsion of electrons is higher than the bond pair - bond pair repulsion.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true, and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true, but R is not the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "bond-parameters",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true, and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldo0umhx",
    "question": "<p>$$\\mathrm{O}-\\mathrm{O}$$ bond length in $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ is $$\\underline{\\mathrm{X}}$$ than the $$\\mathrm{O}-\\mathrm{O}$$ bond length in $$\\mathrm{F}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$. The $$\\mathrm{O}-\\mathrm{H}$$ bond length in $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ is $$\\underline{Y}$$ than that of the $$\\mathrm{O}-\\mathrm{F}$$ bond in $$\\mathrm{F}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct option for $$\\underline{X}$$ and $$\\underline{Y}$$ from those given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{X}$$ - shorter, $$\\mathrm{Y}$$ - longer",
      "$$\\mathrm{X}$$ - longer, $$\\mathrm{Y}$$ - shorter",
      "$$\\mathrm{X}$$ - shorter, $$\\mathrm{Y}$$ - shorter",
      "$$\\mathrm{X}$$ - longer, $$\\mathrm{Y}$$ - longer"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "bond-parameters",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{X}$$ - longer, $$\\mathrm{Y}$$ - shorter"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr41fo8",
    "question": "<p>For $$\\mathrm{OF}_{2}$$ molecule consider the following :</p>\n<p>A. Number of lone pairs on oxygen is 2 .</p>\n<p>B. FOF angle is less than $$104.5^{\\circ}$$.</p>\n<p>C. Oxidation state of $$\\mathrm{O}$$ is $$-2$$.</p>\n<p>D. Molecule is bent '$$\\mathrm{V}$$' shaped.</p>\n<p>E. Molecular geometry is linear.</p>\n<p>correct options are:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, C, D only",
      "A, B, D only",
      "C, D, E only",
      "B, E, A only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "bond-parameters",
    "solution": "A, B, D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsrb3lq",
    "question": "<p>The bond dissociation energy is highest for</p>",
    "options": [
      "Cl$$_2$$",
      "I$$_2$$",
      "Br$$_2$$",
      "F$$_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "bond-parameters",
    "solution": "Cl$$_2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp2tgig",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : $$\\mathrm{SO}_{2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$ both possess V-shaped structure.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The bond angle of $$\\mathrm{SO}_{2}$$ is less than that of $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "bond-parameters",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgyis0f",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : There is a considerable increase in covalent radius from $$\\mathrm{N}$$ to $$\\mathrm{P}$$. However from As to Bi only a small increase in covalent radius is observed.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Covalent and ionic radii in a particular oxidation state increases down the group. In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) is false but (R) is true",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "bond-parameters",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "0UqeO2LY0c5pvpkp",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true?",
    "options": [
      "HF is less polar than HBr",
      "absolutely pure water does not contain any ions",
      "chemical bond formation takes place when forces of attraction overcome the forces of repulsion",
      "in covalency transference of electron takes place"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "covalent-and-co-ordinate-bond",
    "solution": "chemical bond formation takes place when forces of attraction overcome the forces of repulsion"
  },
  {
    "id": "aUOtRsLU7g18b1R8",
    "question": "Which of the following compounds contain(s) no covalent bond(s)?\nKCl, PH<sub>3</sub>, O<sub>2</sub>, B<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>, H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> ",
    "options": [
      "KCl, B<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>",
      "KCl, B<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>, PH<sub>3</sub>",
      "KCl, H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>",
      "KCl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "covalent-and-co-ordinate-bond",
    "solution": "KCl"
  },
  {
    "id": "XWE0iO8fDLO3VWW534T2w",
    "question": "The covalent alkaline earth metal halide\n(X = Cl, Br, I) is :",
    "options": [
      "CaX<sub>2</sub>",
      "SrX<sub>2</sub>",
      "MgX<sub>2</sub>",
      "BeX<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "covalent-and-co-ordinate-bond",
    "solution": "BeX<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i4ejlq",
    "question": "<p>Arrange the following in increasing order of their covalent character.</p>\n<p>A. $$\\mathrm{CaF}_{2}$$</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{CaCl}_{2}$$</p>\n<p>C. $$\\mathrm{CaBr}_{2}$$</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{CaI}_{2}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "B < A < C < D",
      "A < B < C < D",
      "A < B < D < C",
      "A < C < B < D"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "covalent-and-co-ordinate-bond",
    "solution": "A < B < C < D"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jkbg8k",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements.</p>\n<p>Statement I: $$\\mathrm{O}_{2}, \\mathrm{Cu}^{2+}$$, and $$\\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}$$ are weakly attracted by magnetic field and are magnetized in the same direction as magnetic field.</p>\n<p>Statement II: $$\\mathrm{NaCl}$$ and $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$ are weakly magnetized in opposite direction to magnetic field.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "covalent-and-co-ordinate-bond",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldygderb",
    "question": "<p>Order of Covalent bond;</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{A.~KF &gt; KI ; LiF &gt; KF}$$</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{B.~KF &lt; KI ; LiF &gt; KF}$$</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{C.~SnCl_4 &gt; SnCl_2 ; CuCl &gt; NaCl}$$</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{D.~LiF &gt; KF ; CuCl &lt; NaCl}$$</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{E.~KF &lt; KI ; CuCl &gt; NaCl}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "B, C only",
      "A, B only",
      "C, E only",
      "B, C, E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "covalent-and-co-ordinate-bond",
    "solution": "B, C, E only"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v49r8",
    "question": "<p>Number of $$\\sigma$$ and $$\\pi$$ bonds present in ethylene molecule is respectively :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 and 1\n",
      "5 and 1\n",
      "4 and 1\n",
      "5 and 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "covalent-and-co-ordinate-bond",
    "solution": "5 and 1\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "JJFWyBvJ5UgeAmFi",
    "question": "Which one of the following pairs of molecules will have permanent dipole moments for both members",
    "options": [
      "NO<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "NO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub>",
      "SiF<sub>4</sub> abd CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "SiF<sub>4</sub> abd NO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "dipole-moment",
    "solution": "NO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "J4tsIqf7yGQjgt3luQ7k9k2k5dzd7pc",
    "question": "The dipole of CCl<sub>4</sub>, CHCl<sub>3</sub> and CH<sub>4</sub> are in the order :",
    "options": [
      "CCl<sub>4</sub> &lt; CH<sub>4</sub> &lt; CHCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "CH<sub>4</sub> = CCl<sub>4</sub> &lt; CHCl<sub>3</sub>\n",
      "CH<sub>4</sub> &lt; CCl<sub>4</sub> &lt; CHCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "CHCl<sub>3</sub> &lt; CH<sub>4</sub>= CCl<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "dipole-moment",
    "solution": "CH<sub>4</sub> = CCl<sub>4</sub> &lt; CHCl<sub>3</sub>\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kp2rn0",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 494px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 53px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 205px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 40px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 196px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\psi_{\\mathrm{MO}}=\\psi_{\\mathrm{A}}-\\psi_{\\mathrm{B}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Dipole moment</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mu=Q \\times r$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Bonding molecular orbital</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\frac{\\mathrm{N}_{\\mathrm{b}}-\\mathrm{N}_{\\mathrm{a}}}{2}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Anti-bonding molecular orbital</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\psi_{\\mathrm{MO}}=\\psi_{\\mathrm{A}}+\\psi_{\\mathrm{B}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Bond order</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{III})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{II})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{II})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{I})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "dipole-moment",
    "solution": "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{II})$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu0xek7",
    "question": "<p>Statement I : Dipole moment is a vector quantity and by convention it is depicted by a small arrow with tail on the negative centre and head pointing towards the positive centre.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The crossed arrow of the dipole moment symbolizes the direction of the shift of charges in the molecules.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "dipole-moment",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnzt580",
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n<br/><br/>\n(A) NF<sub>3</sub> molecule has a trigonal planar structure.\n<br/><br/>\n(B) Bond length of $\\mathrm{N}_{2}$ is shorter than $\\mathrm{O}_{2}$.\n<br/><br/>\n(C) Isoelectronic molecules or ions have identical bond order.\n<br/><br/>\n(D) Dipole moment of $\\mathrm{H}_{2}\\mathrm{S}$ is higher than that of water molecule.\n<br/><br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below:",
    "options": [
      "(C) and (D) are correct",
      "(A) and (B) are correct",
      "(B) and (C) are correct",
      "(A) and (D) are correct\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "dipole-moment",
    "solution": "(B) and (C) are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc5b7uk",
    "question": "<p>Choose the polar molecule from the following:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{CCl}_4$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CO}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CH}_2=\\mathrm{CH}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CHCl}_3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "dipole-moment",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{CHCl}_3$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg7fij3",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement - I: Since Fluorine is more electronegative than nitrogen, the net dipole moment of $$\\mathrm{NF}_3$$ is greater than $$\\mathrm{NH}_3$$.</p>\n<p>Statement - II: In $$\\mathrm{NH}_3$$, the orbital dipole due to lone pair and the dipole moment of $$\\mathrm{NH}$$ bonds are in opposite direction, but in $$\\mathrm{NF}_3$$ the orbital dipole due to lone pair and dipole moments of N-F bonds are in same direction.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "dipole-moment",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vyr14",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following molecules has maximum dipole moment?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{CH}_4$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{NF}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{NH}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{PF}_5$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "dipole-moment",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{NH}_3$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s2jkm",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : $$\\mathrm{NH}_3$$ and $$\\mathrm{NF}_3$$ molecule have pyramidal shape with a lone pair of electrons on nitrogen atom. The resultant dipole moment of $$\\mathrm{NH}_3$$ is greater than that of $$\\mathrm{NF}_3$$.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : In $$\\mathrm{NH}_3$$, the orbital dipole due to lone pair is in the same direction as the resultant dipole moment of the $$\\mathrm{N}-\\mathrm{H}$$ bonds. $$\\mathrm{F}$$ is the most electronegative element.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) is false but (R) is true",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is NOT the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "dipole-moment",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "mpj6Sr9z39a6FjpW",
    "question": "Hybridisation of underline atom changes in",
    "options": [
      "$$\\underline {Al} {H_3}$$ changes to $$AlH_4^-$$",
      "$${H_2}\\underline O $$ changes to $$H_3O^+$$",
      "$$\\underline N {H_3}$$ changes to $$NH_4^+$$",
      "in all cases"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\underline {Al} {H_3}$$ changes to $$AlH_4^-$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "gm5x4qpYa6KEna62",
    "question": "A square planar complex is formed by hybridisation of which atomic orbitals ?",
    "options": [
      "s, p<sub>x</sub>, p<sub>y</sub>, d<sub>xy</sub>",
      "s, p<sub>x</sub>, p<sub>y</sub>, d<sub>x<sup>2</sup> - y<sup>2</sup></sub>",
      "s, p<sub>x</sub>, p<sub>y</sub>, d<sub>z<sup>2</sup></sub>",
      "s, p<sub>x</sub>, p<sub>y</sub>, d<sub>yz</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "s, p<sub>x</sub>, p<sub>y</sub>, d<sub>x<sup>2</sup> - y<sup>2</sup></sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "jyb6oiwKNBOHn555",
    "question": "In which of the following species the interatomic bond angle is 109<sup>o</sup>28' ?",
    "options": [
      "NH<sub>3</sub>, BF<sub>4</sub><sup>-</sup>",
      "NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>, BF<sub>4</sub><sup>-</sup>",
      "NH<sub>3</sub>, BF<sub>3</sub>",
      "NH<sub>2</sub><sup>-1</sup>, BF<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>, BF<sub>4</sub><sup>-</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "xcsm0nql60z3oXg7",
    "question": "The pair of species having identical shapes for molecules of both species is",
    "options": [
      "XeF<sub>2</sub>, CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "BF<sub>3</sub>, PCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "PF<sub>5</sub>, IF<sub>5</sub>",
      "CF<sub>4</sub>, SF<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "XeF<sub>2</sub>, CO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "f9uqujHVgoME8wvM",
    "question": "Which one of the following compounds has the smallest bond angle in its molecule?",
    "options": [
      "OH<sub>2</sub>",
      "SH<sub>2</sub>",
      "NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "SO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "SH<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "KxDI6IEJbr7AahXR",
    "question": "The states of hybridization of boron and oxygen atoms in boric acid (H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>) are respectively ",
    "options": [
      "sp<sup>2</sup> and sp<sup>2</sup>\n ",
      "sp<sup>3</sup> and sp<sup>3</sup>",
      "sp<sup>3</sup> and sp<sup>2</sup>",
      "sp<sup>2</sup> and sp<sup>3</sup>\n "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "sp<sup>2</sup> and sp<sup>3</sup>\n "
  },
  {
    "id": "5urq95W4yMPfUd4T",
    "question": "Which one of the following has the regular tetrahedral structure? <br/>\n\n(Atomic nos : B = 5, S = 16, Ni = 28, Xe = 54)",
    "options": [
      "XeF<sub>4</sub>",
      "[Ni(CN)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2- </sup>",
      "$$BF_4^-$$",
      "SF<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "$$BF_4^-$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "0vElpsEC64WAiY8W",
    "question": "The maximum number of 90° angles between bond pair of electrons is observed in ",
    "options": [
      "dsp<sup>3</sup> hybridization",
      "sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup> hybridization ",
      "dsp<sup>2</sup> hybridization ",
      "sp<sup>3</sup>d hybridization"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup> hybridization "
  },
  {
    "id": "sqKQ12mYiO4jae8k",
    "question": "In which of the following molecules/ions are all the bonds <b>not</b> equal?",
    "options": [
      "XeF<sub>4</sub>",
      "$$BF_4^−$$",
      "SF<sub>4</sub>",
      "SiF<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "SF<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "UwJG6rOuj439QRBl",
    "question": "The decreasing values of bond angles from NH<sub>3</sub> (106<sup>o</sup>) to SbH<sub>3</sub> (91<sup>o</sup>\n) down group-15 of the periodic table is due to ",
    "options": [
      "increasing bp-bp repulsion",
      "increasing p-orbital character in sp<sup>3</sup>",
      "decreasing lp-bp repulsion",
      "decreasing electronegativity "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "decreasing lp-bp repulsion"
  },
  {
    "id": "9GahDMGK1F3fXjfs",
    "question": "The hybridization of orbitals of N atom in $$NO_3^-$$, $$NO_2^+$$ and $$NH_4^+$$ are respectively :",
    "options": [
      "sp , sp<sup>2</sup>, sp<sup>3</sup>",
      "sp<sup>2</sup>, sp ,  sp<sup>3</sup>",
      "sp ,  sp<sup>3</sup>, sp<sup>2</sup>",
      "sp<sup>2</sup>,  sp<sup>3</sup>,  sp "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "sp<sup>2</sup>, sp ,  sp<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "KElf6QK1sAhJKW8C",
    "question": "The structure of IF<sub>7</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "trigonal bipyramid",
      "octahedral",
      "pentagonal bipyramid",
      "square pyramid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "pentagonal bipyramid"
  },
  {
    "id": "ubhEmYxLSYmZXGqc",
    "question": "In which of the following pairs the two species are not isostructural ?",
    "options": [
      "$$CO_3^{2-}$$ and $$NO_3^-$$",
      "$$PCl_4^{+}$$ and $$SiCl_4$$",
      "PF<sub>5</sub> and BrF<sub>5</sub>",
      "$$AlF_6^-$$ and $$SF_6$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "PF<sub>5</sub> and BrF<sub>5</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "vqAPe6uexarsrvlAJ7vIJ",
    "question": "The group of molecules having identical shape is :",
    "options": [
      "SF<sub>4</sub> , XeF<sub>4</sub> , CCl<sub>4</sub>",
      "ClF<sub>3</sub> , XeOF<sub>2</sub> , XeF$$_3^ + $$",
      "BF<sub>3</sub> , PCl<sub>3</sub> , XeO<sub>3</sub>",
      "PCl<sub>5</sub> , IF<sub>5</sub> , XeO<sub>2</sub>F<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "ClF<sub>3</sub> , XeOF<sub>2</sub> , XeF$$_3^ + $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "l86jb8sy",
    "question": "The species in which the $\\mathrm{N}$ atom is in a state of $s p$ hybridization is :\n",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{NO}_2^{+}$",
      "$\\mathrm{NO}_2^{-}$\n",
      "$\\mathrm{NO}_3^{-}$\n",
      "$\\mathrm{NO}_3^{-}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{NO}_2^{+}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "wJuktyJ7ppW8x7QwGSrdn",
    "question": "sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup>  hybridization is <b>not</b> displayed by :\n",
    "options": [
      "BrF<sub>5</sub>",
      "SF<sub>6</sub>",
      "[CrF<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup>",
      "PF<sub>5</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "PF<sub>5</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "RNVhXFNTgCG2USg2qReSo",
    "question": "The group having triangular planar structures is :\n",
    "options": [
      "BF<sub>3</sub>, NF<sub>3</sub>, $$CO_3^{2 - }$$",
      "$$CO_3^{2 - }$$, $$NO_3^ - $$,  SO<sub>3</sub>",
      "NH<sub>3</sub>, SO<sub>3</sub>, $$CO_3^{2 - }$$",
      "NCl<sub>3</sub>, BCl<sub>3</sub>, SO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "$$CO_3^{2 - }$$, $$NO_3^ - $$,  SO<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Q1FlgwO0fiKugPkd7zZYg",
    "question": "The <b>incorrect</b> geometry is represented by : ",
    "options": [
      "BF<sub>3</sub> - trigonal planar",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O - bent",
      "NF<sub>3</sub> - trigonal planar ",
      "AsF<sub>5</sub> - trigonal bipyramidal "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "NF<sub>3</sub> - trigonal planar "
  },
  {
    "id": "tNZioP85tcK6ubfP68HEi",
    "question": "Which of the following conversions involves change in both shape and hybridisation ? ",
    "options": [
      "NH<sub>3</sub> $$ \\to $$ NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> ",
      "CH<sub>4</sub> $$ \\to $$ C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O $$ \\to $$ H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>",
      "BF<sub>3</sub> $$ \\to $$ BF<sub>4</sub><sup>$$-$$</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "BF<sub>3</sub> $$ \\to $$ BF<sub>4</sub><sup>$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "mH7bhHWLOeDctdqbPfpd6",
    "question": "Identify the pair in which the geometry of the species is $$T$$-shape and square - pyraidal, respectively : ",
    "options": [
      "ClF<sub>3</sub> and $$I{O_4}^ - $$ ",
      "ICl<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup> and ICl<sub>5</sub>",
      "XeOF<sub>2</sub> and XeOF<sub>4</sub>",
      "IO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup> and IO<sub>2</sub>F<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "XeOF<sub>2</sub> and XeOF<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "RrllQEe4krGwgmj9",
    "question": "Total number of lone pair of electrons in $${\\rm I}_3^ - $$ ion is ",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "9",
      "6",
      "12"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "9"
  },
  {
    "id": "JQtM1Iubq2JHnySXbobVJ",
    "question": "The decreasing order of bond angles in BF<sub>3</sub>, NH<sub>3</sub>, PF<sub>3</sub> and I<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup> is :",
    "options": [
      "I<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup> &gt; NH<sub>3</sub> &gt; PF<sub>3</sub> &gt; BF<sub>3</sub>",
      "I<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup> &gt; BF<sub>3</sub> &gt; NH<sub>3</sub> &gt; PF<sub>3</sub>",
      "BF<sub>3</sub> &gt; I<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup> &gt; PF<sub>3</sub> &gt; NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "BF<sub>3</sub>  &gt; NH<sub>3</sub> &gt; PF<sub>3</sub> &gt; I<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "I<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup> &gt; BF<sub>3</sub> &gt; NH<sub>3</sub> &gt; PF<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "trch1UDIBda7MNflGZL6s",
    "question": "The type of hybridisation and number of lone pair (s) of electrons of Xe in XeOF<sub>4</sub>, respectively, are: ",
    "options": [
      "sp<sup>3</sup>d and 2",
      "sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup> and 2",
      "sp<sup>3</sup>d and 1",
      "sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup> and 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup> and 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "xrxSs5Zo7exG8RTfiTO76",
    "question": "The ion that has sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup> hybridization for the\ncentral atom, is :",
    "options": [
      "[ICl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>-</sup>",
      "[ICl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>-</sup>",
      "[IF<sub>6</sub>]<sup>-</sup>",
      "[BrF<sub>2</sub>]<sup>-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "[ICl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>-</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "oAa6YvGMfJQ4vKQf77p3L",
    "question": "The correct statement about ICl<sub>5</sub> and $$ICl_4^-$$ is",
    "options": [
      "ICl<sub>5</sub> is square pyramidal and $$ICl_4^-$$ is square\nplanar.",
      "ICl<sub>5</sub> is trigonal bipyramidal and  is\ntetrahedral.",
      "ICl<sub>5</sub> is square pyramidal and $$ICl_4^-$$ is\ntetrahedral",
      "Both are isostructural."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "ICl<sub>5</sub> is square pyramidal and $$ICl_4^-$$ is square\nplanar."
  },
  {
    "id": "vLMXNDzSRUPPkXYgDM3rsa0w2w9jwwe7xj7",
    "question": "The oxoacid of sulphur that does not contain bond between sulphur atoms is ",
    "options": [
      "H<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>S<sub>4</sub>O<sub>6</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "H<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "CZw8iRqaJAkptjk3dB3rsa0w2w9jx56xgdk",
    "question": "The correct statement among the following is :",
    "options": [
      "(SiH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N is planar and more basic than (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N",
      "(SiH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N is pyramidal and more basic than (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N",
      "(SiH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N is pyramidal and less basic than (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N",
      "(SiH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N is planar and less basic than (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "(SiH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N is planar and less basic than (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N"
  },
  {
    "id": "qq20iRhwJH3Mt3t8PXjgy2xukfoup9d3",
    "question": "The compound that has the largest H–M–H bond angle (M = N, O, S, C) is :",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>4</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>S",
      "NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "CH<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "9fIRZYzuHw4D3nSNnBjgy2xukfjadluh",
    "question": "The structure of PCl<sub>5</sub>\n in the solid state is :",
    "options": [
      "square pyramidal",
      "tetrahedral [PCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>+</sup> and octahedral [PCl<sub>6</sub>]<sup>–</sup>",
      "square planar [PCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>+</sup> and octahedral [PCl<sub>6</sub>]<sup>–</sup>",
      "trigonal bipyramidal"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "tetrahedral [PCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>+</sup> and octahedral [PCl<sub>6</sub>]<sup>–</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "WFXn6ZDj7Ne3LISNMWjgy2xukeyfkp6d",
    "question": "The molecular geometry of SF<sub>6</sub> is octahedral.\nWhat is the geometry of SF<sub>4</sub> (including lone\npair(s) of electrons, if any)?",
    "options": [
      "Tetrahedral",
      "Trigonal bipyramidal",
      "Square planar",
      "Pyramidal"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "Trigonal bipyramidal"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ldjm6F2RcUZqrW6WdQjgy2xukevcl4v7",
    "question": "If AB<sub>4</sub> molecule is a polar molecule, a possible\ngeometry of AB<sub>4</sub> is",
    "options": [
      "Tetrahedral",
      "see-saw",
      "Square pyramidal",
      "Square planar"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "see-saw"
  },
  {
    "id": "m9nI60z407ispZxrApjgy2xukeyg5mny",
    "question": "The shape / structure of [XeF<sub>5</sub>]<sup>–</sup> and XeO<sub>3</sub>F<sub>2</sub>,\nrespectively, are",
    "options": [
      "Pentagonal planar and trigonal bipyramidal",
      "Trigonal bipyramidal and pentagonal\nplanar",
      "Octahedral and square pyramidal",
      "Trigonal bipyramidal and trigonal\nbipyramidal"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "Pentagonal planar and trigonal bipyramidal"
  },
  {
    "id": "EH7XWeAT0VLMyVxT5e7k9k2k5llkutr",
    "question": "The number of sp<sup>2</sup> hybrid orbitals in a molecule\nof benzene is :",
    "options": [
      "24",
      "12",
      "6",
      "18"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "18"
  },
  {
    "id": "PGLMsl7rJFTER4ZNpx1klre2fzp",
    "question": "Which of the following are isostructural pairs ?<br/><br/>\nA. $$SO_4^{2 - }$$ and $$CrO_4^{2 - }$$<br/><br/>\nB. SiCl<sub>4</sub>, and TiCl<sub>4</sub><br/><br/>\nC. NH<sub>3</sub> and NO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup><br/><br/>\nD. BCl<sub>3</sub> and BrCl<sub>3</sub>\n",
    "options": [
      "B and C only",
      "C and D only",
      "A and B only",
      "A and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "A and B only"
  },
  {
    "id": "4OfWGyXWyWzXXzsHEN1klrupxk0",
    "question": "The correct shape and $$I - I - I$$ bond angles respectively in $$I_3^ - $$ ion are :",
    "options": [
      "Linear; 180$$^\\circ$$",
      "T-shaped; 180$$^\\circ$$ and 90$$^\\circ$$",
      "Trigonal planar; 120$$^\\circ$$",
      "Distorted trigonal planar; 135$$^\\circ$$ and 90$$^\\circ$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "Linear; 180$$^\\circ$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "s6ZM9fL2oCgJLMNjDv1kltayvbk",
    "question": "Which among the following species has unequal bond lengths?",
    "options": [
      "XeF<sub>4</sub>",
      "BF$$_4^ - $$",
      "SiF<sub>4</sub>",
      "SF<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "SF<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "eAwLd70abt7Dh4fFYm1kmj7ywbn",
    "question": "A central atom in a molecule has two lone pairs of electrons and forms three single bonds. The shape of this molecule is :",
    "options": [
      "trigonal pyramidal",
      "T-shaped",
      "see-saw",
      "planar triangular"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "T-shaped"
  },
  {
    "id": "bStxnIbOS1q0TO4EeC1kmki78mh",
    "question": "Amongst the following, the linear species is :",
    "options": [
      "O<sub>3</sub>",
      "Cl<sub>2</sub>O",
      "N$$_3^ - $$",
      "NO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "N$$_3^ - $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krriq8sk",
    "question": "The hybridisations of the atomic orbitals of nitrogen in NO$$_2^ - $$, NO$$_2^ + $$ and NH$$_4^ + $$ respectively are.",
    "options": [
      "sp<sup>3</sup>, sp<sup>2</sup> and sp",
      "sp, sp<sup>2</sup> and sp<sup>3</sup>",
      "sp<sup>3</sup>, sp and sp<sup>2</sup>",
      "sp<sup>2</sup>, sp and sp<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "sp<sup>2</sup>, sp and sp<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt46woa",
    "question": "Match List-I with List-II :<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List-I<br/>(Species)</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List-II<br/>(Hybrid Orbitals)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>$$S{F_4}$$</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>$$s{p^3}{d^2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>$$I{F_5}$$</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>$${d^2}s{p^3}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>$$NO_2^ + $$</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>$$s{p^3}d$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>$$NH_4^ + $$</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>$$s{p^3}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td></td>\n<td></td>\n<td>(v)</td>\n<td>$$sp$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(ii), (c)-(v) and (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv) and (d)-(v)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(v) and (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii) and (d)-(v)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(v) and (d)-(iv)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54y1m1n",
    "question": "<p>Consider the species CH<sub>4</sub>, NH$$_4^ + $$ and BH$$_4^ - $$. Choose the correct option with respect to the these species.</p>",
    "options": [
      "They are isoelectronic and only two have tetrahedral structures.",
      "They are isoelectronic and all have tetrahedral structures.",
      "Only two are isoelectronic and all have tetrahedral structures.",
      "Only two are isoelectronic and only two have tetrahedral structures."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "They are isoelectronic and all have tetrahedral structures."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54yhq39",
    "question": "<p>Number of lone pair(s) of electrons on central atom and the shape BrF<sub>3</sub> molecule respectively, are</p>",
    "options": [
      "0, triangular planar.",
      "1, pyramidal.",
      "2, bent T-shape.",
      "1, bent T-shape."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "2, bent T-shape."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55mwdtf",
    "question": "<p>In the structure of SF<sub>4</sub>, the lone pair of electrons on S is in.</p>",
    "options": [
      "equatorial position and there are two lone pair - bond pair repulsions at 90$$^\\circ$$.",
      "equatorial position and there are three lone pair - bond pair repulsions at 90$$^\\circ$$.",
      "axial position and there are three lone pair - bond pair repulsion at 90$$^\\circ$$.",
      "axial position and there are two lone pair - bond pair repulsion at 90$$^\\circ$$."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "equatorial position and there are two lone pair - bond pair repulsions at 90$$^\\circ$$."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56wr85r",
    "question": "<p>Identify the incorrect statement for PCl<sub>5</sub> from the following.</p>",
    "options": [
      "In this molecule, orbitals of phosphorous are assumed to undergo sp<sup>3</sup>d hybridization.",
      "The geometry of PCl<sub>5</sub> is trigonal bipyramidal.",
      "PCl<sub>5</sub> has two axial bonds stronger than three equatorial bonds.",
      "The three equatorial bonds of PCl<sub>5</sub> lie in a plane."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "PCl<sub>5</sub> has two axial bonds stronger than three equatorial bonds."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57r9zwv",
    "question": "<p>Based upon VSEPR theory, match the shape (geometry) of the molecules in List-I with the molecules in List-II and select the most appropriate option.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 472px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 44px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 143px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 42px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 243px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - I<br/>(Shape)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - II<br/>(Molecules)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">T-shaped</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">XeF$$_4$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Trigonal planar</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">SF$$_4$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Square planar</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">ClF$$_3$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">See-saw</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">BF$$_3$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - (I), (B) - (II), (C) - (III), (D) - (IV)",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (IV), (C) - (I), (D) - (II)",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (IV), (C) - (I), (D) - (I)",
      "(A) - (IV), (B) - (III), (C) - (I), (D) - (II)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "(A) - (III), (B) - (IV), (C) - (I), (D) - (II)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5alukek",
    "question": "<p>Number of electron deficient molecules among the following</p>\n<p>PH<sub>3</sub>, B<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>, CCl<sub>4</sub>, NH<sub>3</sub>, LiH and BCl<sub>3</sub> is</p>",
    "options": [
      "0",
      "1",
      "2",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f63903",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II:</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I<br/>(molecule)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II<br/>(hybridization ; shape)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">XeO$$_3$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">sp$$^3$$d ; linear</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">XeF$$_2$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">sp$$^3$$ ; pyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">XeOF$$_4$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">sp$$^3$$d$$^3$$ ; distorted octahedral</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">XeF$$_6$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">sp$$^3$$d$$^2$$ ; square pyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-III, D-I",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-I, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gp10zq",
    "question": "<p>Match List-I with List-II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I<br/>(Compound)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II<br/>(Shape)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">BrF$$_5$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">bent</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">[CrF$$_6$$]$$^{3 - }$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">square pyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">O$$_3$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">trigonal bipyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">PCl$$_5$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">octahedral</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{I})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{III})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{I})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{III})$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p6q3wz",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following pair of molecules contain odd electron molecule and an expanded octet molecule?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{BCl}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{SF}_{6}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{NO}$$ and $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{SF}_{6}$$ and $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{BCl}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{NO}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{NO}$$ and $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p771sz",
    "question": "<p>Number of lone pairs of electrons in the central atom of $$\\mathrm{SCl}_{2}, \\mathrm{O}_{3}, \\mathrm{ClF}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{SF}_{6}$$, respectively, are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0, 1, 2 and 2",
      "2, 1, 2 and 0",
      "1, 2, 2 and 0",
      "2, 1, 0 and 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "2, 1, 2 and 0"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldppgyi8",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 581px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 223px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 263px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{XeF_4}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">See-saw</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{SF_4}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Square-planar</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{NH_{4}^{+}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Bent T-shaped</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{BrF_3}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Tetrahedral</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A - II, B - I, C - III, D - IV",
      "A - II, B - I, C - IV, D - III",
      "A - IV, B - I, C - II, D - III",
      "A - IV, B - III, C - II, D - I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "A - II, B - I, C - IV, D - III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr4ho5x",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 607px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 263px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I<br/>(molecules/ions)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II<br/>(No. of lone pairs of e$$^-$$ on central atom)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{IF_7}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Three</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{ICl}$$$$_4^ - $$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">One</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{XeF_6}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Two</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{XeF_2}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Zero</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A - II, B - I, C - IV, D - III",
      "A - IV, B - I, C - II, D - III",
      "A - IV, B - III, C - II, D - I",
      "A - II, B - III, C - IV, D - I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "A - IV, B - III, C - II, D - I"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnze5sm",
    "question": "The number of $\\mathrm{P}-\\mathrm{O}-\\mathrm{P}$ bonds in $\\mathrm{H}_{4} \\mathrm{P}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{7},\\left(\\mathrm{HPO}_{3}\\right)_{3}$ and $\\mathrm{P}_{4} \\mathrm{O}_{10}$ are respectively :",
    "options": [
      "$1,3,6$",
      "$1,2,4$",
      "$0,3,4$",
      "$0,3,6$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "$1,3,6$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq472j1",
    "question": "$$\\mathrm{ClF}_{5}$$ at room temperature is a:",
    "options": [
      "Colourless liquid with square pyramidal geometry",
      "Colourless gas with square pyramidal geometry",
      "Colourless gas with trigonal bipyramidal geometry.",
      "Colourless liquid with trigonal bipyramidal geometry"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "Colourless liquid with square pyramidal geometry"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguzfmzq",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II:</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 554px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 49px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 201px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 54px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 250px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List - I Species</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List - II Geometry/Shape</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{H_3O^+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">Tetrahedral</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">Acetylide anion</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">Linear</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{NH_4^+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">Pyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{ClO_2^-}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">Bent</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyfyt7u",
    "question": "<p>The compound which does not exist is</p>",
    "options": [
      "(NH$$_4$$)$$_2$$BeF$$_4$$",
      "PbEt$$_4$$",
      "BeH$$_2$$",
      "NaO$$_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "NaO$$_2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh27wei6",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 598px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 240px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I <br/>Oxide</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II <br/>Type of bond</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{N_2O_4}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">1 N = O bond</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{NO_2}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">1 N $$-$$ O $$-$$ N bond</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{N_2O_5}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">1 N $$-$$ N bond</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{N_2O}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">1 N=N / N $$\\equiv$$ N bond</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-I, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg7kbq3",
    "question": "<p>The molecule / ion with square pyramidal shape is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{PCl}_5$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CN})_4\\right]^{2-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{PF}_5$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{BrF}_5$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{BrF}_5$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgxnho5",
    "question": "<p>Aluminium chloride in acidified aqueous solution forms an ion having geometry</p>",
    "options": [
      "Square planar\n",
      "Octahedral\n",
      "Trigonal bipyramidal\n",
      "Tetrahedral"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "Octahedral\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgy08ma",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 551px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 74px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 179px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 82px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 216px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List I<br/>Molecule</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List II<br/>Shape</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{BrF_5}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">T-Shape</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{H_2O}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">See saw</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{ClF_3}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Bent</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{SF_4}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Square pyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(II), (C)-(IV), (D)-(III)\n",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(I), (C)-(III), (D)-(IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxzq9h9",
    "question": "<p>The correct increasing order for bond angles among $$\\mathrm{BF}_3, \\mathrm{PF}_3$$ and $$\\mathrm{ClF}_3$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{BF}_3=\\mathrm{PF}_3<\\mathrm{ClF}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{BF}_3<\\mathrm{PF}_3<\\mathrm{ClF}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{ClF}_3<\\mathrm{PF}_3<\\mathrm{BF}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{PF}_3<\\mathrm{BF}_3<\\mathrm{ClF}_3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{ClF}_3<\\mathrm{PF}_3<\\mathrm{BF}_3$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2un4k",
    "question": "<p>In which one of the following pairs the central atoms exhibit $$\\mathrm{sp}^2$$ hybridization ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{BF}_3$$ and $$\\mathrm{NO}_2^{-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{NH}_2^{-}$$ and $$\\mathrm{BF}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{NH}_2^{-}$$ and $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}$$ and $$\\mathrm{NO}_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{BF}_3$$ and $$\\mathrm{NO}_2^{-}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vyqj5",
    "question": "<p>Number of molecules/ions from the following in which the central atom is involved in $$\\mathrm{sp}^3$$ hybridization is ________.</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{NO}_3^{-}, \\mathrm{BCl}_3, \\mathrm{ClO}_2^{-}, \\mathrm{ClO}_3^{-}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "4",
      "1",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2es2q1",
    "question": "<p>The number of species from the following that have pyramidal geometry around the central atom is _________</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{S}_2 \\mathrm{O}_3^{2-}, \\mathrm{SO}_4^{2-}, \\mathrm{SO}_3^{2-}, \\mathrm{S}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7^{2-}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "3",
      "2",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmasa",
    "question": "<p>The shape of carbocation is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "tetrahedral\n",
      "diagonal pyramidal\n",
      "diagonal\n",
      "trigonal planar"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "trigonal planar"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gsw7q",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 664px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 262px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Molecule)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Shape)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{NH_3}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Square pyramid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{BrF_5}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Tetrahedral</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{PCl_5}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Trigonal pyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{CH_4}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Trigonal bipyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III\n",
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II\n",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s26z7",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 703px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{ICl}<br/>$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">T - shape</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{ICl}_3<br/>$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Square pyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{ClF}_5<br/>$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Pentagonal bipyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{IF}_7<br/>$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Linear</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(IV), (C)-(III), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)\n",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(III), (C)-(II), (D)-(IV)\n",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57i5y",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 690px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 239px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Compound/Species)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Shape/Geometry)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{SF_4}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Tetrahedral</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{BrF_3}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Pyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{BrO_3^-}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">See saw</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{NH_4^+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Bent T-Shape</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I\n",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I\n",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I\n",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc588zk",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 690px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 239px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Molecule/Species)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Property/Shape)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{SO_2Cl_2}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Paramagnetic</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{NO}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Diamagnetic</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{NO_2^-}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Tetrahedral</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{I_3^-}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Linear</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV\n",
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV\n",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II\n",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hybridization-and-vsepr-theory",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "RduOhjDepCS6jqrz",
    "question": "Which of the following hydrogen bonds is the strongest? ",
    "options": [
      "O−H…….N",
      "F−H…….F ",
      "O−H…….O ",
      "O−H…….F "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hydrogen-bonding",
    "solution": "F−H…….F "
  },
  {
    "id": "InA3umoGpofamZ2t",
    "question": "The intermolecular interaction that is dependent on the inverse cube of distance between the molecule is:",
    "options": [
      "ion-dipole interaction",
      "London force",
      "hydrogen bond",
      "ion-ion interaction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hydrogen-bonding",
    "solution": "hydrogen bond"
  },
  {
    "id": "C8wM97uJad4kiBxUSAxvh",
    "question": "HF has highest boiling point among hydrogen\nhalides, because it has :",
    "options": [
      "lowest dissociation enthalpy",
      "strongest hydrogen bonding",
      "lowest ionic character",
      "strongest van der Waals' interactions"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hydrogen-bonding",
    "solution": "strongest hydrogen bonding"
  },
  {
    "id": "jrIpSPZ42eyUlUxyKk1klud2nda",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.<br/><br/>Assertion A : Dipole-dipole interactions are the only non-covalent interactions, resulting in hydrogen bond formation.<br/><br/>Reason R : Fluorine is the most electronegative element and hydrogen bonds in HF are symmetrical.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hydrogen-bonding",
    "solution": "A is false but R is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56wur7s",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of increasing intermolecular hydrogen bond strength is</p>",
    "options": [
      "HCN < H<sub>2</sub>O < NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "HCN < CH<sub>4</sub> < NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "CH<sub>4</sub> < HCN < NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "CH<sub>4</sub> < NH<sub>3</sub> < HCN"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hydrogen-bonding",
    "solution": "CH<sub>4</sub> < HCN < NH<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyfls2h",
    "question": "<p>Decreasing order of the hydrogen bonding in following forms of water is correctly represented by</p>\n<p>A. Liquid water</p>\n<p>B. Ice</p>\n<p>C. Impure water</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A = B > C",
      "B > A > C",
      "A > B > C",
      "C > B > A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hydrogen-bonding",
    "solution": "B > A > C"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbmkq49",
    "question": "Given below are two statements: one is labelled as <b>Assertion (A</b>) and the other is labelled as <b>Reason (R)</b>.<br/><br/>\n<b>Assertion (A)</b>: $\\mathrm{PH}_3$ has lower boiling point than $\\mathrm{NH}_3$.<br/><br/>\n<b>Reason (R)</b> : In liquid state $\\mathrm{NH}_3$ molecules are associated through vander Waal's forces, but $\\mathrm{PH}_3$ molecules are associated through hydrogen bonding.\n<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below :\n\n",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct",
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct",
      "Both $(\\mathbf{A})$ and $(\\mathbf{R})$ are correct but $(\\mathbf{R})$ is not the correct explanation of $(\\mathbf{A})$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hydrogen-bonding",
    "solution": "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erjdj",
    "question": "<p>The correct statement/s about Hydrogen bonding is/are</p>\n<p>A. Hydrogen bonding exists when H is covalently bonded to the highly electro negative atom.</p>\n<p>B. Intermolecular H bonding is present in $$o$$-nitro phenol</p>\n<p>C. Intramolecular $$\\mathrm{H}$$ bonding is present in HF.</p>\n<p>D. The magnitude of $$\\mathrm{H}$$ bonding depends on the physical state of the compound.</p>\n<p>E. H-bonding has powerful effect on the structure and properties of compounds</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B, C only\n",
      "A only\n",
      "A, D, E only\n",
      "A, B, D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "hydrogen-bonding",
    "solution": "A, D, E only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "fq1DNfNhwProQ708",
    "question": "Lattice energy of an ionic compounds depends upon ",
    "options": [
      "Charge on the ion only",
      "Size of the ion only ",
      "Packing of ions only",
      "Charge on the ion and size of the ion"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "ionic-bond",
    "solution": "Charge on the ion and size of the ion"
  },
  {
    "id": "RWNDdbhUYKYBoil1",
    "question": "The charge/size ratio of a cation determines its polarizing power. Which one of the following\nsequences represents the increasing order of the polarizinig order of the polarizing power of the\ncationic species, K<sup>+</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>, Be<sup>2+</sup>? ",
    "options": [
      "Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Be<sup>2+</sup> &lt; K<sup>+</sup> &lt; Ca<sup>2+</sup>",
      "K<sup>+</sup> &lt; Ca<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Be<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Be<sup>2+</sup> &lt; K<sup>+</sup> &lt; Ca<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Ca<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Be<sup>2+</sup> \n &lt; K<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "ionic-bond",
    "solution": "K<sup>+</sup> &lt; Ca<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Be<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "NlQwrJQxyidRbufT",
    "question": "Among the following the maximum covalent character is shown by the compound : ",
    "options": [
      "SnCl<sub>2 </sub>",
      "AlCl<sub>3</sub> ",
      "MgCl<sub>2 </sub>",
      "FeCl<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "ionic-bond",
    "solution": "AlCl<sub>3</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "EKsMjnfbWj3zbUo1ppjgy2xukeyf4obe",
    "question": "Match the type of interaction in column A with\nthe distance dependence of their interaction\nenergy in column B\n<br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">A</th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">B</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(i) ion-ion</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(a) $${1 \\over r}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(ii) dipole-dipole</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(b) $${1 \\over {{r^2}}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(iii) London dispersion</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(c) $${1 \\over {{r^3}}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(d) $${1 \\over {{r^6}}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "(I)-(a), (II)-(b), (III)-(d)",
      "(I)-(b), (II)-(d), (III)-(c)",
      "(I)-(a), (II)-(b), (III)-(c)",
      "(I)-(a), (II)-(c), (III)-(d)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "ionic-bond",
    "solution": "(I)-(a), (II)-(c), (III)-(d)"
  },
  {
    "id": "HFY7Xy1k19cqRCzppU1klru73v4",
    "question": "The correct set from the following in which both pairs are in correct order of melting point is :",
    "options": [
      "LiCl &gt; LiF ; NaCl &gt; MgO",
      "LiCl &gt; LiF ; MgO &gt; NaCl",
      "LiF &gt; LiCl ; NaCl &gt; MgO",
      "LiF &gt; LiCl ; MgO &gt; NaCl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "ionic-bond",
    "solution": "LiF &gt; LiCl ; MgO &gt; NaCl"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbmwjmb",
    "question": "Arrange the bonds in order of increasing ionic character in the molecules. $\\mathrm{LiF}$, $\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{O}, \\mathrm{N}_2, \\mathrm{SO}_2$ and $\\mathrm{ClF}_3$ :",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{N}_2<\\mathrm{SO}_2<\\mathrm{ClF}_3<\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{LiF}$",
      "$\\mathrm{ClF}_3<\\mathrm{N}_2<\\mathrm{SO}_2<\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{LiF}$",
      "$\\mathrm{LiF}<\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{ClF}_3<\\mathrm{SO}_2<\\mathrm{N}_2$",
      "$\\mathrm{N}_2<\\mathrm{ClF}_3<\\mathrm{SO}_2<\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{LiF}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "ionic-bond",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{N}_2<\\mathrm{SO}_2<\\mathrm{ClF}_3<\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{LiF}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd99hn2",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following is least ionic?</p>",
    "options": [
      "CoCl$$_2$$",
      "KCl",
      "BaCl$$_2$$",
      "AgCl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "ionic-bond",
    "solution": "AgCl"
  },
  {
    "id": "5ewmfVaZwhG6amZL",
    "question": "Which of the following are arranged in an increasing order of their bond strengths?",
    "options": [
      "$$O_2^-$$ &lt; O<sub>2</sub> &lt; $$O_2^+$$ &lt; $$O_2^{2-}$$",
      "$$O_2^{2-}$$ &lt; $$O_2^-$$ &lt; $$O_2$$ &lt; $$O_2^{+}$$",
      "$$O_2^-$$ &lt; $$O_2^{2-}$$ &lt; $$O_2$$ &lt; $$O_2^{+}$$",
      "$$O_2^{+}$$ &lt; $$O_2$$ &lt; $$O_2^-$$ &lt; $$O_2^{2-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$O_2^{2-}$$ &lt; $$O_2^-$$ &lt; $$O_2$$ &lt; $$O_2^{+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "nZWgMrVC61t5mc6a",
    "question": "The bond order in NO is 2.5 while that in NO<sup>+</sup> is 3. Which of the following statements is true for these two species? ",
    "options": [
      "Bond length in NO<sup>+</sup> is greater than in NO ",
      "Bond length is unpredictable",
      "Bond length in NO<sup>+</sup> in equal to that in NO",
      "Bond length in NO is greater than in NO<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "Bond length in NO is greater than in NO<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "78vvWsuL3joAOjJY",
    "question": "Which one of the following species is diamagnetic in nature? ",
    "options": [
      "$$He_2^+$$",
      "H<sub>2</sub>",
      "$$H_2^+$$",
      "$$H_2^-$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "H<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "l1VU0nBBIoUEbBGm",
    "question": "Which of the following molecules/ions does not contain unpaired electrons? ",
    "options": [
      "$$O_2^{2−} $$",
      "B<sub>2</sub>",
      "$$N_2^+$$",
      "O<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$O_2^{2−} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "v25tvfRhzo8LhY59",
    "question": "Which of the following species exhibits the diamagnetic behaviour? ",
    "options": [
      "$$O_2^{2−}$$",
      "NO",
      "$$O_2^+$$",
      "O<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$O_2^{2−}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Mk1EqYkRfu6bSrWr",
    "question": "In which of the following ionization processes, the bond order has increased and the magnetic\nbehaviour has changed? ",
    "options": [
      "$$C_2 \\to C_2^+$$",
      "$$N_2 \\to N_2^+$$",
      "$$NO \\to NO^+$$",
      "$$O_2 \\to O_2^+$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$NO \\to NO^+$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "hVhRBuRAwNW6A8B1",
    "question": "Which of the following pair of species have the same bond order?",
    "options": [
      "CN<sup>-</sup> and NO<sup>+</sup>",
      "CN<sup>-</sup> and CN<sup>+</sup>",
      "$$O_2^-$$ and CN<sup>-</sup>",
      "NO<sup>+</sup> and CN<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "CN<sup>-</sup> and NO<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Vnurx6F2t4VBIDLe",
    "question": "Using MO theory, predict which of the following species has the shortest bond length?",
    "options": [
      "$$O_2^+$$",
      "$$O_2^-$$",
      "$$O_2^{2-}$$",
      "$$O_2^{2+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$O_2^{2+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "e9ZZ6hVkVRrr20He",
    "question": "In which of the following pairs of molecules/ions, both the species are not likely to exist?",
    "options": [
      "$$H_2^+$$ , $$He_2^{2-}$$",
      "$$H_2^-$$ , $$He_2^{2-}$$",
      "$$H_2^{2+}$$ , $$He_2$$",
      "$$H_2^-$$ , $$He_2^{2+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$H_2^{2+}$$ , $$He_2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "71vVjiJV8KEZUIQD",
    "question": "Stability of the species Li<sub>2</sub>, $$Li_2^−$$ and $$Li_2^+$$ increases in the order of: ",
    "options": [
      "Li<sub>2</sub> &lt; $$Li_2^+$$ &lt; $$Li_2^-$$",
      "$$Li_2^+$$ &lt; $$Li_2^-$$ &lt; Li<sub>2</sub>",
      "$$Li_2^-$$ &lt;$$Li_2^+$$ &lt;  Li<sub>2</sub>",
      "$$Li_2^-$$ &lt; Li<sub>2</sub> &lt; $$Li_2^+$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$Li_2^-$$ &lt;$$Li_2^+$$ &lt;  Li<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "2I94DYV587XfHvOi",
    "question": "Which of the following species is <b>not</b> paramagnetic?\n",
    "options": [
      "CO",
      "O<sub>2</sub>",
      "B<sub>2</sub>",
      "NO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "CO"
  },
  {
    "id": "YFVl81zZz9l5GTXPCmqsx",
    "question": "Which of the following is paramagnetic ? ",
    "options": [
      "NO<sup>+</sup> ",
      "CO",
      "$$O_2^{2 - }$$",
      "B<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "B<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "ifAENWMErstj8jr3HyiMV",
    "question": "In the molecular orbital diagram for the molecular ion, N<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup>, the number of electrons in the $$\\sigma $$<sub>2p<sub>z</sub></sub> molecular orbital is : ",
    "options": [
      "0",
      "1",
      "2",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "xbbpwAyMOufn5c54",
    "question": "According to molecular orbital theory, which of the following will not be a viable molecule?",
    "options": [
      "$${\\rm H}e_2^{2 + }$$ ",
      "$${\\rm H}e_2^{ + }$$",
      "$${\\rm H}_2^{- }$$",
      "$${\\rm H}_2^{2 - }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$${\\rm H}_2^{2 - }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "5QPKgmMT1jSaJIB9R9HXC",
    "question": "According to molecular orbital theory, which of the following is true with respect to Li<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup> and Li<sub>2</sub><sup>$$-$$</sup> ? ",
    "options": [
      "$$Li_2^ + $$ is unstable and $$Li_2^ - $$ is stable",
      "$$Li_2^ + $$ is stable and $$Li_2^ - $$ unstable",
      "Both are stable ",
      "Both are unstable "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "Both are stable "
  },
  {
    "id": "HPd9AXNBinv1Zb9G5x3rsa0w2w9jww9gavo",
    "question": "During the change of O<sub>2</sub> to O<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup>\n, the incoming electron goes to the orbital :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\pi 2{p_y}$$",
      "$${\\sigma ^*}2{p_z}$$",
      "$${\\pi ^*}2{p_x}$$",
      "$$\\pi 2{p_x}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$${\\pi ^*}2{p_x}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "tajJ8St48Q1lcW1qdYfUS",
    "question": "Among the following species, the diamagnetic\nmolecule is",
    "options": [
      "CO",
      "B<sub>2</sub>",
      "O<sub>2</sub>",
      "NO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "CO"
  },
  {
    "id": "4kAdZGcAFWDgiyauTrdhC",
    "question": "Among the following, the molecule expected\nto be stabilized by anion formation is :<br/>\nC<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>2</sub>, NO, F<sub>2</sub>",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>2</sub>",
      "NO",
      "O<sub>2</sub>",
      "F<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "C<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "5PO70AvHVPwuEkXuNRcN5",
    "question": "Among the following molecules / ions,\n$$C_2^{2 - },N_2^{2 - },O_2^{2 - },{O_2}$$\nwhich one is diamagnetic and has the shortest\nbond length?",
    "options": [
      "$${O_2}$$",
      "$$C_2^{2 - }$$",
      "$$N_2^{2 - }$$",
      "$$O_2^{2 - }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$C_2^{2 - }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jyTyBEbXoLWjxRE6s2Jln",
    "question": "Two pi and half sigma bonds are present in : ",
    "options": [
      "O<sub>2</sub>",
      "N$$_2^ + $$",
      "O$$_2^ + $$",
      "N<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "N$$_2^ + $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "rZmnCDvb0RMeec8w5Dkta",
    "question": "In which of the following process, the bond order has increased and paramagnetic character has charged to diamagnetic ? ",
    "options": [
      "NO $$ \\to $$ NO<sup>+</sup>",
      "N<sub>2</sub> $$ \\to $$&nbsp;N<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup>",
      "O<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;O<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup>",
      "O<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;O<sub>2</sub><sup>2$$-$$</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "NO $$ \\to $$ NO<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "39uduN98fcC5Wjng4F7k9k2k5epf47d",
    "question": "The bond order and the magnetic characteristics of CN<sup>-</sup>\n are :",
    "options": [
      "3, paramagnetic",
      "$$2{1 \\over 2}$$, paramagnetic",
      "3, diamagnetic",
      "$$2{1 \\over 2}$$, diamagnetic"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "3, diamagnetic"
  },
  {
    "id": "OJ4HXN2l6O25EZHBDR7k9k2k5icjff5",
    "question": "If the magnetic moment of a dioxygen species\nis 1.73 B.M, it may be :",
    "options": [
      "$$O_2^ - $$ or $$O_2^ + $$",
      "O<sub>2</sub>, $$O_2^ - $$ or $$O_2^ + $$",
      "O<sub>2</sub> or $$O_2^ + $$",
      "O<sub>2</sub> or $$O_2^ - $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$O_2^ - $$ or $$O_2^ + $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "mHQPHyo2fQemHaqz1Fjgy2xukf2b5jgn",
    "question": "Of the species, NO, NO<sup>+</sup>, NO<sup>2+</sup> and NO<sup>-</sup>\n, the one with minimum bond strength is :",
    "options": [
      "NO<sup>–</sup>",
      "NO",
      "NO<sup>+</sup>",
      "NO<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "NO<sup>–</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "LWpA0sfVy1vp0ZMoaD1kls92xym",
    "question": "According to molecular orbital theory, the species among the following that does not exist is :",
    "options": [
      "$${O_2}^{2 - }$$",
      "$$B{e_2}$$",
      "$$H{e_2}^ - $$",
      "$$H{e_2}^ + $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$B{e_2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "OJX2Tfv6pbCnjqppz81klurauoc",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I (Molecule)</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II (Bond order)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>$$N{e_2}$$</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>1</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>$${N_2}$$</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>2</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>$${F_2}$$</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>0</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>$${O_2}$$</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>3</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (i), (b) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iv)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (d) $$ \\to $$ (i)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (c) $$ \\to $$ (i), (d) $$ \\to $$ (ii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (i), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (c) $$ \\to $$ (i), (d) $$ \\to $$ (ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krx4sr8p",
    "question": "In the following the correct bond order sequence is :",
    "options": [
      "$$O_2^{2 - } &gt; O_2^ +  &gt; O_2^ -  &gt; {O_2}$$",
      "$$O_2^ +  &gt; O_2^ -  &gt; O_2^{2 - } &gt; {O_2}$$",
      "$$O_2^ +  &gt; {O_2} &gt; O_2^ -  &gt; O_2^{2 - }$$",
      "$${O_2} &gt; O_2^ -  &gt; O_2^{2 - } &gt; O_2^ + $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$O_2^ +  &gt; {O_2} &gt; O_2^ -  &gt; O_2^{2 - }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktcnvdv8",
    "question": "The bond order and magnetic behaviour of $$O_2^ - $$ ion are respectively :",
    "options": [
      "1.5 and paramagnetic ",
      "1.5 and diamagnetic",
      "2 and diamagnetic",
      "1 and paramagnetic "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "1.5 and paramagnetic "
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktebop1v",
    "question": "Match items of List-I with those of List-II :<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I<br/>(Property)</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II<br/>(Example)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Diamagnetism</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>MnO</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Ferrimagnetism</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>$${O_2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Paramagnetism</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>NaCl</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Antiferromagnetism</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>$$F{e_3}{O_4}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(ii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn1rdyb",
    "question": "Number of paramagnetic oxides among the following given oxides is ____________.<br/><br/>Li<sub>2</sub>O, CaO, Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, KO<sub>2</sub>, MgO and K<sub>2</sub>O",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "2",
      "3",
      "0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58di4xa",
    "question": "<p>Consider the ions/molecule</p>\n<p>O$$_2^ + $$, O<sub>2</sub>, O$$_2^ - $$, O$$_2^ {2-} $$</p>\n<p>For increasing bond order the correct option is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "O$$_2^ {2-} $$ < O$$_2^ - $$ < O<sub>2</sub> < O$$_2^ + $$",
      "O$$_2^ - $$ < O$$_2^ {2-} $$ < O<sub>2</sub> < O$$_2^ + $$",
      "O$$_2^ - $$ < O$$_2^ {2-} $$ < O$$_2^ + $$ < O<sub>2</sub>",
      "O$$_2^ - $$ < O$$_2^ + $$ < O$$_2^ {2-} $$ < O<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "O$$_2^ {2-} $$ < O$$_2^ - $$ < O<sub>2</sub> < O$$_2^ + $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5alkri6",
    "question": "<p>Bonding in which of the following diatomic molecule(s) become(s) stronger, on the basis of MO Theory, by removal of an electron?</p>\n<p>(A) NO</p>\n<p>(B) N<sub>2</sub></p>\n<p>(C) O<sub>2</sub></p>\n<p>(D) C<sub>2</sub></p>\n<p>(E) B<sub>2</sub></p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A), (B), (C) only",
      "(B), (C), (E) only",
      "(A), (C) only",
      "(D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "(A), (C) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bcwle0",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of bond orders of $${C_2}^{2 - }$$, $${N_2}^{2 - }$$ and $${O_2}^{2 - }$$</p> is, respectively",
    "options": [
      "$${C_2}^{2 - }$$ < $${N_2}^{2 - }$$ < $${O_2}^{2 - }$$",
      "$${O_2}^{2 - }$$ < $${N_2}^{2 - }$$ < $${C_2}^{2 - }$$",
      "$${C_2}^{2 - }$$ < $${O_2}^{2 - }$$ < $${N_2}^{2 - }$$",
      "$${N_2}^{2 - }$$ < $${C_2}^{2 - }$$ < $${O_2}^{2 - }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$${O_2}^{2 - }$$ < $${N_2}^{2 - }$$ < $${C_2}^{2 - }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldscb4vt",
    "question": "<p>According to MO theory the bond orders for $$\\mathrm{O}$$$$_2^{2 - }$$, $$\\mathrm{CO}$$ and $$\\mathrm{NO^+}$$ respectively, are</p>",
    "options": [
      "1, 3 and 3",
      "2, 3 and 3",
      "1, 2 and 3",
      "1, 3 and 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "1, 3 and 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsqoz4v",
    "question": "<p>The magnetic behaviour of $$\\mathrm{Li_2O,Na_2O_2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{KO_2}$$, respectively, are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "paramagnetic, paramagnetic and diamagnetic",
      "paramagnetic, diamagnetic and paramagnetic",
      "diamagnetic, paramagnetic and diamagnetic",
      "diamagnetic, diamagnetic and paramagnetic"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "diamagnetic, diamagnetic and paramagnetic"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwsjb3e",
    "question": "<p>What is the number of unpaired electron(s) in the highest occupied molecular orbital of the following species : $$\\mathrm{{N_2};N_2^ + ;{O_2};O_2^ + }$$ ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "0, 1, 0, 1",
      "2, 1, 0, 1",
      "0, 1, 2, 1",
      "2, 1, 2, 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "0, 1, 2, 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq3vwp7",
    "question": "<p>In which of the following processes, the bond order increases and paramagnetic character changes to diamagnetic one ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{O}_{2} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{O}_{2}^{2-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{N}_{2} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{N}_{2}^{+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{NO} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{NO}^{+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{O}_{2} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{O}_{2}^{+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{NO} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{NO}^{+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrkbmlp",
    "question": "<p>The bond order and magnetic property of acetylide ion are same as that of</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{O}_{2}^{+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{O}_{2}^{-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{N}_{2}^{+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{NO}^{+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{NO}^{+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaowhvy",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (I)</b> : A $\\pi$ bonding MO has lower electron density above and below the inter-nuclear axis.\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (II)</b> : The $\\pi^*$ antibonding MO has a node between the nuclei.<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7imu1",
    "question": "<p>The linear combination of atomic orbitals to form molecular orbitals takes place only when the combining atomic orbitals</p>\n<p>A. have the same energy</p>\n<p>B. have the minimum overlap</p>\n<p>C. have same symmetry about the molecular axis</p>\n<p>D. have different symmetry about the molecular axis</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "B, C, D only",
      "A, B, C only",
      "B and D only",
      "A and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "A and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xm5q9",
    "question": "<p>When $$\\psi_{\\mathrm{A}}$$ and $$\\psi_{\\mathrm{B}}$$ are the wave functions of atomic orbitals, then $$\\sigma^*$$ is represented by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\psi_A+2 \\psi_B$$\n",
      "$$\\psi_{\\mathrm{A}}-\\psi_{\\mathrm{B}}$$\n",
      "$$\\psi_A-2 \\psi_B$$\n",
      "$$\\psi_{\\mathrm{A}}+\\psi_{\\mathrm{B}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "molecular-orbital-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\psi_{\\mathrm{A}}-\\psi_{\\mathrm{B}}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krx8h5dq",
    "question": "Identify the species having one $$\\pi$$-bond and maximum number of canonical forms from the following :",
    "options": [
      "SO<sub>3</sub>",
      "O<sub>2</sub>",
      "SO<sub>2</sub>",
      "CO$$_3^{2 - }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "resonance",
    "solution": "CO$$_3^{2 - }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjlsrq",
    "question": "<p>The difference in energy between the actual structure and the lowest energy resonance structure for the given compound is</p>",
    "options": [
      "electromeric energy\n",
      "resonance energy\n",
      "ionization energy\n",
      "hyperconjugation energy"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "resonance",
    "solution": "resonance energy\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "SH9c4822qbHkKs4MGODP9",
    "question": "The pair that contains two P – H bonds in each of the oxoacids is ",
    "options": [
      "H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>",
      "H<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and H<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>6</sub>",
      "H<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>3</sub>",
      "H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>3</sub> and H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "VLonTGvaaXvC2Rn2Px7k9k2k5dz61w9",
    "question": "The relative strength of interionic/intermolecular forces in decreasing order is :\n",
    "options": [
      "dipole-dipole $$&gt;$$ ion-dipole $$&gt;$$ ion-ion",
      "ion-dipole $$&gt;$$ dipole-dipole $$&gt;$$ ion-ion",
      "ion-dipole $$&gt;$$ ion-ion $$&gt;$$ dipole-dipole",
      "ion-ion $$&gt;$$ ion-dipole $$&gt;$$ dipole-dipole"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-bonding-and-molecular-structure",
    "topic": "van-der-walls-forces",
    "solution": "ion-ion $$&gt;$$ ion-dipole $$&gt;$$ dipole-dipole"
  },
  {
    "id": "zIzC0tNqd3aPhBvL",
    "question": "For the reaction CO (g) + (1/2) O<sub>2</sub> (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ CO<sub>2</sub> (g), K<sub>p</sub>/K<sub>c</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "RT",
      "(RT)<sup>-1</sup>",
      "(RT)<sup>-1/2</sup>",
      "(RT)<sup>1/2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "(RT)<sup>-1/2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "SS6zCGlJmHjYxkXJ",
    "question": "For the reaction equilibrium <br/>\nN<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2NO<sub>2</sub> (g)<br/>\nthe concentrations of N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> at equilibrium are 4.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> and 1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> mol L<sup>-1</sup> respectively. The value of K<sub>c</sub> for the reaction is",
    "options": [
      "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-1</sup> mol L<sup>-1</sup>",
      "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-3</sup> mol L<sup>-1</sup>",
      "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> mol L<sup>-1</sup>",
      "3.3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>2</sup> mol L<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-3</sup> mol L<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "xnMc4pIlDWh0AoYp",
    "question": "For the reaction, CO(g) + Cl<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ COCl<sub>2</sub>(g) the $${{{K_p}} \\over {{K_c}}}$$ is equal to :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {RT} $$",
      "RT",
      "1/RT",
      "1.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "1/RT"
  },
  {
    "id": "FOPtW9AewX3ZEoEr",
    "question": "What is the equilibrium expression for the reaction <br/>\nP<sub>4</sub> (s) + 5O<sub>2</sub> $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ P<sub>4</sub>O<sub>10</sub> (s)?",
    "options": [
      "K<sub>c</sub> = [P<sub>4</sub>O<sub>10</sub>] / 5[P<sub>4</sub>] [O<sub>2</sub>] ",
      "K<sub>c</sub> = 1/[O<sub>2</sub>]<sup>5</sup>",
      "K<sub>c</sub> = [P<sub>4</sub>O<sub>10</sub>] / [P<sub>4</sub>] [O<sub>2</sub>]<sup>5</sup>",
      "K<sub>c</sub> = [O<sub>2</sub>]<sup>5</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "K<sub>c</sub> = 1/[O<sub>2</sub>]<sup>5</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "jBYItI7R5Faztuq9",
    "question": "The equilibrium constant for the reaction N<sub>2</sub>(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2NO(g) at temperature T is\n4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-4</sup>. The value of K<sub>c</sub> for the reaction NO(g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ $$1 \\over 2$$N<sub>2</sub> (g) + $$1 \\over 2$$O<sub>2</sub> (g) at the same temperature is :",
    "options": [
      "2.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>2</sup>",
      "4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-4</sup>",
      "50",
      "0.02"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "50"
  },
  {
    "id": "es64H9nSDhNRSnA4",
    "question": "For the reaction\n2NO<sub>2</sub> (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2NO (g) + O<sub>2</sub> (g), (K<sub>c</sub> = 1.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-6</sup> at 184<sup>o</sup>C) (R = 0.0831 kJ/(mol. K))<br/>\nWhen K<sub>p</sub> and K<sub>c</sub> are compared at 184<sup>o</sup>C , it is found that :",
    "options": [
      "K<sub>p</sub> is greater than K<sub>c</sub>",
      "K<sub>p</sub> is less than K<sub>c</sub>",
      "K<sub>p</sub> = K<sub>c</sub>",
      "Whether K<sub>p</sub> is greater than, less than or equal to K<sub>c</sub> depends upon the total gas\npressure "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "K<sub>p</sub> is greater than K<sub>c</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "ufl7V9IaTO6yQwmK",
    "question": "An amount of solid NH4<sub></sub>HS is placed in a flask already containing ammonia gas at a\ncertain temperature and 0.50 atm. Pressure. Ammonium hydrogen sulphide\ndecomposes to yield NH<sub>3</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>S gases in the flask. When the decomposition\nreaction reaches equilibrium, the total pressure in the flask rises to 0.84 atm. The\nequilibrium constant for NH<sub>4</sub>HS decomposition at this temperature is :",
    "options": [
      "0.30",
      "0.11",
      "0.17",
      "0.18"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "0.11"
  },
  {
    "id": "7T1O7dmxQQdrgE6B",
    "question": "Phosphorus pentachloride dissociates as follows, in a closed reaction vessel<br/>\nPCl<sub>5</sub> (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ PCl<sub>3</sub> (g) + Cl<sub>2</sub> (g) <br/>\nIf total pressure at equilibrium of the reaction mixture is P and degree of dissociation of PCl<sub>5</sub> is x, the\npartial pressure of PCl<sub>3</sub> will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {{x \\over {x + 1}}} \\right)P$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {{2x \\over {1 - x}}} \\right)P$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {{x \\over {x - 1}}} \\right)P$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {{x \\over {1 - x}}} \\right)P$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {{x \\over {x + 1}}} \\right)P$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "BN4EdeIy0Gczcmki",
    "question": "The equilibrium constant for the reaction <br/>\nSO<sub>3</sub> (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ SO<sub>2</sub> (g) + $$1 \\over 2$$ O<sub>2</sub> (g)<br/> \nis K<sub>c</sub> = 4.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–2</sup>. The value of K<sub>c</sub> for the reaction<br/>\n2SO<sub>2</sub> (g) + O<sub>2</sub> (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2SO<sub>3</sub> (g) will be :",
    "options": [
      "416",
      "9.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup>",
      "4.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup>",
      "2.40 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "416"
  },
  {
    "id": "3yX4MhgoPTGVHeB5",
    "question": "The equilibrium constants K<sub>P1</sub> and K<sub>P2</sub> for the reactions X $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2Y and Z  $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ P + Q, respectively are in\nthe ratio of 1 : 9. If the degree of dissociation of X and Z be equal then the ratio of total pressure at\nthese equilibria is :",
    "options": [
      "1 : 36",
      "1 : 1",
      "1 : 3",
      "1 : 9"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "1 : 36"
  },
  {
    "id": "iZjadyhBb82AiAfg",
    "question": "For the following three reactions a, b and c, equilibrium constants are given: <br/>\na. CO (g) + H<sub>2</sub>O (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ CO<sub>2</sub>(g) + H<sub>2</sub> (g) ; K<sub>1</sub><br/>\nb. CH<sub>4</sub> (g) + H<sub>2</sub>O (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ CO(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub> (g) ; K<sub>2</sub><br/>\nc. CH<sub>4</sub> (g) + 2H<sub>2</sub>O (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ CO<sub>2</sub>(g) + 4H<sub>2</sub> (g) ; K<sub>3</sub><br/>",
    "options": [
      "$${K_1}\\sqrt {{K_2}}  = {K_3}$$ ",
      "K<sub>2</sub>K<sub>3</sub> = K<sub>1</sub>",
      "K<sub>3</sub> = K<sub>1</sub>K<sub>2</sub>",
      "K<sub>3</sub>.$$K_2^3$$ = $$K_1^2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "K<sub>3</sub> = K<sub>1</sub>K<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "vI7YE9JePw4pjj4J",
    "question": "In aqueous solution the ionization constants for carbonic acid are<br/>\nK<sub>1</sub> = 4.2 x 10<sup>–7</sup> and K<sub>2</sub> = 4.8 x 10<sup>–11</sup><br/>\nSelect the correct statement for a saturated 0.034 M solution of the carbonic acid.",
    "options": [
      "The concentration of\n$$CO_3^{2−}$$ is 0.034 M.",
      "The concentration of\n$$CO_3^{2−}$$ is greater than that of $$HCO_3^{−}$$",
      "The concentration of H<sup>+</sup> and $$HCO_3^−$$ are approximately equal.",
      "The concentration of H<sup>+</sup> is double that of $$CO_3^−$$."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "The concentration of H<sup>+</sup> and $$HCO_3^−$$ are approximately equal."
  },
  {
    "id": "07XXSkPNgWGKLYw1",
    "question": "A vessel at 1000 K contains CO<sub>2</sub> with a pressure of 0.5 atm. Some of the CO<sub>2</sub> is converted into CO on\nthe addition of graphite. If the total pressure at equilibrium is 0.8 atm, the value of K is :",
    "options": [
      "3 atm ",
      "0.3 atm ",
      "0.18 atm",
      "1.8 atm "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "1.8 atm "
  },
  {
    "id": "OZsFoYVKT9unygaB",
    "question": "The equilibrium constant (K<sub>C</sub>) for the reaction N<sub>2</sub>(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\to$$ 2NO(g) at temperature T is 4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–4</sup>. The value of K<sub>C</sub> for the reaction, NO(g) $$\\to$$ 1/2N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 1/2O<sub>2</sub>(g) at the same temperature is : ",
    "options": [
      "0.02",
      "2.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>2</sup>",
      "4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-4</sup>",
      "50.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "50.0"
  },
  {
    "id": "I2FfcEHEOHxjLXgs",
    "question": "For the reaction SO<sub>2</sub> (g) + $${1 \\over 2} O_2(g) \\leftrightharpoons$$ SO<sub>3</sub>(g). <br/>\n if K<sub>P</sub> = K<sub>C</sub>(RT)<sup>x</sup> where the symbols have usual meaning then\nthe value of x is: (assuming ideality)",
    "options": [
      "-1",
      "-1/2",
      "1/2",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "-1/2"
  },
  {
    "id": "slcAxWaeZqwRmZga",
    "question": "The standard Gibbs energy change at 300 K for the reaction 2A $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ B + C is 2494.2 J. At a given time,\nthe composition of the reaction mixture is [A] = 1/2, [B] = 2 and [C] = 1/2. The reaction proceeds in the: [R = 8.314 J/K/mol, e = 2.718]",
    "options": [
      "reverse direction because Q &gt; K<sub>c</sub>",
      "forward direction because Q &lt; K<sub>c</sub>",
      "reverse direction because Q &lt; K<sub>c</sub>",
      "forward direction because Q &gt; K<sub>c</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "reverse direction because Q &gt; K<sub>c</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "iBWkn6XhSK3d12VG",
    "question": "The equilibrium constant at 298 K for a reaction A + B $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ C + D is 100. If the initial concentration of\nall the four species were 1M each, then equilibrium concentration of D (in mol L<sup>–1</sup>) will be: ",
    "options": [
      "0.818",
      "1.818",
      "1.182",
      "0.182"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "1.818"
  },
  {
    "id": "ax46xkqWgYsItJK5jVP6o",
    "question": "A solid XY kept in an evacuated sealed container undergoes decomposition to form a mixture of gases X and Y at temperature T. The equilibrium pressure is 10 bar in this vessel. K<sub>p</sub> for this reaction is :\n",
    "options": [
      "5",
      "10",
      "25",
      "100"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "25"
  },
  {
    "id": "CprqaIhBf2B6XthNgHb7s",
    "question": "At a certain temperature in a $$5$$ $$L$$ vessel, 2 moles of carbon monoxide and 3 moles of chlorine were allowed to reach equilibrium according to the reaction,  \n<br/>         CO + Cl<sub>2</sub> $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ COCl<sub>2</sub>\n<br/>At equilibrium, if one mole of CO is present then equilibrium constant (K<sub>c</sub>) for the reaction is : ",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "2.5",
      "3",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "2.5"
  },
  {
    "id": "5DyBjOOhCKpSEcMoeo3rsa0w2w9jx97n6gj",
    "question": "In which one of the following equilibria, K<sub>p</sub> $$ \\ne $$ K<sub>C</sub> ?",
    "options": [
      "2NO(g) ⇋ N<sub>2</sub>(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g)",
      "2C(s) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) ⇋ 2CO(g)",
      "2HI(g) ⇋ H<sub>2</sub>(g) + I<sub>2</sub>(g)",
      "NO<sub>2</sub>(g) + SO<sub>2</sub>(g) ⇋ NO(g) + SO<sub>3</sub>(g)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "2C(s) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) ⇋ 2CO(g)"
  },
  {
    "id": "WTrxdDGwVVa5QCJNsLbQe",
    "question": "For the following reactions, equilibrium\nconstants are given :<br/>\n<br/>S(s) + O<sub>2</sub>(g)  ⇋  SO<sub>2</sub>(g); K<sub>1</sub> = 10<sup>52</sup><br/>\n<br/>2S(s) + 3O<sub>2</sub>(g) ⇋  2SO<sub>3</sub>(g); K<sub>2</sub> = 10<sup>129</sup><br/>\n<br/>The equilibrium constant for the reaction,<br/>\n<br/>2SO<sub>2</sub>(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) ⇋  2SO<sub>3</sub>(g) is :",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>181</sup>",
      "10<sup>25</sup>",
      "10<sup>77</sup>",
      "10<sup>154</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "10<sup>25</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "7Wlg8vyQeUZ8Nfndzb1Ko",
    "question": "Consider the reaction \n<br/>N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ 2NH<sub>3</sub>(g)\n<br/><br/>The equilibrium constant of the above reaction is K<sub>p</sub>. If pure ammonia is left to dissociate, the partial pressure of ammonia at equilibrium is given by (Assume that P<sub>NH<sub>3</sub></sub>  &lt;&lt; P<sub>total</sub> at equilibrium) ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{3^{{3 \\over 2}}}{K_P^{{1 \\over 2}}}{P^2}} \\over 4}$$",
      "$${{K_P^{{1 \\over 2}}{P^2}} \\over 4}$$",
      "$${{{3^{{3 \\over 2}}}{K_P^{{1 \\over 2}}}{P^2}} \\over 16}$$",
      "$${{K_P^{{1 \\over 2}}{P^2}} \\over 16}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "$${{{3^{{3 \\over 2}}}{K_P^{{1 \\over 2}}}{P^2}} \\over 16}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "JX0ZZZbwalKbgS6Jp2vRQ",
    "question": "5.1 g NH<sub>4</sub>SH is introduced in 3.0 L evacuated flask at 327ºC. 30% of the solid NH<sub>4</sub>SH decomposed to NH<sub>3</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>S as gases . The Kp of the reaction at 327<sup>o</sup>C is (R = 0.082 L atm mol<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>, Molar mass of S = 32 g mol<sup>–1</sup> molar mass of N = 14 g mol<sup>–1</sup>) \n",
    "options": [
      "0.242 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> atm<sup>2</sup>",
      "1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup> atm<sup>2</sup>\n",
      "4.9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> atm<sup>2</sup>",
      "0.242 atm<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "0.242 atm<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "sCuCIyzQctkzU3Yg4cnVF",
    "question": "The values of K<sub>p</sub>/K<sub>c</sub> for the following reactions at 300 K are, respectively : (At 300 K, RT = 24.62 dm<sup>3</sup> atm mol<sup>–1</sup>) \n<br/><br/>N<sub>2</sub>(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g)  $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ 2 NO(g)\n<br/><br/>N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>(g)  $$\\rightleftharpoons$$    2 NO(g)\n<br/><br/>N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ 2 NH<sub>3</sub>(g)",
    "options": [
      "24.62 dm<sup>3</sup> atm mol<sup>–1</sup>, 606.0 dm<sup>6</sup> atm<sup>2</sup> mol<sup>–2</sup> 1.65 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> dm<sup>–6</sup> atm<sup>–2</sup> mol<sup>2</sup>",
      "1,4.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–2</sup> dm<sup>–3</sup> atm<sup>–1</sup> mol, 606 dm<sup>6</sup> atm<sup>2</sup> mol<sup>–2</sup>",
      "1,24.62 dm<sup>3</sup> atm mol<sup>–1</sup> , 1.65 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> dm<sup>–6</sup> atm <sup>–2</sup> mol<sup>2</sup>",
      "1, 24.62 dm<sup>3</sup> atm mol<sup>–1</sup>, 606.0 dm<sup>6</sup> atm<sup>2</sup> mol<sup>–2</sup>\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "1,24.62 dm<sup>3</sup> atm mol<sup>–1</sup> , 1.65 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> dm<sup>–6</sup> atm <sup>–2</sup> mol<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "dfT78WspfSOKCkAFl9jgy2xukg3fgqra",
    "question": "The value of K<sub>C</sub> is 64 at 800 K for the reaction\n<br/><br/>N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub>(g) ⇌ 2NH<sub>3</sub>(g)\n<br/><br/>The value of K<sub>C</sub> for the following reaction is :\n<br/><br/>NH<sub>3</sub>(g) ⇌ $${1 \\over 2}$$N<sub>2</sub>(g) + $${3 \\over 2}$$H<sub>2</sub>(g)",
    "options": [
      "8",
      "$${1 \\over 8}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {64}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 8}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "tGqFP5AUBgiAasKCDRjgy2xukfuptcel",
    "question": "The variation of equilibrium constant with\ntemperature is given below :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\">Temperature</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\">Equilibrium Constant</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">T<sub>1</sub> = 25<sup>o</sup>C</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">K<sub>1</sub> = 10</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">T<sub>2</sub> = 100<sup>o</sup>C</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">K<sub>2</sub> = 100</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>\n<br/>The values of $$\\Delta $$H<sup>o</sup>, $$\\Delta $$G<sup>o</sup> at <br/>T<sub>1</sub> and $$\\Delta $$G<sup>o</sup> at T<sub>2</sub>\n(in kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>) respectively, are close to :<br/>[Use\nR = 8.314 J K<sup>–1</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "28.4, –5.71 and –14.29",
      "0.64, –7.14 and –5.71",
      "28.4, –7.14 and –5.71",
      "0.64, –5.71 and –14.29"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "28.4, –5.71 and –14.29"
  },
  {
    "id": "KYfGgwFztyUfWPCoG2jgy2xukft7tr3c",
    "question": "For the reaction\n<br/><br/>Fe<sub>2</sub>N(s) + $${3 \\over 2}$$H<sub>2</sub>(g) ⇌ 2Fe(s) + NH<sub>3</sub>(g)",
    "options": [
      "K<sub>C</sub> = K<sub>p</sub>(RT)<sup>1/2</sup>",
      "K<sub>C</sub> = K<sub>p</sub>(RT)<sup>-1/2</sup>",
      "K<sub>C</sub> = K<sub>p</sub>(RT)",
      "K<sub>C</sub> = K<sub>p</sub>(RT)<sup>3/2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "K<sub>C</sub> = K<sub>p</sub>(RT)<sup>1/2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Wymv2TIWJaheArgnEdjgy2xukfi6jvls",
    "question": "Consider the following reaction:\n<br/><br/>N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>(g) ⇌ 2NO<sub>2</sub>(g); $$\\Delta $$H<sup>o</sup> = +58 kJ\n<br/><br/>For each of the following cases (a, b), the direction in which the equilibrium shifts is :\n<br/>(a) Temperature is decreased.\n<br/>(b) Pressure is increased by adding N<sub>2</sub>\n at constant T.",
    "options": [
      "(a) towards reactant, (b) towards product",
      "(a) towards reactant, (b) no change",
      "(a) towards product, (b) towards reactant",
      "(a) towards product, (b) no change"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "(a) towards reactant, (b) no change"
  },
  {
    "id": "TIkZn72VO1Voziu4yojgy2xukfc91f9y",
    "question": "If the equilibrium constant for<br/> A ⇌ B + C is $$K_{eq}^{(1)}$$ and that of\n<br/>B + C ⇌ P is $$K_{eq}^{(2)}$$, the equilibrium\n<br/>constant for A ⇌ P is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{K_{eq}^{(1)}} \\over {K_{eq}^{(2)}}}$$",
      "$${K_{eq}^{(1)}}$$ + $${K_{eq}^{(2)}}$$",
      "$${K_{eq}^{(2)}}$$ - $${K_{eq}^{(1)}}$$",
      "$${K_{eq}^{(1)}}$$ $${K_{eq}^{(2)}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "$${K_{eq}^{(1)}}$$ $${K_{eq}^{(2)}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "yEdUCUZPSH3TjZAnJAjgy2xukevgnseq",
    "question": "An open beaker of water in equilibrium with\nwater vapour is in a sealed container. When a\nfew grams of glucose are added to the beaker\nof water, the rate at which water molecules :",
    "options": [
      "leaves the solution increases",
      "leaves the vapour increases",
      "leaves the vapour decreases",
      "leaves the solution decreases"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "leaves the solution decreases"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54y48r6",
    "question": "<p>4.0 moles of argon and 5.0 moles of PCl<sub>5</sub> are introduced into an evacuated flask of 100 litre capacity at 610 K. The system is allowed to equilibrate. At equilibrium, the total pressure of mixture was found to be 6.0 atm. The K<sub>p</sub> for the reaction is :</p>\n<p>[Given : R = 0.082 L atm K<sup>$$-$$1</sup> mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.25",
      "6.24",
      "12.13",
      "15.24"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "2.25"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c689au",
    "question": "<p>For a reaction at equilibrium</p>\n<p>A(g) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ B(g) + $${1 \\over 2}$$ C(g)</p>\n<p>the relation between dissociation constant (K), degree of dissociation ($$\\alpha$$) and equilibrium pressure (p) is given by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$K = {{{\\alpha ^{{1 \\over 2}}}{p^{{3 \\over 2}}}} \\over {{{\\left( {1 + {3 \\over 2}\\alpha } \\right)}^{{1 \\over 2}}}(1 - \\alpha )}}$$",
      "$$K = {{{\\alpha ^{{3 \\over 2}}}{p^{{1 \\over 2}}}} \\over {{{\\left( {2 + \\alpha } \\right)}^{{1 \\over 2}}}(1 - \\alpha )}}$$",
      "$$K = {{{{(\\alpha \\,p)}^{{3 \\over 2}}}} \\over {{{\\left( {1 + {3 \\over 2}\\alpha } \\right)}^{{1 \\over 2}}}(1 - \\alpha )}}$$",
      "$$K = {{{{(\\alpha \\,p)}^{{3 \\over 2}}}} \\over {{{\\left( {1 + \\alpha } \\right)}}{{(1 - \\alpha )}^{{1 \\over 2}}}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "$$K = {{{\\alpha ^{{3 \\over 2}}}{p^{{1 \\over 2}}}} \\over {{{\\left( {2 + \\alpha } \\right)}^{{1 \\over 2}}}(1 - \\alpha )}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w5kyld",
    "question": "<p>The equilibrium constant for the reversible reaction</p>\n<p>2A(g) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ 2B(g) + C(g) is K<sub>1</sub></p>\n<p>$${3 \\over 2}$$A(g) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ $${3 \\over 2}$$B(g) + $${3 \\over 4}$$C(g) is K<sub>2</sub>.</p>\n<p>K<sub>1</sub> and K<sub>2</sub> are related as :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${K_1} = \\sqrt {{K_2}} $$",
      "$${K_2} = \\sqrt {{K_1}} $$",
      "$${K_2} = K_1^{3/4}$$",
      "$${K_1} = K_2^{3/4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "$${K_2} = K_1^{3/4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh27t8xf",
    "question": "<p> For a concentrated solution of a weak electrolyte ($$\\mathrm{K}_{\\text {eq }}=$$ equilibrium constant) $$\\mathrm{A}_{2} \\mathrm{B}_{3}$$ of concentration '$$c$$', the degree of dissociation '$$\\alpha$$' is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left(\\frac{K_{e q}}{25 c^{2}}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{5}}$$",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{K_{e q}}{108 c^{4}}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{5}}$$",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{K_{e q}}{5 c^{4}}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{5}}$$",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{K_{e q}}{6 c^{5}}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{5}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "$$\\left(\\frac{K_{e q}}{108 c^{4}}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{5}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd8scgy",
    "question": "<p>$$\\mathrm{A}_{(\\mathrm{g})} \\rightleftharpoons \\mathrm{B}_{(\\mathrm{g})}+\\frac{\\mathrm{C}}{2}(\\mathrm{g})$$ The correct relationship between $$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{P}}, \\alpha$$ and equilibrium pressure $$\\mathrm{P}$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$K_P=\\frac{\\alpha^{1 / 2} P^{3 / 2}}{(2+\\alpha)^{3 / 2}}$$\n",
      "$$K_P=\\frac{\\alpha^{3 / 2} P^{1 / 2}}{(2+\\alpha)^{1 / 2}(1-\\alpha)}$$\n",
      "$$K_P=\\frac{\\alpha^{1 / 2} P^{1 / 2}}{(2+\\alpha)^{3 / 2}}$$\n",
      "$$K_P=\\frac{\\alpha^{1 / 2} P^{1 / 2}}{(2+\\alpha)^{1 / 2}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "$$K_P=\\frac{\\alpha^{3 / 2} P^{1 / 2}}{(2+\\alpha)^{1 / 2}(1-\\alpha)}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7hf3x",
    "question": "<p>For the given reaction, choose the correct expression of $$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{C}}$$ from the following :-</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{Fe}_{(\\mathrm{aq})}^{3+}+\\mathrm{SCN}_{(\\mathrm{aq})}^{-} \\rightleftharpoons(\\mathrm{FeSCN})_{(\\mathrm{aq})}^{2+}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{C}}=\\frac{\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}\\right]\\left[\\mathrm{SCN}^{-}\\right]}{\\left[\\mathrm{FeSCN}^{2+}\\right]}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{C}}=\\frac{\\left[\\mathrm{FeSCN}^{2+}\\right]}{\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}\\right]\\left[\\mathrm{SCN}^{-}\\right]}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{C}}=\\frac{\\left[\\mathrm{FeSCN}^{2+}\\right]^2}{\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}\\right]\\left[\\mathrm{SCN}^{-}\\right]}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{C}}=\\frac{\\left[\\mathrm{FeSCN}^{2+}\\right]}{\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}\\right]^2\\left[\\mathrm{SCN}^{-}\\right]^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{C}}=\\frac{\\left[\\mathrm{FeSCN}^{2+}\\right]}{\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}\\right]\\left[\\mathrm{SCN}^{-}\\right]}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2er9pz",
    "question": "<p>The equilibrium constant for the reaction</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{SO}_3(\\mathrm{~g}) \\rightleftharpoons \\mathrm{SO}_2(\\mathrm{~g})+\\frac{1}{2} \\mathrm{O}_2(\\mathrm{~g})$$</p>\n<p>is $$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{c}}=4.9 \\times 10^{-2}$$. The value of $$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{c}}$$ for the reaction given below is $$2 \\mathrm{SO}_2(\\mathrm{~g})+\\mathrm{O}_2(\\mathrm{~g}) \\rightleftharpoons 2 \\mathrm{SO}_3(\\mathrm{~g})$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "49",
      "416",
      "41.6",
      "4.9"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "416"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gspnf",
    "question": "<p>For the given hypothetical reactions, the equilibrium constants are as follows :</p>\n<p>$$\\begin{aligned}\n&amp; \\mathrm{X} \\rightleftharpoons \\mathrm{Y} ; \\mathrm{K}_1=1.0 \\\\\n&amp; \\mathrm{Y} \\rightleftharpoons \\mathrm{Z} ; \\mathrm{K}_2=2.0 \\\\\n&amp; \\mathrm{Z} \\rightleftharpoons \\mathrm{W} ; \\mathrm{K}_3=4.0\n\\end{aligned}$$</p>\n<p>The equilibrium constant for the reaction $$\\mathrm{X} \\rightleftharpoons \\mathrm{W}$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "12.0",
      "8.0",
      "6.0",
      "7.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "8.0"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s2805",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : On passing $$\\mathrm{HCl}_{(\\mathrm{g})}$$ through a saturated solution of $$\\mathrm{BaCl}_2$$, at room temperature white turbidity appears.</p>\n<p>Statement II : When $$\\mathrm{HCl}$$ gas is passed through a saturated solution of $$\\mathrm{NaCl}$$, sodium chloride is precipitated due to common ion effect.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct\n",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect\n",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2a7x3",
    "question": "<p>The ratio $$\\frac{K_P}{K_C}$$ for the reaction :</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{CO}_{(\\mathrm{g})}+\\frac{1}{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})} \\rightleftharpoons \\mathrm{CO}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "$$\n(\\mathrm{RT})^{1 / 2}\n$$",
      "RT",
      "$$\\mathrm{\n\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{R T}}}\n$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{\n\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{R T}}}\n$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc587ob",
    "question": "<p>At $$-20^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ and $$1 \\mathrm{~atm}$$ pressure, a cylinder is filled with equal number of $$\\mathrm{H}_2, \\mathrm{I}_2$$ and $$\\mathrm{HI}$$ molecules for the reaction\n$$\\mathrm{H}_2(\\mathrm{~g})+\\mathrm{I}_2(\\mathrm{~g}) \\rightleftharpoons 2 \\mathrm{HI}(\\mathrm{g})$$, the $$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{p}}$$ for the process is $$x \\times 10^{-1}$$.</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{x}=$$ __________.</p>\n<p>[Given : $$\\mathrm{R}=0.082 \\mathrm{~L} \\mathrm{~atm} \\mathrm{~K}^{-1} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$]</p>",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "1",
      "10",
      "0.01"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "chemical-equilibrium,-law-of-mass-action-and-equilibrium-constant",
    "solution": "10"
  },
  {
    "id": "lAbL1dOH9madyBTF",
    "question": "Change in volume of the system does not alter which of the following equilibria?",
    "options": [
      "N<sub>2</sub>(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2NO (g)",
      "PCl<sub>5</sub>(g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ PCl<sub>3</sub> (g) + Cl<sub>2</sub> (g)",
      "N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2NH<sub>3</sub> (g)",
      "SO<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ SO<sub>2</sub> (g) + Cl<sub>2</sub> (g)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "le-chatelier's-principle-and-factors-affecting-chemical-equilibrium",
    "solution": "N<sub>2</sub>(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2NO (g)"
  },
  {
    "id": "3F69yMnkhThKnTAU",
    "question": "Consider the reaction equilibrium<br/>\n2 SO<sub>2</sub> (g) + O<sub>2</sub> (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2 SO<sub>3</sub> (g); $$\\Delta H^o$$ = -198 kJ<br/>\nOne the basis of Le Chatelier's principle, the condition favourable for the forward reaction is :",
    "options": [
      "increasing temperature as well as pressure",
      "lowering the temperature and increasing the pressure",
      "any value of temperature and pressure",
      "lowering temperature as well as pressure"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "le-chatelier's-principle-and-factors-affecting-chemical-equilibrium",
    "solution": "lowering the temperature and increasing the pressure"
  },
  {
    "id": "iCB432yoEFUORD9G",
    "question": "The exothermic formation of ClF<sub>3</sub> is represented by the equation: <br/>\nCl<sub>2</sub> (g) + 3F<sub>2</sub> (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2ClF<sub>3</sub> (g); $$\\Delta H$$ = -329 kJ<br/>\nWhich of the following will increase the quantity of ClF<sub>3</sub> in an equilibrium mixture of\nCl<sub>2</sub>, F<sub>2</sub> and ClF<sub>3</sub>? ",
    "options": [
      "Increasing the temperature",
      "Removing Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "Increasing the volume of the container ",
      "Adding F<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "le-chatelier's-principle-and-factors-affecting-chemical-equilibrium",
    "solution": "Adding F<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "6vmuqmKCuf8FOH8rAjOWz",
    "question": "The following reaction occurs in the Blast Furnace where iron ore is reduced to iron\nmetal :\n<br/><br/>Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>(s) + 3 CO(g) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ 2 Fe(1) + 3 CO<sub>2</sub>(g)\n<br/><br/>Using the Le Chatelier’s principle, predict which one of the following will not disturb the equilibrium ?",
    "options": [
      "Removal of CO ",
      "Removal of CO<sub>2</sub> ",
      "Addition of CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "Addition of Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "le-chatelier's-principle-and-factors-affecting-chemical-equilibrium",
    "solution": "Addition of Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "O2mqgIpwasZAg7L4e5sLG",
    "question": "In which of the following reactions, an increase in the volume of the container will favour the formation of products? ",
    "options": [
      "2NO<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ 2NO(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g)",
      "H<sub>2</sub>(g) + I<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ 2HI(g)",
      "4NH<sub>3</sub>(g) + 5O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ 4NO(g) + 6H<sub>2</sub>O(1)",
      "3O<sub>2</sub> (g) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ 2O<sub>3</sub>(g)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "le-chatelier's-principle-and-factors-affecting-chemical-equilibrium",
    "solution": "2NO<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ 2NO(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g)"
  },
  {
    "id": "ujFoukI0ZKA9R7QeWXVur",
    "question": "The gas phase reaction 2NO<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>(g) is an exothermic reaction.  The decomposition of N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>,  in equilibrium mixture of NO<sub>2</sub>(g) and N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>(g),  can be increased by : ",
    "options": [
      "lowering the temperature.",
      "increasing the pressure.",
      "addition of an inert gas at constant volume. ",
      "addition of an inert gas at constant pressure. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "le-chatelier's-principle-and-factors-affecting-chemical-equilibrium",
    "solution": "addition of an inert gas at constant pressure. "
  },
  {
    "id": "d02h5fIw8PMD42WGT93rsa0w2w9jx0x1gkb",
    "question": "For the reaction,\n<br/> 2SO<sub>2</sub>(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) = 2SO<sub>3</sub>(g), $$\\Delta $$H = –57.2 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>\n and K<sub>C</sub> = 1.7 × 10<sup>16</sup>\n<br/>Which of the following statement is incorrect ? ",
    "options": [
      "The equilibrium will shift in forward direction as the pressure increase.",
      "The addition of inert gas at constant volume will be not affect the equilibrium constant.",
      "The equilibrium constant is large suggestive of reaction going to completion and so no catalyst is\nrequired.",
      "The equilibrium constant decreases as the temperature increase."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "le-chatelier's-principle-and-factors-affecting-chemical-equilibrium",
    "solution": "The equilibrium constant is large suggestive of reaction going to completion and so no catalyst is\nrequired."
  },
  {
    "id": "bkjyti2pc4gu9E5DFQ3rsa0w2w9jx83y3v4",
    "question": "The INCORRECT match in the following is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta $$G<sup>o</sup>\n = 0, K = 1",
      "$$\\Delta $$G<sup>o</sup>\n &lt; 0, K &lt; 1",
      "$$\\Delta $$G<sup>o</sup>\n &gt; 0, K &lt; 1",
      "$$\\Delta $$G<sup>o</sup>\n &lt; 0, K &gt; 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "le-chatelier's-principle-and-factors-affecting-chemical-equilibrium",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta $$G<sup>o</sup>\n &lt; 0, K &lt; 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v4nyl",
    "question": "<p>The following reaction occurs in the Blast furnance where iron ore is reduced to iron metal</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{Fe}_2 \\mathrm{O}_{3(s)}+3 \\mathrm{CO}_{(g)} \\rightleftharpoons \\mathrm{Fe}_{(j)}+3 \\mathrm{CO}_{2(g)}$$</p>\n<p>Using the Le-chatelier's principle, predict which one of the following will not disturb the equilibrium.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Addition of $$\\mathrm{CO}_2$$\n",
      "Removal of $$\\mathrm{CO}$$\n",
      "Addition of $$\\mathrm{Fe}_2 \\mathrm{O}_3$$\n",
      "Removal of $$\\mathrm{CO}_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-equilibrium",
    "topic": "le-chatelier's-principle-and-factors-affecting-chemical-equilibrium",
    "solution": "Addition of $$\\mathrm{Fe}_2 \\mathrm{O}_3$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "VcCAgyN3fplIli6M",
    "question": "In respect of the equation k = Ae<sup>-E<sub>a</sub>/RT</sup> in chemical kinetics, which one of the following statements is correct?",
    "options": [
      "A is adsorption factor",
      "E<sub>a</sub> is energy of activation",
      "R is Rydberg’s constant",
      "k is equilibrium constant"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "E<sub>a</sub> is energy of activation"
  },
  {
    "id": "bFM8KL83corCGEsg",
    "question": "Rate of a reaction can be expressed by Arrhenius equation as: <br/>\n$$$k = A\\,{e^{ - E/RT}}$$$\nIn this equation, E represents ",
    "options": [
      "the energy above which all the colliding molecules will react",
      "the energy below which colliding molecules will not react ",
      "the total energy of the reacting molecules at a temperature, T ",
      "the fraction of molecules with energy greater than the activation energy of the reaction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "the energy above which all the colliding molecules will react"
  },
  {
    "id": "HCILgcwKXnYVtRGp",
    "question": "The energies of activation for forward and reverse reactions for A<sub>2</sub> + B<sub>2</sub> $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2AB are 180 kJ mol<sup>−1</sup>\nand 200 kJ mol<sup>−1</sup> respectively. The presence of catalyst lowers the activation energy of both (forward and reverse) reactions by 100 kJ mol<sup>−1</sup>. The enthalpy change of the reaction ( A<sub>2</sub> + B<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ 2AB) in the presence of catalyst will be (in kJ mol<sup>−1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "300",
      "120",
      "200",
      "20"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "20"
  },
  {
    "id": "hfgD93hASiXKWbBb",
    "question": "The rate of a reaction doubles when its temperature changes from 300K to 310K. Activation energy of such\na reaction will be:(R = 8.314 JK<sup>–1</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup> and log 2 = 0.301) ",
    "options": [
      "48.6 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup> ",
      "58.5 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "60.5 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup> ",
      "53.6 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "53.6 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "dwGTF5etVJOvFtl9",
    "question": "Two reactions R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> have identical pre-exponential factors. Activation energy of R<sub>1</sub> exceeds that of R<sub>2</sub> by 10 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>. If k<sub>1</sub> and k<sub>2</sub> are rate constants for reactions R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> respectively at 300 K, then ln(k<sub>2</sub>/k<sub>1</sub>) is equal to :   <br/>\n(R = 8.314 J mol<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "12",
      "6",
      "4",
      "8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "GXzTlAJFalSuW7k6TcPVS",
    "question": "The rate of a reaction A doubles on increasing the temperature from 300 to 310 K. By how much, the temperature of reaction B should be Increased from 300 K so that rate doubles if activation energy of the reaction B is twice to that of reaction A.",
    "options": [
      "9.84 K",
      "4.92 K",
      "2.45 K",
      "19.67 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "4.92 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "OU0GIizMN5uNzlPOBbG31",
    "question": "The rate of a reaction quadruples when the temperature changes from 300 to 310 K. The activation energy of this reaction is :\n<br/><br/>(Assume activation energy and preexponential factor are independent of\ntemperature; ln 2 = 0.693; R = 8.314 J mol<sup>−1</sup>  K<sup>−1</sup>)\n",
    "options": [
      "107.2 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "53.6 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "26.8 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "214.4 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "107.2 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "3q0krlWokhcZPlqUCoIQV",
    "question": "If a reaction follows the Arrhenius equation, the plot ln k vs $${1 \\over {\\left( {RT} \\right)}}$$ gives straight line with a gradient ($$-$$ y) unit. \n<br/><br/>The energy required to active the reactant is : ",
    "options": [
      "y unit",
      "y/R unit",
      "yR unit",
      "$$-$$y unit"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "y unit"
  },
  {
    "id": "IVPcWimfkzGXc9GmeQ3rsa0w2w9jx0vyjfc",
    "question": "For the reaction of H<sub>2</sub> with I<sub>2</sub>, the rate constant is 2.5 × 10<sup>–4</sup> dm<sup>3</sup>\n mol<sup>–1</sup>s<sup>–1</sup>\n at 327°C and 1.0 dm<sup>3</sup>\n mol<sup>–1</sup>\n at\n527°C. The activation energy for the reaction, in kJ mole<sup>–1</sup>\n is : (R = 8.314 JK<sup>–1</sup>\n mol<sup>–1</sup>\n)",
    "options": [
      "59",
      "166",
      "72",
      "150"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "166"
  },
  {
    "id": "yVktXwXyziBaymmJTG7k9k2k5h5sfuo",
    "question": "The rate of a certain biochemical reaction at physiological temperature (T) occurs 10<sup>6</sup> times faster with\nenzyme than without. The change in the activation energy upon adding enzyme is :",
    "options": [
      "+ 6RT",
      "– 6 (2.303)RT",
      "– 6RT",
      "+ 6(2.303)RT"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "– 6 (2.303)RT"
  },
  {
    "id": "lX2NTCfJLnRUqPdoJijgy2xukfjbf57i",
    "question": "A flask contains a mixture of compounds A and\nB. Both compounds decompose by first-order\nkinetics. The half-lives for A and B are 300 s\nand 180 s, respectively. If the concentrations\nof A and B are equal initially, the time required\nfor the concentration of A to be four times that\nof B(in s) : \n<br/>(Use ln 2 = 0.693)",
    "options": [
      "180",
      "120",
      "300",
      "900"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "900"
  },
  {
    "id": "39ebrqeMsCvjMWY1ET7k9k2k5ibxkiy",
    "question": "For the following reactions<br/>\n$$A\\buildrel {700K} \\over\n \\longrightarrow {\\mathop{\\rm Product}\\nolimits} $$<br/>\n$$A\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{catalyst}^{500K}} {\\mathop{\\rm Product}\\nolimits} $$<br/>\nit was found that E<sub>a</sub> is decreased by 30 kJ/mol\nin the presence of catalyst.<br/>\nIf the rate remains unchanged, the activation\nenergy for catalysed reaction is (Assume pre\nexponential factor is same):",
    "options": [
      "198 kJ/mol",
      "135 kJ/mol",
      "105 kJ/mol",
      "75 kJ/mol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "arrhenius-equation",
    "solution": "75 kJ/mol"
  },
  {
    "id": "fkD6oNW2wDzvFnrU",
    "question": "Consider the reaction, 2A + B $$\\to$$ products. When concentration of B alone was doubled, the half-life did not change. When the concentration of A\nalone was doubled, the rate increased by two times. The unit of rate constant for this reaction is ",
    "options": [
      "L mol<sup>-1</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> ",
      "no unit",
      "mol L<sup>-1</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> ",
      "s<sup>-1</sup> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "different-methods-to-determine-order-of-reaction",
    "solution": "L mol<sup>-1</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "E3S8gyHmFrA7wN2W",
    "question": "At 518<sup>o</sup>C the rate of decomposition of a sample of gaseous acetaldehyde initially at a pressure of 363 Torr,\nwas 1.00 Torr s<sup>–1</sup> when 5% had reacted and 0.5 Torr s<sup>–1</sup> when 33% had reacted. The order of the reaction is  ",
    "options": [
      "0",
      "2",
      "3",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "different-methods-to-determine-order-of-reaction",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "68MCVsfs1li737zTxRAo6",
    "question": "For the reaction, 2A + B $$ \\to $$ products, when the concentrations of A and B both were doubled, the rate of the reaction increased from 0.3 mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>s<sup>$$-$$1</sup> to 2.4 mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. When the concentration of A alone is doubled, the rate increased from 0.3 mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>s<sup>$$-$$1</sup> to 0.6 mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. ",
    "options": [
      "Total order of the reaction is 4",
      "Order of the reaction with respect to B is 2",
      "Order of the reaction with respect to B is 1",
      "Order of the reaction with respect to A is 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "different-methods-to-determine-order-of-reaction",
    "solution": "Order of the reaction with respect to B is 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mdte0d",
    "question": "<p>For kinetic study of the reaction of iodide ion with $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ at room temperature :</p>\n<p>(A) Always use freshly prepared starch solution.</p>\n<p>(B) Always keep the concentration of sodium thiosulphate solution less than that of KI solution.</p>\n<p>(C) Record the time immediately after the appearance of blue colour.</p>\n<p>(D) Record the time immediately before the appearance of blue colour.</p>\n<p>(E) Always keep the concentration of sodium thiosulphate solution more than that of KI solution.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(\\mathrm{A}),(\\mathrm{B}),(\\mathrm{C})$$ only",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A}),(\\mathrm{D}),(\\mathrm{E})$$ only",
      "$$(\\mathrm{D}),(\\mathrm{E})$$ only",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A}),(\\mathrm{B}),(\\mathrm{E})$$ only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "different-methods-to-determine-order-of-reaction",
    "solution": "$$(\\mathrm{A}),(\\mathrm{B}),(\\mathrm{C})$$ only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwuw5nx",
    "question": "<p>A student has studied the decomposition of a gas AB$$_3$$ at 25$$^\\circ$$C. He obtained the following data.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 427px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 202px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 60px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 57px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 58px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">p (mm Hg)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">50</th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">100</th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">200</th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">400</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">relative t$$_{1/2}$$ (s)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">4</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">2</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">1</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.5</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>The order of the reaction is</p>",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "0.5",
      "1",
      "0 (zero)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "different-methods-to-determine-order-of-reaction",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsyyzmb",
    "question": "<p>For a chemical reaction $$\\mathrm{A}+\\mathrm{B} \\rightarrow$$ Product, the order is 1 with respect to $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 509px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 169px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 169px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 171px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">$$\\mathrm{Rate}$$<br/>$$\\mathrm{mol~L^{-1}~S^{-1}}$$</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">$$\\mathrm{[A]}$$<br/>$$\\mathrm{mol~L^{-1}}$$</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">$$\\mathrm{[B]}$$<br/>$$\\mathrm{mol~L^{-1}}$$</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.10</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">20</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.5</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.40</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$x$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.5</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.80</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">40</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$y$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>What is the value of $$x$$ and $$y$$ ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "80 and 4",
      "160 and 4",
      "80 and 2",
      "40 and 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "different-methods-to-determine-order-of-reaction",
    "solution": "80 and 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "0pAS0aK9pMdrCa6s",
    "question": "If half-life of a substance is 5 yrs, then the total amount of substance left after 15 years, when initial amount is 64 grams is",
    "options": [
      "16 grams",
      "2 grams",
      "32 grams",
      "8 grams"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "8 grams"
  },
  {
    "id": "xnvgmpRJqqNhBIOS",
    "question": "The integrated rate equation is Rt = log C<sub>0</sub> - log C<sub>t</sub> . The straight line graph is obtained by\nplotting",
    "options": [
      "time vs log C<sub>t</sub>",
      "$${1 \\over {time}}$$ vs C<sub>t</sub>",
      "time vs C<sub>t</sub>",
      "$${1 \\over {time}}$$ vs $${1 \\over {{C_t}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "time vs log C<sub>t</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "eHXEeCKSb75YwkZC",
    "question": "Units of rate constant of first and zero order reactions in terms of molarity M unit are respectively",
    "options": [
      "sec<sup>-1</sup>, Msec<sup>-1</sup>",
      "sec<sup>-1</sup>, M",
      "Msec<sup>-1</sup>, sec<sup>-1</sup>",
      "M, sec<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "sec<sup>-1</sup>, Msec<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "3zlLJSuwq89PodyV",
    "question": "For the reaction system: \n<br/><br/>2NO(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\to$$ 2NO<sub>2</sub>(g) volume is suddenly reduce to half its value by increasing the pressure on it. If the reaction is of first order with respect to O<sub>2</sub> and second order with respect to NO, the rate of reaction will",
    "options": [
      "diminish to one-eighth of its initial value",
      "increase to eight times of its initial value",
      "increase to four times of its initial value",
      "diminish to one-fourth of its initial value"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "increase to eight times of its initial value"
  },
  {
    "id": "HL9Tlarq21Om9HRm",
    "question": "In a first order reaction, the concentration of the reactant decreases from 0.8 M to 0.4 M in 15\nminutes. The time taken for the concentration to change from 0.1 M to 0.025 M is",
    "options": [
      "30 minutes",
      "60 minutes",
      "7.5 minutes",
      "15 minutes"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "30 minutes"
  },
  {
    "id": "rQQOGpPKH7jhMLFx",
    "question": "A reaction involving two different reactants can never be ",
    "options": [
      "Unimolecular reaction ",
      "First order reaction",
      "second order reaction",
      "Bimolecular reaction "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "Unimolecular reaction "
  },
  {
    "id": "y3iZdaYIT0PcqWtg",
    "question": "t<sub>1/4</sub> can be taken as the time taken for the concentration of a reactant to drop to $$3 \\over 4$$ of its initial value. If the rate constant for a first order reaction is K, the t<sub>1/4</sub> can be written as ",
    "options": [
      "0.10 / K",
      "0.29 / K",
      "0.69 / K ",
      "0.75 / K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "0.29 / K"
  },
  {
    "id": "IHfYxx3h2h00in84",
    "question": "The following mechanism has been proposed for the reaction of NO with Br<sub>2</sub> to form NOBr: <br/>\nNO(g) + Br<sub>2</sub> (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ NOBr<sub>2</sub> (g) <br/>\nNOBr<sub>2</sub> (g)  + NO (g) $$\\to$$ 2NOBr (g)<br/>\nIf the second step is the rate determining step, the order of the reaction with respect to NO(g) is ",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "0",
      "3",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "COrQxrpmaLWvDtVr",
    "question": "The half life period of a first order chemical reaction is 6.93 minutes. The time required for the\ncompletion of 99% of the chemical reaction will be (log 2=0.301) :",
    "options": [
      "230.3 minutes",
      "23.03 minutes ",
      "46.06 minutes ",
      "460.6 minutes "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "46.06 minutes "
  },
  {
    "id": "wIBQPE0mUFRgwXdL",
    "question": "The time for half life period of a certain reaction A $$\\to$$ products is 1 hour. When the initial\nconcentration of the reactant ‘A’, is 2.0 mol L<sup>–1</sup>, how much time does it take for its concentration to\ncome from 0.50 to 0.25 mol L<sup>–1</sup> if it is a zero order reaction ?",
    "options": [
      "4 h",
      "0.5 h",
      "0.25 h",
      "1 h"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "0.25 h"
  },
  {
    "id": "hLktTOPDljWkQjIX",
    "question": "For a first order reaction, (A) $$\\to$$ products, the concentration of A changes from 0.1 M to 0.025 M in 40\nminutes. The rate of reaction when the concentration of A is 0.01 M is :",
    "options": [
      "1.73 x 10<sup>–5</sup> M/ min",
      "3.47 x 10<sup>–4</sup> M/min",
      "3.47 x 10<sup>–5 </sup> M/min",
      "1.73 x 10<sup>–4</sup> M/min"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "3.47 x 10<sup>–4</sup> M/min"
  },
  {
    "id": "tGD5YikwpgBoGz2p",
    "question": "Higher order (&gt;3) reactions are rare due to",
    "options": [
      "increase in entropy and activation energy as more molecules are involved",
      "shifting of equilibrium towards reactants due to elastic collisions",
      "loss of active species on collision",
      "low probability of simultaneous collision of all the reacting species"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "low probability of simultaneous collision of all the reacting species"
  },
  {
    "id": "IyrK6QjVck6E2yrI",
    "question": "Decomposition of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> follows a first order reaction. In fifty minutes the concentration of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> decreases\nfrom 0.5 to 0.125 M in one such decomposition. When the concentration of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> reaches 0.05 M, the rate of formation of O<sub>2</sub> will be :",
    "options": [
      "6.93 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-4</sup> mol min<sup>-1</sup>",
      "6.96 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> mol min<sup>-1</sup>",
      "1.34 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> mol min<sup>-1</sup>",
      "2.66 L min<sup>–1</sup> at STP"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "6.93 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-4</sup> mol min<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "VI1ZCGKHXMmHURKiRYM1q",
    "question": "N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> decomposes to NO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> and follows first order kinetics. After 50 minutes, the pressure inside the vessel increases from 50 mmHg to 87.5 mmHg. The pressure of the gaseous mixture after 100 minute at constant temperature will be :",
    "options": [
      "175.0 mmHg",
      "116.25 mmHg",
      "136.25 mmHg",
      "106.25 mmHg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "106.25 mmHg"
  },
  {
    "id": "YlCdJY31C8nFgTVGaXo1t",
    "question": "For a first order reaction, A $$ \\to $$ P, t<sub>1/2</sub> (half-life) is 10 days The time required for $${1 \\over 4}$$<sup>th</sup> conversion of A (in days) is : (ln 2 = 0.693,    ln 3 = 1.1)",
    "options": [
      "5",
      "3.2",
      "4.1",
      "2.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "4.1"
  },
  {
    "id": "t0FqjpWS7TTNgAE8QXJGS",
    "question": "If 50% of a reaction occurs in 100 second and 75% of the reaction occurs in  200 secod, the order of this reaction is : ",
    "options": [
      "Zero ",
      "1",
      "2",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ft8kB9UjMuylZgY1AeiLm",
    "question": "The reaction 2X $$ \\to $$ B is a zeroth order reaction. If the initial concentration of X is 0.2 M, the half-life is 6 h. When the initial concentration of X is 0.5 M, the time required to reach its final concentration of 0.2 M will\nbe: \n",
    "options": [
      "18.0 h",
      "9.0 h",
      "7.2 h",
      "12.0 h"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "18.0 h"
  },
  {
    "id": "q1CV8nEPaS9ridZCobb3R",
    "question": "Decomposition of X exhibits a rate constant of 0.05 $$\\mu $$g/year. How many year are required for the decomposition of 5$$\\mu $$g of X into 2.5 $$\\mu $$g? \n",
    "options": [
      "50",
      "20",
      "25",
      "40"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "50"
  },
  {
    "id": "6t6QNoFnJSEbjAZcG3jgy2xukf25i9vq",
    "question": "It is true that :",
    "options": [
      "A first order reaction is always a single step reaction",
      "A zero order reaction is a multistep reaction",
      "A zero order reaction is a single step reaction",
      "A second order reaction is always a multistep reaction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "A zero order reaction is a multistep reaction"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bd3dqg",
    "question": "<p>For a first order reaction, the time required for completion of 90% reaction is 'x' times the half life of the reaction. The value of 'x' is</p>\n<p>(Given : ln 10 = 2.303 and log 2 = 0.3010)</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.12",
      "2.43",
      "3.32",
      "33.31"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "3.32"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i4mchh",
    "question": "<p>At $$30^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$, the half life for the decomposition of $$\\mathrm{AB}_{2}$$ is $$200 \\mathrm{~s}$$ and is independent of the initial concentration of $$\\mathrm{AB}_{2}$$. The time required for $$80 \\%$$ of the $$\\mathrm{AB}_{2}$$ to decompose is</p>\n<p>Given: $$\\log 2=0.30$$ $$\\quad \\log 3=0.48$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "200 s",
      "323 s",
      "467 s",
      "532 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "467 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7exen",
    "question": "<p>Integrated rate law equation for a first order gas phase reaction is given by (where $$\\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{i}}$$ is initial pressure and $$\\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{t}}$$ is total pressure at time $$t$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$k=\\frac{2.303}{t} \\times \\log \\frac{P_i}{\\left(2 P_i-P_t\\right)}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{k}=\\frac{2.303}{\\mathrm{t}} \\times \\log \\frac{\\left(2 \\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{i}}-\\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{t}}\\right)}{\\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{i}}}$$\n",
      "$$k=\\frac{2.303}{t} \\times \\frac{P_i}{\\left(2 P_i-P_t\\right)}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{k}=\\frac{2.303}{\\mathrm{t}} \\times \\log \\frac{2 \\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{i}}}{\\left(2 \\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{i}}-\\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{t}}\\right)}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "integrated-rate-law-equations",
    "solution": "$$k=\\frac{2.303}{t} \\times \\log \\frac{P_i}{\\left(2 P_i-P_t\\right)}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "CZAJ4QtIBawaIF5v",
    "question": "$$\\beta$$ - particle is emitted in radioactivity by",
    "options": [
      "conversion of proton to neutron",
      "from outermost orbit",
      "conversion of neutron to proton",
      "$$\\beta$$ -particle is not emitted"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "nuclear-chemistry",
    "solution": "conversion of neutron to proton"
  },
  {
    "id": "T6sg5c4kC0Snw7S3",
    "question": "The radionucleide $${}_{90}^{234}Th$$ undergoes two successive $$\\beta$$ -decays followed by one $$\\alpha$$-decay. The atomic number\nand the mass number respectively of the resulting radionucleide are",
    "options": [
      "94 and 230",
      "90 and 230",
      "92 and 230",
      "92 and 234"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "nuclear-chemistry",
    "solution": "90 and 230"
  },
  {
    "id": "4OgYvm3kGvpGgflZ",
    "question": "The half-life of a radioactive isotope is three hours. If the initial mass of the isotope were 256 g, the mass of\nit remaining undecayed after 18 hours would be",
    "options": [
      "8.0 g",
      "12.0 g",
      "16.0 g",
      "4.0 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "nuclear-chemistry",
    "solution": "4.0 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "WvCZlt17emHVZCdl",
    "question": "Consider the following nuclear reactions<br/>\n$${}_{92}^{238}M \\to {}_Y^XN + 2{}_2^4He$$<br/>\n$${}_Y^XN \\to {}_B^AL + 2{\\beta ^ + }$$<br/>\nThe number of neutrons in the element L is ",
    "options": [
      "140",
      "144",
      "142",
      "146"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "nuclear-chemistry",
    "solution": "144"
  },
  {
    "id": "DunluWXxDbsm6TNI",
    "question": "The half – life of a radioisotope is four hours. If the initial mass of the isotope was 200 g, the\nmass remaining after 24 hours undecayed is",
    "options": [
      "1.042 g ",
      "4.167 g",
      "3.125 g",
      "2.084 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "nuclear-chemistry",
    "solution": "3.125 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "78t8epYJFcyyNFUz",
    "question": "Hydrogen bomb is based on the principle of ",
    "options": [
      "Nuclear fission ",
      "Natural radioactivity ",
      "Nuclear fusion",
      "Artificial radioactivity"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "nuclear-chemistry",
    "solution": "Nuclear fusion"
  },
  {
    "id": "Dq2pjZLuBqRJanv6",
    "question": "The photon of hard gamma radiation knocks a proton out of $${}_{12}^{24}Mg$$ nucleus to form ",
    "options": [
      "the isotope of parent nucleus",
      "the isobar of parent nucleus ",
      "the nuclide $${}_{11}^{23}Na$$",
      "the isobar of  $${}_{11}^{23}Na$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "nuclear-chemistry",
    "solution": "the nuclide $${}_{11}^{23}Na$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "kUkCNXWLkUBsUDI0",
    "question": "In the transformation of $${}_{92}^{238}U$$ to $${}_{92}^{234}U$$, if one emission is an α-particle, what should be the other\nemission(s)? ",
    "options": [
      "Two $$\\beta^-$$",
      "Two $$\\beta^-$$ and one $$\\beta^+$$",
      "One $$\\beta^-$$ and one $$\\gamma$$",
      "One $$\\beta^+$$ and One $$\\beta^-$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "nuclear-chemistry",
    "solution": "Two $$\\beta^-$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "rQtJEhNZohnohoAz",
    "question": "A radioactive element gets spilled over the floor of a room. Its half-life period is 30 days. If the initial\nactivity is ten times the permissible value, after how many days will it be safe to enter the room? ",
    "options": [
      "1000 days",
      "300 days ",
      "10 days",
      "100 days"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "nuclear-chemistry",
    "solution": "100 days"
  },
  {
    "id": "FQS6yLzHkmhyTZ0M",
    "question": "Which of the following nuclear reactions will generate an isotope?",
    "options": [
      "neutron particle emission",
      "positron emission ",
      "$$\\alpha$$-particle emission",
      "$$\\beta$$-particle emission"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "nuclear-chemistry",
    "solution": "neutron particle emission"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt3yw5x",
    "question": "Isotope(s) of hydrogen which emits low energy $$\\beta$$<sup>$$-$$</sup> particles with t<sub>1/2</sub> value &gt; 12 years is/are",
    "options": [
      "Protium",
      "Tritium",
      "Deuterium",
      "Deuterium and Tritium"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "nuclear-chemistry",
    "solution": "Tritium"
  },
  {
    "id": "A4qBbd9hlrVScvAw",
    "question": "For the reaction A + 2B $$\\to$$ C, rate is given by R = [A] [B]<sup>2</sup> then the order of the reaction is",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "6",
      "5",
      "7"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ew0zFtKLlZmvWycu",
    "question": "The rate law for a reaction between the substances A and B is given by Rate = k[A]<sup>n</sup> [B]<sup>m</sup> On doubling the concentration of A and halving the concentration of B, the ratio of the new rate to the earlier rate of the reaction will be as",
    "options": [
      "(m + n)",
      "(n - m) ",
      "2<sup>( n - m)</sup>",
      "$${1 \\over {{2^{(m + n)}}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "2<sup>( n - m)</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "s2ZXsTcGrJPXu1R4",
    "question": "The rate equation for the reaction 2A + B $$\\to$$ C is found to be: rate k[A][B]. The correct\nstatement in relation to this reaction is that the ",
    "options": [
      "unit of K must be s<sup>-1</sup>",
      "values of k is independent of the initial concentration of A and B",
      "rate of formation of C is twice the rate of disappearance of A ",
      "t<sub>1/2</sub> is a constant"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "values of k is independent of the initial concentration of A and B"
  },
  {
    "id": "kKwqLviw41BLPotu",
    "question": "A reaction was found to be second order with respect to the concentration of carbon monoxide. If the\nconcentration of carbon monoxide is doubled, with everything else kept the same, the rate of reaction\nwill",
    "options": [
      "remain unchanged ",
      "triple",
      "increase by a factor of 4",
      "double"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "increase by a factor of 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "zv76zbXIJUzZ4o8E",
    "question": "<p>Consider the reaction :<br/>\n<br>Cl<sub>2</sub>(aq) + H<sub>2</sub>S(aq) → S(s) + 2H<sup>+</sup> (aq) + 2Cl<sup>–</sup> (aq)<br/>\n<br>The rate equation for this reaction is rate = k [Cl<sub>2</sub>] [H<sub>2</sub>S]<br/>\n<br>Which of these mechanisms is/are consistent with this rate equation?</br></br></br></p>\n<p>(A) Cl<sub>2</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>S $$\\to$$ H<sup>+</sup> + Cl<sup>–</sup> + Cl<sup>+</sup> + HS<sup>–</sup> (slow)<br/>\n<br>Cl<sup>+</sup> + HS<sup>–</sup> $$\\to$$ H<sup>+</sup> + Cl<sup>–</sup> + S (fast) </br></p>\n<p>(B) H<sub>2</sub>S $$ \\Leftrightarrow $$ H<sup>+</sup> + HS<sup>–</sup> (fast equilibrium) <br/>\n<br>Cl<sub>2</sub> + HS<sup>–</sup> $$\\to$$ 2Cl<sup>–</sup> + H<sup>+</sup> + S (slow) </br></p>",
    "options": [
      "B only",
      "Both A and B",
      "Neither A nor B",
      "A only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "A only"
  },
  {
    "id": "NXeuAeEwemgjHCld",
    "question": "For the non – stoichiometre reaction 2A + B $$\\to$$ C + D, the following kinetic data were obtained in three\nseparate experiments, all at 298 K.\n<div style=\"overflow-x: auto\">\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-s6z2{text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-hgcj{font-weight:bold;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-hgcj\">Initial Concentration (A)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-hgcj\"><span style=\"font-weight:700\">Initial Concentration (B)</span></th>\n<th class=\"tg-hgcj\">Initial rate of formation of C (mol L<sup>-1</sup> s<sup>-1</sup>)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">0.1 M</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">0.1 M</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">1.2 x 10<sup>-3</sup></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.1 M</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.2 M</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">1.2 x 10<sup>-3</sup></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.2 M</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.1 M</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">2.4 x 10<sup>-3</sup></td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>\n</div> \nThe rate law for the formation of C is:",
    "options": [
      "$${{dc} \\over {dt}} = k[A]{[B]^2}$$ ",
      "$${{dc} \\over {dt}} = k[A]$$ ",
      "$${{dc} \\over {dt}} = k[A]{[B]}$$",
      "$${{dc} \\over {dt}} = k[A^2]{[B]}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "$${{dc} \\over {dt}} = k[A]$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ZAGoXhMCcdUYG1BZD96tY",
    "question": "The reaction of ozone with oxygen atoms in the presence of chlorine atoms can occur\nby a two step process shown below :\n<br/><br/>O<sub>3</sub>(g) + Cl$${^ \\bullet }$$ (g) $$ \\to $$ O<sub>2</sub>(g) + ClO$${^ \\bullet }$$ (g) . . . . . .(i)\n<br/><br/>k<sub>i</sub> =  5.2 × 10<sup>9</sup> L mol<sup>−1</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>\n<br/><br/>ClO$${^ \\bullet }$$(g) + O$${^ \\bullet }$$(g) $$ \\to $$ O<sub>2</sub>(g) + Cl$${^ \\bullet }$$ (g) . . . . . . (ii)\n<br/><br/>k<sub>ii</sub> =  2.6 × 10<sup>10</sup> L mol<sup>−1</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>\n<br/><br/>The closest rate constant for the overall reaction O<sub>3</sub>(g) + O$${^ \\bullet }$$ (g) $$ \\to $$ 2 O<sub>2</sub>(g) is : ",
    "options": [
      "5.2 × 10<sup>9</sup> L mol<sup>−1</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>",
      "2.6 × 10<sup>10</sup> L mol<sup>−1</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>",
      "3.1 × 10<sup>10</sup> L mol<sup>−1</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>",
      "1.4 × 10<sup>20</sup> L mol<sup>−1</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "1.4 × 10<sup>20</sup> L mol<sup>−1</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "9ZokgutcPux9fYlMYPzm1",
    "question": "The rate law for the reaction below is given by the expression k [A] [B]\n<br/><br/>A + B $$ \\to $$ Product\n<br/><br/>If the concentration of B is increased from 0.1 to 0.3 mole, keeping the value of A at 0.1 mole, the rate constant will be :\n",
    "options": [
      "k",
      "k/3",
      "3k",
      "9k"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "k"
  },
  {
    "id": "Sda0nfjcRYSDjjEV8p9xO",
    "question": "For the reaction 2A + B $$ \\to $$ C, the values of initial rate at diffrent reactant concentrations are\ngiven in the table below. The rate law for the reaction is :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-s6z2{text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\">[A] (mol L<sup>-1</sup>) </th>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\">[B] (mol L<sup>-1</sup>)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\">Initial Rate (mol L<sup>-1</sup>s<sup>-1</sup>)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">0.05</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">0.05</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">0.045</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.10</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.05</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.090</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.20</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.10</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">0.72</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "Rate = k[A][B]<sup>2</sup>",
      "Rate = k[A]<sup>2</sup>[B]<sup>2</sup>",
      "Rate = k[A]<sup>2</sup>[B]",
      "Rate = k[A][B]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "Rate = k[A][B]<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "77MBz4uXb4bQpusHe22VA",
    "question": "The following results were obtained during kinetic studies of the reaction ; \n<br/><br/>2A + B $$ \\to $$ Products\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-wv9z{font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-de48{font-weight:bold;font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\">Experiment</th>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\">[A] (in mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\">[b] (in mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\">Initial Rate of reaction<br/>(In mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup> min<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">I</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">0.10</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">0.20</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">6.93 G 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">II</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">0.10</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">0.25</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">6.93 G 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">III</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">0.20</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">0.30</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">1.386 G 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup></td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>\n<br/><br/>The time (in minutes) required to consume half of A is : ",
    "options": [
      "5",
      "10",
      "1",
      "100"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "10"
  },
  {
    "id": "q0IVR2nhiJ2VxRHW7v7k9k2k5eos93e",
    "question": "For the reaction <br/>2H<sub>2</sub>(g) + 2NO(g) $$ \\to $$ N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 2H<sub>2</sub>O(g) <br/>the observed rate expression is, rate = K<sub>f</sub>[NO]<sup>2</sup>[H<sub>2</sub>]. The rate expression for the reverse reaction is :",
    "options": [
      "K<sub>b</sub>[N<sub>2</sub>][H<sub>2</sub>O]",
      "K<sub>b</sub>[N<sub>2</sub>][H<sub>2</sub>O]<sup>2</sup>/[H<sub>2</sub>]",
      "K<sub>b</sub>[N<sub>2</sub>][H<sub>2</sub>O]<sup>2</sup>/[NO] ",
      "K<sub>b</sub>[N<sub>2</sub>][H<sub>2</sub>O]<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "K<sub>b</sub>[N<sub>2</sub>][H<sub>2</sub>O]<sup>2</sup>/[H<sub>2</sub>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz07z5u",
    "question": "For a reaction of order n, the unit of the rate constant is :",
    "options": [
      "mol<sup>1$$-$$n</sup> L<sup>1$$-$$n</sup> s",
      "mol<sup>1$$-$$n</sup> L<sup>2n</sup> s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "mol<sup>1$$-$$n</sup> L<sup>n$$-$$1</sup> s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "mol<sup>1$$-$$n</sup> L<sup>1$$-$$n</sup> s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "mol<sup>1$$-$$n</sup> L<sup>n$$-$$1</sup> s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xm5t5",
    "question": "<p>For a reaction $$A \\xrightarrow{\\mathrm{K}_1} \\mathrm{~B} \\xrightarrow{\\mathrm{K}_2} \\mathrm{C}$$\nIf the rate of formation of B is set to be zero then the concentration of B is given by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(\\mathrm{K}_1-\\mathrm{K}_2)[\\mathrm{A}]$$\n",
      "$$(\\mathrm{K}_1+\\mathrm{K}_2)[\\mathrm{A}]$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_1 \\mathrm{K}_2[\\mathrm{~A}]$$\n",
      "$$(\\mathrm{K}_1 / \\mathrm{K}_2)[\\mathrm{A}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-laws-and-rate-constant",
    "solution": "$$(\\mathrm{K}_1 / \\mathrm{K}_2)[\\mathrm{A}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZwNFCsTerSdJh5af",
    "question": "The differential rate law for the reaction H<sub>2</sub> + I<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ 2HI is",
    "options": [
      "$$ - {{d\\left[ {{H_2}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $$ - {{d\\left[ {{I_2}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $$ - {{d\\left[ {{HI}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$",
      "$$ {{d\\left[ {{H_2}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $$ {{d\\left[ {{I_2}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $$ {{d\\left[ {{HI}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}{{d\\left[ {{H_2}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $${1 \\over 2}{{d\\left[ {{I_2}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $$ - {{d\\left[ {{HI}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$",
      "$$ - 2{{d\\left[ {{H_2}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $$ - 2{{d\\left[ {{I_2}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $${{d\\left[ {{HI}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-of-reaction",
    "solution": "$$ - 2{{d\\left[ {{H_2}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $$ - 2{{d\\left[ {{I_2}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $${{d\\left[ {{HI}} \\right]} \\over {dt}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "kMSXVWGi653VzsQd",
    "question": "For a reaction $${1 \\over 2}A \\to 2B$$  rate of disappearance of ‘A’ is related to the rate of appearance of ‘B’ by the\nexpression ",
    "options": [
      "$$ - {{d[A]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $${1 \\over 2}{{d[B]} \\over {dt}}$$",
      "$$ - {{d[A]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $${1 \\over 4}{{d[B]} \\over {dt}}$$",
      "$$ - {{d[A]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $${{d[B]} \\over {dt}}$$ ",
      "$$ - {{d[A]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $$4{{d[B]} \\over {dt}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-of-reaction",
    "solution": "$$ - {{d[A]} \\over {dt}}$$ = $${1 \\over 4}{{d[B]} \\over {dt}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Fee6Hpm0BqiHYc6y",
    "question": "The rate of a chemical reaction doubles for every 10<sup>o</sup>C rise of temperature. If the temperature is raised\nby 50<sup>o</sup>C , the rate of the reaction increases by about :",
    "options": [
      "24 times ",
      "32 times",
      "64 times",
      "10 times "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-of-reaction",
    "solution": "32 times"
  },
  {
    "id": "XBGUNKwE9hF2PnBg4THCA",
    "question": "For a reaction scheme $$A\\buildrel {{k_1}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow B\\buildrel {{k_2}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow C$$,\n<br/><br/> if\nthe rate of formation of B is set to be zero then\nthe concentration of B is given by :",
    "options": [
      "$${k_1}{k_2}[A]$$",
      "$$\\left( {{{{k_1}} \\over {{k_2}}}} \\right)[A]$$",
      "$$({k_1} + {k_2})[A]$$",
      "$$({k_1} - {k_2})[A]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-of-reaction",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {{{{k_1}} \\over {{k_2}}}} \\right)[A]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "y3VJgXGz1vuzitLKAm3rsa0w2w9jx54j4lu",
    "question": "In the following reaction; xA $$ \\to $$ yB\n<br/>$${\\log _{10}}\\left[ { - {{d\\left[ A \\right]} \\over {dt}}} \\right] = {\\log _{10}}\\left[ {{{d\\left[ B \\right]} \\over {dt}}} \\right] + 0.3010$$\n<br/>'A' and 'B' respectively can be :",
    "options": [
      "n-Butane and Iso-butane",
      "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>8</sub>",
      "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>6</sub>",
      "N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-of-reaction",
    "solution": "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>8</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "SAPfnXOxLl6aUoklKX3rsa0w2w9jx8xfted",
    "question": "NO<sub>2</sub> required for a reaction is produced by the decomposition of N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> in CCl<sub>4</sub> as per the equation,\n<br/>2N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 4NO<sub>2</sub>(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g).\n<br/>The initial concentration of N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> is 3.00 mol L<sup>–1</sup>\n and it is 2.75 mol L<sup>–1</sup>\n after 30 minutes. The rate of\nformation of NO<sub>2</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "2.083 × 10<sup>–3</sup>\n mol L<sup>–1</sup>\n min<sup>–1</sup>",
      "8.333 × 10<sup>–3</sup>\n mol L<sup>–1</sup>\n min<sup>–1</sup>",
      "4.167 × 10<sup>–3</sup>\n mol L<sup>–1</sup>\n min<sup>–1</sup>",
      "1.667 × 10<sup>–2</sup>\n mol L<sup>–1</sup>\n min<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-of-reaction",
    "solution": "1.667 × 10<sup>–2</sup>\n mol L<sup>–1</sup>\n min<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "LzKEZm6Pvx9ZSE16mgjgy2xukf3n9s43",
    "question": "For the reaction<br/> 2A + 3B +\n$${3 \\over 2}$$C\n$$ \\to $$ 3P, which\nstatement is correct ?",
    "options": [
      "$${{d{n_A}} \\over {dt}} = {{d{n_B}} \\over {dt}} = {{d{n_C}} \\over {dt}}$$",
      "$${{d{n_A}} \\over {dt}} = {2 \\over 3}{{d{n_B}} \\over {dt}} = {3 \\over 4}{{d{n_C}} \\over {dt}}$$",
      "$${{d{n_A}} \\over {dt}} = {3 \\over 2}{{d{n_B}} \\over {dt}} = {3 \\over 4}{{d{n_C}} \\over {dt}}$$",
      "$${{d{n_A}} \\over {dt}} = {2 \\over 3}{{d{n_B}} \\over {dt}} = {4 \\over 3}{{d{n_C}} \\over {dt}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemical-kinetics-and-nuclear-chemistry",
    "topic": "rate-of-reaction",
    "solution": "$${{d{n_A}} \\over {dt}} = {2 \\over 3}{{d{n_B}} \\over {dt}} = {4 \\over 3}{{d{n_C}} \\over {dt}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "KeX2EQGcbfNhLoHjpLFId",
    "question": "The artificial sweetener that has the highest sweetness value in comparison to cane\nsugar is :",
    "options": [
      "Aspartane ",
      "Saccharin ",
      "Sucralose",
      "Alitame"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemistry-in-everyday-life",
    "topic": "chemicals-in-foods",
    "solution": "Alitame"
  },
  {
    "id": "cMe4dhu2jPZUfxFnbd7k9k2k5ic4p3m",
    "question": "A chemist has 4 samples of artificial sweetener\nA, B, C and D. To identify these samples, he\nperformed certain experiments and noted the\nfollowing observations :<br/><br/>\n(i) A and D both form blue-violet colour with\nninhydrin.<br/><br/>\n(ii) Lassaigne extract of C gives positive\nAgNO<sub>3</sub> test and negative Fe<sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sub>3</sub> test.<br/><br/>\n(iii) Lassaigne extract of B and D gives positive\nsodium nitroprusside test<br/><br/>\nBased on these observations which option is\ncorrect ?",
    "options": [
      "A : Aspartame ; B : Alitame ;\nC : Saccharin ; D ; Sucralose",
      "A : Alitame ; B : Saccharin ;\nC : Aspartame ; D ; Sucralose",
      "A : Aspartame ; B : Saccharin ;\nC : Sucralose ; D ; Alitame",
      "A : Saccharin ; B : Alitame ;\nC : Sucralose ; D ; Aspartame"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "chemistry-in-everyday-life",
    "topic": "chemicals-in-foods",
    "solution": "A : Aspartame ; B : Saccharin ;\nC : Sucralose ; D ; Alitame"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ee1fTQlxcMglJQiUDL1kmkiydfq",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I<br/>Chemical Compound</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II<br/>Used as</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Sucralose</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Synthetic detergent</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Glyceryl ester of stearic acid</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Artificial sweetener</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Sodium benzoate</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Antiseptic</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Bithionol</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Food preservative</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct match :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemistry-in-everyday-life",
    "topic": "chemicals-in-foods",
    "solution": "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(iii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56azl51",
    "question": "<p>Which amongst the following is not a pesticide?</p>",
    "options": [
      "DDT",
      "Organophosphates",
      "Dieldrin",
      "Sodium arsenite"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "chemistry-in-everyday-life",
    "topic": "chemicals-in-foods",
    "solution": "Sodium arsenite"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59qouhu",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 573px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 62px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 195px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 80px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 236px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\">List -II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Zymase</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Stomach</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Diastase</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Yeast</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Urease</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Malt</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Pepsin</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Soyabean</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemistry-in-everyday-life",
    "topic": "chemicals-in-foods",
    "solution": "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5amaph1",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following is an example of artificial sweetner?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Bithional",
      "Alitame",
      "Salvarsan",
      "Lactose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemistry-in-everyday-life",
    "topic": "chemicals-in-foods",
    "solution": "Alitame"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldppif4t",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following artificial sweeteners has the highest sweetness value in comparison to cane sugar ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Alitame",
      "Sucralose",
      "Saccharin",
      "Aspartame"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemistry-in-everyday-life",
    "topic": "chemicals-in-foods",
    "solution": "Alitame"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh02z8a1",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II:</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 598px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 240px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Saccharin</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">High potency sweetener</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Aspartame</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">First artificial sweetening agent</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Alitame</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Stable at cooking temperature</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Sucralose</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Unstable at cooking temperature</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemistry-in-everyday-life",
    "topic": "chemicals-in-foods",
    "solution": "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh27gxfb",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 598px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 240px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I <br/>Vitamin</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II <br/>Deficiency disease</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Vitamin A</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Beri-Beri</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Thiamine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Cheilosis</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ascorbic acid</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Xeropthalmia</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Riboflavin</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Scurvy</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-III, D-I",
      " A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "chemistry-in-everyday-life",
    "topic": "chemicals-in-foods",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc58edm",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 690px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 239px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Compound)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Uses)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Idoform</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Fire extinguisher  </td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Carbon tetrachloride</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Insecticide</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">CFC</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Antiseptic</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">DDT</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Refrigerants</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III\n",
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II\n",
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I\n",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemistry-in-everyday-life",
    "topic": "chemicals-in-medicines",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaofgdj",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.\n<br/><br/>\n<style>\n  table {\n    border-collapse: collapse;\n    width: 100%;\n  }\n  th, td {\n    border: 1px solid black;\n    padding: 8px;\n    text-align: left;\n  }\n  th {\n    background-color: blue;\n    color: white;\n  }\n</style>\n<table>\n<tr>\n<th>List I (Compound)</th>\n<th>List II (Use)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(A) Carbon tetrachloride</td>\n<td>(I) Paint remover</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(B) Methylene chloride</td>\n<td>(II) Refrigerators and air conditioners</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(C) DDT</td>\n<td>(III) Fire extinguisher</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(D) Freons</td>\n<td>(IV) Non Biodegradable insecticide</td>\n</tr>\n</table>\n<br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(II), (C)-(III), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "chemistry-in-everyday-life",
    "topic": "cleansing-agents",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1wuw1ZJYf4CjXzFL",
    "question": "Which one of the following methods is neither meant for the synthesis nor for\nseparation of amines?",
    "options": [
      "Hinsberg method",
      "Hofmann method ",
      "Wurtz reaction",
      "Curtius reaction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "Wurtz reaction"
  },
  {
    "id": "hke6MPMCXaonrXTi",
    "question": "Which one of the following is the strongest base in aqueous solution? ",
    "options": [
      "Trimethylamine ",
      "Aniline",
      "Dimethylamine",
      "Methylamine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "Dimethylamine"
  },
  {
    "id": "OW5Yew1POHLRleED",
    "question": "Considering the basic strength of amines in aqueous solution, which one has the smallest pK<sub>b</sub> value?",
    "options": [
      "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>",
      "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>NH",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>NH"
  },
  {
    "id": "wHLdpNBwztknpOVP",
    "question": "On heating an aliphatic primary amine with chloroform and ethanolic potassium hydroxide, the organic\ncompound formed is:",
    "options": [
      "an alkyl cyanide",
      "an alkyl isocyanide",
      "an alkanol",
      "an alkanediol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "an alkyl isocyanide"
  },
  {
    "id": "FgWsiOBla9Dqi6ph",
    "question": "In the Hofmann bromamide degradation reaction, the number of moles of NaOH and Br<sub>2</sub> used per mole of\namine produced are:",
    "options": [
      "Four moles of NaOH and two moles of Br<sub>2</sub>.",
      "Two moles of NaOH and two moles of Br<sub>2</sub>",
      "Four moles of NaOH and one mole of Br<sub>2</sub>",
      "One mole of NaOH and one mole of Br<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "Four moles of NaOH and one mole of Br<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "2GYzQ9iPnqF8sJJmBAeQ4",
    "question": "The test to distinguish primary, secondary and tertiary amines is :",
    "options": [
      "Carbylamine reaction",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>SO<sub>2</sub>Cl",
      "Sandmeyer’s reaction",
      "Mustard oil test"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>SO<sub>2</sub>Cl"
  },
  {
    "id": "59BJhaBiyFUZMKkVX83rsa0w2w9jx0tyhjc",
    "question": "Which of the following is not a correct method of the preparation of benzylamine from cyanobenzene ?",
    "options": [
      "(i) SnCl<sub>2</sub> + HCl(gas) &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(ii) NaBH<sub>4</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>/Ni\n",
      "(i) LiAlH<sub>4</sub> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(ii) H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup>",
      "(i) HCl/H<sub>2</sub>O &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(ii) NaBH<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "(i) HCl/H<sub>2</sub>O &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(ii) NaBH<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "BmfR8TNQ4WXroQOVbo3rsa0w2w9jwuoung4",
    "question": "Ethylamine (C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>) can be obtained from N-ethylphatalimide on treatment with :",
    "options": [
      "CaH<sub>2</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "NaBH<sub>4</sub>",
      "NH<sub>2</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "NH<sub>2</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "P56KeZgF4iXyWbgL0g94w",
    "question": "Which of the following amines can be prepared by Gabriel phthalimide reaction ?",
    "options": [
      "neo-pentylamine",
      "n-butylamine",
      "t-butylamine",
      "triethylamine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "n-butylamine"
  },
  {
    "id": "rRfLD2FDqqZzzzktRYfds",
    "question": "A compound 'X' on treatment with Br<sub>2</sub>/NaOH, provided C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>9</sub>N, which gives positive carbylamine test. Compound 'X' is : ",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CONH<sub>2</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CON(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COCH<sub>2</sub>NH",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COCH<sub>2</sub>NHCH<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CONH<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "rkxCXZW1PjLQ7qUzSJjgy2xukfjah2zh",
    "question": "The most appropriate reagent for conversion of\nC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>CN into CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>NH<sub>2</sub> is",
    "options": [
      "NaBH<sub>4</sub>",
      "CaH<sub>2</sub>",
      "Na(CN)BH<sub>3</sub>",
      "LiAlH<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "LiAlH<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "fVsnuiPkKHTkWjuYUc1kmitlhyd",
    "question": "Which of the following is least basic?",
    "options": [
      "$${(C{H_3}CO)_2}\\mathop N\\limits^{..} H$$",
      "$$(C{H_3}CO)\\mathop N\\limits^{..} H{C_2}{H_5}$$",
      "$${({C_2}{H_5})_3}\\mathop N\\limits^{..} $$",
      "$${({C_2}{H_5})_2}\\mathop N\\limits^{..} H$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "$${(C{H_3}CO)_2}\\mathop N\\limits^{..} H$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "DmrPZdbthdot2aUXpD1kmitq92x",
    "question": "Ammonolysis of Alkyl halides followed by the treatment with NaOH solution can be used to prepare primary, secondary and tertiary amines. The purpose of NaOH in the reaction is :",
    "options": [
      "to remove acidic impurities",
      "to remove basic impurities",
      "to activate NH<sub>3</sub> used in the reaction",
      "to increase the reactivity of alkyl halide"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "to remove acidic impurities"
  },
  {
    "id": "lXqqqlAxX4ZbbG6NXt1kmkisrv9",
    "question": "Primary, secondary and tertiary amines can be separated using:",
    "options": [
      "Chloroform and KOH",
      "Acetyl amide",
      "Benzene sulphonic acid",
      "para-Toluene sulphonyl chloride"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "para-Toluene sulphonyl chloride"
  },
  {
    "id": "vLAfMdDZwU0wZaX6gq1kmm0yfvt",
    "question": "In the reaction of hypobromite with amide, the carbonyl carbon is lost as :",
    "options": [
      "CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "CO",
      "HCO$$_3^ - $$",
      "CO$$_3^{2 - }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "CO$$_3^{2 - }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq637r5",
    "question": "Compound A is converted to B on reaction with CHCl<sub>3</sub> and KOH. The compound B is toxic and can be decomposed by C. A, B and C respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "primary amine, nitrile compound, conc. HCl",
      "secondary amine, isonitrile compound, conc. NaOH",
      "primary amine, isonitrile compound, conc. HCl",
      "secondary amine, nitrile compound, conc. NaOH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "primary amine, isonitrile compound, conc. HCl"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktebukq3",
    "question": "Which of the following is not a correct statement for primary aliphatic amines?",
    "options": [
      "The intermolecular association in primary amines is less than the intermolecular association in secondary amines.",
      "Primary amines on treating with nitrous acid solution from corresponding alcohols except mythyl amine.",
      "Primary amines are less basic than the secondary amines.",
      "Primary amines can be prepared by the Gabriel phthalimide synthesis."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "The intermolecular association in primary amines is less than the intermolecular association in secondary amines."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57selme",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : In Hofmann degradation reaction, the migration of only an alkyl group takes place from carbonyl carbon of the amide to the nitrogen atom.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The group is migrated in Hofmann degradation reaction to electron deficient atom.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58jvea5",
    "question": "<p>Which statement is NOT correct for p-toluenesulphonyl chloride?</p>",
    "options": [
      "It is known as Hinsberg's reagent.",
      "It is used to distinguish primary and secondary amines.",
      "On treatment with secondary amine, it leads to a product, that is soluble in alkali.",
      "It doesn't react with tertiary amines."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "On treatment with secondary amine, it leads to a product, that is soluble in alkali."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bdlh0b",
    "question": "<p>The conversion of propan-1-ol to n-butylamine involves the sequential addition of reagents. The correct sequential order of reagents is</p>",
    "options": [
      "(i) SOCl<sub>2</sub> (ii) KCN (iii) H<sub>2</sub>/Ni, Na(Hg)/C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH",
      "(i) HCl (ii) H<sub>2</sub>/Ni, Na(Hg)/C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH",
      "(i) SOCl<sub>2</sub> (ii) KCN (iii) CH<sub>3</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>",
      "(i) HCl (ii) CH<sub>3</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "(i) SOCl<sub>2</sub> (ii) KCN (iii) H<sub>2</sub>/Ni, Na(Hg)/C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jmd7lc",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 545px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 35px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 244px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 34px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 232px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Benzenesulphonyl chloride</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Test for primary amines</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Hoffmann bromamide reaction</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Anti Saytzeff</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Carbylamine reaction</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Hinsberg reagent</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Hoffmann orientation</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Known reaction of Isocyanates.</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-I, D-III",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldscxm1g",
    "question": "<p>Reaction of propanamide with $$\\mathrm{Br_2/KOH(aq)}$$ produces :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Propanenitrile",
      "Propylamine",
      "Ethylnitrile",
      "Ethylamine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aliphatic-amines",
    "solution": "Ethylamine"
  },
  {
    "id": "NReYmPyrooo4Ow5dgV1klurhdy6",
    "question": "A. Phenyl methanamine<br/><br/>B. N,N-Dimethylaniline<br/><br/>C. N-Methyl aniline<br/><br/>D. Benzenamine<br/><br/>Choose the correct order of basic nature of the above amines.",
    "options": [
      "D &gt; C &gt; B &gt; A",
      "A &gt; C &gt; B &gt; D",
      "D &gt; B &gt; C &gt; A",
      "A &gt; B &gt; C &gt; D"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "A &gt; B &gt; C &gt; D"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krus9sp2",
    "question": "Given below are two statements, one is labelled as Assertion (A) and other is labelled as Reason (R). <br/><br/>Assertion (A) : Gabriel phthalimide synthesis cannot be used to prepare aromatic primary amines.<br/><br/>Reason (R) : Aryl halides do not undergo nucleophilic substitution reaction.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true.",
      "Both (A) and (R) true and (R) is correct explanation of (A).",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) true and (R) is correct explanation of (A)."
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz0c21g",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : <br/><br/>Statement I : Aniline is less basic than acetamide.<br/><br/>Statement II : In aniline, the lone pair of electrons on nitrogen atom is delocalized over benzene ring due to resonance and hence less available to a proton.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate option;",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true.",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true.",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but statement II is true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1i58yf",
    "question": "$$R - CN\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{(ii){H_2}O}^{(i)DIBAL - H}} R - Y$$<br/><br/>Consider the above reaction and identify \"Y\"",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$CH<sub>2</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>",
      "$$-$$CONH<sub>2</sub>",
      "$$-$$CHO",
      "$$-$$COOH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "$$-$$CHO"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54yqd21",
    "question": "<p>In Friedel-Crafts alkylation of aniline, one gets</p>",
    "options": [
      "alkylated product with ortho and para substitution.",
      "secondary amine after acidic treatment.",
      "an amide product.",
      "positively charged nitrogen at benzene ring."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "positively charged nitrogen at benzene ring."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56y55q4",
    "question": "<p>Decarboxylation of all six possible forms of diaminobenzoic acids C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>3</sub>(NH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>COOH yields three products A, B and C. Three acids give a product 'A', two acids gives a product 'B' and one acid give a product 'C'. The melting point of product 'C' is</p>",
    "options": [
      "63$$^\\circ$$C",
      "90$$^\\circ$$C",
      "104$$^\\circ$$C",
      "142$$^\\circ$$C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "142$$^\\circ$$C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gr5n2c",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : Experimental reaction of $$\\mathrm{CH}_{3} \\mathrm{Cl}$$ with aniline and anhydrous $$\\mathrm{AlCl}_{3}$$ does not give $$o$$ and $$p$$-methylaniline.</p>\n<p>Reason (R): The $$-\\mathrm{NH}_{2}$$ group of aniline becomes deactivating because of salt formation with anhydrous $$\\mathrm{AlCl}_{3}$$ and hence yields $$m$$-methyl aniline as the product.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
      "Both A and R are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A).",
      "(A) is true, but (R) is false.",
      "(A) is false, but (R) is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "(A) is true, but (R) is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nwylpp",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Aniline on nitration yields ortho, meta &amp; para nitro derivatives of aniline.</p>\n<p>Reason $$\\mathrm{R}$$ : Nitrating mixture is a strong acidic mixture.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ are true but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathrm{A}$$",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsrr7vt",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 633px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 205px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 54px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 326px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-7btt\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-7btt\">Reaction</td>\n<td class=\"tg-7btt\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-7btt\">Reagents</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Hoffmann Degradation</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Conc. KOH}$$, $$\\Delta$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Clemenson reduction</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{CHCl_3,NaOH/H_3O}$$$$^ \\oplus $$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Cannizaro reaction</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Br_2,NaOH}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Reimer-Tiemann Reaction</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Zn-Hg/HCl}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - III, (B) - IV, (C) - I, (D) - II",
      "(A) - II, (B) - IV, (C) - I, (D) - III",
      "(A) - III, (B) - IV, (C) - II, (D) - I",
      "(A) - II, (B) - I, (C) - III, (D) - IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "(A) - III, (B) - IV, (C) - I, (D) - II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu0dxv5",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 669px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I (Amines)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II ($$\\mathrm{pK_b}$$)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Aniline</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">3.25</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ethanamine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">3.00</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">N-Ethylethanamine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">9.38</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">N, N-Diethylethanamine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">3.29</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I",
      "A-I, B-IV, C-II, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu0t1mv",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 691px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 271px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I<br/>Isomeric pairs</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II<br/>Type of isomers</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Propanamine and N-Methylethanamine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Metamers</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Hexan-2-one and Hexan-3-one</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Positional isomers</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ethanamide and Hydroxyethanimine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Functional isomers</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">o-nitrophenol and p-nitrophenol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Tautomers</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwvc0r5",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Pure Aniline and other arylamines are usually colourless.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Arylamines get coloured on storage due to atmospheric reduction.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement I is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbmht85",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (I)</b> : The $\\mathrm{NH}_2$ group in Aniline is ortho and para directing and a powerful activating group.\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (II)</b> : Aniline does not undergo Friedel-Craft's reaction (alkylation and acylation).<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below :\n",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      " Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbmt320",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (I)</b> : Aminobenzene and aniline are same organic compounds.<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (II)</b> : Aminobenzene and aniline are different organic compounds.<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd9uetm",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p><b>Statement I</b> : Aniline reacts with con. $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{SO}_4$$, followed by heating at $$453-473 \\mathrm{~K}$$ gives $$\\mathrm{p}$$-aminobenzene sulphonic acid, which gives blood red colour in the 'Lassaigne's test'.</p>\n<p><b>Statement II</b> : In Friedel - Craft's alkylation and acylation reactions, aniline forms salt with the $$\\mathrm{AlCl}_3$$ catalyst. Due to this, nitrogen of aniline aquires a positive charge and acts as deactivating group.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both statement I and statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false\n",
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true\n",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "Both statement I and statement II are true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmb83",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : All the following compounds react with p-toluenesulfonyl chloride.</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_5 \\mathrm{NH}_2 \\quad\\left(\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_5\\right)_2 \\mathrm{NH} \\quad\\left(\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_5\\right)_3 \\mathrm{N}$$</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : Their products in the above reaction are soluble is aqueous $$\\mathrm{NaOH}$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "aromatic-amines",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "O9PF9AzPPibDyUmMwkS2V",
    "question": "Fluorination of an aromatic ring is easily accomplished by treating a diazonium salt with HBF<sub>4</sub>. Which of the following conditions is correct about this reaction ?",
    "options": [
      "Only heat",
      "NaNO<sub>2</sub>/Cu",
      "Cu<sub>2</sub>O/H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "NaF/Cu"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "diazonium-salts-and-other-nitrogen-containing-compounds",
    "solution": "Only heat"
  },
  {
    "id": "IraPHZmXOikPwDmCaphaf",
    "question": "Hinsberg's reagent is :",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>COCl",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>SO<sub>2</sub>Cl",
      "SOCl<sub>2</sub>",
      "(COCl)<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "diazonium-salts-and-other-nitrogen-containing-compounds",
    "solution": "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>SO<sub>2</sub>Cl"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krx604we",
    "question": "A reaction of benzonitrile with one equivalent CH<sub>3</sub>MgBr followed by hydrolysis produces a yellow liquid \"P\". The compound \"P\" will give positive _________.",
    "options": [
      "Iodoform test",
      "Schiff's test",
      "Ninhydrin's test",
      "Tollen's test"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "diazonium-salts-and-other-nitrogen-containing-compounds",
    "solution": "Iodoform test"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56b6oim",
    "question": "<p>A primary aliphatic amine on reaction with nitrous acid in cold (273 K) and there after raising temperature of reaction mixture to room temperature (298 K), gives a/an</p>",
    "options": [
      "nitrile",
      "alcohol",
      "diazonium salt",
      "secondary amine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "diazonium-salts-and-other-nitrogen-containing-compounds",
    "solution": "alcohol"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp35q1o",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p>1 - Bromopropane is reacted with reagents in List I to give product in List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 689px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 62px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 58px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 320px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST I - Reagent</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST II - Product</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{KOH}$$ (alc)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Nitrile</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{KCN}$$ (alc)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Ester</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{AgNO_2}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Alkene</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{H_3CCOOAg}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Nitroalkane</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-I, B-III, C-IV, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "diazonium-salts-and-other-nitrogen-containing-compounds",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vyqyn",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following nitrogen containing compound does not give Lassaigne's test ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Glycene\n",
      "Phenyl hydrazine\n",
      "Urea\n",
      "Hydrazine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "diazonium-salts-and-other-nitrogen-containing-compounds",
    "solution": "Hydrazine"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv40va1g",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : Kjeldahl method is applicable to estimate nitrogen in pyridine.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : The nitrogen present in pyridine can easily be converted into ammonium sulphate in Kjeldahl method.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "diazonium-salts-and-other-nitrogen-containing-compounds",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57nv7",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Piciric acid is 2,4,6 - trinitrotoluene.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Phenol - 2,4 - disulphonic acid is treated with Conc. $$\\mathrm{HNO}_3$$ to get picric acid.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct\n",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "compounds-containing-nitrogen",
    "topic": "diazonium-salts-and-other-nitrogen-containing-compounds",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "gRDD8OhaGDx8HL0M",
    "question": "CH<sub>3</sub> - Mg - Br is an organometallic compound due to :",
    "options": [
      "Mg - Br bond",
      "C - Mg bond",
      "C - Br bond",
      "C - H bond"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "C - Mg bond"
  },
  {
    "id": "fyWjReJCkGyNc8K9",
    "question": "Coordination compound have great importance in biological systems. In this context which of\nthe following statements is incorrect?",
    "options": [
      "Chlorophylls are green pigments in plants and contains calcium",
      "Carboxypeptidase – A is an enzyme and contains zinc ",
      "Cyanocobalamin is B<sub>12</sub> and contains cobalt ",
      "Haemoglobin is the red pigment of blood and contains iron"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "Chlorophylls are green pigments in plants and contains calcium"
  },
  {
    "id": "28SJsWQzIl0segT6FGpWu",
    "question": "Match the metals (column I) with the coordination compound(s)/enzyme(s) (column II) \n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-x1hj{font-size:22px;border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-nhda{font-size:22px;border-color:inherit;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-9d8n{font-size:22px;border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-c4o0{font-size:22px;border-color:inherit;text-align:left}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-nhda\" colspan=\"2\">(Column I) Metals<br/></th>\n<th class=\"tg-9d8n\" colspan=\"2\">(Column II) Coordination <br/>compounds(s) enzyme(s)<br/></th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c4o0\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-nhda\">Co</td>\n<td class=\"tg-x1hj\">(i)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">Wilkinson catalyst</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c4o0\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-nhda\">Zn</td>\n<td class=\"tg-x1hj\">(ii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">Chlorophyl</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c4o0\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-nhda\">Rh</td>\n<td class=\"tg-x1hj\">(iii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">Vitamin B<sub>12</sub></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-x1hj\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">Mg</td>\n<td class=\"tg-x1hj\">(iv)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-9d8n\">Carbonic anhydrase</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(iii); (B)-(iv); (C)-(i); (D)-(ii)",
      "(A)-(iv); (B)-(iii); (C)-(i); (D)-(ii)",
      "(A)-(i); (B)-(ii); (C)-(iii); (D)-(iv)",
      "(A)-(ii); (B)-(i); (C)-(iv); (D)-(iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "(A)-(iii); (B)-(iv); (C)-(i); (D)-(ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "lqv8LdKmfE4KuilL0KfXD",
    "question": "The number of bridging CO ligand(s) and Co-Co bond(s) in Co<sub>2</sub>(CO)<sub>8</sub>, respectively are : ",
    "options": [
      "2 and 0",
      "0 and 2",
      "4 and 0",
      "2 and 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "2 and 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "QYRCfnRzkCW7qARawIlXU",
    "question": "Mn<sub>2</sub>(CO)<sub>10</sub> is an organometallic compound due to the presence of - ",
    "options": [
      "C–O bond",
      "Mn – Mn bond ",
      "Mn – O bond",
      "Mn – C bond "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "Mn – C bond "
  },
  {
    "id": "qZLig152B79JwxKeDl8G3",
    "question": "The compound that inhibits the growth of\ntumors is :",
    "options": [
      "cis-[Pd(Cl)<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]",
      "trans-[Pd(Cl)<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]",
      "cis-[Pt(Cl)<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]",
      "trans-[Pt(Cl)<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "cis-[Pt(Cl)<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "7VzLGcI1yYO0ZI2Hus3rsa0w2w9jx960wt4",
    "question": "The compound used in the treatment of lead poisoning is :",
    "options": [
      "desferrioxime B",
      "Cis-platin",
      "D-penicillamine",
      "EDTA"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "EDTA"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn1hzsy",
    "question": "The potassium ferrocyanide solution gives a Prussian blue colour, when added to :",
    "options": [
      "CoCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "FeCl<sub>2</sub>",
      "CoCl<sub>2</sub>",
      "FeCl<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "FeCl<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58ebadt",
    "question": "<p>Which statement is not true with respect to nitrate ion test?</p>",
    "options": [
      "A dark brown ring is formed at the junction of two solutions.",
      "Ring is formed due to nitroferrous sulphate complex.",
      "The brown complex is [Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>5</sub> (NO)]SO<sub>4</sub>.",
      "Heating the nitrate salt with conc. H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, light brown fumes are evolved."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "Ring is formed due to nitroferrous sulphate complex."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w62mgh",
    "question": "<p>Correct formula of the compound which gives a white precipitate with BaCl<sub>2</sub> solution, but not with AgNO<sub>3</sub> solution, is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>Br]SO<sub>4</sub>",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>]Br",
      "[Pt(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]Br<sub>2</sub>",
      "[Pt(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Br<sub>2</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>Br]SO<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kr74l7",
    "question": "<p>$$\\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}$$ cation gives a prussian blue precipitate on addition of potassium ferrocyanide solution due to the formation of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]_{2}\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Fe}_{2}\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Fe}_{3}\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}(\\mathrm{CN})_{4}\\right]_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Fe}_{4}\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]_{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Fe}_{4}\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]_{3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldojoi8m",
    "question": "<p>A solution of $$\\mathrm{FeCl_3}$$ when treated with $$\\mathrm{K_4[Fe(CN)_6]}$$ gives a prussium blue precipitate due to the formation of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Fe[Fe(CN)_{6}]}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Fe_{4}[Fe(CN)_{6}]_{3}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Fe_{3}[Fe(CN)_{6}]_{2}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K[Fe_{2}(CN)_{6}]}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Fe_{4}[Fe(CN)_{6}]_{3}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr3cela",
    "question": "<p>To inhibit the growth of tumours, identify the compounds used from the following :</p>\n<p>A. EDTA</p>\n<p>B. Coordination Compounds of Pt</p>\n<p>C. D - Penicillamine</p>\n<p>D. Cis - Platin</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the option given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and B Only",
      "C and D Only",
      "B and D Only",
      "A and C Only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "B and D Only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq460xg",
    "question": "<p>The mismatched combinations are</p>\n<p>A. Chlorophyll - Co</p>\n<p>B. Water hardness - EDTA</p>\n<p>C. Photography $$-\\left[\\mathrm{Ag}(\\mathrm{CN})_{2}\\right]^{-}$$</p>\n<p>D. Wilkinson catalyst $$-\\left[\\left(\\mathrm{Ph}_{3} \\mathrm{P}\\right)_{3} \\mathrm{RhCl}\\right]$$</p>\n<p>E. Chelating ligand - D-Penicillamine</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and E Only",
      "D and E Only",
      "A and C Only",
      "A, C, and E Only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "A and C Only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsy5qq9",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements, one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : $$\\left[\\mathrm{CoCl}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{5}\\right]^{2+}$$ absorbs at lower wavelength of light with respect to $$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{5}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)\\right]^{3+}$$</p>\n<p>Reason R : It is because the wavelength of the light absorbed depends on the oxidation state of the metal ion.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is true",
      "Both $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ are true but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$A$$",
      "Both $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathrm{A}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsyenrz",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 616px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 246px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 270px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>Complex</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>Colour</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$Mg(N{H_4})P{O_4}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">brown</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${K_3}[Co{(N{O_2})_6}]$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">white</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$MnO{(OH)_2}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">yellow</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$F{e_4}{[Fe{(CN)_6}]_3}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">blue</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguz4cl9",
    "question": "<p>The complex that dissolves in water is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Fe}_{4}\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]_{3}$$",
      "$$\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{4}\\right)_{3}\\left[\\mathrm{As}\\left(\\mathrm{Mo}_{3} \\mathrm{O}_{10}\\right)_{4}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{3}\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NO}_{2}\\right)_{6}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}_{3}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}(\\mathrm{OAc})_{6}\\right] \\mathrm{Cl}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}_{3}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}(\\mathrm{OAc})_{6}\\right] \\mathrm{Cl}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaomryz",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (I)</b> : Dimethyl glyoxime forms a six-membered covalent chelate when treated with $\\mathrm{NiCl}_2$ solution in presence of $\\mathrm{NH}_4 \\mathrm{OH}$.\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (II)</b> : Prussian blue precipitate contains iron both in $(+2)$ and $(+3)$ oxidation states.<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscqbsh5",
    "question": "<p>Identity the incorrect pair from the following :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Haber process - Iron\n",
      "Polythene preparation - $$\\mathrm{TiCl}_4, \\mathrm{Al}\\left(\\mathrm{CH}_3\\right)_3$$\n",
      "Photography - AgBr\n",
      "Wacker process - $$\\mathrm{Pt} \\mathrm{Cl}_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "Wacker process - $$\\mathrm{Pt} \\mathrm{Cl}_2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjo31i",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 523px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 70px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 184px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 94px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 175px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - I<br/>(Substances)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - II<br/>(Element Present)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ziegler catalyst</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Rhodium</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Blood Pigment</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Cobalt</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Wilkinson catalyst</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Iron</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Vitamin $$\\mathrm{B_{12}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Titanium</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III\n",
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I\n",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjtkwr",
    "question": "<p>In which one of the following metal carbonyls, $$\\mathrm{CO}$$ forms a bridge between metal atoms?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Os}_3(\\mathrm{CO})_{12}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Ru}_3(\\mathrm{CO})_{12}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Mn}_2(\\mathrm{CO})_{10}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}_2(\\mathrm{CO})_8\\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}_2(\\mathrm{CO})_8\\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfpafnm",
    "question": "<p>A reagent which gives brilliant red precipitate with Nickel ions in basic medium is</p>",
    "options": [
      "dimethyl glyoxime\n",
      "sodium nitroprusside\n",
      "meta-dinitrobenzene\n",
      "neutral $$\\mathrm{FeCl}_3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "dimethyl glyoxime\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgydxdm",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct statements from the following :</p>\n<p>(A) Ethane-1, 2-diamine is a chelating ligand.</p>\n<p>(B) Metallic aluminium is produced by electrolysis of aluminium oxide in presence of cryolite.</p>\n<p>(C) Cyanide ion is used as ligand for leaching of silver.</p>\n<p>(D) Phosphine act as a ligand in Wilkinson catalyst.</p>\n<p>(E) The stability constants of $$\\mathrm{Ca}^{2+}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Mg}^{2+}$$ are similar with EDTA complexes.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(B), (C), (E) only",
      "(A), (D), (E) only",
      "(C), (D), (E) only",
      "(A), (B), (C) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "(A), (B), (C) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gsy29",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I: $$\\mathrm{N}\\left(\\mathrm{CH}_3\\right)_3$$ and $$\\mathrm{P}\\left(\\mathrm{CH}_3\\right)_3$$ can act as ligands to form transition metal complexes.</p>\n<p>Statement II: As N and P are from same group, the nature of bonding of $$\\mathrm{N}\\left(\\mathrm{CH}_3\\right)_3$$ and $$\\mathrm{P}\\left(\\mathrm{CH}_3\\right)_3$$ is always same with transition metals.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.\n",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct.\n",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect."
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gsxvf",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 776px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 374px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Compound)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Colour]</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Fe}_4\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_6\\right]_3 \\cdot \\mathrm{xH_2O}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Violet</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_5 \\mathrm{NOS}\\right]^{4-}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Blood Red</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{SCN})]^{2+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Prussian Blue</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_4\\right)_3 \\mathrm{PO}_4\\cdot12 \\mathrm{MoO}_3$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Yellow</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III\n",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV\n",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I\n",
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "application-of-coordination-compound-and-organometallic-compounds",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "NneRvARPcpPIxjCg",
    "question": "One mole of the complex compound Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>Cl<sub>3</sub>, gives 3 moles of ions on dissolution in water. One mole of the same complex reacts with two moles of AgNO<sub>3</sub> solution to yield two moles of AgCl (s). The structure of the complex is :",
    "options": [
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>Cl<sub>3</sub>]. 2NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>] Cl. NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Cl] Cl<sub>2</sub>. NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>Cl] Cl<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>Cl] Cl<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "sPBN67dgOCrMtgwi",
    "question": "Ammonia forms the complex ion [Cu(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> with copper ions in alkaline solutions but not in acidic solutions. What is the reason for it? ",
    "options": [
      "In acidic solutions protons coordinate with ammonia molecules forming $$NH^+_4$$ ions and NH<sub>3</sub>\n molecules are not available",
      "In alkaline solutions insoluble Cu(OH)<sub>2</sub>\n is precipitated which is soluble in excess of any alkali",
      "Copper hydroxide is an amphoteric substance",
      "In acidic solutions hydration protects copper ions."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "In acidic solutions protons coordinate with ammonia molecules forming $$NH^+_4$$ ions and NH<sub>3</sub>\n molecules are not available"
  },
  {
    "id": "FyrfArQlQ6aVkS0J",
    "question": "In the coordination compound, K<sub>4</sub>[Ni(CN)<sub>4</sub>], the oxidation state of nickel is :",
    "options": [
      "0",
      "+1",
      "+2",
      "-1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "0"
  },
  {
    "id": "BZ38P7EdQ4ozjTng",
    "question": "The coordination number of central metal atom in a complex is determined by :",
    "options": [
      "the number of ligands around a metal ion bonded by sigma bonds",
      "the number of only anionic ligands bonded to the metal ion",
      "the number of ligands around a metal ion bonded by sigma and pi- bonds both ",
      "the number of ligands around a metal ion bonded by pi-bonds"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "the number of ligands around a metal ion bonded by sigma bonds"
  },
  {
    "id": "MpWtq2oy9tnQz8Ep",
    "question": "The oxidation state of Cr in [Cr(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup> is :",
    "options": [
      "+3 ",
      "+2",
      "+1",
      "0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "+3 "
  },
  {
    "id": "FD0P0S8Y7sknRr5S",
    "question": "How many EDTA (ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid) molecules are required to make an octahedral\ncomplex with a Ca<sup>2+</sup> ion?",
    "options": [
      "Six",
      "Three",
      "One",
      "Two"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "One"
  },
  {
    "id": "Cn2wgMcrjcJG9d4E",
    "question": "The coordination number and the oxidation state of the element ‘E’ in the complex [E(en)<sub>2</sub>(C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>)]NO<sub>2</sub> (where (en) is ethylene diamine) are, respectively,",
    "options": [
      "6 and 2 ",
      "4 and 2",
      "4 and 3",
      "6 and 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "6 and 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "MLrMp0HwUL2LURQX",
    "question": "A solution containing 2.675g of CoCl<sub>3</sub>. 6NH<sub>3</sub> (molar mass = 267.5 g mol<sup>–1</sup>) is passed through a cation exchanger. The chloride ions obtained in solution were treated with excess of AgNO<sub>3</sub> to give\n4.78 g of AgCl (molar mass = 143.5 g mol<sup>–1</sup>). The formula of the complex is : (At. Mass of Ag = 108 u)",
    "options": [
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub> ",
      "[CoCl<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>]Cl ",
      "[CoCl<sub>3</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>] ",
      "[CoCl(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "Fl6mTAWICJ141OJv",
    "question": "The equation which is balanced and represents the correct product(s) is :",
    "options": [
      "[Mg (H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub> ]<sup>2+</sup> + (EDTA)<sup>4-</sup> $$\\buildrel {excess\\,NaOH} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ [Mg (EDTA) ]<sup>2+</sup> + 6H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "CuSO<sub>4 </sub> + KCN $$\\to$$ K<sub>2</sub> [Cu (CN)<sub>4</sub>] + K<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> ",
      "Li<sub>2</sub>O + 2KCl $$\\to$$ 2LiCl + K<sub>2</sub>O ",
      "[CoCl(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>]<sup>+</sup> + 5H<sup>+</sup> $$\\to$$ Co<sup>2+</sup> + $$5NH_4^+$$ + Cl<sup>-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "[CoCl(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>]<sup>+</sup> + 5H<sup>+</sup> $$\\to$$ Co<sup>2+</sup> + $$5NH_4^+$$ + Cl<sup>-</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "s2RtTKpizKRKhZjzKd4Ww",
    "question": "Which of the following is an example of homoleptic complex?",
    "options": [
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub>",
      "[Pt(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]\n",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>Cl]Cl<sub>2</sub>\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Uv7Ejwn6P9fmRJY5iIDOv",
    "question": "[Co<sub>2</sub>(CO)<sub>8</sub>] displays :",
    "options": [
      "one Co−Co bond, six terminal CO and two bridging CO",
      "one Co−Co bond, four terminal CO and four bridging CO",
      "no Co−Co bond, six terminal CO and two bridging CO",
      "no Co−Co bond, four terminal CO and four bridging CO\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "one Co−Co bond, six terminal CO and two bridging CO"
  },
  {
    "id": "FEA2E7hJEgrOHByr",
    "question": "The oxidation states of Cr in [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub>, [Cr(C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>6</sub>)<sub>2</sub>] and K<sub>2</sub>[Cr(CN)<sub>2</sub>(O)<sub>2</sub>(O<sub>2</sub>)(NH<sub>3</sub>)] respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "+3, 0 and +4",
      "+3, +4 and +6 ",
      "+3, +2 and +4",
      "+3, 0 and +6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "+3, 0 and +6"
  },
  {
    "id": "guuG6KZsCG56DlUZZcrEJ",
    "question": "The coordination number of Th in K<sub>4</sub>[Th(C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>)<sub>4</sub>(OH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>] is :\n<br/>(C<sub>2</sub>O$${_4^{2 - }}$$ = Oxalato)",
    "options": [
      "14",
      "10",
      "8",
      "6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "10"
  },
  {
    "id": "OFSyftywEhWNx8diCt3rsa0w2w9jx82u9nv",
    "question": "The coordination numbers of Co and Al in [Co(Cl)(en)<sub>2</sub>]Cl and K<sub>3</sub>[Al(C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>], respectively, are :\n(en = ethane-1, 2-diamine) ",
    "options": [
      "3 and 3",
      "6 and 6",
      "5 and 3",
      "5 and 6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "5 and 6"
  },
  {
    "id": "GkRzsetVzXfZ4CMKJD1kmm0zhdr",
    "question": "The secondary valency and the number of hydrogen bonded water molecule(s) in CuSO<sub>4</sub> . 5H<sub>2</sub>O, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "5 and 1",
      "4 and 1",
      "6 and 5",
      "6 and 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "4 and 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krx564o8",
    "question": "Which one of the following metal complexes is most stable?",
    "options": [
      "[Co(en)(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "[Co(en)<sub>3</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "[Co(en)<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "[Co(en)<sub>3</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kticxdxx",
    "question": "The denticity of an organic ligand, biuret is :",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "4",
      "3",
      "6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54yfkx5",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements.</p>\n<p>$$\\bullet$$ Statement I : In CuSO<sub>4</sub> . 5H<sub>2</sub>O, Cu-O bonds are present.</p>\n<p>$$\\bullet$$ Statement II : In CuSO<sub>4</sub> . 5H<sub>2</sub>O, ligands coordinating with Cu(II) ion are O-and S-based ligands.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kptft0",
    "question": "<p>Low oxidation state of metals in their complexes are common when ligands :</p>",
    "options": [
      "have good $$\\pi$$-accepting character",
      "have good $$\\sigma$$-donor character",
      "are having good $$\\pi$$-donating ability",
      "are having poor $$\\sigma$$-donating ability"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "have good $$\\pi$$-accepting character"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldohwegg",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following are the example of double salt?</p>\n<p>A. $$\\mathrm{FeSO}_{4} \\cdot\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{4}\\right)_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4} \\cdot 6 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{CuSO}_{4}\\cdot 4 \\mathrm{NH}_{3} \\cdot \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$</p>\n<p>C. $$\\mathrm{K}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4} \\cdot \\mathrm{Al}_{2}\\left(\\mathrm{SO}_{4}\\right)_{3} \\cdot 24 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{2}\\cdot4 \\mathrm{KCN}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B and D only",
      "B and D only",
      "A and B only",
      "A and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "A and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyfis33",
    "question": "<p>The primary and secondary valencies of cobalt respectively in $$\\mathrm{[Co(NH_3)_5Cl]Cl_2}$$ are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 and 8",
      "2 and 6",
      "3 and 5",
      "3 and 6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "3 and 6"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguzwndi",
    "question": "<p>The set which does not have ambidentate ligand(s) is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}{ }^{2-}, \\mathrm{NO}_{2}{ }^{-}, \\mathrm{NCS}^{-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}{ }^{2-}$$, ethylene diammine, $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{NO}_{2}^{-}, \\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}{ }^{2-}$$, EDTA $$^{4-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{EDTA}^{4-}, \\mathrm{NCS}^{-}, \\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}{ }^{2-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}{ }^{2-}$$, ethylene diammine, $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc5vuvd",
    "question": "<p>Yellow compound of lead chromate gets dissolved on treatment with hot $$\\mathrm{NaOH}$$ solution. The product of lead formed is a :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Tetraanionic complex with coordination number six\n",
      "Neutral complex with coordination number four\n",
      "Dianionic complex with coordination number six\n",
      "Dianionic complex with coordination number four"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "Dianionic complex with coordination number four"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg80hy9",
    "question": "<p>The coordination geometry around the manganese in decacarbonyldimanganese $$(0)$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "Trigonal bipyramidal\n",
      "Square pyramidal\n",
      "Square planar\n",
      "Octahedral"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "Octahedral"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gs17g",
    "question": "<p>An octahedral complex with the formula $$\\mathrm{CoCl}_3 \\cdot \\mathrm{nNH}_3$$ upon reaction with excess of $$\\mathrm{AgNO}_3$$ solution gives 2 moles of $$\\mathrm{AgCl}$$. Consider the oxidation state of $$\\mathrm{Co}$$ in the complex is '$$x$$'. The value of \"$$x+n$$\" is __________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "6",
      "5",
      "3",
      "8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "coordination-number",
    "solution": "8"
  },
  {
    "id": "9ZY5gOQdqatXf70b",
    "question": "The most stable ion is :",
    "options": [
      "[Fe(OH)<sub>3</sub>]<sup>3-</sup>",
      "[Fe(Cl)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3-</sup>",
      "[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3-</sup>",
      "[Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3-</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "pGopIxlIyhSj72pu",
    "question": "The value of the ‘spin only’ magnetic moment for one of the following configurations\nis 2.84 BM. The correct one is :",
    "options": [
      "d<sup>4</sup> (in strong ligand field)",
      "d<sup>4</sup> (in weak ligand field) ",
      "d<sup>3</sup> (in weak as well as in strong fields)",
      "d<sup>5</sup> (in strong ligand field) "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "d<sup>4</sup> (in strong ligand field)"
  },
  {
    "id": "Pw6f7UHc6R1TzVSM",
    "question": "In which of the following octahedral complexes of Co (at. no. 27), will the magnitude of $$\\Delta _o$$ be the highest?",
    "options": [
      "[Co(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3−</sup> ",
      "[Co(C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>]<sup>3−</sup> ",
      "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+ </sup>",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "[Co(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3−</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "GsCnYEACxA3oPy51",
    "question": "The octahedral complex of a metal ion M<sup>3+</sup> with four monodentate ligands L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2</sub>, L<sub>3</sub> and L<sub>4</sub> absorb wavelengths in the region of red, green, yellow and blue, respectively. The increasing order of ligand strength of the four ligands is :",
    "options": [
      "L<sub>3</sub> &lt; L<sub>2</sub> &lt; L<sub>4</sub> &lt; L<sub>1</sub>",
      "L<sub>1</sub> &lt; L<sub>2</sub> &lt; L<sub>4</sub> &lt; L<sub>3</sub>",
      "L<sub>4</sub> &lt; L<sub>3</sub> &lt; L<sub>2</sub> &lt; L<sub>1</sub>",
      "L<sub>1</sub> &lt; L<sub>3</sub> &lt; L<sub>2</sub> &lt; L<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "L<sub>1</sub> &lt; L<sub>3</sub> &lt; L<sub>2</sub> &lt; L<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "svPpDst4r3r0aDg5",
    "question": "Which of the following compounds is not colored yellow?",
    "options": [
      "K<sub>3</sub>[Co(NO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]",
      "(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>[As(Mo<sub>3</sub>O<sub>10</sub>)<sub>4</sub>]",
      "BaCrO<sub>4</sub>",
      "Zn<sub>2</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "Zn<sub>2</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "gF6Zz0zRliURejj7un5gP",
    "question": "Identify the correct trend given below : (Atomic No.=Ti : 22, Cr : 24 and Mo : 42)\n",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta $$<sup>o</sup> of [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> &gt;\n<br><br>[Mo(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and\n<br><br>$$\\Delta $$<sup>o</sup> of [Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup> &gt; [Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "$$\\Delta $$<sup>o</sup> of [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> &gt;\n<br><br>[Mo(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and\n<br><br>$$\\Delta $$<sup>o</sup> of [Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup> &lt; [Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "$$\\Delta $$<sup>o</sup> of [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> \n<br><br>&lt; [Mo(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and\n<br><br>$$\\Delta $$<sup>o</sup> of [Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup> &gt; [Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "$$\\Delta $$<sup>o</sup> of [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> \n<br><br>&lt; [Mo(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and\n<br><br>$$\\Delta $$<sup>o</sup> of [Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup> &lt; [Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta $$<sup>o</sup> of [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> \n<br><br>&lt; [Mo(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and\n<br><br>$$\\Delta $$<sup>o</sup> of [Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup> &gt; [Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Y2UXFleT6aLkgyNK4nLNY",
    "question": "Two complexes [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub> (A) and [Cr(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub> (B) are violet and yellow coloured, respectively. The <b>incorrect</b> statement regarding them is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> values of (A) and (B) are calculated from the energies of violet and yellow light, respectively ",
      "both are paramagnetic with three unpaired electrons",
      "both absorb energies corresponding to their complementry colors. ",
      "$$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> value for (A) is less than that of (B). "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> values of (A) and (B) are calculated from the energies of violet and yellow light, respectively "
  },
  {
    "id": "1ViL2MIGbWBbnq7GlV3rsa0w2w9jx0zcf9h",
    "question": "The crystal field stabilization energy (CFSE) of [Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub> and K<sub>2</sub>[NiCl<sub>4</sub>] respectively, are : ",
    "options": [
      "– 0.4 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> and – 0.8 $$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>",
      "– 0.6 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> and – 0.8 $$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>",
      "– 2.4 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> and – 1.2 $$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>",
      "– 0.4 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> and – 1.2 $$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "– 0.4 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> and – 0.8 $$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "gt7V2lmnkPohTlQ4MJ3rsa0w2w9jwvgdznz",
    "question": "Three complexes,\n<br/>[CoCl(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>]\n<sup>2+</sup>(I),\n<br/>[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>H<sub>2</sub>O]<sup>3+</sup> (II) and\n<br/>[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]\n<sup>3+</sup>(III)\n<br/>absorb light in the visible region. The correct order of the wavelength of light absorbed by them is :",
    "options": [
      "(III) &gt; (I) &gt; (II)",
      "(III) &gt; (II) &gt; (I)",
      "(I) &gt; (II) &gt; (III)",
      "(II) &gt; (I) &gt; (III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "(I) &gt; (II) &gt; (III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "uBVPt3jTNxlbyRzAXz6l4",
    "question": "The degenerate orbitals of [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup> are :",
    "options": [
      "d<sub>x<sup>2</sup></sub> and d<sub>xz</sub>",
      "d<sub>xz</sub> and d<sub>yz</sub>",
      "d<sub>yz</sub> and d<sub>z<sup>2</sup></sub>",
      "d<sub>x<sup>2</sup> - y<sup>2</sup></sub> and d<sub>xy</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "d<sub>xz</sub> and d<sub>yz</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "HyE3ZOWLgdRdXhES5TfWN",
    "question": "The correct order of the spin-only magnetic moment of metal ions in the following low-spin\ncomplexes, [V(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>4–</sup>,[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>4–</sup>, [Ru(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>, and [Cr(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> , is :",
    "options": [
      "V<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Ru<sup>3+</sup> &gt; Cr<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Fe<sup>2+</sup>",
      "V<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Cr<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Ru<sup>3+</sup> &gt; Fe<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Cr<sup>2+</sup> &gt; V<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Ru<sup>3+</sup> &gt; Fe<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Cr<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Ru<sup>3+</sup> &gt; Fe<sup>2+</sup> &gt; V<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "V<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Cr<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Ru<sup>3+</sup> &gt; Fe<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "FfcPR8gIUJ2hhhvHGEZzh",
    "question": "The pair of metal ions that can give a spin only magnetic moment of 3.9 BM for the complex [M(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub>, is - \n",
    "options": [
      "V<sup>2+</sup> and Fe<sup>2+ </sup>",
      "V<sup>2+</sup> and Co<sup>2+</sup> ",
      "Co<sup>2+</sup> and Fe<sup>2+ </sup>",
      "Cr<sup>2+</sup> and Mn<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "V<sup>2+</sup> and Co<sup>2+</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "6dIx9zUiYCgIHiDh8wVey",
    "question": "Homoleptic octahedral complexes of a metal ion 'M<sup>3+</sup>' with three monodenate ligands L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> adsorb wavelenths in the region of green, blue and red  respectively. The increasing order of the ligands strength is : ",
    "options": [
      "L<sub>3</sub> &lt; L<sub>1</sub> &lt; L<sub>2</sub>",
      "L<sub>3</sub> &lt; L<sub>2</sub> &lt; L<sub>1</sub>",
      "L<sub>1</sub> &lt; L<sub>2</sub> &lt; L<sub>3</sub>",
      "L<sub>2</sub> &lt; L<sub>1</sub> &lt; L<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "L<sub>3</sub> &lt; L<sub>1</sub> &lt; L<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "9qyYXzzDtwoGSFhpGFCFg",
    "question": "The complex that has highest crystal field splitting energy ($$\\Delta $$), is : ",
    "options": [
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O)]Cl<sub>3</sub>",
      "K<sub>2</sub>[CoCl<sub>4</sub>]",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>Cl]Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "K<sub>3</sub>[Co(CN)<sub>6</sub>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "K<sub>3</sub>[Co(CN)<sub>6</sub>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "HRtASpwepo7rvKHVtWjgy2xukg4mx8ci",
    "question": "For a d<sup>4</sup> metal ion in an octahedral field, the\ncorrect electronic configuration is :",
    "options": [
      "$$t_{2g}^4e_g^0$$ when $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> &lt; P",
      "$$t_{2g}^3e_g^1$$ when $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> &gt; P",
      "$$e_g^2t_{2g}^2$$ when $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> &lt; P",
      "$$t_{2g}^3e_g^1$$ when $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> &lt; P"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$t_{2g}^3e_g^1$$ when $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> &lt; P"
  },
  {
    "id": "vYz5jY82McEo24xKnBjgy2xukfi6o24i",
    "question": "The values of the crystal field stabilization\nenergies for a high spin d<sup>6</sup> metal ion in\noctahedral and tetrahedral fields, respectively,\nare :",
    "options": [
      "–0.4$$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>\n and –0.27$$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>",
      "–1.6$$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>\n and –0.4$$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>",
      "–0.4$$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>\n and –0.6$$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>",
      "–2.4$$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>\n and –0.27$$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "–0.4$$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>\n and –0.6$$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "lZ4p6Vl2UkoCLifoXfjgy2xukfc87raa",
    "question": "The one that can exhibit highest paramagnetic\nbehaviour among the following is :\n<br/><br/>gly = glycinato; bpy = 2, 2'-bipyridine",
    "options": [
      "[Fe(en)(bpy)(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "[Pd(gly)<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[Co(OX)<sub>2</sub>(OH)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>–</sup> ($$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> &gt; P)",
      "[Ti(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "[Co(OX)<sub>2</sub>(OH)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>–</sup> ($$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> &gt; P)"
  },
  {
    "id": "QiMblWxMflXS4K8haBjgy2xukfc8atg4",
    "question": "The Crystal Field Stabilization Energy\n<br/>(CFSE) of [CoF<sub>3</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>3</sub>] ($$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> &lt; P) is :",
    "options": [
      "-0.8 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>",
      "-0.4 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>",
      "-0.8 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> + 2P",
      "-0.4 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> + P"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "-0.4 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "IbmQJ85JPADbQ2iTtIjgy2xukf3iy9ik",
    "question": "The d-electron configuration of [Ru(en)<sub>3</sub>\n]Cl<sub>2</sub>\n<br/>and [Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub>\n, respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "$$t_{2g}^4e_g^2$$ and $$t_{2g}^6e_g^0$$",
      "$$t_{2g}^6e_g^0$$ and $$t_{2g}^6e_g^0$$",
      "$$t_{2g}^6e_g^0$$ and $$t_{2g}^4e_g^2$$",
      "$$t_{2g}^4e_g^2$$ and $$t_{2g}^4e_g^2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$t_{2g}^6e_g^0$$ and $$t_{2g}^4e_g^2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "TZZX87DcwY7nt5j5Bfjgy2xukevjckxq",
    "question": "Consider that a d<sup>6</sup> metal ion (M<sup>2+</sup>) forms a\ncomplex with aqua ligands, and the spin only\nmagnetic moment of the complex is 4.90 BM.\nThe geometry and the crystal field stabilization\nenergy of the complex is",
    "options": [
      "tetrahedral and – 1.6 $$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>\n + 1P",
      "octahedral and –2.4 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> + 2P",
      "tetrahedral and –0.6 $$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>",
      "octahedral and –1.6 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "tetrahedral and –0.6 $$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "J670qIOJf8TCJbrQOL7k9k2k5lfxdrf",
    "question": "The correct order of the spin-only magnetic\nmoments of the following complexes is :\n<br/>(I) [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Br<sub>2</sub>\n<br/>(II) Na<sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]\n<br/>(III) Na<sub>3</sub>[Fe(C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>] ($$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> $$&gt;$$ P)\n<br/>(IV) (Et<sub>4</sub>N)<sub>2</sub>[CoCl<sub>4</sub>]",
    "options": [
      "(III) &gt; (I) &gt; (II) &gt; (IV)",
      "(II) $$ \\approx $$ (I) &gt; (IV) &gt; (III)",
      "(III) &gt; (I) &gt; (IV) &gt; (II)",
      "(I) &gt; (IV) &gt; (III) &gt; (II)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "(I) &gt; (IV) &gt; (III) &gt; (II)"
  },
  {
    "id": "TT4o76P73fFNvO5eIk7k9k2k5ich322",
    "question": "[Pd(F)(Cl)(Br)(I)]<sup>2–</sup> has n number of\ngeometrical isomers. Then, the spin-only\nmagnetic moment and crystal field stabilisation\nenergy [CFSE] of [Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>n–6</sup>, respectively,\nare:<br/>\n[Note : Ignore the pairing energy]",
    "options": [
      "1.73 BM and –2.0 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>",
      "5.92 BM and 0",
      "2.84 BM and –1.6 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>",
      "0 BM and –2.4 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "1.73 BM and –2.0 $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "XDUzg5DoQarDMuAp537k9k2k5eqefcq",
    "question": "Among the statements(a)-(d) the incorrect ones are :<br/>\n(a) Octahedral CO(III) complexes with strong fields ligands have very high magnetic moments.<br/>\n(b) When $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> &lt; P, the d-electron configuration of Co(III) in an octahedral complex is $$t_{eg}^4e_g^2$$<br/>\n(c) Wavelength of light absorbed by [Co(en)<sub>3</sub>]<sup>3+</sup> is lower than that of [CoF<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3-</sup><br/>\n(d) If the $$\\Delta $$<sub>0</sub> for an octahedral complex of CO(III) is 18,000 cm<sup>-1</sup>, the $$\\Delta $$<sub>t</sub> for its tetrahedral complex with the same ligand be 16,000 cm<sup>-1</sup>\n",
    "options": [
      "(a) and (b) only",
      "(b) and (c) only ",
      "(c) and (d) only ",
      "(a) and (d) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "(a) and (d) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "uGblS1FzMMqObBG6QR7k9k2k5dynlpn",
    "question": "The theory that can completely/properly explain the nature of bonding in [Ni(Co)<sub>4</sub>] is :",
    "options": [
      "Wemer's theory",
      "Valence bond theory",
      "Crystal field theory",
      "Molecular orbital theory"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "Molecular orbital theory"
  },
  {
    "id": "HA7y49WAB7Vbk6mGDUjgy2xukf2bpba1",
    "question": "The electronic spectrum of [Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup> shows a single broad peak with a maximum at 20,300 cm<sup>-1</sup>\n.\nThe crystal field stabilization energy (CFSE) of the complex ion, in kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>, is :",
    "options": [
      "83.7",
      "242.5",
      "145.5",
      "97"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "97"
  },
  {
    "id": "KLqteFY6332f5wfXVl1klrucjz7",
    "question": "The calculated magnetic moments (spin only value) for species $${[FeC{l_4}]^{2 - }}$$, $${[Co{({C_2}{O_4})_3}]^{3 - }}$$ and $$MnO_4^{2 - }$$ respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "5.92, 4.90 and 0 BM",
      "4.90, 0 and 1.73 BM",
      "5.82, 0 and 0 BM",
      "4.90, 0 and 2.83 BM"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "4.90, 0 and 1.73 BM"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq5awhz",
    "question": "The correct order of intensity of colors of the compounds is :",
    "options": [
      "$${[Ni{(CN)_4}]^{2 - }} &gt; {[NiC{l_4}]^{2 - }} &gt; {[Ni{({H_2}O)_6}]^{2 + }}$$",
      "$${[Ni{({H_2}O)_6}]^{2 + }} &gt; {[NiC{l_4}]^{2 - }} &gt; {[Ni{(CN)_4}]^{2 - }}$$",
      "$${[NiC{l_4}]^{2 - }} &gt; {[Ni{({H_2}O)_6}]^{2 + }} &gt; {[Ni{(CN)_4}]^{2 - }}$$",
      "$${[NiC{l_4}]^{2 - }} &gt; {[Ni{(CN)_4}]^{2 - }} &gt; {[Ni{({H_2}O)_6}]^{2 + }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$${[NiC{l_4}]^{2 - }} &gt; {[Ni{({H_2}O)_6}]^{2 + }} &gt; {[Ni{(CN)_4}]^{2 - }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktcr70r7",
    "question": "Arrange the following Cobalt complexes in the order of increasing Crystal Field Stabilization Energy (CFSE) value.<br/><br/>Complexes : $$\\mathop {{{[Co{F_6}]}^{3 - }}}\\limits_A ,\\mathop {{{[Co{{({H_2}O)}_6}]}^{2 + }}}\\limits_B ,\\mathop {{{[Co{{(N{H_3})}_6}]}^{3 + }}}\\limits_C and \\mathop {{{[Co{{({en})}_3}]}^{3 + }}}\\limits_D $$<br/><br/>Choose the correct option :",
    "options": [
      "A &lt; B &lt; C &lt; D",
      "B &lt; A &lt; C &lt; D",
      "B &lt; C &lt; D &lt; A",
      "C &lt; D &lt; B &lt; A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "B &lt; A &lt; C &lt; D"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn0jsc8",
    "question": "The Crystal Field Stabilization Energy (CFSE) and magnetic moment (spin-only) of an octahedral aqua complex of a metal ion (M<sup>z+</sup>) are $$-$$0.8 $$\\Delta$$<sub>0</sub> and 3.87 BM, respectively. Identify (M<sup>z+</sup>) :",
    "options": [
      "V<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Cr<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Mn<sup>4+</sup>",
      "Co<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "Co<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57s48u6",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following will have maximum stabilization due to crystal field?</p>",
    "options": [
      "[Ti(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>",
      "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "[Co(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup>",
      "[Cu(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "[Co(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bdbow9",
    "question": "<p>Transition metal complex with highest value of crystal field splitting ($$\\Delta$$<sub>0</sub>) will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>",
      "[Mo(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>",
      "[Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>",
      "[Os(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "[Os(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f6yqm1",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of energy of absorption for the following metal complexes is :</p>\n<p>A : [Ni(en)<sub>3</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> , B : [Ni(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> , C : [Ni(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup></p>",
    "options": [
      "C < B < A",
      "B < C < A",
      "C < A < B",
      "A < C < B"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "C < B < A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rk6l2h",
    "question": "<p>Octahedral complexes of copper(II) undergo structural distortion (Jahn-Teller). Which one of the given copper (II) complexes will show the maximum structural distortion? (en - ethylenediamine; $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{~N}_{-} \\mathrm{CH}_{2}-\\mathrm{CH}_{2}-\\mathrm{NH}_{2}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Cu}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right] \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{en})\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{4}\\right] \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$$",
      "cis-$$\\left[\\mathrm{Cu}\\left(\\mathrm{en})_{2} \\mathrm{Cl}_{2}\\right]\\right.$$",
      "trans-$$\\left[\\mathrm{Cu}\\left(\\mathrm{en})_{2} \\mathrm{Cl}_{2}\\right]\\right.$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Cu}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right] \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldohre4r",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following complex will show largest splitting of d-orbitals?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$[\\mathrm{Fe(C_2O_4)_3]^{3-}}$$",
      "$$[\\mathrm{Fe(CN)_6]^{3-}}$$",
      "$$[\\mathrm{Fe(NH_3)_6]^{3+}}$$",
      "$$[\\mathrm{FeF_6]^{3-}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$[\\mathrm{Fe(CN)_6]^{3-}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr3nt6h",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following is correct order of ligand field strength?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{S}^{2-}<\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}^{2-}<\\mathrm{NH}_{3} < $$ en $$<\\mathrm{CO}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{CO}<\\mathrm{en}<\\mathrm{NH}_{3}<\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}^{2}<\\mathrm{S}^{2-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{S}^{2-}<\\mathrm{NH}_{3}<$$ en $$<\\mathrm{CO}<\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}^{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{NH}_{3}<\\mathrm{en}<\\mathrm{CO}<\\mathrm{S}^{2-}<\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}^{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{S}^{2-}<\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}^{2-}<\\mathrm{NH}_{3} < $$ en $$<\\mathrm{CO}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldscv6rg",
    "question": "<p>Correct order of spin only magnetic moment of the following complex ions is :</p>\n<p>(Given At.no. Fe : 26, Co : 27)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{[CoF_6]^{3-} > [FeF_6]^{3-} > [Co(C_2O_4)_3]^{3-}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{[FeF_6]^{3-} > [Co(C_2O_4)_3]^{3-} > [CoF_6]^{3-}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{[FeF_6]^{3-} > [CoF_6]^{3-} > [Co(C_2O_4)_3]^{3-}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{[Co(C_2O_4)_3]^{3-} > [CoF_6]^{3-} > [FeF_6]^{3-}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{[FeF_6]^{3-} > [CoF_6]^{3-} > [Co(C_2O_4)_3]^{3-}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu138c7",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 691px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 271px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I<br/>Coordination entity</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II<br/>Wavelength of light absorbed in nm</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[CoCl(NH_3)_5]^{2+}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">310</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[Co(NH_3)_6]^{3+}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">475</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[Co(CN)_6]^{3-}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">535</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[Cu(H_2O)_4]^{2+}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">600</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II",
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwv1u69",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following cannot be explained by crystal field theory?</p>",
    "options": [
      "The order of spectrochemical series",
      "Stability of metal complexes",
      "Magnetic properties of transition metal complexes",
      "Colour of metal complexes"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "The order of spectrochemical series"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnzajcc",
    "question": " The complex with highest magnitude of crystal field splitting energy $\\left(\\Delta_{0}\\right)$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{OH}_{2}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{3+}$",
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{Mn}\\left(\\mathrm{OH}_{2}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{3+}$",
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{Cr}\\left(\\mathrm{OH}_{2}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{3+}$",
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{Ti}\\left(\\mathrm{OH}_{2}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{3+}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$\\left[\\mathrm{Cr}\\left(\\mathrm{OH}_{2}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{3+}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrk665p",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 529px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 159px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 270px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>Complex</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>CFSE ($$\\Delta_0$$)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[Cu(NH_3)_6]^{2+}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$-0.6$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[Ti(H_2O)_6]^{3+}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$-2.0$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[Fe(CN)_6]^{3-}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$-1.2$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[NiF_6]^{4-}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$-0.4$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-IV, C-II, D-III",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-I, B-II, C-IV, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "A-I, B-IV, C-II, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvu5u41",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of the number of unpaired electrons in the given complexes is</p>\n<p>A. $$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}$$</p>\n<p>B. $$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe} \\mathrm{F}_{6}\\right]^{3-}$$</p>\n<p>C. $$\\left[\\mathrm{CoF}_{6}\\right]^{3-}$$</p>\n<p>D. $$\\left.[\\mathrm{Cr} \\text { (oxalate})_{3}\\right]^{3-}$$</p>\n<p>E. $$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CO})_{4}\\right]$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "E < A < B < D < C",
      "A < E < D < C < B",
      "A < E < C < B < D",
      "E < A < D < C < B"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "E < A < D < C < B"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvuvhk7",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 554px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 49px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 201px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 54px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 250px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - I<br/>Complex</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - II<br/>Crystal Field splitting energy ($$\\Delta_0$$)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$${[Ti{({H_2}O)_6}]^{2 + }}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$$-1.2$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$${[V{({H_2}O)_6}]^{2 + }}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$$-0.6$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$${[Mn{({H_2}O)_6}]^{3 + }}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">0</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$${[Fe{({H_2}O)_6}]^{3 + }}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$$-0.8$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgygiaty",
    "question": "<p>The octahedral diamagnetic low spin complex among the following is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "[Co(NH$$_3$$)$$_6$$]$$^{3+}$$",
      "[NiCl$$_4$$]$$^{2-}$$",
      "[CoCl$$_6$$]$$^{3-}$$",
      "[CoF$$_6$$]$$^{3-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "[Co(NH$$_3$$)$$_6$$]$$^{3+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyrpygh",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 693px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 335px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST I<br/>Coordination Complex</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST II<br/>Number of unpaired electrons</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{Cr}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">0</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{2+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">3</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{3+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">2</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{2+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">4</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh02sqpy",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following complex is octahedral, diamagnetic and the most stable?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Na}_{3}\\left[\\mathrm{CoCl}_{6}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right] \\mathrm{Cl}_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{3}\\left[\\mathrm{Co}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{6}\\right] \\mathrm{Cl}_{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{K}_{3}\\left[\\mathrm{Co}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh030hwr",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of spin only magnetic moments for the following complex ions is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{CoF}_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{MnBr}_{4}\\right]^{2-}<\\left[\\mathrm{Mn}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{MnBr}_{4}\\right]^{2-}<\\left[\\mathrm{CoF}_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{Mn}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{Mn}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{CoF}_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{MnBr}_{4}\\right]^{2-}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{CoF}_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{MnBr}_{4}\\right]^{2-}<\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{Mn}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{Mn}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{CoF}_{6}\\right]^{3-}<\\left[\\mathrm{MnBr}_{4}\\right]^{2-}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh27ear9",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements, one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$.</p>\n<p>Assertion A: The spin only magnetic moment value for $$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}$$ is $$1.74 \\mathrm{BM}$$, whereas for $$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{3+}$$ is $$5.92 \\mathrm{BM}$$.</p>\n<p>Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$ : In both complexes, $$\\mathrm{Fe}$$ is present in +3 oxidation state.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaobjj7",
    "question": "$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_3\\right)_6\\right]^{3+}$ and $\\left[\\mathrm{CoF}_6\\right]^{3-}$ are respectively known as :",
    "options": [
      "Inner orbital Complex, Spin paired Complex",
      "Spin paired Complex, Spin free Complex",
      "Spin free Complex, Spin paired Complex",
      "Outer orbital Complex, Inner orbital Complex"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "Spin paired Complex, Spin free Complex"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaoznvo",
    "question": "Which of the following compounds show colour due to d-d transition?",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7$",
      "$\\mathrm{CuSO}_4 \\cdot 5 \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}$",
      "$\\mathrm{KMnO}_4$",
      "$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{CrO}_4$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{CuSO}_4 \\cdot 5 \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbmdoyp",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (I)</b> : A solution of $\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+}$ is green in colour.<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (II)</b> : A solution of $\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CN})_4\\right]^{2-}$ is colourless.<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below :\n\n",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc59izv",
    "question": "<p>Consider the following complex ions</p>\n<p>$$\\begin{aligned}\n&amp; \\mathrm{P}=\\left[\\mathrm{FeF}_6\\right]^{3-} \\\\\n&amp; \\mathrm{Q}=\\left[\\mathrm{V}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+} \\\\\n&amp; \\mathrm{R}=\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+}\n\\end{aligned}$$</p>\n<p>The correct order of the complex ions, according to their spin only magnetic moment values (in B.M.) is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "R < Q < P",
      "R < P < Q",
      "Q < R < P",
      "Q < P < R"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "Q < R < P"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd98of1",
    "question": "<p>Select the option with correct property -</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CO})_4\\right]$$ and $$\\left[\\mathrm{NiCl}_4\\right]^{2-}$$ both Paramagnetic\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CO})_4\\right]$$ and $$\\left[\\mathrm{NiCl}_4\\right]^{2-}$$ both Diamagnetic\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{NiCl}_4\\right]^{2-}$$ Diamagnetic, $$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CO})_4\\right]$$ Paramagnetic\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CO})_4\\right]$$ Diamagnetic, $$\\left[\\mathrm{NiCl}_4\\right]^{2-}$$ Paramagnetic"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CO})_4\\right]$$ Diamagnetic, $$\\left[\\mathrm{NiCl}_4\\right]^{2-}$$ Paramagnetic"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd9sc34",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 565px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 70px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 184px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 94px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 217px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List - I<br/>(Complex ion)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List - II<br/>(Electronic Configuration)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{[Cr(H_2O)_6]^{3+}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$t_{2 g}{ }^2 e_g^0$$<br/></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{3+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$t_{2 g}{ }^3 e_g{ }^0$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$t_{2 g}{ }^3 e_g{ }^2$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{V}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{3+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$t_{2 g}{ }^6 e_g^2$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III\n",
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I\n",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I\n",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vy3lp",
    "question": "<p>Number of complexes from the following with even number of unpaired \"$$\\mathrm{d}$$\" electrons is ________ $$[\\mathrm{V}(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O})_6]^{3+},[\\mathrm{Cr}(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O})_6]^{2+},[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O})_6]^{3+},[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O})_6]^{3+},[\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O})_6]^{2+}$$ [Given atomic numbers: $$\\mathrm{V}=23, \\mathrm{Cr}=24, \\mathrm{Fe}=26, \\mathrm{Ni}=28 \\mathrm{Cu}=29$$]</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "5",
      "2",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vyqlr",
    "question": "<p>The correct sequence of ligands in the order of decreasing field strength is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{NCS}^{-}>\\mathrm{EDTA}^{4-}>\\mathrm{CN}^{-}>\\mathrm{CO}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CO}>\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}>\\mathrm{F}^{-}>\\mathrm{S}^{2-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{S}^{2-}>{ }^{-} \\mathrm{OH}>\\mathrm{EDTA}^{4-}>\\mathrm{CO}$$\n",
      "$${ }^{-} \\mathrm{OH}>\\mathrm{F}^{-}>\\mathrm{NH}_3>\\mathrm{CN}^{-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{CO}>\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}>\\mathrm{F}^{-}>\\mathrm{S}^{2-}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2es1b9",
    "question": "<p>If an iron (III) complex with the formula $$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_3\\right)_x(\\mathrm{CN})_y\\right]^-$$ has no electron in its $$e_g$$ orbital, then the value of $$x+y$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "6",
      "4",
      "3",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "6"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erl1i",
    "question": "<p>The number of unpaired d-electrons in $$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{3+}$$ is ________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "0",
      "2",
      "1",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "0"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2ertmu",
    "question": "<p>A first row transition metal in its +2 oxidation state has a spin-only magnetic moment value of $$3.86 \\mathrm{~BM}$$. The atomic number of the metal is</p>",
    "options": [
      "22",
      "23",
      "26",
      "25"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "23"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xm5x0",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 664px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 262px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Complex ion)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Spin only magnetic moment in B.M.)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\left[\\mathrm{Cr}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_3\\right)_6\\right]^{3+}<br/>$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">4.90</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\left[\\mathrm{NiCl}_4\\right]^{2-}<br/>$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">3.87</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\left[\\mathrm{CoF}_6\\right]^{3-}<br/>$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">0.0</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CN})_4\\right]^{2-}<br/>$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">2.83</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(IV)\n",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(IV), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)\n",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "(A)-(II), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gs2vh",
    "question": "<p>Number of Complexes with even number of electrons in $$\\mathrm{t_{2 g}}$$ orbitals is -</p>\n<p>$$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+},\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+},\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{3+},\\left[\\mathrm{Cu}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+},\\left[\\mathrm{Cr}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "2",
      "1",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v4q6u",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of ligands arranged in increasing field strength.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{F}^{-}<\\mathrm{Br}^{-}<\\mathrm{I}^{-}<\\mathrm{NH}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{^{-}OH}<\\mathrm{CN}^{-}<\\mathrm{NH}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Br}^{-}<\\mathrm{F}^{-}<\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{NH}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Cl}^{-}<\\mathrm{^{-}OH}<\\mathrm{Br}^{-}<\\mathrm{CN}^{-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Br}^{-}<\\mathrm{F}^{-}<\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{NH}_3$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3qt8",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following complexes will exhibit the least paramagnetic behaviour ?\n[Atomic number, $$\\mathrm{Cr}=24, \\mathrm{Mn}=25, \\mathrm{Fe}=26, \\mathrm{Co}=27$$]</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+}$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Mn}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+}$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+}$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Cr}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{2+}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s26x9",
    "question": "<p>The number of complexes from the following with no electrons in the $$t_2$$ orbital is ______.</p> <p>$$\\mathrm{TiCl}_4,\\left[\\mathrm{MnO}_4\\right]^{-},\\left[\\mathrm{FeO}_4\\right]^{2-},\\left[\\mathrm{FeCl}_4\\right]^{-},\\left[\\mathrm{CoCl}_4\\right]^{2-}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "2",
      "3",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2a2am",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 771px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 320px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>Tetrahedral Complex</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>Electronic configuration</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{TiCl}_4<br/>$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{e}^2, \\mathrm{t}_2^0<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\left[\\mathrm{FeO}_4\\right]^{2-}<br/>$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{e^4, t_2^3}<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\left[\\mathrm{FeCl}_4\\right]^{-}<br/>$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{e}^0, \\mathrm{t}_2^0<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\left[\\mathrm{CoCl}_4\\right]^{2-}<br/>$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{e}^2, \\mathrm{t}_2^3<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(III), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc58e8v",
    "question": "<p>Consider the following complexes</p>\n<p>(A) $$\\left[\\mathrm{CoCl}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_3\\right)_5\\right]^{2+}$$, (B) $$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}(\\mathrm{CN})_6\\right]^{3-}$$, (C) $$\n\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_3\\right)_5\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)\\right]^{3+}\n$$, (D) $$\\left[\\mathrm{Cu}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_4\\right]^{2+}$$</p>\n<p>The correct order of A, B, C and D in terms of wavenumber of light absorbed is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "D < A < C < B",
      "B < C < A < D",
      "C < D < A < B",
      "A < C < B < D"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "crystal-field-theory-(cft)",
    "solution": "D < A < C < B"
  },
  {
    "id": "X0DYnEtttuwQZqGT",
    "question": "The type isomerism present in nitropentammine chromium $$\\left( {{\\rm I}{\\rm I}{\\rm I}} \\right)$$ chloride is :",
    "options": [
      "optical ",
      "linkage",
      "ionization",
      "polymerisation."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "linkage"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ayp9esSeCFh069MM",
    "question": "Which one the following has largest number of isomers? (R = alkyl group, en = ethylenediamine) ",
    "options": [
      "[Ru(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup>",
      "[Co(en)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup>",
      "[Ir(PR<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> H(CO)]<sup>2+</sup> ",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>Cl]<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Co(en)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "40k4wR3leD7b6ASn",
    "question": "Which of the following compounds shows optical isomerism? ",
    "options": [
      "[Cu(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>+2</sup> ",
      "[ZnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>-2</sup>",
      "[Cr(C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>]<sup>-3</sup>",
      "[Co(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>-3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Cr(C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>]<sup>-3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "kGFNoDOimVAYdSaC",
    "question": "Which of the following pairs represents linkage isomers ? ",
    "options": [
      "[Pd (P Ph<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> (NCS)<sub>2</sub>] and [Pd (P Ph<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> (SCN)<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub> NO<sub>3</sub>]SO<sub>4</sub> and [Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub> SO<sub>4</sub>]NO<sub>3</sub>",
      "[Pt Cl<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>] Br<sub>2</sub> and [Pt Br<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>] Cl<sub>2</sub> ",
      "[Cu (NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>] [Pt Cl<sub>4</sub>] and [Pt (NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>] [CuCl<sub>4</sub>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Pd (P Ph<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> (NCS)<sub>2</sub>] and [Pd (P Ph<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> (SCN)<sub>2</sub>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "HLJEP8t0WzG85cu7",
    "question": "Which of the following has an optical isomer ? \n",
    "options": [
      "[Co(en)(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>4</sub>(en)]<sup>3+</sup>",
      "[Co(en)<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>Cl]<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Co(en)<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "masR4Kqxbhmju2CT",
    "question": "Which one of the following has an optical isomer ?<br/>\n(en = ethylenediamine)",
    "options": [
      "[Zn (en) (NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> ",
      "[Co (en)<sub>3</sub>]<sup>3+</sup> ",
      "[Co (H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>4</sub> en]<sup>3+</sup> ",
      "[Zn (en)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Co (en)<sub>3</sub>]<sup>3+</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "m3hpz4Vfwxw80D63",
    "question": "Which of the following complex species is not expected to exhibit optical isomerism?",
    "options": [
      "[Co (en)<sub>2</sub> Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>-</sup>",
      "[Co (NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> Cl<sub>3</sub>]",
      "[Co (en) (NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup>",
      "[Co (en)<sub>3</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Co (NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> Cl<sub>3</sub>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "SgYdXDfyjDlA5dSk",
    "question": "The number of geometric isomers that can exist for square planar [Pt (Cl) (py) (NH<sub>3</sub>) (NH<sub>2</sub>OH)]+ is (py = pyridine) :",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "4",
      "6",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "OFVTMSbLgw8PXc7Z",
    "question": "Which one of the following complexes shows optical isomerism?<br/>\n(en = ethylenediamine)",
    "options": [
      "cis[Co(en)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]Cl",
      "trans[Co(en)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]Cl",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]Cl",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>Cl<sub>3</sub>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "cis[Co(en)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]Cl"
  },
  {
    "id": "poQKH4U75Dh7P0AnRk4xT",
    "question": "The total number of possible isomers for square-planar [Pt(Cl)(NO<sub>2</sub>)(NO<sub>3</sub>)(SCN)]<sup>2-</sup> is :",
    "options": [
      "8",
      "12",
      "16",
      "24"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "12"
  },
  {
    "id": "zht8mnncfPR1IjJBESERU",
    "question": "Which of the following complexes will shows geometrical isomerism ? ",
    "options": [
      "aquachlorobis (ethylenediamine) cobalt (II) chloride",
      "pentaaquachlorohromium (III) chloride",
      "potassium amminetrichloropltinate (II) ",
      "potassium tris(oxalato) chromate (III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "aquachlorobis (ethylenediamine) cobalt (II) chloride"
  },
  {
    "id": "qXDYEcfHKbmURV1O",
    "question": "Consider the following reaction and statements:<br/>\n[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Br<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup> + Br<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$ [Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>Br<sub>3</sub>] + NH<sub>3</sub><br/>\n(I) Two isomers are produced if the reactant complex ion is a cis-isomer<br/>\n(II) Two isomers are produced if the reactant complex ion is a trans-isomer<br/>\n(III) Only one isomer is produced if the reactant complex ion is a trans-isomer<br/>\n(IV) Only one isomer is produced if the reactant complex ion is a cis – isomer<br/>\nThe correct statements are<br/> ",
    "options": [
      "(II) and (IV)",
      "(I) and (II)",
      "(I) and (III)",
      "(III) and (IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "(I) and (III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "gr67zpMmJ2f4WyiBKU4Zo",
    "question": "The total number of isomers for a square planar complex<br/> [M(F)(Cl)(SCN)(NO<sub>2</sub>)] is",
    "options": [
      "16",
      "8",
      "12",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "12"
  },
  {
    "id": "EWk3FD5LCpoxqEbnu8M7C",
    "question": "A reaction of cobalt (III) chloride and ethylenediamine in a 1 : 2 mole ratio generates two isomeric products A (violet coloured) and B (green coloured). A can show optical activity, but B is optically inactive. What\ntype of isomers does A and B represcent? ",
    "options": [
      "Ionisation isomers",
      "Linkage isomers ",
      "Coordination isomers ",
      "Geometrical isomers "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "Geometrical isomers "
  },
  {
    "id": "tNYwnhBB08JlR4v5kX3rsa0w2w9jwvfk50q",
    "question": "The species that can have a trans-isomer is :\n<br/>(en = ehane-1, 2-diamine, ox = oxalate)",
    "options": [
      "[Cr(en)<sup>2</sup>(ox)]<sup>+</sup>",
      "[Pt(en)Cl<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[Pt(en)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "[Zn(en)Cl<sub>2</sub>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Pt(en)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "fft7VUommHheSwG2EAjgy2xukf260nxu",
    "question": "The complex that can show optical activity is :",
    "options": [
      "cis-[Fe(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(CN)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>–</sup>",
      "trans-[Cr(Cl<sub>2</sub>)(ox)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>3–</sup>",
      "trans-[Fe(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(CN)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>–</sup>",
      "cis-[CrCl<sub>2</sub>(ox)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>3–</sup> (ox = oxalate)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "cis-[CrCl<sub>2</sub>(ox)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>3–</sup> (ox = oxalate)"
  },
  {
    "id": "k91xz6Jve9MlE14YZAjgy2xukfp2qqku",
    "question": "Consider the complex ions,\n<br/>trans-[Co(en)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup> (A) and<br/> cis-[Co(en)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup> (B).\n<br/>The correct statement regarding them is :",
    "options": [
      "both (A) and (B) can be optically active.",
      "both (A) and (B) can not be optically active.",
      "(A) can not be optically active, but (B) can\nbe optically active.",
      "(A) can be optically active, but (B) can not\nbe optically active."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "(A) can not be optically active, but (B) can\nbe optically active."
  },
  {
    "id": "fwfAGYIljIqSeKNWEcjgy2xukf93y6xw",
    "question": "The number of isomers possible for\n<br/>[Pt(en)(NO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>] is :",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "1",
      "4",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "mfJx94Bp9k9spINXJMjgy2xukeyfafid",
    "question": "The one that is not expected to show isomerism\nis :",
    "options": [
      "[Pt(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[Ni(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>\n",
      "[Ni(en)<sub>3</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "[Ni(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Ni(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "yO2oNOERoTRIcfsnUt7k9k2k5idm5w4",
    "question": "Complex X of composition Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>Cl<sub>n</sub>\nhas a spin only magnetic moment of 3.83\nBM. It reacts with AgNO<sub>3</sub> and shows\ngeometrical isomerism. The IUPAC\nnomenclature of X is :",
    "options": [
      "Hexaaqua chromium (III) chloride",
      "Tetraaquadichlorido chromium(IV)\nchloride dihydrate",
      "Tetraaquadichlorido chromium (III)\nchloride dihydrate",
      "Dichloridotetraaqua chromium (IV)\nchloride dihydrate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "Tetraaquadichlorido chromium (III)\nchloride dihydrate"
  },
  {
    "id": "ghTjG9Ue6vkfOiRHW27k9k2k5hlmtrs",
    "question": "Among (a) – (d) the complexes that can display\ngeometrical isomerism are :<br/>\n(a) [Pt(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>Cl]<sup>+</sup> <br/>\n(b) [Pt(NH<sub>3</sub>)Cl<sub>5</sub>]<sup>–</sup><br/>\n(c) [Pt(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>Cl(NO<sub>2</sub>)]<br/>\n (d) [Pt(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>ClBr]<sup>2+</sup>",
    "options": [
      "(a) and (b)",
      "(c) and (d)",
      "(d) and (a)",
      "(b) and (c)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "(c) and (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": "LD4JFANZA4KqWGKO8g7k9k2k5h0mokz",
    "question": "The complex that can show fac- and mer-isomers is :",
    "options": [
      "[CoCl<sub>2</sub>(en)<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[Pt(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>(NO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>]",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>(NO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "lQ3SCNbx9Fdlsguz0u7k9k2k5ephcwc",
    "question": "The number of possible optical isomers for the complexes MA<sub>2</sub>B<sub>2</sub> with sp<sup>3</sup> and dsp<sup>2</sup> hydridized metal atom. respectively, is :<br/>\nNote : A and B are unidentate netural and unidentate monoanionic ligands, respectively.",
    "options": [
      "0 and 2\n",
      "0 and 0",
      "0 and 1",
      "2 and 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "0 and 0"
  },
  {
    "id": "GXBsGf7nXWdtJ5R3Fp7k9k2k5llk6yl",
    "question": "The isomer(s) of [Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>] that has/have\na Cl–Co–Cl angle of 90°, is/are :",
    "options": [
      "cis only",
      "cis and trans",
      "meridional and trans",
      "trans only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "cis only"
  },
  {
    "id": "nK8A6SQhxF15DHEJB91kmkj4496",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II :<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I<br/></th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II<br/></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>$$[Co{(N{H_3})_6}][Cr{(CN)_6}]$$</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Linkage isomerism</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>$$[Co{(N{H_3})_3}{(N{O_2})_3}]$$</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Solvate isomerism</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>$$[Cr{({H_2}O)_6}C{l_3}$$</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Co-ordination isomerism</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>$$cis - {[CrC{l_2}{(ox)_2}]^{3 - }}$$</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Optical isomerism</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iii), (d)-(i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iv)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz0jp1u",
    "question": "The number of geometrical isomers found in the metal <br/>complexes [PtCl<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>], [Ni(CO)<sub>4</sub>], [Ru(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>3</sub>Cl<sub>3</sub> and [CoCl<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>+</sup> respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "1, 1, 1, 1",
      "2, 1, 2, 2",
      "2, 0, 2, 2",
      "2, 1, 2, 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "2, 0, 2, 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktcozpiz",
    "question": "Indicate the complex/complex ion which did not show any geometrical isomerism :",
    "options": [
      "[CoCl<sub>2</sub>(en)<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[Co(CN)<sub>5</sub>(NC)]<sup>3$$-$$</sup>",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>(NO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>]",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Co(CN)<sub>5</sub>(NC)]<sup>3$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldo2xcgw",
    "question": "<p>The complex cation which has two isomers is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{5} \\mathrm{Cl}\\right]^{+}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{3+}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{5} \\mathrm{NO}_{2}\\right]^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{5} \\mathrm{Cl}\\right]^{2+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{5} \\mathrm{NO}_{2}\\right]^{2+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqwv6uk",
    "question": "The $\\mathrm{Cl}-\\mathrm{Co}-\\mathrm{Cl}$ bond angle values in a fac- $\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{3} \\mathrm{Cl}_{3}\\right]$ complex is/are :",
    "options": [
      "$90^{\\circ} ~\\&~ 120^{\\circ}$",
      "$90^{\\circ}$",
      "$180^{\\circ}$",
      "$90^{\\circ} ~\\& ~180^{\\circ}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "$90^{\\circ}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldss91g5",
    "question": "<p>Chiral complex from the following is :</p>\n<p>Here en = ethylene diamine</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{cis-[PtCl_2(en)_2]^{2+}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{trans-[Co(NH_3)_4Cl_2]^{+}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{trans-[PtCl_2(en)_2]^{2+}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{cis-[PtCl_2(NH_3)_2]}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{cis-[PtCl_2(en)_2]^{2+}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp2fvmg",
    "question": "<p>The total number of stereoisomers for the complex $$\\left[\\mathrm{Cr}(o x)_{2} \\mathrm{ClBr}\\right]^{3-}$$ (where $$o x=$$ oxalate) is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "3",
      "2",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsy839o",
    "question": "<p>If $$\\mathrm{Ni}^{2+}$$ is replaced by $$\\mathrm{Pt}^{2+}$$ in the complex $$\\left[\\mathrm{NiCl}_{2} \\mathrm{Br}_{2}\\right]^{2-}$$, which of the following properties are expected to get changed ?</p>\n<p>A. Geometry</p>\n<p>B. Geometrical isomerism</p>\n<p>C. Optical isomerism</p>\n<p>D. Magnetic properties</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and D",
      "A, B and D",
      "A, B and C",
      "B and C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "A, B and D"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbm3yq7",
    "question": "Which of the following complex is homoleptic?",
    "options": [
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_3\\right)_2 \\mathrm{Cl}_2\\right]$",
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_3\\right)_4 \\mathrm{Cl}_2\\right]^{+}$",
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_3\\right)_4 \\mathrm{Cl}_2\\right]^{+}$",
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CN})_4\\right]^{2-}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CN})_4\\right]^{2-}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2u40s",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A): The total number of geometrical isomers shown by $$[\\mathrm{Co}(\\mathrm{en})_2 \\mathrm{Cl}_2]^{+}$$ complex ion is three.</p>\n<p>Reason (R): $$[\\mathrm{Co}(\\mathrm{en})_2 \\mathrm{Cl}_2]^{+}$$ complex ion has an octahedral geometry.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s2pwh",
    "question": "<p>The metal atom present in the complex MABXL (where A, B, X and L are unidentate ligands and $$\\mathrm{M}$$ is metal) involves $$\\mathrm{sp}^3$$ hybridization. The number of geometrical isomers exhibited by the complex is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0",
      "2",
      "3",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "isomerism-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "0"
  },
  {
    "id": "o6qiYzxzuWmBQihq",
    "question": "The IUPAC name of the coordination compound K<sub>3</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>] is",
    "options": [
      "Potassium hexacyanoferrate (II)",
      "Potassium hexacyanoferrate (III)",
      "Potassium hexacyanoiron (II)",
      "Tripotassium hexcyanoiron (II) "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "nomenclature-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "Potassium hexacyanoferrate (III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "fZGIaIOBAdwc2YmS",
    "question": "The IUPAC name for the complex [Co(NO<sub>2</sub>)(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub> is ",
    "options": [
      "nitrito-N-pentaamminecobalt (III) chloride",
      "nitrito-N-pentaamminecobalt (II) chloride",
      "pentaammine nitrito-N-cobalt (II) chloride",
      "pentaammine nitrito-N-cobalt (III) chloride "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "nomenclature-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "pentaammine nitrito-N-cobalt (III) chloride "
  },
  {
    "id": "6XZUImf3vFKRewJX",
    "question": "Which among the following will be named as dibromidobis (ethylene diamine) chromium(III) bromide?",
    "options": [
      "[Cr (en)<sub>3</sub> ] Br<sub>3</sub> ",
      "[Cr (en)<sub>2</sub> Br<sub>2</sub> ] Br",
      "[Cr (en) Br<sub>4</sub> ]<sup>-</sup>",
      "[Cr (en) Br<sub>2</sub> ] Br"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "nomenclature-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Cr (en)<sub>2</sub> Br<sub>2</sub> ] Br"
  },
  {
    "id": "svmtYVHA3K02hH7BRP7k9k2k5dz59pb",
    "question": "The IUPAC name of complex [Pt(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>Cl(NH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>)]Cl is:\n",
    "options": [
      "Diamminechlorido (methanamine) platinum(II)chloride.",
      "Biasmmine (methanamine)chlorido platinum(II)chloride.",
      "Diamminechlorido (amminomethane) platinum(II) chloride.",
      "Diammine (methanamine) chlorido platinum(II)Chloride."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "nomenclature-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "Diamminechlorido (methanamine) platinum(II)chloride."
  },
  {
    "id": "YyHh4Kf0uIXBWaLwWMjgy2xukf3ngbjk",
    "question": "Complex A has a composition of H<sub>12</sub>O<sub>6</sub>Cl<sub>3</sub>Cr. If the complex on treatment with conc.H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>\n loses\n13.5% of its original mass, the correct molecular formula of A is :\n<br/>[Given: atomic mass of Cr = 52 amu and Cl = 35 amu]",
    "options": [
      "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>5</sub>Cl]Cl<sub>2</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]Cl.2H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>3</sub>Cl<sub>3</sub>].3H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "nomenclature-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]Cl.2H<sub>2</sub>O"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh329qjt",
    "question": "<p>The IUPAC name of $$\\mathrm{K}_{3}\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}\\right)_{3}\\right]$$ is:-</p>",
    "options": [
      "Potassium tris(oxalato)cobalt(III)",
      "Potassium tris(oxalato)cobaltate(III)",
      "Potassium trioxalatocobaltate(III)",
      "Potassium trioxalatocobalt(III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "nomenclature-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "Potassium trioxalatocobaltate(III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2a7ya",
    "question": "<p>The correct IUPAC name of $$[\\mathrm{PtBr}_2(\\mathrm{PMe}_3)_2]$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "bis(trimethylphosphine)dibromoplatinum(II)\n",
      "dibromodi(trimethylphosphine)platinum(II)\n",
      "dibromobis(trimethylphosphine)platinum(II)\n",
      "bis[bromo(trimethylphosphine)]platinum(II)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "nomenclature-of-coordination-compounds",
    "solution": "dibromobis(trimethylphosphine)platinum(II)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "40Jnl2W98XY3AZTR",
    "question": "The correct order of magnetic moments (spin only values in B.M.) among is :<br/>\n(Atomic numbers: Mn = 25; Fe = 26, Co =27) ",
    "options": [
      "[MnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>-2</sup> &gt; [Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>-4</sup>",
      "[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>-4</sup> &gt; [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [MnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>",
      "[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>4-</sup> &gt; [MnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>",
      "[MnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>4-</sup> &gt; [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[MnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>-2</sup> &gt; [Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>-4</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "NkthvtwsouqmRRNd",
    "question": "Which one of the following complexes in an outer orbital complex? ",
    "options": [
      "[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>4-</sup> ",
      "[Ni(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "[Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+ </sup>",
      "[Mn(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>4-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[Ni(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "vaZqaiWXWkvBFFT0",
    "question": "Among the properties (a) reducing (b) oxidising (c) complexing, the set of properties shown by CN<sup>–</sup> ion\ntowards metal species is :",
    "options": [
      "c, a",
      "b, c",
      "a, b",
      "a, b, c"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "c, a"
  },
  {
    "id": "BClBtSUGp0NJL2jm",
    "question": "Which one of the following cyano complexes would exhibit the lowest value of\nparamagnetic behaviour? <br/>\n(At. No. Cr = 24, Mn = 25, Fe = 26, Co = 27) ",
    "options": [
      "[Cr(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>-3 </sup>",
      "[Mn(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>-3</sup>",
      "[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>-3</sup> ",
      "[Co(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>-3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[Co(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>-3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "qV8n6cJID5GHsZ6b",
    "question": "Nickel (Z = 28) combines with a uninegative monodentate ligand X<sup>–</sup> to form a paramagnetic complex [NiX<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2−</sup> . The number of unpaired electron(s) in the nickel and geometry of this complex ion are,\nrespectively ",
    "options": [
      "one, tetrahedral",
      "two, tetrahedral ",
      "one, square planar",
      "two, square planar"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "two, tetrahedral "
  },
  {
    "id": "KBYjU1PZq4M3XljT",
    "question": "In Fe(CO)<sub>5</sub>, the Fe – C bond possesses :",
    "options": [
      "π-character only",
      "both $$\\sigma$$ and π characters ",
      "ionic character",
      "$$\\sigma$$-character"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "both $$\\sigma$$ and π characters "
  },
  {
    "id": "TOAWMOIzh3scQl0m",
    "question": "Which one of the following has a square planar geometry? ",
    "options": [
      "[CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>",
      "[FeCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>",
      "[NiCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>",
      "[PtCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[PtCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "7TnFUrrxH2mrZkAd",
    "question": "Which of the following facts about the complex [Cr (NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub> ]Cl<sub>3</sub> is wrong?",
    "options": [
      "The complex is paramagnetic ",
      "The complex is an outer orbital complex ",
      "The complex gives white precipitate with silver nitrate solution",
      "The complex involves d<sup>2</sup>sp<sup>3</sup> hybridization and is octahedral in shape."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "The complex is an outer orbital complex "
  },
  {
    "id": "4ECfPwwyPWONuD2m",
    "question": "The magnetic moment (spin only) of [NiCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2−</sup> is",
    "options": [
      "5.46 BM ",
      "2.82 BM",
      "1.41 BM ",
      "1.82 BM"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "2.82 BM"
  },
  {
    "id": "TFd6QU4VPk9f6eLx",
    "question": "The pair having the same magnetic moment is : <br/>\n[At. No.: Cr = 24, Mn = 25, Fe = 26, Co = 27] ",
    "options": [
      "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and [Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+ </sup>",
      "[Mn(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "[CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2–</sup> and [Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> ",
      "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2–</sup> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and [Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+ </sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Q7VKeI1XWxrg8kUF8NDHp",
    "question": "Which one of the following complexes will consume more equivalents of aqueous\nsolution of Ag(NO<sub>3</sub>)?",
    "options": [
      "Na<sub>3</sub>[CrCl<sub>6</sub>]\n",
      "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>5</sub>Cl]Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub>",
      "Na<sub>2</sub>[CrCl<sub>5</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O)]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "gMdsz15sySHNjT7B",
    "question": "On treatment of 100 mL of 0.1 M solution of CoCl<sub>3</sub>. 6H<sub>2</sub>O with excess AgNO<sub>3</sub>; 1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>22</sup> ions are precipitated. The complex is :",
    "options": [
      "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>3</sub>Cl<sub>3</sub>].3H<sub>2</sub>O ",
      "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub>",
      "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>5</sub>Cl]Cl<sub>2</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O ",
      "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>]Cl.2H<sub>2</sub>O "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>5</sub>Cl]Cl<sub>2</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O "
  },
  {
    "id": "z1kU5ZSykT5i8HUR5a1DX",
    "question": "The correct combination is : ",
    "options": [
      "[Ni(CN)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> $$-$$ tetrahedral ;\n<br><br>[Ni(CO)<sub>4</sub>] $$-$$ paramagnetic",
      "[Ni(Cl)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> $$-$$ paramagnetic ;\n<br><br>[Ni(CO)<sub>4</sub>] $$-$$ tetrahedral",
      "[Ni(Cl)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> $$-$$ square-planar ;\n<br><br>[Ni(CN)<sub>4</sub>] <sup>2-</sup>$$-$$ paramagnetic",
      "[Ni(Cl)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> $$-$$ diamagnetic ;\n<br><br>[Ni(CO)<sub>4</sub>] $$-$$square-planar"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[Ni(Cl)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> $$-$$ paramagnetic ;\n<br><br>[Ni(CO)<sub>4</sub>] $$-$$ tetrahedral"
  },
  {
    "id": "YTGe2XX7oM0ligefG7cFx",
    "question": "The correct order of spin-only magnetic moments among the following is : \n<br/>(Atomic number : Mn = 25, Co = 27, Ni = 28, Zn = 30)",
    "options": [
      "[ZnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [NiCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [MnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>",
      "[CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [MnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [NiCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [ZnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>",
      "[NiCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [MnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [ZnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>",
      "[MnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [NiCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [ZnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[MnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [NiCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup> &gt; [ZnCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2-</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "EAll4IJyp7ZT1pHuN8CRh",
    "question": "In Wilkinson's catalyst, the hybridization of central metal ion and its shape are respectively : ",
    "options": [
      "sp<sup>3</sup>d, trigonal bipyramidal ",
      "sp<sup>3</sup>, tetrahedral",
      "dsp<sup>2</sup>, square planar ",
      "d<sup>2</sup>sp<sup>3</sup>,  octahedral "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "dsp<sup>2</sup>, square planar "
  },
  {
    "id": "iuI2LTDhrKzwH2z46ifKC",
    "question": "The calculated spin-only magnetic moments\n(BM) of the anionic and cationic species of\n[Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sub>2</sub> and [Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>], respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "2.84 and 5.92",
      "4.9 and 0",
      "0 and 4.9",
      "0 and 5.92"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "4.9 and 0"
  },
  {
    "id": "EqgJ5MWVQbKw7AJZzYit0",
    "question": "The correct statements among I to III are :<br/>\n(I) Valence bond theory cannot explain the\ncolor exhibited by transition metal\ncomplexes.<br/>\n(II) Valence bond theory can predict\nquantitatively the magnetic properties of\ntranstition metal complexes.<br/>\n(III) Valence bond theory cannot distinguish\nligands as weak and strong field ones.",
    "options": [
      "(II) and (III) only",
      "(I) and (II) only",
      "(I), (II) and (III)",
      "(I) and (III) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "(I) and (III) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "OUtaGWaKrVIRiBLKUMfw6",
    "question": "The metal d-orbitals that are directly facing the ligands in K<sub>3</sub>[Co(CN)<sub>6</sub>] are - ",
    "options": [
      "d<sub>x<sup>2</sup></sub><sub>$$-$$y<sup>2</sup></sub> and d<sub>z<sup>2</sup></sub>",
      "d<sub>xy</sub>, d<sub>xz</sub> and d<sub>yz </sub>",
      "d<sub>xz</sub>, d<sub>yz</sub> and d<sub>z<sup>2</sup> </sub>",
      "d<sub>xy</sub> and d<sub>x<sup>2</sup> $$-$$ y<sup>2</sup></sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "d<sub>x<sup>2</sup></sub><sub>$$-$$y<sup>2</sup></sub> and d<sub>z<sup>2</sup></sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "DwWbP3BYMHmPulSs8YQtZ",
    "question": "The difference in the number of unpaired electrons of a metal ion in its high spin and low-spin octahedral complexes is two. The metal ion is :",
    "options": [
      "Mn<sup>2+</sup> ",
      "Ni<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Co<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Fe<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "Co<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "5puJOFmSTYWrMnOJNt7hp",
    "question": "The magnetic moment of an octahedral homoleptic Mn(II) complex is 5.9 BM. The suitable ligand for this complex is - ",
    "options": [
      "CN<sup>$$-$$</sup> ",
      "ethylenediamine ",
      "NCS<sup>–</sup>",
      "CO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "NCS<sup>–</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "ASpAiFIOIhLRaDcL5S7k9k2k5hlys9f",
    "question": "The correct order of the calculated spin-only\nmagnetic moments of complexs (A) to (D) is:<br/>\n(A) Ni(CO)<sub>4</sub><br/>\n(B) [Ni(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub><br/>\n(C) Na<sub>2</sub>[Ni(CN)<sub>4</sub>]<br/>\n(D) PdCl<sub>2</sub>(PPh<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
    "options": [
      "(C) &lt; (D) &lt; (B) &lt; (A)",
      "(C) $$ \\approx $$ (D) &lt; (B) &lt; (A)",
      "(A) $$ \\approx $$ (C) $$ \\approx $$ (D) &lt; (B)",
      "(A) $$ \\approx $$ (C) &lt; (B) $$ \\approx $$ (D)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "(A) $$ \\approx $$ (C) $$ \\approx $$ (D) &lt; (B)"
  },
  {
    "id": "zOQUVaJo6QRX1LvRXWjgy2xukevh5zy7",
    "question": "For octahedral Mn(II) and tetrahedral Ni(II)\ncomplexes, consider the following statements:\n<br/><br/>(I) both the complexes can be high spin.\n<br/>(II) Ni(II) complex can very rarely be low spin.\n<br/>(III) with strong field ligands, Mn(II) complexes\ncan be low spin.\n<br/>(IV)aqueous solution of Mn(II) ions is yellow in\ncolour.\n<br/><br/>The <b>correct</b> statements are :",
    "options": [
      "(I), (III) and (IV) only",
      "(I) and (II) only",
      "(II), (III) and (IV) only",
      "(I), (II) and (III) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "(I), (II) and (III) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZasO1dmCZvKvS5eZ86jgy2xukf9juj6x",
    "question": "The pair in which both the species have the\nsame magnetic moment (spin only) is :",
    "options": [
      "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2–</sup>",
      "[Co(OH)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2–</sup> and [Fe(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "[Mn(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)]<sup>2+</sup>",
      "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and [Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and [Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "L0VS4HVimhCxFQFW0sjgy2xukfcf82dc",
    "question": "The molecule in which hybrid MOs involve only\none d-orbital of the central atom is :",
    "options": [
      "XeF<sub>4</sub>",
      "[Ni(CN)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2–</sup>",
      "[CrF<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3–</sup>",
      "BrF<sub>5</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[Ni(CN)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2–</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "SgQsFCyYe575cK39zIjgy2xukftb36fy",
    "question": "The species that has a spin-only magnetic\nmoment of 5.9 BM, is :\n<br/>(T<sub>d</sub> = tetrahedral)",
    "options": [
      "[MnBr<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2–</sup> (T<sub>d</sub>)",
      "[NiCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2–</sup> (T<sub>d</sub>)",
      "Ni(CO)<sub>4</sub> (T<sub>d</sub>)",
      "[Ni(CN)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2–</sup> (square planar)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[MnBr<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2–</sup> (T<sub>d</sub>)"
  },
  {
    "id": "iGJEzyo9vo7mWRQwjv1kls99g04",
    "question": "The hybridization and magnetic nature of $${[Mn{(CN)_6}]^{4 - }}$$ and $${[Fe{(CN)_6}]^{3 - }}$$, respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup> and diamagnetic",
      "d<sup>2</sup>sp<sup>3</sup> and paramagnetic",
      "sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup> and paramagnetic ",
      "d<sup>2</sup>sp<sup>3</sup> and diamagnetic"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "d<sup>2</sup>sp<sup>3</sup> and paramagnetic"
  },
  {
    "id": "KUZ5uhS8NaNi6g5iLt1kltb3bda",
    "question": "In which of the following order the given complex ions are arranged correctly with respect to their decreasing spin only magnetic moment?<br/><br/>(i) [FeF<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup><br/><br/>(ii) [Co(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup><br/><br/>(iii) [NiCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup><br/><br/>(iv) [Cu(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2+</sup>",
    "options": [
      "(iii) &gt; (iv) &gt; (ii) &gt; (i)",
      "(ii) &gt; (iii) &gt; (i) &gt; (iv)",
      "(i) &gt; (iii) &gt; (iv) &gt; (ii)",
      "(ii) &gt; (i) &gt; (iii) &gt; (iv)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "(i) &gt; (iii) &gt; (iv) &gt; (ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq52f6z",
    "question": "According to the valence bond theory the hybridization of central metal atom is dsp<sup>2</sup> for which one of the following compounds?",
    "options": [
      "$$NiC{l_2}.6{H_2}O$$",
      "$${K_2}[Ni{(CN)_4}]$$",
      "$$[Ni{(CO)_4}]$$",
      "$$N{a_2}[NiC{l_4}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "$${K_2}[Ni{(CN)_4}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krri1uc9",
    "question": "Spin only magnetic moment of an octahedral complex of Fe<sup>2+</sup> in the presence of a strong field ligand in BM is :",
    "options": [
      "4.89",
      "2.82",
      "0",
      "3.46"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "0"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krri3h2e",
    "question": "Which one of the following species doesn't have a magnetic moment of 1.73 BM, (spin only value)?",
    "options": [
      "O$$_2^ + $$",
      "CuI",
      "[Cu(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "O$$_2^ - $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "CuI"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krursjoe",
    "question": "Which one of the following species responds to an external magnetic field?",
    "options": [
      "[Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>",
      "[Ni(CN)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup>",
      "[Co(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup>",
      "[Ni(CO)<sub>4</sub>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "[Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz0epef",
    "question": "The type of hybridisation and magnetic property of the complex [MnCl<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup>, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup> and diamagnetic",
      "d<sup>2</sup>sp<sup>3</sup> and diamagnetic",
      "d<sup>2</sup>sp<sup>3</sup> and paramagnetic",
      "sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup> and paramagnetic"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "sp<sup>3</sup>d<sup>2</sup> and paramagnetic"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1hr11y",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : $${[Mn{(CN)_6}]^{3 - }}$$, $${[Fe{(CN)_6}]^{3 - }}$$ and $${[Co{({C_2}{O_4})_3}]^{3 - }}$$ are d<sup>2</sup>sp<sup>3</sup> hybridised.<br/><br/>Statement II : $${[MnCl)_6}{]^{3 - }}$$ and $${[Fe{F_6}]^{3 - }}$$ are paramagnetic and have 4 and 5 unpaired electrons, respectively.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is false",
      "Both statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is incorrect but statement II is true",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "Both statement I and statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjvkord",
    "question": "Spin only magnetic moment in BM of [Fe(CO)<sub>4</sub>(C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>)]<sup>+</sup> is :",
    "options": [
      "5.92",
      "0",
      "1",
      "1.73"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "1.73"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56aywg1",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : [Ni(CN)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup> is square planar and diamagnetic complex, with dsp<sup>2</sup> hybridization for Ni but [Ni(CO)<sub>4</sub>] is tetrahedral, paramagnetic and with sp<sup>3</sup>-hybridication for Ni.</p>\n<p>Statement  II : [NiCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup> and [Ni(CO)<sub>4</sub>] both have same d-electron configuration have same geometry and are paramagnetic.</p>\n<p>In light the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56xoaew",
    "question": "<p>Arrange the following coordination compounds in the increasing order of magnetic moments. (Atomic numbers : Mn = 25; Fe = 26)</p>\n<p>A. [FeF<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup></p>\n<p>B. [Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup></p>\n<p>C. [MnCl<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup> (high spin)</p>\n<p>D. [Mn(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A < B < D < C",
      "B < D < C < A",
      "A < C < D < B",
      "B < D < A < C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "B < D < C < A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c644lu",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 505px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 62px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 195px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 80px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 168px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\">List -II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${[PtC{l_4}]^{2 - }}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$s{p^3}d$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$Br{F_5}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${d^2}s{p^3}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$PC{l_5}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$ds{p^2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${[Co{(N{H_3})_6}]^{3 + }}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$s{p^3}{d^2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i597wj",
    "question": "<p>The metal complex that is diamagnetic is (Atomic number: $$\\mathrm{Fe}, 26 ; \\mathrm{Cu}, 29)$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{3}\\left[\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{CN})_{4}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{2}\\left[\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{CN})_{4}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{3}\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{4}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{4}\\left[\\mathrm{FeCl}_{6}\\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{K}_{3}\\left[\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{CN})_{4}\\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nwo1vw",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-fymr{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 530px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 53px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 179px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 40px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 258px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-fymr\">List - I (Complex)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-fymr\">List - II (Hybridization)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$Ni{(CO)_4}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$s{p^3}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${[Ni{(CN)_4}]^{2 - }}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$s{p^3}{d^2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${[Co{(CN)_6}]^{3 - }}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${d^2}s{p^3}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${[Co{F_6}]^{3 - }}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$ds{p^2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II",
      "A-I, B-IV, C-III, D-II",
      "A-I, B-IV, C-II, D-III",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "A-I, B-IV, C-III, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpp939b",
    "question": "<p>Cobalt chloride when dissolved in water forms pink colored complex $$\\underline{\\mathrm{X}}$$ which has\noctahedral geometry. This solution on treating with conc $$\\mathrm{HCl}$$ forms deep blue complex, $$\\underline{\\mathrm{Y}}$$ which has a $$\\underline{\\mathrm{Z}}$$ geometry. $$\\mathrm{X}, \\mathrm{Y}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Z}$$, respectively, are</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{X}=\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{2+}, \\mathrm{Y}=\\left[\\mathrm{CoCl}_{4}\\right]^{2-}, \\mathrm{Z}=$$ Tetrahedral",
      "$$\\mathrm{X}=\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{2+}, \\mathrm{Y}=\\left[\\mathrm{CoCl}_{6}\\right]^{3-}, \\mathrm{Z}=$$ Octahedral",
      "$$\\mathrm{X}=\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{4} \\mathrm{Cl}_{2}\\right]^{+}, \\mathrm{Y}=\\left[\\mathrm{CoCl}_{4}\\right]^{2-}, \\mathrm{Z}=$$ Tetrahedral",
      "$$\\mathrm{X}=\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{3+}, \\mathrm{Y}=\\left[\\mathrm{CoCl}_{6}\\right]^{3-}, \\mathrm{Z}=$$ Octahedral"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{X}=\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{2+}, \\mathrm{Y}=\\left[\\mathrm{CoCl}_{4}\\right]^{2-}, \\mathrm{Z}=$$ Tetrahedral"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqwtmcv",
    "question": "<p>Match List <b>I</b> with List <b>II</b>:</p>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\" colspan=\"2\"> List I (Complexes) </th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\" colspan=\"2\"> List II (Hybridisation) </th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CO})_{4}\\right]$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\mathrm{sp}^{3}$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\left[\\mathrm{Cu}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{4}\\right]^{2+}$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">dsp$^{2}$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{2+}$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\mathrm{sp}^{3}\\mathrm{d}^{2}$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{2+}$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\mathrm{d}^{2} \\mathrm{sp}^{3}$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-I, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-I, B-II, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "A-I, B-II, C-IV, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwuyjew",
    "question": "<p>The hybridization and magnetic behaviour of cobalt ion in $$\\mathrm{[Co(NH_3)_6]^{3+}}$$ complex, respectively is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{sp^3d^2}$$ and paramagnetic",
      "$$\\mathrm{sp^3d^2}$$ and diamagnetic",
      "$$\\mathrm{d^2sp^3}$$ and diamagnetic",
      "$$\\mathrm{d^2sp^3}$$ and paramagnetic"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{d^2sp^3}$$ and diamagnetic"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp2ph10",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following complexes will exhibit maximum attraction to an applied magnetic field?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}(\\mathrm{en})_{3}\\right]^{3+}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Zn}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{2+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{2+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsyk75j",
    "question": "<p>The magnetic moment is measured in Bohr Magneton (BM).</p>\n<p>Spin only magnetic moment of $$\\mathrm{Fe}$$ in $$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}\\right)_{6}\\right]^{3+}$$ and $$\\left[\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CN})_{6}\\right]^{3-}$$ complexes respectively is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3.87 B.M. and 1.732 B.M.",
      "5.92 B.M. and 1.732 B.M.",
      "6.92 B.M. in both",
      "4.89 B.M. and 6.92 B.M."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "5.92 B.M. and 1.732 B.M."
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscrbrsx",
    "question": "<p>Identify from the following species in which $$\\mathrm{d}^2 \\mathrm{sp}^3$$ hybridization is shown by central atom :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_3\\right)_6\\right]^{3+}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{SF}_6$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Pt}\\left(\\mathrm{Cl}_4\\right)\\right]^{2-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{BrF}_5$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_3\\right)_6\\right]^{3+}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse78fvs",
    "question": "<p>The correct statements from following are:</p>\n<p>A. The strength of anionic ligands can be explained by crystal field theory.</p>\n<p>B. Valence bond theory does not give a quantitative interpretation of kinetic stability of coordination compounds.</p>\n<p>C. The hybridization involved in formation of $$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CN})_4\\right]^{2-}$$ complex is $$\\mathrm{dsp}^2$$.</p>\n<p>D. The number of possible isomer(s) of cis- $$\\left[\\mathrm{PtCl}_2(\\mathrm{en})_2\\right]^{2+}$$ is one</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "B, C only",
      "B, D only",
      "A, C only",
      "A, D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "B, C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxzq6jp",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 572px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 160px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 262px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{K}_2\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CN})_4\\right]$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$sp^3$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CO})_4\\right]$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$sp^3d^2$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_3\\right)_6\\right] \\mathrm{Cl}_3$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$dsp^2$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Na}_3\\left[\\mathrm{CoF}_6\\right]$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$d^2sp^3$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I\n",
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV\n",
      "A-I, B-III, C-II, D-IV\n",
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxzq6ml",
    "question": "<p>The coordination environment of $$\\mathrm{Ca}^{2+}$$ ion in its complex with $$\\mathrm{EDTA}^{4-}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "trigonal prismatic\n",
      "octahedral\n",
      "square planar\n",
      "tetrahedral"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "octahedral\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2a27q",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I: $$\\mathrm{PF}_5$$ and $$\\mathrm{BrF}_5$$ both exhibit $$\\mathrm{sp}^3 \\mathrm{~d}$$ hybridisation.</p>\n<p>Statement II: Both $$\\mathrm{SF}_6$$ and $$[\\mathrm{Co}(\\mathrm{NH}_3)_6]^{3+}$$ exhibit $$\\mathrm{sp}^3 \\mathrm{~d}^2$$ hybridisation.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc583fj",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 690px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 239px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Hybridization)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Orientation in Shape)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">sp$$^3$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Trigonal bipyramidal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">dsp$$^2$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Octahedral</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">sp$$^3$$d</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Tetrahedral</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">sp$$^3$$d$$^2$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Square planar</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II\n",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "coordination-compounds",
    "topic": "warner's-theory-and-valence-bond-theory",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "aQaC4dPa13FZvLPn",
    "question": "When KMnO<sub>4</sub> acts as an oxidising agent and ultimately forms [MnO<sub>4</sub>]<sup>-2</sup>, MnO<sub>2</sub>, Mn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, Mn<sup>+2</sup>\nthen the number of electrons transferred in each case respectively is :",
    "options": [
      "4, 3, 1, 5",
      "1, 5, 3, 7",
      "1, 3, 4, 5",
      "3, 5, 7, 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "1, 3, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "id": "TlqI0SzeQZIcJIl3",
    "question": "How do we differentiate between Fe<sup>3+</sup> and Cr<sup>3+</sup> in group III?",
    "options": [
      "by taking excess of NH<sub>4</sub>OH solution",
      "by increasing $$NH_4^+$$ ion concentration",
      "by decreasing OH<sup>-</sup> ion concentration",
      "both (b) and (c)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "by increasing $$NH_4^+$$ ion concentration"
  },
  {
    "id": "KugVJyu3U5Sj62wc",
    "question": "What would happen when a solution of potassium chromate is treated with an excess of dilute nitric acid?",
    "options": [
      "$$Cr_2O^{2-}_7$$ and H<sub>2</sub>O are formed",
      "$$CrO^{2-}_4$$ is reduced to +3 state of Cr",
      "$$CrO^{2-}_4$$ is oxidized to +7 state of Cr",
      "Cr<sup>3+</sup> and $$Cr_2O^{2-}_7$$ are formed"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$Cr_2O^{2-}_7$$ and H<sub>2</sub>O are formed"
  },
  {
    "id": "qRZOZiuvp3UDoAVQ",
    "question": "Which one of the following nitrates will leave behind a metal on strong heating?",
    "options": [
      "Copper nitrate",
      "Manganese nitrate",
      "Silver nitrate",
      "Ferric nitrate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Silver nitrate"
  },
  {
    "id": "3EsBxv3qNbGk3x9Q",
    "question": "Excess of KI reacts with CuSO<sub>4</sub> solution and then Na<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> solution is added to it. Which of the statements is incorrect for this reaction?",
    "options": [
      "Cu<sub>2</sub>I<sub>2</sub> is reduced",
      "Evolved I<sub>2</sub> is reduced ",
      "Na<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is oxidized ",
      "CuI<sub>2</sub> is formed"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "CuI<sub>2</sub> is formed"
  },
  {
    "id": "giu36jkEKD5k2Tao",
    "question": "The oxidation state of chromium in the final product formed the reaction between $$K{\\rm I}$$ and acidified potassium dichromate solution is :",
    "options": [
      "$$+3$$ ",
      "$$+2$$ ",
      "$$+6$$ ",
      "$$+4$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$+3$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "PlZTAZeOs28jTLd8",
    "question": "Amount of oxalic  acid present in a solution can be determined by its titration with $$KMn{O_4}$$ solution in the presence of $${H_2}S{O_4}.$$ The titration gives unsatisfactory result when carried out in the presence of $$HCl,$$ because $$HCl$$ :",
    "options": [
      "gets oxidised by oxalic acid to chlorine",
      "furnishes $${H^ + }$$ ions in addition to those from oxalic acid ",
      "reduces permanganate to $$M{n^{2 + }}$$ ",
      "oxaidises oxalic acid to carbon doxide and water "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "reduces permanganate to $$M{n^{2 + }}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "eMllOmkYpMeILw7S",
    "question": "The colour of KMnO<sub>4</sub> is due to :",
    "options": [
      "d – d transition",
      "L $$\\to$$ M charge transfer transition",
      "$$\\sigma$$ – $$\\sigma$$* transition",
      "M $$\\to$$ L charge transfer transition"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "L $$\\to$$ M charge transfer transition"
  },
  {
    "id": "OFwhY75bqYtioWQosutex",
    "question": "Wilkinson catalyst is : (Et = C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)",
    "options": [
      "[(Ph<sub>3</sub>P)<sub>3</sub> RhCl]",
      "[(Et<sub>3</sub>P)<sub>3</sub>RhCl] \n",
      "[(Et<sub>3</sub>P)<sub>3</sub>IrCl] ",
      "[(Ph<sub>3</sub>P)<sub>3</sub>IrCl]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "[(Ph<sub>3</sub>P)<sub>3</sub> RhCl]"
  },
  {
    "id": "JIbxcz8597tBsSKstVsXW",
    "question": "$$\\underline A \\,\\,\\buildrel {4KOH,{O_2}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow \\,\\,\\mathop {2\\underline B }\\limits_{\\left( {Green} \\right)} \\,\\, + \\,\\,2{H_2}O$$\n<br/><br/>$$3\\underline B \\,\\,\\buildrel {4HCl} \\over\n \\longrightarrow \\,\\,\\mathop {2\\underline C }\\limits_{\\left( {Purple} \\right)} \\,\\, + \\,\\,Mn{O_2} + 2{H_2}O$$\n<br/><br/>$$2\\underline C \\,\\,\\buildrel {{H_2}O.KI} \\over\n \\longrightarrow \\,\\,\\mathop {2\\underline A }\\limits_{\\left( {Purple} \\right)} \\,\\, + \\,\\,2KOH\\,\\, + \\,\\,\\underline D $$\n<br/><br/>In the above sequence of reactions,  $${\\underline A }$$ and $${\\underline D }$$,  respectively, are : ",
    "options": [
      "Kl and KMnO<sub>4</sub>",
      "Kl and K<sub>2</sub>MnO<sub>4</sub>",
      "KlO<sub>3</sub> and MnO<sub>2</sub>",
      "MnO<sub>2</sub> and KlO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "MnO<sub>2</sub> and KlO<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "SxP5UynwIehkRfgJOp7k9k2k5llbck3",
    "question": "5 g of zinc is treated separately with an excess\nof<br/><br/>\n(a) dilute hydrochloric acid and<br/>\n(b) aqueous sodium hydroxide.<br/><br/>\nThe ratio of the volumes of H<sub>2</sub> evolved in these\ntwo reactions is :",
    "options": [
      "1 : 2",
      "1 : 1",
      "1 : 4",
      "2 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "1 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "gafN2KKWlOo1S7JqAljgy2xukf3lsk6i",
    "question": "The incorrect statement is :",
    "options": [
      "In manganate and permanganate ions, the p-bonding takes place by overlap of p-orbitals\nof oxygen and d-orbitals of manganese",
      "Manganate ion is green in colour and\npermanganate ion in purple in colour",
      "Manganate and permanganate ions are\nparamagnetic",
      "Manganate and permanganate ions are\ntetrahedral"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Manganate and permanganate ions are\nparamagnetic"
  },
  {
    "id": "gUir0qIwpPZX21KJaN1klrtkun7",
    "question": "The <b>incorrect</b> statement among the following is :",
    "options": [
      "RuO<sub>4</sub> is an oxidizing agent",
      "Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is an amphoteric oxide.",
      "VOSO<sub>4</sub> is a reducing agent",
      "Red colour of ruby is due to the presence of Co<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Red colour of ruby is due to the presence of Co<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1E1QnAxA5sobgtH1AF1kmittq0r",
    "question": "Fex<sub>2</sub> and Fey<sub>3</sub> are known when x and y are :",
    "options": [
      "x = F, Cl, Br, I and y = F, Cl, Br, I",
      "x = F, Cl, Br and y = F, Cl, Br, I",
      "x = F, Cl, Br, I and y = F, Cl, Br",
      "x = Cl, Br, I and y = F, Cl, Br, I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "x = F, Cl, Br, I and y = F, Cl, Br"
  },
  {
    "id": "CivhjvqqskbrvQSBAK1kmj7jzgu",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : Potassium permanganate on heating at 573K forms potassium manganate.<br/><br/>Statement II : Both potassium permanganate and potassium manganate are tetrahedral and paramagnetic in nature.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "nsNSJSMsWHkLexcvYi1kmlmoebj",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I<br/></th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II<br/></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Chlorophyll</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Ruthenium</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Vitamin-$${B_{12}}$$</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Platinum</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Anticancer drug</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Cobalt</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Grubbs catalyst</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Magnesium</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a) - (iii), (b) - (ii), (c) - (iv), (d) - (i)",
      "(a) - (iv), (b) - (iii), (c) - (ii), (d) - (i)",
      "(a) - (iv), (b) - (iii), (c) - (i), (d) - (ii)",
      "(a) - (iv), (b) - (ii), (c) - (iii), (d) - (i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "(a) - (iv), (b) - (iii), (c) - (ii), (d) - (i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "KYRVypzy7VyKvyLJhc1kmm0le8t",
    "question": "The oxide that shows magnetic property is :",
    "options": [
      "MgO",
      "SiO<sub>2</sub>",
      "Mn<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>",
      "Na<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Mn<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krut0zde",
    "question": "The correct order of following 3d metal oxides, according to their oxidation numbers is :<br/><br/>(a) CrO<sub>3</sub>, (b) Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, (c) MnO<sub>2</sub>, (d) V<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>, (e) Cu<sub>2</sub>O",
    "options": [
      "(d) &gt; (a) &gt; (b) &gt; (c) &gt; (e)",
      "(a) &gt; (c) &gt; (d) &gt; (b) &gt; (e)",
      "(a) &gt; (d) &gt; (c) &gt; (b) &gt; (e)",
      "(c) &gt; (a) &gt; (d) &gt; (e) &gt; (b)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "(a) &gt; (d) &gt; (c) &gt; (b) &gt; (e)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krx8i6bf",
    "question": "Which one of the following metals forms interstitial hydride easily?",
    "options": [
      "Cr",
      "Fe",
      "Mn",
      "Co"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Cr"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfrjv92",
    "question": "The addition of dilute NaOH to Cr<sup>3+</sup> salt solution will give :",
    "options": [
      "a solution of [Cr(OH)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "precipitate of Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>n</sub>",
      "precipitate of [Cr(OH)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup>",
      "precipitate of Cr(OH)<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "precipitate of Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>n</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfsikza",
    "question": "Potassium permanganate on heating at 513 K gives a product which is :",
    "options": [
      "paramagnetic and colourless",
      "diamagnetic and green",
      "diamagnetic and colourless",
      "paramagnetic and green"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "paramagnetic and green"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktia93a7",
    "question": "In the structure of the dichromate ion, there is a :",
    "options": [
      "linear symmetrical Cr-O-Cr bond.",
      "non-linear symmetrical Cr-O-Cr bond.",
      "linear unsymmetrical Cr-O-Cr bond.",
      "non-linear unsymmetrical Cr-O-Cr bond."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "non-linear symmetrical Cr-O-Cr bond."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn0xa2k",
    "question": "In the given chemical reaction, colors of the Fe<sup>2+</sup> and Fe<sup>3+</sup> ions, are respectively :<br/><br/>5Fe<sup>2+</sup> + MnO$$_4^ - $$ + 8H<sup>+</sup> $$\\to$$ Mn<sup>2+</sup> + 4H<sub>2</sub>O + 5Fe<sup>3+</sup>",
    "options": [
      "Yellow, Orange",
      "Yellow, Green",
      "Green, Orange",
      "Green, Yellow"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Green, Yellow"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gqc32g",
    "question": "<p>The dark purple colour of $$\\mathrm{KMnO}_{4}$$ disappears in the titration with oxalic acid in acidic medium. The overall change in the oxidation number of manganese in the reaction is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "5",
      "1",
      "7",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "5"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jldi23",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements.</p>\n<p>Statement I : Iron (III) catalyst, acidified $$\\mathrm{K}_{2} \\mathrm{Cr}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{7}$$ and neutral $$\\mathrm{KMnO}_{4}$$ have the ability to oxidise $$\\mathrm{I}^{-}$$ to $$\\mathrm{I}_{2}$$ independently.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Manganate ion is paramagnetic in nature and involves $$\\mathrm{p} \\pi-\\mathrm{p} \\pi$$ bonding.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jlflsr",
    "question": "<p>The total number of $$\\mathrm{Mn}=\\mathrm{O}$$ bonds in $$\\mathrm{Mn}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{7}$$ is __________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "5",
      "6",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "6"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kppnlu",
    "question": "<p>In neutral or alkaline solution, $$\\mathrm{MnO}_{4}^{-}$$ oxidises thiosulphate to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{S}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{7}^{2-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{S}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{8}^{2-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{SO}_{3}^{2-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{SO}_{4}^{2-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{SO}_{4}^{2-}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mcwkxm",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II, match the gas evolved during each reaction.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-fymr{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-fymr\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-fymr\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{4}\\right)_{2} \\mathrm{Cr}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{7} \\stackrel{\\Delta}{\\longrightarrow}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{H}_{2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{KMnO}_{4}+\\mathrm{HCl} \\rightarrow$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{N}_{2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Al}+\\mathrm{NaOH}+\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{O}_{2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{NaNO}_{3} \\stackrel{\\Delta}{\\longrightarrow}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Cl}_{2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose  the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{II})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{III})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{II})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{III})$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p79nx0",
    "question": "<p>In neutral or faintly alkaline medium, $$\\mathrm{KMnO}_{4}$$ being a powerful oxidant can oxidize, thiosulphate almost quantitatively, to sulphate. In this reaction overall change in oxidation state of manganese will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "5",
      "1",
      "0",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldo21hi2",
    "question": "<p>Which element is not present in Nessler's reagent?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Mercury",
      "Iodine",
      "Potassium",
      "Oxygen"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Oxygen"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpnrqsa",
    "question": "<p>When $$\\mathrm{Cu}^{2+}$$ ion is treated with $$\\mathrm{KI}$$, a white precipitate, $$\\mathrm{X}$$ appears in solution. The solution is titrated with sodium thiosulphate, the compound $$\\mathrm{Y}$$ is formed. $$\\mathrm{X}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Y}$$ respectively are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 362px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 148px\">\n<col style=\"width: 214px\">\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{X=CuI_2}$$</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Y=Na_2S_4O_6}$$</td>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n</table>",
      "<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 362px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 148px\">\n<col style=\"width: 214px\">\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{X=Cu_2I_2}$$</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Y=Na_2S_4O_6}$$</td>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n</table>",
      "<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 362px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 148px\">\n<col style=\"width: 214px\">\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{X=CuI_2}$$</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Y=Na_2S_2O_3}$$</td>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n</table>",
      "<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 362px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 148px\">\n<col style=\"width: 214px\">\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{X=Cu_2I_2}$$</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Y=Na_2S_4O_5}$$</td>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n</table>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 362px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 148px\">\n<col style=\"width: 214px\">\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{X=Cu_2I_2}$$</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Y=Na_2S_4O_6}$$</td>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n</table>"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqwh7u7",
    "question": "Formulae for Nessler's reagent is :",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{KHgI}_3$",
      "$\\mathrm{HgI}_2$",
      "$\\mathrm{KHg}_2 \\mathrm{I}_2$",
      "$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{HgI}_4$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{HgI}_4$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqx15cc",
    "question": "$\\mathrm{KMnO}_4$ oxidises $\\mathrm{I}^{-}$ in acidic and neutral/faintly alkaline solutions, respectively, to :",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{IO}_3^{-} ~\\&~ \\mathrm{IO}_3^{-}$",
      "$\\mathrm{I}_2 ~\\&~ \\mathrm{I}_2$",
      "$\\mathrm{I}_2 ~\\&~ \\mathrm{IO}_3^{-}$",
      "$\\mathrm{IO}_3^{-} ~\\&~ \\mathrm{I}_2$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{I}_2 ~\\&~ \\mathrm{IO}_3^{-}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr3yvmy",
    "question": "<p>During the qualitative analysis of $$\\mathrm{SO}_{3}^{2-}$$ using dilute $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}, \\mathrm{SO}_{2}$$ gas is evolved which turns $$\\mathrm{K}_{2} \\mathrm{Cr}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{7}$$ solution (acidified with dilute $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$$) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "blue",
      "black",
      "red",
      "green"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "green"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsdaytw",
    "question": "<p>An indicator 'X' is used for studying the effect of variation in concentration of iodide on the rate of reaction of iodide ion with $$\\mathrm{H_2O_2}$$ at room temp. The indicator 'X' forms blue coloured complex with compound 'A' present in the solution. The indicator 'X' and compound 'A' respectively are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Methyl orange and $$\\mathrm{H_2O_2}$$",
      "Methyl orange and iodine",
      "Starch and $$\\mathrm{H_2O_2}$$",
      "Starch and iodine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Starch and iodine"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu17vhf",
    "question": "<p>A chloride salt solution acidified with dil.HNO$$_3$$ gives a curdy white precipitate, [A], on addition of AgNO$$_3$$. [A] on treatment with NH$$_4$$OH gives a clear solution B. A and B are respectively :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{H[AgCl_3]~\\&~(NH_4)[Ag(OH)_2]}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{AgCl~\\&~[Ag(NH_3)_2]Cl}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{H[AgCl_3]~\\&~[Ag(NH_3)_2]Cl}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{AgCl~\\&~(NH_4)[Ag(OH)_2]}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{AgCl~\\&~[Ag(NH_3)_2]Cl}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyftq2e",
    "question": "<p>An ammoniacal metal salt solution gives a brilliant red precipitate on addition of dimethylglyoxime. The metal ion is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Co$$^{2+}$$",
      "Fe$$^{2+}$$",
      "Ni$$^{2+}$$",
      "Cu$$^{2+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Ni$$^{2+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyg9nee",
    "question": "<p>Prolonged heating is avoided during the preparation of ferrous ammonium sulphate to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "prevent hydrolysis",
      "prevent breaking",
      "prevent oxidation",
      "prevent reduction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "prevent oxidation"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh0385nl",
    "question": "<p>Which halogen is known to cause the reaction given below :</p>\n<p>$$2 \\mathrm{Cu}^{2+}+4 \\mathrm{X}^{-} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{Cu}_{2} \\mathrm{X}_{2}(\\mathrm{s})+\\mathrm{X}_{2}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "All halogens",
      "Only Iodine",
      "Only Bromine",
      "Only Chlorine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Only Iodine"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh31tr0z",
    "question": "<p>Element not present in Nessler's reagent is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "I",
      "$$\\mathrm{N}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Hg}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{N}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc62dmq",
    "question": "<p>$$\\mathrm{NaCl}$$ reacts with conc. $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{SO}_4$$ and $$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7$$ to give reddish fumes (B), which react with $$\\mathrm{NaOH}$$ to give yellow solution (C). (B) and (C) respectively are ;</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{CrO}_2 \\mathrm{Cl}_2, \\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{CrO}_4$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{CrO}_4, \\mathrm{CrO}_2 \\mathrm{Cl}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CrO}_2 \\mathrm{Cl}_2, \\mathrm{KHSO}_4$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CrO}_2 \\mathrm{Cl}_2, \\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{CrO}_2 \\mathrm{Cl}_2, \\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{CrO}_4$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd96guq",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct statements from the following</p>\n<p>A. $$\\mathrm{Mn}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7$$ is an oil at room temperature</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{V}_2 \\mathrm{O}_4$$ reacts with acid to give $$\\mathrm{VO}_2{ }^{2+}$$</p>\n<p>C. $$\\mathrm{CrO}$$ is a basic oxide</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{V}_2 \\mathrm{O}_5$$ does not react with acid</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B and D only",
      "A, B and C only",
      "A and C only",
      "B and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "A and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7jz29",
    "question": "<p>Identify correct statements from below:</p>\n<p>A. The chromate ion is square planar.</p>\n<p>B. Dichromates are generally prepared from chromates.</p>\n<p>C. The green manganate ion is diamagnetic.</p>\n<p>D. Dark green coloured $$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{MnO}_4$$ disproportionates in a neutral or acidic medium to give permanganate.</p>\n<p>E. With increasing oxidation number of transition metal, ionic character of the oxides decreases.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "B, D, E only",
      "A, B, C only",
      "A, D, E only",
      "B, C, D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "B, D, E only"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7lhct",
    "question": "<p>The metals that are employed in the battery industries are</p>\n<p>A. $$\\mathrm{Fe}$$</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{Mn}$$</p>\n<p>C. $$\\mathrm{Ni}$$</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{Cr}$$</p>\n<p>E. $$\\mathrm{Cd}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B, C, D and E",
      "A, B, C and D only",
      "B, D and E only",
      "B, C and E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "B, C and E only"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjw2ps",
    "question": "<p>$$\\mathrm{KMnO}_4$$ decomposes on heating at $$513 \\mathrm{~K}$$ to form $$\\mathrm{O}_2$$ along with</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{MnO}_4 ~\\& \\mathrm{~Mn}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{MnO}_2 ~\\& \\mathrm{~K}_2 \\mathrm{O}_2$$\n",
      "\n$$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{MnO}_4 ~\\& \\mathrm{~MnO}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Mn} ~\\& \\mathrm{~KO}_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "\n$$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{MnO}_4 ~\\& \\mathrm{~MnO}_2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfmsj1m",
    "question": "<p>The correct IUPAC name of $$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{MnO}_4$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "Potassium tetraoxidomanganate (VI)\n",
      "Dipotassium tetraoxidomanganate (VII)\n",
      "Potassium tetraoxopermanganate (VI)\n",
      "Potassium tetraoxidomanganese (VI)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Potassium tetraoxidomanganate (VI)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg7zp1o",
    "question": "<p>The orange colour of $$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7$$ and purple colour of $$\\mathrm{KMnO}_4$$ is due to\n</p>",
    "options": [
      "Charge transfer transition in both.\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{d} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{d}$$ transitions in $$\\mathrm{KMnO}_4$$ and charge transfer transitions in $$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7$$.\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{d} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{d}$$ transitions in both\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{d} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{d}$$ transitions in $$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7$$ and charge transfer transitions in $$\\mathrm{KMnO}_4$$."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Charge transfer transition in both.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s2836",
    "question": "<p>While preparing crystals of Mohr's salt, dil $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{SO}_4$$ is added to a mixture of ferrous sulphate and ammonium sulphate, before dissolving this mixture in water, dil $$\\mathrm{H_2SO_4}$$ is added here to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "prevent the hydrolysis of ferrous sulphate\n",
      "prevent the hydrolysis of ammonium sulphate\n",
      "increase the rate of formation of crystals\n",
      "make the medium strongly acidic"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "important-compounds-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "prevent the hydrolysis of ferrous sulphate\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "rMWuSvmK8txGwumX",
    "question": "Most common oxidation states of Ce (cerium) are :",
    "options": [
      "+3, +4",
      "+2, +3",
      "+2, +4",
      "+3, +5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "+3, +4"
  },
  {
    "id": "BzdJkiaPuWzEeo3R",
    "question": "The radius of La<sup>3+</sup> (Atomic number of La = 57) is 1.06 Å. Which one of the following given values will be\nclosest to the radius of Lu<sup>3+</sup> (Atomic number of Lu = 71) ?",
    "options": [
      "1.60 Å",
      "1.40 Å",
      "0.85 Å",
      "1.60 Å"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "0.85 Å"
  },
  {
    "id": "SOC7p4CYPq8SZE4f",
    "question": "Cerium (Z = 58) is an important member of the lanthanoids. Which of the following\nstatements about cerium is incorrect? ",
    "options": [
      "The common oxidation states of cerium are +3 and +4 ",
      "Cerium (IV) acts as an oxidizing agent",
      "The +4 oxidation state of cerium is not known in solutions",
      "The +3 oxidation state of cerium is more stable than the +4 oxidation state "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "The +4 oxidation state of cerium is not known in solutions"
  },
  {
    "id": "UNfFO5A13eyZ3FwU",
    "question": "The lanthanide contraction is responsible for the fact that :",
    "options": [
      "Zr and Y have about the same radius",
      "Zr and Nb have similar oxidation\nstate",
      "Zr and Hf have about the same radius",
      "Zr and Zn have the same oxidation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Zr and Hf have about the same radius"
  },
  {
    "id": "MQUhnNMPhu0Dt5XM",
    "question": "Which of the following factors may be regarded as the main cause of lanthanide\ncontraction?",
    "options": [
      "Poor shielding of one of 4f electron by another in the subshell",
      "Effective shielding of one of 4f electrons by another in the subshell ",
      "Poorer shielding of 5d electrons by 4f electrons",
      "Greater shielding of 5d electrons by 4f electrons"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Poorer shielding of 5d electrons by 4f electrons"
  },
  {
    "id": "xHdlQU9vRCF2N2Dt",
    "question": "Lanthanoid contraction is caused due to :",
    "options": [
      "the appreciable shielding on outer electrons by 4f electrons from the nuclear charge ",
      "the appreciable shielding on outer electrons by 5d electrons from the nuclear charge ",
      "the same effective nuclear charge from Ce to Lu ",
      "the imperfect shielding on outer electrons by 4f electrons from the nuclear charge "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "the imperfect shielding on outer electrons by 4f electrons from the nuclear charge "
  },
  {
    "id": "vkQWbGmfXb3czMGv",
    "question": "Identify the incorrect statement among the following :",
    "options": [
      "d-Block elements show irregular and erratic chemical properties among themselves ",
      "La and Lu have partially filled d orbitals and no other partially filled orbitals ",
      "The chemistry of various lanthanoids is very similar ",
      "4f and 5f orbitals are equally shielded "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "4f and 5f orbitals are equally shielded "
  },
  {
    "id": "f17ZKRxpl8yhjmJE",
    "question": "The actinoids exhibits more number of oxidation states in general than the lanthanoids. This is\nbecause :",
    "options": [
      "the 5f orbitals are more buried than the 4f orbitals ",
      "there is a similarity between 4f and 5f orbitals in their angular part of the wave function ",
      "the actinoids are more reactive than the lanthanoids",
      "the 5f orbitals extend further from the nucleus than the 4f orbitals "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "the 5f orbitals extend further from the nucleus than the 4f orbitals "
  },
  {
    "id": "qK2zwlzeX3zDXROa",
    "question": "Larger number of oxidation states are exhibited by the actinoids than those by the lanthanoids, the\nmain reason being :",
    "options": [
      "4f orbitals more diffused than the 5f orbitals ",
      "lesser energy difference between 5f and 6d than between 4f and 5d orbitals ",
      "more energy difference between 5f and 6d than between 4f and 5d orbitals",
      "more reactive nature of the actinoids than the lanthanoids"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "lesser energy difference between 5f and 6d than between 4f and 5d orbitals "
  },
  {
    "id": "hNmVvGkN1yQnU3ow",
    "question": "Knowing that the Chemistry of lanthanoids (Ln) is dominated by its +3 oxidation state, which of the\nfollowing statements is incorrect?",
    "options": [
      "Because of the large size of the Ln (III) ions the bonding in its compounds is predominantly ionic in\n character.",
      "The ionic sizes of Ln (III) decrease in general with increasing atomic number. ",
      "Ln (III) compounds are generally colourless",
      "Ln (III) hydroxides are mainly basic in character."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Ln (III) compounds are generally colourless"
  },
  {
    "id": "nkVm8W9hbavBMelJ",
    "question": "In context of the lanthanoids, which of the following statements is not correct?",
    "options": [
      "All the members exhibit +3 oxidation state ",
      "Because of similar properties the separation of lanthanoids is not easy. ",
      "Availability of 4f electrons results in the formation of compounds in +4 state for all the members\n of the series.",
      "There is a gradual decrease in the radii of the members with increasing atomic number in the\n series. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Availability of 4f electrons results in the formation of compounds in +4 state for all the members\n of the series."
  },
  {
    "id": "WgbWXKM8BPGc0MzE",
    "question": "The outer electron configuration of $$Gd$$ (Atomic No. $$64$$) is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$4{f^3}\\,5{d^5}\\,6{s^2}$$ ",
      "$$4{f^8}\\,5{d^0}\\,6{s^2}$$ ",
      "$$4{f^4}\\,5{d^4}\\,6{s^2}$$ ",
      "$$4{f^7}\\,5{d^1}\\,6{s^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "$$4{f^7}\\,5{d^1}\\,6{s^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "k0uJtq12n57MHda8pZnYI",
    "question": "The 71<sup>st</sup> electron of an element X with an atomic number of 71 enters into the orbital :",
    "options": [
      "4f",
      "6s",
      "6p",
      "5d"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "5d"
  },
  {
    "id": "aWVsQPjYWGgDCNuRY93rsa0w2w9jx0usadf",
    "question": "The highest possible oxidation states of uranium and plutonium, respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "4 and 6",
      "6 and 4",
      "7 and 6",
      "6 and 7"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "6 and 7"
  },
  {
    "id": "YZw5LxVmGvfP0XcP7o2Nb",
    "question": "The maximum number of possible oxidation\nstates of actinoides are shown by :",
    "options": [
      "nobelium (No) and lawrencium (Lr)",
      "actinium (Ac) and thorium (Th)",
      "neptunium (Np) and plutonium (Pu)",
      "berkelium (Bk) and californium (Cf)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "neptunium (Np) and plutonium (Pu)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1MZzz4wqtDUcxVNzr5Ztk",
    "question": "The correct order of atomic radii is :",
    "options": [
      "Ho &gt; N &gt; Eu &gt; Ce ",
      "Ce &gt; Eu &gt; Ho &gt; N ",
      "N &gt; Ce &gt; Eu &gt; Ho",
      "Eu &gt; Ce &gt; Ho &gt; N "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Eu &gt; Ce &gt; Ho &gt; N "
  },
  {
    "id": "hJceUi53qvfwOqjCcuZnk",
    "question": "The effect of lanthanoid contraction in the lanthanoid series of elements by and large means : ",
    "options": [
      "increase in atomic radii and decrease in ionic radii \n",
      "increase in both atomic and ionic radii\n",
      "decrease in both atomic and ionic radii ",
      "decrease in atomic radii and increase in ionic radii"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "decrease in both atomic and ionic radii "
  },
  {
    "id": "lIWVGnyLpdmSmh30Pa7k9k2k5dyq67i",
    "question": "The atomic radius of Ag is closed to :",
    "options": [
      "Au",
      "Cu",
      "Hg",
      "Ni"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Au"
  },
  {
    "id": "tjhpo7wTWUUy8ri0CGjgy2xukf7tp6os",
    "question": "The elements with atomic numbers 101 and 104\nbelong to, respectively :",
    "options": [
      "Group 6 and Actinoids",
      "Actinoids and Group 4",
      "Group 11 and Group 4",
      "Actinoids and Group 6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Actinoids and Group 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "EE7yHwfZ44ANu6MLUWjgy2xukfjernn9",
    "question": "The correct electronic configuration and spin-only<br/> magnetic moment (BM) of Gd<sup>3+</sup> (Z = 64),\nrespectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "[Xe]5f<sup>7</sup> and 8.9",
      "[Xe]4f<sup>7</sup> and 7.9",
      "[Xe]5f<sup>7</sup> and 7.9",
      "[Xe]4f<sup>7</sup> and 8.9"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "[Xe]4f<sup>7</sup> and 7.9"
  },
  {
    "id": "MrqfcjQFcUHNHBRLD5jgy2xukfjew7v5",
    "question": "In the sixth period, the orbitals that are filled are :",
    "options": [
      "6s, 5d, 5f, 6p",
      "6s, 4f, 5d, 6p",
      "6s, 6p, 6d, 6f",
      "6s, 5f, 6d, 6p"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "6s, 4f, 5d, 6p"
  },
  {
    "id": "hxibXXrIJqOcv64lxcjgy2xukftcqe4v",
    "question": "The lanthanoid that does NOT show +4 oxidation\nstate is :",
    "options": [
      "Tb",
      "Dy",
      "Ce",
      "Eu"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Eu"
  },
  {
    "id": "ccqOfVQo69dnf1hXLSjgy2xukg395sas",
    "question": "Mischmetal is an alloy consisting mainly of :",
    "options": [
      "lanthanoid and actinoid metals",
      "actinoid and transition metals",
      "lanthanoid metals",
      "actinoid metals"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "lanthanoid metals"
  },
  {
    "id": "kn7Boe9n5zzM1GWloO1kls8ub6s",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : CeO<sub>2</sub> can be used for oxidation of aldehydes and ketones.<br/><br/>Statement II : Aqueous solution of EuSO<sub>4</sub> is a strong reducing agent.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "j7TTVpuLtdcxOEc0UU1klud3myx",
    "question": "Which one of the following lanthanoids does not form MO<sub>2</sub>? [M is lanthanoid metal]",
    "options": [
      "Nd",
      "Dy",
      "Yb",
      "Pr"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Yb"
  },
  {
    "id": "InQgxujNCfLRXCd2q91kmht4ltc",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : The E<sup>o</sup> value for Ce<sup>4+</sup> / Ce<sup>3+</sup> is + 1.74 V.<br/><br/>Statement II : Ce is more stable in Ce<sup>4+</sup> state than Ce<sup>3+</sup> state.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but statement II is correct",
      "Both statement I and statement II are correct",
      "Both statement I and statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "VydGFYjRQaFrqKxMRP1kmhul9yp",
    "question": "Given below are two statement : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R :<br/><br/>Assertion A : Size of Bk<sup>3+</sup> ion is less than Np<sup>3+</sup> ion.<br/><br/>Reason R : The above is a consequence of the lanthanoid contraction.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both A and B are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "Both A and B are true but R is not the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "A is true but R is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "yyV2ZybXjY8yaSjjSW1kmiukl04",
    "question": "Arrange the following metal complex/compounds in the increasing order of spin only magnetic moment. Presume all the three, high spin system.<br/><br/>(Atomic numbers Ce = 58, Gd = 64 and Eu = 63)<br/><br/>(a) (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>[Ce(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>]<br/><br/>(b) Gd(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> and <br/><br/>(c) Eu(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>",
    "options": [
      "(a) &lt; (b) &lt; (c)",
      "(b) &lt; (a) &lt; (c)",
      "(a) &lt; (c) &lt; (b)",
      "(c) &lt; (a) &lt; (b)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "(a) &lt; (c) &lt; (b)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktiado5m",
    "question": "Which one of the following lanthanides exhibits +2 oxidation state with diamagnetic nature? (Given Z for Nd = 60, Yb = 70, La = 57, Ce = 58)",
    "options": [
      "Nd",
      "Yb",
      "La",
      "Ce"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Yb"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjuwuhj",
    "question": "The Eu<sup>2+</sup> ion is a strong reducing agent in spite of its ground state electronic configuration (outermost) : [Atomic number of Eu = 63]",
    "options": [
      "4f<sup>7</sup>6s<sup>2</sup>",
      "4f<sup>6</sup>",
      "4f<sup>7</sup>",
      "4f<sup>6</sup>6s<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "4f<sup>7</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56auy63",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the lanthanoids given below is the most stable in divalent form?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Ce (Atomic Number 58)",
      "Sm (Atomic number 62)",
      "Eu (Atomic Number 63)",
      "Yb (Atomic Number 70)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Eu (Atomic Number 63)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56xmd5o",
    "question": "The 'f' orbitals are half and completely filled, respectively in lanthanide ions :\n<p>[Given : Atomic no. Eu, 63; Sm, 62; Tm, 69; Tb, 65; Yb, 70; Dy, 66]</p>",
    "options": [
      "Eu<sup>2+</sup> and Tm<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Sm<sup>2+</sup> and Tm<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Tb<sup>4+</sup> and Yb<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Dy<sup>3+</sup> and Yb<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Tb<sup>4+</sup> and Yb<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58jk4d5",
    "question": "<p>The most common oxidation state of Lanthanoid elements is +3. Which of the following is likely to deviate easily from +3 oxidation state?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Ce (At. No. 58)",
      "La (At. No. 57)",
      "Lu (At. No. 71)",
      "Gd (At. No. 64)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Ce (At. No. 58)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5alz4ou",
    "question": "<p>Cerium (IV) has a noble gas configuration. Which of the following is correct statement about it?</p>",
    "options": [
      "It will not prefer to undergo redox reactions.",
      "It will prefer to gain electron and act as an oxidizing agent.",
      "It will prefer to give away an electron and behave as reducing agent.",
      "It acts as both, oxidizing and reducing agent."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "It will prefer to gain electron and act as an oxidizing agent."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwutc9l",
    "question": "<p>Which one amongst the following are good oxidizing agents?</p>\n<p>A. Sm$$^{2+}$$</p>\n<p>B. Ce$$^{2+}$$</p>\n<p>C. Ce$$^{4+}$$</p>\n<p>D. Tb$$^{4+}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "C and D only",
      "A and B only",
      "D only",
      "C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "C and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq4hhq5",
    "question": "<p>The pair of lanthanides in which both elements have high third - ionization energy is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Dy, Gd",
      "Lu, Yb",
      "Eu, Yb",
      "Eu, Gd"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Eu, Yb"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrkkssk",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statement: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A: $$5 \\mathrm{f}$$ electrons can participate in bonding to a far greater extent than $$4 \\mathrm{f}$$ electrons</p>\n<p>Reason R: $$5 \\mathrm{f}$$ orbitals are not as buried as $$4 \\mathrm{f}$$ orbitals</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh29chdj",
    "question": "<p>Strong reducing and oxidizing agents among the following, respectively, are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Ce}^{4+}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Eu}^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Eu}^{2+}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Ce}^{4+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ce}^{4+}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Tb}^{4+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ce}^{3+}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Ce}^{4+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Eu}^{2+}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Ce}^{4+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc68b7k",
    "question": "<p>The electronic configuration for Neodymium is:</p>\n<p>[Atomic Number for Neodymium 60]</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$[\\mathrm{Xe}] 4 \\mathrm{f}^4 6 \\mathrm{~s}^2$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{Xe}] 5 \\mathrm{f}^4 7 \\mathrm{~s}^2$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{Xe}] 4 \\mathrm{f}^6 6 \\mathrm{~s}^2$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{Xe}] 4 \\mathrm{f}^1 5 \\mathrm{~d}^1 6 \\mathrm{~s}^2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "$$[\\mathrm{Xe}] 4 \\mathrm{f}^4 6 \\mathrm{~s}^2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscrt1vb",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : In the Lanthanoids, the formation $$\\mathrm{Ce}^{+4}$$ is favoured by its noble gas configuration.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : $$\\mathrm{Ce}^{+4}$$ is a strong oxidant reverting to the common +3 state.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfmj26w",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following acts as a strong reducing agent? (Atomic number: $$\\mathrm{Ce}=58, \\mathrm{Eu}=63, \\mathrm{Gd}=64, \\mathrm{Lu}=71$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Eu}^{2+}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Gd}^{3+}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Lu}^{3+}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ce}^{4+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Eu}^{2+}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgyc3vg",
    "question": "<p>Diamagnetic Lanthanoid ions are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{La}^{3+} \\& \\mathrm{~Ce}^{4+}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Nd}^{3+} \\& \\mathrm{~Ce}^{4+}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Lu}^{3+} \\& \\mathrm{~Eu}^{3+}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Nd}^{3+} \\& \\mathrm{~Eu}^{3+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{La}^{3+} \\& \\mathrm{~Ce}^{4+}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwda65",
    "question": "<p>The electronic configuration of Einsteinium is :</p>\n<p>(Given atomic number of Einsteinium $$=99$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$[\\mathrm{Rn}] 5 \\mathrm{f}^{13} 6 \\mathrm{~d}^{\\circ} 7 \\mathrm{~s}^2$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{Rn}] 5 \\mathrm{f}^{12} 6 \\mathrm{~d}^{\\circ} 7 \\mathrm{~s}^2$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{Rn}] 5 \\mathrm{f}^{11} 6 \\mathrm{~d}^{\\circ} 7 \\mathrm{~s}^2$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{Rn}] 5 \\mathrm{f}^{10} 6 \\mathrm{~d}^{\\circ} 7 \\mathrm{~s}^2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "$$[\\mathrm{Rn}] 5 \\mathrm{f}^{11} 6 \\mathrm{~d}^{\\circ} 7 \\mathrm{~s}^2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc583a5",
    "question": "<p>The number of element from the following that do not belong to lanthanoids is $$\\mathrm{Eu}, \\mathrm{Cm}, \\mathrm{Er}, \\mathrm{Tb}, \\mathrm{Yb}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Lu}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "1",
      "4",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "inner-transition-elements-(lanthanoids-and-actinoids)",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "c9CfP11DD59HCuJp",
    "question": "Which of the following ions has the maximum magnetic moment?",
    "options": [
      "Mn<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Fe<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Ti<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Cr<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Mn<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "5JCcajI2355RhPMV",
    "question": "For making good quality mirrors, plates of float glass are used. These are obtained by floating molten glass\nover a liquid metal which does not solidify before glass. The metal used can be :",
    "options": [
      "tin",
      "sodium",
      "magnesium",
      "mercury"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "mercury"
  },
  {
    "id": "hGEtNUeb5K39R755",
    "question": "The number of d-electrons retained in Fe<sup>2+</sup> (At no of Fe = 26) ion is :",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "5",
      "6",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "6"
  },
  {
    "id": "D020DFkDCUuyNIUy",
    "question": "A red solid is insolvable in water. However it becomes soluble if some $$K{\\rm I}$$ is added to water. Heating the red solid in a test tube results in liberation of some violet colored fumes and droplets of a metal appear on the cooler parts of the test tube. The red solid is :",
    "options": [
      "$$Hg{{\\rm I}_2}$$ ",
      "$$HgO$$ ",
      "$$P{b_3}{O_4}$$ ",
      "$${\\left( {N{H_4}} \\right)_2}C{r_2}{O_7}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$Hg{{\\rm I}_2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "5HjCzx5CqeurAtFp",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is correct?",
    "options": [
      "From a mixed precipitate of AgCl and AgI, ammonia solution dissolves only AgCl",
      "Ferric ions give a deep green precipitate on adding potassium ferrocyanide solution",
      "On boiling a solution having K<sup>+</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup> and HCO<sub>3</sub> ions we get a precipitate of K<sub>2</sub>Ca(CO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>.",
      "Manganese salts give a violet borax bead test in the reducing flame"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "From a mixed precipitate of AgCl and AgI, ammonia solution dissolves only AgCl"
  },
  {
    "id": "VSob9iz7js68bxWY",
    "question": "The atomic numbers of vanadium (V), Chromium (Cr), manganese (Mn) and iron (Fe) are respectively 23, 24, 25 and 26. Which one of these may be expected to have the highest second ionization enthalpy?",
    "options": [
      "Cr",
      "Mn",
      "Fe",
      "V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Cr"
  },
  {
    "id": "ma733DAZrAFJUpsP",
    "question": "Of the following outer electronic configurations of atoms, the highest oxidation state is achieved by which one of them?",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {n - 1} \\right){d^3}n{s^2}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {n - 1} \\right){d^5}n{s^1}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {n - 1} \\right){d^8}n{s^2}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {n - 1} \\right){d^5}n{s^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {n - 1} \\right){d^5}n{s^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ZG09M74QnL8XaH55",
    "question": "On heating mixture of $$C{u_2}O$$ and $$C{u_2}S$$ will give :",
    "options": [
      "$$C{u_2}S{O_3}$$ ",
      "$$CuO + CuS$$ ",
      "$$Cu + S{O_3}$$",
      "$$Cu + S{O_2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$Cu + S{O_2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "efXG3Dh3pwlmlKzq",
    "question": "Calomel $$\\left( {H{g_2}C{l_2}} \\right)$$ on reaction with ammonium hydroxide gives :",
    "options": [
      "$$HgO$$ ",
      "$$H{g_2}O$$ ",
      "$$N{H_2} - Hg - Hg - Cl$$ ",
      "$$HgN{H_2}Cl$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$HgN{H_2}Cl$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "WNl4yt1lk4CGgbeG",
    "question": "The “spin-only” magnetic moment [in units of Bohr magneton, (µ<sub>B</sub>)]  of Ni<sup>2+</sup> in aqueous solution would\nbe : (Atomic number of Ni = 28) ",
    "options": [
      "2.84",
      "4.90",
      "0 ",
      "1.73"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "2.84"
  },
  {
    "id": "n6iax5V3UOLwVYDX",
    "question": "A metal, $$M$$ forms chlorides in its $$+2$$ and $$+4$$ oxidation states. Which of the following statements about these chlorides is correct?",
    "options": [
      "$$MC{l_2}$$  is more ionic than $$MC{l_4}$$",
      "$$MC{l_2}$$ is more easily hydrolysed than $$MC{l_4}$$ ",
      "$$MC{l_2}$$ is more volatile than $$MC{l_4}$$",
      "$$MC{l_2}$$ is  more soluble in anhydrous ethanol than $$MC{l_4}$$."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$MC{l_2}$$  is more ionic than $$MC{l_4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ILFYxYbfngSaUPPX",
    "question": "In context with the transition elements, which of the following statements is incorrect ? ",
    "options": [
      "In addition to the normal oxidation states, the zero oxidation state is also shown by these elements in complexes.",
      "In the highest oxidation states, the transition metal show basic character and form cationic complexes.",
      "In the highest oxidation states of the first five transition elements (Sc to Mn), all the 4s and 3d electrons are used for bonding",
      "Once the d<sup>5</sup> configuration is exceeded, the tendency to involve all the 3d electrons in bonding\n decreases. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "In the highest oxidation states, the transition metal show basic character and form cationic complexes."
  },
  {
    "id": "1Veu1FbftW8jrnlq",
    "question": "Iron exhibits + 2 and +3 oxidation states. Which of the following statements about iron is incorrect?",
    "options": [
      "Ferrous oxide is more basic in nature than the ferric oxide",
      "Ferrous compounds are relatively more ionic than the corresponding ferric compounds",
      "Ferrous compounds are less volatile than the corresponding ferric compounds",
      "Ferrous compounds are more easily hydrolysed than the corresponding ferric compounds."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Ferrous compounds are more easily hydrolysed than the corresponding ferric compounds."
  },
  {
    "id": "ZEn7ZcaWUGRdcXzd",
    "question": "Which of the following arrangements does not represent the correct order of the property stated against it? ",
    "options": [
      "Ni<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Co<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Fe<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Mn<sup>2+</sup> : ionic size ",
      "Co<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Fe<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Cr<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Sc<sup>3+</sup> : stability in aqueous solution ",
      "Sc &lt; Ti &lt; Cr &lt; Mn : number of oxidation states",
      "V<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Cr<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Mn<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Fe<sup>2+</sup> : paramagnetic behaviour"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "V<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Cr<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Mn<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Fe<sup>2+</sup> : paramagnetic behaviour"
  },
  {
    "id": "uw6OJOAmba4vPAyR",
    "question": "Four successive members of the first row transition elements are listed below with atomic numbers. Which\none of them is expected to have the highest $$E_{{M^{3 + }}/{M^{2 + }}}^0$$  value? ",
    "options": [
      "Mn (Z = 25)",
      "Fe (Z = 26) ",
      "Co (Z = 27) ",
      "Cr (Z = 24) "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Co (Z = 27) "
  },
  {
    "id": "GtFJfnzqReh9jFJu",
    "question": "Which series of reactions correctly represents chemical relations related to iron and its compound?",
    "options": [
      "Fe $$\\buildrel {dil.\\,{H_2}S{O_4}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ FeSO<sub>4</sub> $$\\buildrel {{H_2}S{O_4},{O_2}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ Fe<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub> $$\\buildrel {heat} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ Fe",
      "Fe $$\\buildrel {{O_2} \\, {, heat}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ FeO $$\\buildrel {dil.\\,{H_2}S{O_4}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ FeSO<sub>4</sub> $$\\buildrel {heat} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ Fe ",
      "Fe $$\\buildrel {{Cl_2} \\, {, heat}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ FeCl<sub>3</sub> $$\\buildrel {heat, \\, air} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ FeCl<sub>2</sub> $$\\buildrel {Zn} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ Fe  ",
      "Fe $$\\buildrel {{O_2},\\,heat} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> $$\\buildrel {CO,\\,{{600}^o}C} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ FeO $$\\buildrel {CO,\\,{{700}^o}C} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ Fe"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Fe $$\\buildrel {{O_2},\\,heat} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> $$\\buildrel {CO,\\,{{600}^o}C} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ FeO $$\\buildrel {CO,\\,{{700}^o}C} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ Fe"
  },
  {
    "id": "xkWSCELBONRsag68",
    "question": "Match the catalysts to the correct processes :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border:none;border-color:#999;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:0px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#999;color:#444;background-color:#F7FDFA;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:0px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#999;color:#fff;background-color:#26ADE4;}\n.tg .tg-p7ly{font-weight:bold;font-size:20px;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-4kyz{font-size:20px;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-p7ly\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-p7ly\">Catalyst</th>\n<th class=\"tg-p7ly\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-p7ly\">Process</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">TiCl<sub>3</sub></td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">(i)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">Wacker process</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">PdCl<sub>2</sub></td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">(ii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">Ziegler - Natta<br/>polymerization</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">CuCl<sub>2</sub></td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">(iii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">Contact process</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">V<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">(iv)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">Deacon's process</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table> ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( A \\right) - \\left( {ii} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( B \\right) - \\left( {iii} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( C \\right) - \\left( {iv} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( D \\right) - \\left( i \\right)$$ ",
      "$$\\left( A \\right) - \\left( {iii} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( B \\right) - \\left( i \\right),\\,\\,\\left( C \\right) - \\left( {ii} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( D \\right) - \\left( {iv} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$\\left( A \\right) - \\left( {iii} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( B \\right) - \\left( {ii} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( C \\right) - \\left( {iv} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( D \\right) - \\left( i \\right)$$ ",
      "$$\\left( A \\right) - \\left( {ii} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( B \\right) - \\left( i \\right),\\,\\,\\left( C \\right) - \\left( {iv} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( D \\right) - \\left( {iii} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\left( A \\right) - \\left( {ii} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( B \\right) - \\left( i \\right),\\,\\,\\left( C \\right) - \\left( {iv} \\right),\\,\\,\\left( D \\right) - \\left( {iii} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "0bI33Q8gRyRyHAmOSTCH3",
    "question": "The transition metal ions responsible for color in ruby and emerald are,\nrespectively :",
    "options": [
      "Cr<sup>3+</sup> &nbsp;&nbsp;and&nbsp;&nbsp; Co<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Co<sup>3+</sup> &nbsp;&nbsp; and &nbsp;&nbsp; Cr<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Co<sup>3+</sup> &nbsp;&nbsp; and &nbsp;&nbsp; Co<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Cr<sup>3+</sup> &nbsp;&nbsp; and &nbsp;&nbsp; Cr<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Cr<sup>3+</sup> &nbsp;&nbsp; and &nbsp;&nbsp; Cr<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "7GAS0vqEQNgjTXsvn3fQP",
    "question": "Which one of the following species is stable in aqueous solution?",
    "options": [
      "Cr<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Cu<sup>+</sup>",
      "MnO$$_4^{3 - }$$",
      "MnO$$_4^{2 - }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "MnO$$_4^{2 - }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "qyoOw2xejgRXvsZR",
    "question": "Which of the following compounds is metallic and ferromagnetic ?",
    "options": [
      "CrO<sub>2</sub>",
      "VO<sub>2</sub>",
      "MnO<sub>2</sub>",
      "TiO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "CrO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "dcWMvOofLYfatKDV",
    "question": "The reaction of zinc with dilute and concentrated nitric acid, respectively, produces :",
    "options": [
      "NO<sub>2</sub> and NO",
      "NO and N<sub>2</sub>O",
      "NO<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>O",
      "N<sub>2</sub>O and NO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "N<sub>2</sub>O and NO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "NkZEuTNQSoNDA0AV85XZv",
    "question": "The pair of compounds having metals in their highest oxidation state is :",
    "options": [
      "MnO<sub>2</sub> and CrO<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> ",
      "[NiCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup>  and  [CoCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup> ",
      "[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3$$-$$</sup>  and [Cu(CN)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup>",
      "[FeCl<sub>4</sub>]<sup>$$-$$</sup> and Co<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "MnO<sub>2</sub> and CrO<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "gaA0LD1rUUEOITt1JGxwE",
    "question": "Which of the following ions does not liberate hydrogen gas on reaction with dilute acids ?",
    "options": [
      "Ti<sup>2+</sup> ",
      "V<sup>2+</sup> ",
      "Cr<sup>2+</sup> ",
      "Mn<sup>2+</sup> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Mn<sup>2+</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "QNm9gElfLK0sQuob",
    "question": "In the following reactions, ZnO is respectively acting as a/an :<br/><br/>\n(a) ZnO + Na<sub>2</sub>O $$\\to$$ Na<sub>2</sub>ZnO<sub>2</sub><br/><br/>\n(b) ZnO + CO<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ ZnCO<sub>3</sub>",
    "options": [
      "base and base ",
      "acid and acid ",
      "acid and base",
      "base and acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "acid and base"
  },
  {
    "id": "29z4WLBVmkEWrQH1s65uX",
    "question": "The <b>incorrect</b> statement is : ",
    "options": [
      "Cu<sup>2+</sup> salts give red coloured borax bead test in reducing flame. ",
      "Cu2<sup>+</sup> and Ni<sup>2+</sup> ions give black precipitate with H<sub>2</sub>S in presence of HCl solution. ",
      "Ferric ion gives blood red color with potasium thiocyanate.",
      "Cu<sup>2+</sup> ion gives chocolate coloured preciitate with potassium ferrocyanide solution. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Cu2<sup>+</sup> and Ni<sup>2+</sup> ions give black precipitate with H<sub>2</sub>S in presence of HCl solution. "
  },
  {
    "id": "zgBfbn87LAqAVVrkjFhdE",
    "question": "When XO<sub>2</sub> is fused with an alkali metal hydroxide in presence of an oxidizing agent such as KNO<sub>3</sub> ;  a dark green product is formed which disproportioates in acidic solution  to afforda dark purple solution. X is : ",
    "options": [
      "Ti",
      "V",
      "Cr",
      "Mn"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Mn"
  },
  {
    "id": "72wdcRU913iyDz3goz3rsa0w2w9jx84mp1q",
    "question": "The pair that has similar atomic radii is :",
    "options": [
      "Mo and W",
      "Mn and Fe",
      "Ti and Hf",
      "Sc and Ni"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Mo and W"
  },
  {
    "id": "UnC644xgIaYoAbpIMK3rsa0w2w9jx0wy2s5",
    "question": "The correct order of the first ionization enthalpies is :",
    "options": [
      "Ti &lt; Mn &lt; Zn &lt; Ni",
      "Zn &lt; Ni &lt; Mn &lt; Ti",
      "Mn &lt; Ti &lt; Zn &lt; Ni",
      "Ti &lt; Mn &lt; Ni &lt; Zn"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Ti &lt; Mn &lt; Ni &lt; Zn"
  },
  {
    "id": "jAjxHUi8dGw6c6ergM3rsa0w2w9jx0vnj7e",
    "question": "The INCORRECT statement is :",
    "options": [
      "the color of [CoCl(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> is violet as it absorbs the yellow light.",
      "the gemstone, ruby, has Cr<sup>3+</sup> ions occupying the octahedral sites of beryl.",
      "the spin-only magnetic moment of [Ni(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> is 2.83 BM.",
      "the spin-only magnetic moments of [Fe(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> and [Cr(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2+</sup> are nearly similar. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "the gemstone, ruby, has Cr<sup>3+</sup> ions occupying the octahedral sites of beryl."
  },
  {
    "id": "zrVLr8ceUTyQreQyErrNL",
    "question": "The statement that is INCORRECT about the\ninterstitial compounds is :",
    "options": [
      "They are chemically reactive",
      "They have metallic conductivity",
      "They have high melting points",
      "They are very hard"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "They are chemically reactive"
  },
  {
    "id": "46UxNzW3L3kHE8SIbHDFz",
    "question": "The element that usually does NOT show variable oxidation states is : ",
    "options": [
      "V",
      "Cu",
      "Sc",
      "ti"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Sc"
  },
  {
    "id": "qQs8g3YGZrpLu4Wo2eSO2",
    "question": "The transition element that has lowest enthalpy of atomisation, is : ",
    "options": [
      "Fe",
      "Cu",
      "V",
      "Zn"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Cu"
  },
  {
    "id": "cLlbls1u2VuJCmxa8J3rsa0w2w9jwv595b6",
    "question": "Consider the hydrated ions of Ti<sup>2+</sup>, V<sup>2+</sup>, Ti<sup>3+</sup>, and Sc<sup>3+</sup>. The correct order of their spin-only magnetic\nmoments is : ",
    "options": [
      "Sc<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Ti<sup>3+</sup> &lt; V<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Ti<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Sc<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Ti<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Ti<sup>2+</sup> &lt; V<sup>2+</sup> ",
      "Ti<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Ti<sup>2+</sup> &lt;  Sc<sup>3+</sup> &lt; V<sup>2+</sup> ",
      "V<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Ti<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Ti<sup>3+</sup> &lt;  Sc<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Sc<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Ti<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Ti<sup>2+</sup> &lt; V<sup>2+</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "IGNpQdkaQP2HUPSpUMjgy2xukfc7rdzf",
    "question": "The incorrect statement(s) among (a) - (c) is\n(are)\n<br/><br/>(a) W(VI) is more stable than Cr(VI).\n<br/><br>(b) In the presence of HCl, permanganate\ntitrations provide satisfactory results.\n<br/><br>(c) Some lanthanoid oxides can be used as\nphosphors.</br></br>",
    "options": [
      "(a) and (b) only",
      "(a) only",
      "(b) only",
      "(b) and (c) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "(b) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "rf72m9NwGZF3e0at8kjgy2xukfupzwsz",
    "question": "The set that contains atomic numbers of only\ntransition elements, is :",
    "options": [
      "21, 32, 53, 64",
      "9, 17, 34, 38",
      "37, 42, 50, 64",
      "21, 25, 42, 72"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "21, 25, 42, 72"
  },
  {
    "id": "XGDo6LHy3Q7xpRmLOR1klrf0f1y",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement I :</b> Colourless cupric metaborate is reduced to cuprous metaborate in a luminous\nflame.<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement II :</b> Cuprous metaborate is obtained by heating boric anhydride and copper\nsulphate in a non-luminous flame.<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options\ngiven below.",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
  },
  {
    "id": "X2VwEKJZGNlP1mQDw51klruko33",
    "question": "What is the correct order of the following elements with respect to their density?",
    "options": [
      "Cr &lt; Zn &lt; Co &lt; Cu &lt; Fe",
      "Cr &lt; Fe &lt; Co &lt; Cu &lt; Zn",
      "Zn &lt; Cr &lt; Fe &lt; Co &lt; Cu",
      "Zn &lt; Cu &lt; Co &lt; Fe &lt; Cr"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Zn &lt; Cr &lt; Fe &lt; Co &lt; Cu"
  },
  {
    "id": "7P1TduXRH2wlYGxgqA1klsbh33h",
    "question": "In which of the following pairs, the outer most electronic configuration will be the same?",
    "options": [
      "Cr<sup>+</sup> and Mn<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Ni<sup>2+</sup> and Cu<sup>+</sup>",
      "V<sup>2+</sup> and Cr<sup>+</sup>",
      "Fe<sup>2+</sup> and Co<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Cr<sup>+</sup> and Mn<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "V7tz4oL9700z3b4sjr1kmj6iv65",
    "question": "What is the spin-only magnetic moment value (BM) of a divalent metal ion with atomic number 25, in it's aqueous solution?",
    "options": [
      "zero",
      "5.26",
      "5.0",
      "5.92"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "5.92"
  },
  {
    "id": "m4Vp6gla5yF6tpFZWY1kmkj8wn3",
    "question": "The common positive oxidation states for an element with atomic number 24, are :",
    "options": [
      "+1 and +3",
      "+2 to +6",
      "+1 to +6",
      "+1 and +3 to +6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "+2 to +6"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt55gkz",
    "question": "The set having ions which are coloured and paramagnetic both is :",
    "options": [
      "Cu<sup>2+</sup>, Cr<sup>3+</sup>, Sc<sup>+</sup>",
      "Cu<sup>2+</sup>, Zn<sup>2+</sup>, Mn<sup>4+</sup>",
      "Sc<sup>3+</sup>, V<sup>5+</sup>, Ti<sup>4+</sup>",
      "Ni<sup>2+</sup>, Mn<sup>7+</sup>, Hg<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Cu<sup>2+</sup>, Cr<sup>3+</sup>, Sc<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krx64sfv",
    "question": "The spin only magnetic moments (in BM) for free Ti<sup>3+</sup>, V<sup>2+</sup> and Sc<sup>3+</sup> ions respectively are :<br/><br/>(At.No. Sc : 21, Ti : 22, V : 23)",
    "options": [
      "3.87, 1.73, 0",
      "1.73, 3.87, 0",
      "1.73, 0, 3.87",
      "0, 3.87, 1.73"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "1.73, 3.87, 0"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktb3tx4q",
    "question": "Which one of the following when dissolved in water gives coloured solution in nitrogen atmosphere?",
    "options": [
      "CuCl<sub>2</sub>",
      "AgCl",
      "ZnCl<sub>2</sub>",
      "Cu<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "CuCl<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktecd6r2",
    "question": "The nature of oxides V<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and CrO is indexed as 'X' and 'Y' type respectively. The correct set of X and Y is :",
    "options": [
      "<table>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <td>X = basic</td>\n    <td></td>\n    <td>Y = amphoteric</td>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n</table>",
      "<table>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <td>X = amphoteric</td>\n    <td></td>\n    <td>Y = basic</td>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n</table>",
      "<table>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <td>X = acidic</td>\n    <td></td>\n    <td>Y = acidic</td>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n</table>",
      "<table>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <td>X = basic</td>\n    <td></td>\n    <td>Y = basic</td>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n</table>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "<table>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <td>X = basic</td>\n    <td></td>\n    <td>Y = basic</td>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n</table>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn1sujz",
    "question": "Identify the element for which electronic configuration in +3 oxidation state is [Ar]3d<sup>5</sup> :",
    "options": [
      "Ru",
      "Mn",
      "Co",
      "Fe"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Fe"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l548o996",
    "question": "<p>The electronic configuration of Pt (atomic number 78)  is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "[Xe] 4f<sup>14</sup> 5d<sup>9</sup> 6s<sup>1</sup>",
      "[Kr] 4f<sup>14</sup> 5d<sup>10</sup>",
      "[Xe] 4f<sup>14</sup> 5d<sup>10</sup>",
      "[Xe] 4f<sup>14</sup> 5d<sup>8</sup> 6s<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "[Xe] 4f<sup>14</sup> 5d<sup>9</sup> 6s<sup>1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59qzy9a",
    "question": "<p>The metal ion (in gaseous state) with lowest spin-only magnetic moment value is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "V<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Ni<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Cr<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Fe<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Ni<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5alzs8s",
    "question": "<p>Among the following, which is the strongest oxidizing agent?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Mn<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Fe<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Ti<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Cr<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Mn<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bd4516",
    "question": "<p>Metals generally melt at very high temperature. Amongst the following, the metal with the highest melting point will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Hg",
      "Ag",
      "Ga",
      "Cs"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Ag"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mcxhni",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following has least tendency to liberate $$\\mathrm{H}_{2}$$ from mineral acids?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Cu",
      "Mn",
      "Ni",
      "Zn"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Cu"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p73eob",
    "question": "<p>The reaction of zinc with excess of aqueous alkali, evolves hydrogen gas and gives :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Zn}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{ZnO}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Zn}(\\mathrm{OH})_{4}\\right]^{2-}$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{ZnO}_{2}\\right]^{2-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{Zn}(\\mathrm{OH})_{4}\\right]^{2-}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p78dnl",
    "question": "<p>In following pairs, the one in which both transition metal ions are colourless is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Sc}^{3+}, \\mathrm{Zn}^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ti}^{4+}, \\mathrm{Cu}^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{V}^{2+}, \\mathrm{Ti}^{3+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Zn}^{2+}, \\mathrm{Mn}^{2+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Sc}^{3+}, \\mathrm{Zn}^{2+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rju2l8",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following $$3\\mathrm{d}$$-metal ion will give the lowest enthalpy of hydration $$\\left(\\Delta_{\\text {hyd }} \\mathrm{H}\\right)$$ when dissolved in water ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Cr}^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\operatorname{Mn}^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Fe}^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Co}^{2+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\operatorname{Mn}^{2+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldo2crr0",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : $$\\mathrm{Cu^{2+}}$$ in water is more stable than $$\\mathrm{Cu^{+}}$$.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Enthalpy of hydration for $$\\mathrm{Cu^{2+}}$$ is much less than that of $$\\mathrm{Cu^{+}}$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldoiic07",
    "question": "<p>Highest oxidation state of Mn is exhibited in $$\\mathrm{Mn_2O_7}$$. The correct statements about $$\\mathrm{Mn_2O_7}$$ are</p>\n<p>(A) Mn is tetrahedrally surrounded by oxygen atoms.</p>\n<p>(B) Mn is octahedrally surrounded by oxygen atoms.</p>\n<p>(C) Contains Mn-O-Mn bridge.</p>\n<p>(D) Contains Mn-Mn bond.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and C only",
      "A and D only",
      "B and C only",
      "B and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "A and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpo9hzf",
    "question": "<p>$$\\mathrm{Nd^{2+}}$$ = __________</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{4f^4 6s^2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{4f^3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{4f^4}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{4f^2 6s^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{4f^4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpoc2dx",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of basicity of oxides of vanadium is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{V_2O_3 > V_2O_5 > V_2O_4}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{V_2O_3 > V_2O_4 > V_2O_5}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{V_2O_5 > V_2O_4 > V_2O_3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{V_2O_4 > V_2O_3 > V_2O_5}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{V_2O_3 > V_2O_4 > V_2O_5}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsc4z1h",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Nickel is being used as the catalyst for producing syn gas and edible fats.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Silicon forms both electron rich and electron deficient hydrides.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect",
      "Both the statements I and II are correct",
      "Both the statements I and II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsckotv",
    "question": "<p>The set of correct statements is :</p>\n<p>(i) Manganese exhibits +7 oxidation state in its oxide.</p>\n<p>(ii) Ruthenium and Osmium exhibit +8 oxidation in their oxides.</p>\n<p>(iii) Sc shows +4 oxidation state which is oxidizing in nature.</p>\n<p>(iv) Cr shows oxidising nature in +6 oxidation state.</p>",
    "options": [
      "(ii), (iii) and (iv)",
      "(ii) and (iii)",
      "(i) and (iii)",
      "(i), (ii) and (iv)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "(i), (ii) and (iv)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgygcvay",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following statements are correct?</p>\n<p>(A) The M$$^{3+}$$/M$$^{2+}$$ reduction potential for iron is greater than manganese.</p>\n<p>(B) The higher oxidation states of first row d-block elements get stabilized by oxide ion.</p>\n<p>(C) Aqueous solution of Cr$$^{2+}$$ can liberate hydrogen from dilute acid.</p>\n<p>(D) Magnetic moment of V$$^{2+}$$ is observed between 4.4 - 5.2 BM.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(B), (C) only",
      "(A), (B) only",
      "(A), (B), (D) only",
      "(C), (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "(B), (C) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh039s6e",
    "question": "<p>In chromyl chloride, the number of d-electrons present on chromium is same as in<br/><br/> (Given at no. of $$\\mathrm{Ti}: 22, \\mathrm{~V}: 23, \\mathrm{Cr}: 24, \\mathrm{Mn}: 25, \\mathrm{Fe}: 26$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "Mn (VII)",
      "Ti (III)",
      "Fe (III)",
      "V (IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Mn (VII)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh324jwf",
    "question": "<p> Given below are two statements: one is labelled as \"Assertion A\" and the other is labelled as \"Reason R\"</p>\n<p>Assertion A : In the complex $$\\mathrm{Ni}(\\mathrm{CO})_{4}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Fe}(\\mathrm{CO})_{5}$$, the metals have zero oxidation state.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Low oxidation states are found when a complex has ligands capable of $$\\pi$$-donor character in addition to the $\\sigma$-bonding.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "A is correct but R is not correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh327e1j",
    "question": "<p>During the reaction of permanganate with thiosulphate, the change in oxidation of manganese occurs by value of 3. Identify which of the below medium will favour the reaction.</p>",
    "options": [
      "aqueous neutral",
      "both aqueous acidic and faintly alkaline",
      "both aqueous acidic and neutral",
      "aqueous acidic"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "aqueous neutral"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaorn4w",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as <b>Assertion (A)</b> and the other is labelled as <b>Reason (R)</b>.<br/><br/>\n<b>Assertion (A)</b> : In aqueous solutions $\\mathrm{Cr}^{2+}$ is reducing while $\\mathrm{Mn}^{3+}$ is oxidising in nature.<br/><br/>\n<b>Reason (R)</b> :  Extra stability to half filled electronic configuration is observed than incompletely filled electronic configuration.\n<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc514nf",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following electronic configuration would be associated with the highest magnetic moment?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$[\\mathrm{Ar}] 3 \\mathrm{~d}^7$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{Ar}] 3 \\mathrm{~d}^8$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{Ar}] 3 \\mathrm{~d}^3$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{Ar}] 3 \\mathrm{~d}^6$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$[\\mathrm{Ar}] 3 \\mathrm{~d}^6$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscruebh",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct option having all the elements with $$\\mathrm{d}^{10}$$ electronic configuration from the following :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${ }^{46} \\mathrm{Pd},{ }^{28} \\mathrm{Ni},{ }^{26} \\mathrm{Fe},{ }^{24} \\mathrm{Cr}$$\n",
      "$${ }^{29} \\mathrm{Cu},{ }^{30} \\mathrm{Zn},{ }^{48} \\mathrm{Cd},{ }^{47} \\mathrm{Ag}$$\n",
      "$${ }^{27} \\mathrm{Co},{ }^{28} \\mathrm{Ni},{ }^{26} \\mathrm{Fe},{ }^{24} \\mathrm{Cr}$$\n",
      "$${ }^{28} \\mathrm{Ni},{ }^{24} \\mathrm{Cr},{ }^{26} \\mathrm{Fe},{ }^{29} \\mathrm{Cu}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$${ }^{29} \\mathrm{Cu},{ }^{30} \\mathrm{Zn},{ }^{48} \\mathrm{Cd},{ }^{47} \\mathrm{Ag}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfmqt69",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following statements are correct about $$\\mathrm{Zn}, \\mathrm{Cd}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Hg}$$ ?</p>\n<p>A. They exhibit high enthalpy of atomization as the d-subshell is full.</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{Zn}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cd}$$ do not show variable oxidation state while $$\\mathrm{Hg}$$ shows $$+\\mathrm{I}$$ and $$+\\mathrm{II}$$.</p>\n<p>C. Compounds of $$\\mathrm{Zn}, \\mathrm{Cd}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Hg}$$ are paramagnetic in nature.</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{Zn}, \\mathrm{Cd}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Hg}$$ are called soft metals.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "C, D only",
      "B, C only",
      "A, D only",
      "B, D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "B, D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwe3if",
    "question": "<p>Give below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The higher oxidation states are more stable down the group among transition elements unlike p-block elements.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Copper can not liberate hydrogen from weak acids.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2v3a2",
    "question": "<p>The electronic configuration of $$\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{II})$$ is $$3 \\mathrm{~d}^9$$ whereas that of $$\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{I})$$ is $$3 \\mathrm{~d}^{10}$$. Which of the following is correct?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{II})$$ is more stable\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Cu}$$ (II) is less stable\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{I})$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{II})$$ are equally stable\n",
      "Stability of $$\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{I})$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{II})$$ depends on nature of copper salts"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Cu}(\\mathrm{II})$$ is more stable\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vychy",
    "question": "<p>The element which shows only one oxidation state other than its elemental form is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Nickel\n",
      "Titanium\n",
      "Cobalt\n",
      "Scandium"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Scandium"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gsk5f",
    "question": "<p>Iron (III) catalyses the reaction between iodide and persulphate ions, in which</p>\n<p>A. $$\\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}$$ oxidises the iodide ion</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}$$ oxidises the persulphate ion</p>\n<p>C. $$\\mathrm{Fe}^{2+}$$ reduces the iodide ion</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{Fe}^{2+}$$ reduces the persulphate ion</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "B and C only\n",
      "A only\n",
      "A and D only\n",
      "B only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "A and D only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v4hdn",
    "question": "<p>The metal that shows highest and maximum number of oxidation state is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Co",
      "Mn",
      "Fe",
      "Ti"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "Mn"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s2pr8",
    "question": "<p>The number of ions from the following that have the ability to liberate hydrogen from a dilute acid is _________.</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{Ti}^{2+}, \\mathrm{Cr}^{2+} \\text { and } \\mathrm{V}^{2+}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "2",
      "3",
      "0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2a2ec",
    "question": "<p>Arrange the following elements in the increasing order of number of unpaired electrons in it.</p>\n<p>(A) $$\\mathrm{Sc}$$</p>\n<p>(B) $$\\mathrm{Cr}$$</p>\n<p>(C) $$\\mathrm{V}$$</p>\n<p>(D) $$\\mathrm{Ti}$$</p>\n<p>(E) $$\\mathrm{Mn}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\n(\\mathrm{A})<(\\mathrm{D})<(\\mathrm{C})<(\\mathrm{B})<(\\mathrm{E})\n$$",
      "$$\n(\\mathrm{A})<(\\mathrm{D})<(\\mathrm{C})<(\\mathrm{E})<(\\mathrm{B})\n$$",
      "$$\n(\\mathrm{B})<(\\mathrm{C})<(\\mathrm{D})<(\\mathrm{E})<(\\mathrm{A})\n$$",
      "$$\n(\\mathrm{C})<(\\mathrm{E})<(\\mathrm{B})<(\\mathrm{A})<(\\mathrm{D})\n$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "d-and-f-block-elements",
    "topic": "properties-of-transition-elements",
    "solution": "$$\n(\\mathrm{A})<(\\mathrm{D})<(\\mathrm{C})<(\\mathrm{E})<(\\mathrm{B})\n$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "8wA5QcfJErs5YYwq",
    "question": "Several blocks of magnesium are fixed to the bottom of a ship to :",
    "options": [
      "make the ship lighter",
      "prevent action of water and salt",
      "prevent puncturing by under-sea rocks",
      "keep away the sharks"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "prevent action of water and salt"
  },
  {
    "id": "Cq7eb3s671Jb9l1c",
    "question": "In a hydrogen – oxygen fuel cell, combustion of hydrogen occurs to :",
    "options": [
      "generate heat ",
      "remove adsorbed oxygen from electrode surfaces ",
      "produce high purity water",
      "create potential difference between the two electrodes"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "create potential difference between the two electrodes"
  },
  {
    "id": "OFxUwl1UpzGI2692",
    "question": "In a fuel cell methanol is used as fuel and oxygen gas is used as an oxidizer. The reaction is<br/>\nCH<sub>3</sub>OH(l) + 3/2O<sub>2 </sub> $$\\to$$ CO<sub>2</sub> (g) + 2H<sub>2</sub>O (l) <br/>\nAt 298K standard Gibb’s energies of formation for CH<sub>3</sub>OH(l), H<sub>2</sub>O(l) and CO<sub>2</sub> (g) are -166.2, -237.2 and -394.4 kJ mol<sup>−1</sup> respectively. If standard enthalpy of combustion of methanol is -726 kJ mol<sup>−1</sup>, efficiency of the fuel cell will be ",
    "options": [
      "87%",
      "90%",
      "97%",
      "80%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "97%"
  },
  {
    "id": "JYJFqFkkk6669jFQ",
    "question": "Galvanization is applying a coating of :",
    "options": [
      "Cr",
      "Cu",
      "Zn",
      "Pb"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "Zn"
  },
  {
    "id": "BDZrcHtJ0K9DBMLjx0tQD",
    "question": "Identify the correct statement :",
    "options": [
      "Iron corrodes in oxygen-free water.",
      "Iron corrodes more rapidly in salt water because its electrochemical\npotential is higher.",
      "Corrosion of iron can be minimized by forming a contact with another\nmetal with a higher reduction potential.",
      "Corrosion of iron can be minimized by forming an impermeable barrier\nat its surface."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "Corrosion of iron can be minimized by forming an impermeable barrier\nat its surface."
  },
  {
    "id": "wrvo2JTJ5c8kR6aM7R1kludnpno",
    "question": "Compound A used as a strong oxidizing agent is amphoteric in nature. It is the part of lead storage batteries. Compound A is :",
    "options": [
      "PbO",
      "PbO<sub>2</sub>",
      "PbSO<sub>4</sub>",
      "Pb<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "PbO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mc6ibo",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-fymr{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-fymr\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-fymr\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$Cd(s) + 2Ni{(OH)_3}(s) \\to CdO(s) + 2Ni{(OH)_2}(s) + {H_2}O(l)$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Primary battery</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$Zn(Hg) + HgO(s) \\to ZnO(s) + Hg(l)$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Discharging of secondary battery</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$2PbS{O_4}(s) + 2{H_2}O(l) \\to Pb(s) + Pb{O_2}(s) + 2{H_2}S{O_4}(aq)$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Fuel cell</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$2{H_2}(g) + {O_2}(g) \\to 2{H_2}O(l)$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Charging of secondary battery</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{III})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{III})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{III})$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrl0m11",
    "question": "<p>For lead storage battery pick the correct statements</p>\n<p>A. During charging of battery, $$\\mathrm{PbSO}_{4}$$ on anode is converted into $$\\mathrm{PbO}_{2}$$</p>\n<p>B. During charging of battery, $$\\mathrm{PbSO}_{4}$$ on cathode is converted into $$\\mathrm{PbO}_{2}$$</p>\n<p>C. Lead storage battery consists of grid of lead packed with $$\\mathrm{PbO}_{2}$$ as anode</p>\n<p>D. Lead storage battery has $$\\sim 38 \\%$$ solution of sulphuric acid as an electrolyte</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B, D only",
      "B, C only",
      "B, C, D only",
      "B, D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "B, D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscrpjrl",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following statements is not correct about rusting of iron?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Rusting of iron is envisaged as setting up of electrochemical cell on the surface of iron object.\n",
      "Dissolved acidic oxides $$\\mathrm{SO}_2, \\mathrm{NO}_2$$ in water act as catalyst in the process of rusting.\n",
      "Coating of iron surface by tin prevents rusting, even if the tin coating is peeling off.\n",
      "When $$\\mathrm{pH}$$ lies above 9 or 10, rusting of iron does not take place."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "Coating of iron surface by tin prevents rusting, even if the tin coating is peeling off.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxzq6ft",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 572px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 160px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 262px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Cell)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Use/Property/Reaction)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Leclanche cell</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Converts energy of combustion into electrical energy</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ni - Cd cell</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Does not involve any ion in solution and is used in hearing aids</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Fuel cell</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Rechargeable</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Mercury cell</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Reaction at anode $$\\mathrm{Zn} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{Zn}^{2+}+2 \\mathrm{e}^{-}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II\n",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV\n",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2ertkj",
    "question": "<p>Fuel cell, using hydrogen and oxygen as fuels,</p>\n<p>A. has been used in spaceship</p>\n<p>B. has as efficiency of $$40 \\%$$ to produce electricity</p>\n<p>C. uses aluminum as catalysts</p>\n<p>D. is eco-friendly</p>\n<p>E. is actually a type of Galvanic cell only</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, D, E only\n",
      "A, B, C only\n",
      "A, B, D only\n",
      "A, B, D, E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "A, D, E only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3yzz",
    "question": "<p>The reaction at cathode in the cells commonly used in clocks involves.</p>\n",
    "options": [
      "oxidation of $$\\mathrm{Mn}$$ from +2 to +7\n",
      "reduction of $$\\mathrm{Mn}$$ from +4 to +3\n",
      "oxidation of $$\\mathrm{Mn}$$ from +3 to +4\n",
      "reduction of $$\\mathrm{Mn}$$ from +7 to +2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "batteries,-fuel-cells-and-corrosion",
    "solution": "reduction of $$\\mathrm{Mn}$$ from +4 to +3\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "CiFEmbp3pMNxIYZE",
    "question": "Conductivity (Seimen’s S) is directly proportional to area of the vessel and the concentration\nof the solution in it and is inversely proportional to the length of the vessel then, then constant of proportionality is expressed in :",
    "options": [
      "Sm mol<sup>-1</sup>",
      "Sm<sup>2 </sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>",
      "S<sup>-2</sup>m<sup>2</sup> mol",
      "S<sup>2</sup>m<sup>2</sup> mol<sup>-2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "Sm<sup>2 </sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "asbxbSBympPpDT76",
    "question": "When during electrolysis of a solution of AgNO<sub>3</sub>, 9650 coulombs of charge pass through the electroplating\nbath, the mass of silver deposited on the cathode will be :",
    "options": [
      "10.8 g",
      "21.6 g",
      "108 g",
      "1.08 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "10.8 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "SzA3psjoCBYySpI0",
    "question": "The limiting molar conductivities Λ° for NaCl, KBr and KCl are 126, 152 and 150 S cm<sup>2</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup> respectively. The Λ° for NaBr is ",
    "options": [
      "128 S cm<sup>2</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>",
      "278 S cm<sup>2</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>",
      "176 S cm<sup>2</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>",
      "302 S cm<sup>2</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "128 S cm<sup>2</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "bYbJGByTiEe5k0xZ",
    "question": "Aluminium oxide may be electrolysed at 1000<sup>o</sup>C to furnish aluminium metal (Atomic\nmass = 27 amu; 1 Faraday = 96,500 Coulombs). The cathode reaction is Al<sup>3+</sup> + 3e<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$ Al<sup>o</sup> To prepare 5.12 kg of aluminium metal by this method would require ",
    "options": [
      "5.49 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> C of electricity ",
      "1.83 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> C of electricity ",
      "5.49 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup> C of electricity ",
      "5.49 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>1</sup> C of electricity "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "5.49 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> C of electricity "
  },
  {
    "id": "TgPxnqNHi2MYD4Ah",
    "question": "The highest electrical conductivity of the following aqueous solutions is of :",
    "options": [
      "0.1 M acetic acid",
      "0.1 M chloroacetic acid",
      "0.1 M fluoroacetic acid ",
      "0.1 M difluoroacetic acid "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "0.1 M difluoroacetic acid "
  },
  {
    "id": "gne2KSHrilaUfc6x",
    "question": "<div style=\"overflow-x: auto;\">\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-uys7{border-color:inherit;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-xldj{border-color:inherit;text-align:left}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-uys7\">Electrolyte:</th>\n<th class=\"tg-xldj\">KCl</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\">KNO<sub>3</sub></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\">HCl</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\">NaOAc</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\">NaCl</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-uys7\">$${ \\wedge ^\\infty }(Sc{m^2}mo{l^{ - 1}}):$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-uys7\">149.9</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">145</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">426.2</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">91</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">126.5</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>\n</div>\nCalculate $$ \\wedge _{HOAc}^\\infty $$  Using appropriate molar conductances of the electrolytes listed\nabove at infinite dilution in H<sub>2</sub>O at 25<sup>o</sup>C",
    "options": [
      "517.2 ",
      "552.7 ",
      "390.7",
      "217.5 "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "390.7"
  },
  {
    "id": "Mq9Iv1ngH7Opdlng",
    "question": "The molar conductivities $$ \\wedge _{NaOAc}^o$$ and  $$ \\wedge _{HCl}^o$$ and at infinite dilution in water at 25<sup>o</sup>C are 91.0 and 426.2 Scm<sup>2</sup>/mol respectively. To calculate $$ \\wedge _{HOAc}^o$$  , the additional value required is ",
    "options": [
      "$$ \\wedge _{{H_2}O}^o$$",
      "$$ \\wedge _{KCl}^o$$ ",
      "$$ \\wedge _{NaOH}^o$$",
      "$$ \\wedge _{NaCl}^o$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "$$ \\wedge _{NaCl}^o$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "OLMbCGTlkXvrtGM3",
    "question": "Resistance of a conductivity cell filled with a solution of an electrolyte of concentration 0.1 M is 100$$\\Omega $$.\nThe conductivity of this solution is 1.29 S m<sup>–1</sup>. Resistance of the same cell when filled with 0.2 M of\nthe same solution is 520 $$\\Omega $$, The molar conductivity of 0.02 M solution of the electrolyte will be ",
    "options": [
      "124 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–4 </sup> S m<sup>2 </sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "1240 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–4 </sup> S m<sup>2 </sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "1.24 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–4 </sup> S m<sup>2 </sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "12.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–4 </sup> S m<sup>2 </sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "12.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–4 </sup> S m<sup>2 </sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "82P6cYNxCChvG7DX",
    "question": "The equivalent conductances of two strong electrolytes at infinite dilution in H<sub>2</sub>O (where ions move\nfreely through a solution) at 25<sup>o</sup>C are given below: <br/>\n$$ \\wedge _{C{H_3}COONa}^o$$ = 91.0 S cm<sup>2</sup>/equiv<br/>\n$$ \\wedge _{HCl}^o$$ = 426.2 S cm<sup>2</sup>/equiv<br/>\nWhat additional information/quantity one needs to calculate $$ \\wedge ^o$$ of an aqueous solution of acetic acid? ",
    "options": [
      "$$ \\wedge ^o$$ of chloroacetic acid (C/CH<sub>2</sub>COOH)",
      "$$ \\wedge ^o$$ of NaCl",
      "$$ \\wedge ^o$$ of CH<sub>3</sub>COOK",
      "The limiting equivalent conductance of $${H^ + }( \\wedge _{{H^ + }}^o)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "$$ \\wedge ^o$$ of NaCl"
  },
  {
    "id": "GENLBQdzkzTSXUCQ",
    "question": "Resistance of 0.2 M solution of an electrolyte is 50 $$\\Omega$$. The specific conductance of the solution is 1.4 S m<sup>-1</sup>. The resistance of 0.5 M solution of the same electrolyte is 280 $$\\Omega$$. The molar conductivity of 0.5 M solution of the electrolyte in S m<sup>2</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup> is :",
    "options": [
      "5 × 10<sup>3</sup>",
      "5 × 10<sup>2</sup>",
      "5 × 10<sup>-4</sup>",
      "5 × 10<sup>-3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "5 × 10<sup>-4</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "9B83K2rNrhZIcWdy",
    "question": "The equivalent conductance of NaCl at concentration C and at infinite dilution are $${\\lambda _C}$$  and $${\\lambda _\\infty }$$, respectively. The correct relationship between $${\\lambda _C}$$  and $${\\lambda _\\infty }$$ is given as:\n(where the constant B is positive)",
    "options": [
      "$${\\lambda _C} = {\\lambda _\\infty } + (B)C$$",
      "$${\\lambda _C} = {\\lambda _\\infty } - (B)C$$",
      "$${\\lambda _C} = {\\lambda _\\infty } - (B)\\sqrt C$$",
      "$${\\lambda _C} = {\\lambda _\\infty } + (B)\\sqrt C$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "$${\\lambda _C} = {\\lambda _\\infty } - (B)\\sqrt C$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "wQZhoL2I8GFK6YPP",
    "question": "Two Faraday of electricity is passed through a solution of CuSO<sub>4</sub>. The mass of copper deposited at the\ncathode is: (at. mass of Cu = 63.5 amu)",
    "options": [
      "63.5 g",
      "2 g",
      "127 g",
      "0 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "63.5 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "carxJYhGrMbmiDcNAGpd7",
    "question": "Oxidation of succinate ion produces ethylene and carbon dioxide gases. On passing 0.2 Faraday electricity through an aqueous solution of potassium succinate, the total volume of gases (at both cathode and anode) at STP (1 atm and 273 K) is :",
    "options": [
      "2.24 L",
      "4.48 L",
      "6.72 L ",
      "8.96 L "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "8.96 L "
  },
  {
    "id": "qOEpVdldNK7Ce1uJ",
    "question": "How long (approximate) should water be electrolysed by passing through 100 amperes current so that the\noxygen released can completely burn 27.66 g of diborane?<br/>\n(Atomic weight of B = 10.8 u)",
    "options": [
      "1.6 hours",
      "6.4 hours",
      "0.8 hours",
      "3.2 hours"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "3.2 hours"
  },
  {
    "id": "Z89d2iucGgQrFVsuxdnOP",
    "question": "When an electric currents passed through acidified water, 112 mL of hydrogen gas at N.T.P. was collected at the cathode in 965 seconds. The current passed, in ampere, is : ",
    "options": [
      "1.0",
      "0.5",
      "0.1",
      "2.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "1.0"
  },
  {
    "id": "jSrsVc414XRCcl9cmjHvy",
    "question": "When 9.65 ampere current was passed for 1.0 hour into nitrobenzene in acidic medium, the amount of p-aminophenol produced is : ",
    "options": [
      "9.81 g",
      "10.9 g",
      "98.1 g",
      "109.0 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "9.81 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "QiJQ3TTC2PU4GT8FGk3rsa0w2w9jwv8740b",
    "question": "Consider the statements S1 and S2\n<br/><br>S1 : Conductivity always increases with decrease in the concentration of electrolyte.\n<br/><br>S2 : Molar conductivity always increases with decrease in the concentration of electrolyte.\n<br/><br>The correct option among the following is :</br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "Both S1 and S2 are wrong",
      "S1 is correct and S2 is wrong",
      "Both S1 and S2 are correct",
      "S1 is wrong and S2 is correct "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "S1 is wrong and S2 is correct "
  },
  {
    "id": "95BpaQdmmggnxsGyQHSyQ",
    "question": "$$ \\wedge _m^ \\circ $$ for NaCl, HCl and NaA are 126.4, 425.9 and 100.5 S cm<sup>2</sup>  mol<sup>–1</sup>, respectively. If the conductivity of 0.001 M HA is- \n<br/><br/>5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–5</sup> S cm<sup>–1</sup>, degree of dissociation of HA is - ",
    "options": [
      "0.50",
      "0.125",
      "0.25",
      "0.75"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "0.125"
  },
  {
    "id": "mSgr7enqEwoMXtcYZZlWu",
    "question": "A solution of Ni(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> is electrolysed between\nplatinum electrodes using 0.1 Faraday\nelectricity. How many mole of Ni will be\ndeposited at the cathode?",
    "options": [
      "0.10",
      "0.15",
      "0.20",
      "0.05"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "0.05"
  },
  {
    "id": "uwGoOZ2KsiqNeEcwYJjgy2xukfceu0cf",
    "question": "250 mL of a waste solution obtained from the\nworkshop of a goldsmith contains 0.1 M AgNO<sub>3</sub>\nand 0.1 M AuCl. The solution was electrolyzed\nat 2V by passing a current of 1A for 15\nminutes. The metal/metals electrodeposited will\nbe\n<br/><br/>[ $$E_{A{g^ + }/Ag}^0$$ = 0.80 V, $$E_{A{u^ + }/Au}^0$$ = 1.69 V ]",
    "options": [
      "Silver and gold in equal mass proportion",
      "Silver and gold in proportion to their atomic\nweights",
      "Only gold",
      "Only silver"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "Only gold"
  },
  {
    "id": "HjakCQRwzFuKTw4SW3jgy2xukf2clg52",
    "question": "Let C<sub>NaCl</sub> \nand C<sub>BaSO<sub>4</sub></sub> be the conductances (in S) measured for saturated aqueous solutions of NaCl\nand BaSO<sub>4</sub>, respectively, at a temperature T.\nWhich of the following is false?\n",
    "options": [
      "Ionic mobilities of ions from both salts increase with T.",
      "C<sub>NaCl</sub>(T<sub>2</sub>) &gt;  C<sub>NaCl</sub>(T<sub>1</sub>) for T<sub>2</sub> &gt; T<sub>1</sub>",
      "C<sub>BaSO<sub>4</sub></sub>(T<sub>2</sub>) &gt;  C<sub>BaSO<sub>4</sub></sub>(T<sub>1</sub>) for T<sub>2</sub> &gt; T<sub>1</sub>",
      "C<sub>NaCl</sub> &gt;&gt; C<sub>BaSO<sub>4</sub></sub> at a given T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "C<sub>NaCl</sub> &gt;&gt; C<sub>BaSO<sub>4</sub></sub> at a given T"
  },
  {
    "id": "cuQCtLDotzQNDXNsFG7k9k2k5epdscq",
    "question": "The equation that is incorrect is :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{KCl}} - {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaCl}} = {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{KBr}} - {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaBr}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaBr}} - {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaI}} = {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{KBr}} - {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaBr}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaBr}} - {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaCl}} = {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{KBr}} - {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{KCl}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{{H_2}O}} = {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{HCl}} + {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaOH}} - {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaCl}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "$${\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaBr}} - {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaI}} = {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{KBr}} - {\\left( {\\Lambda _m^0} \\right)_{NaBr}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktb4bcnb",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : The limiting molar conductivity of KCl (strong electrolyte) is higher compared to that of CH<sub>3</sub>COOH (weak electrolyte).<br/><br/>Statement II : Molar conductivity decreases with decrease in concentration of electrolyte.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjvcwac",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I<br/>(Parmeter)</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II<br/>(Unit)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Cell constant</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>$$S\\,c{m^2}mo{l^{ - 1}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Molar conductivity</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Dimensionless</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Conductivity</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>$${m^{ - 1}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Degree of dissociation of electrolyte</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>$${\\Omega ^{ - 1}}{m^{ - 1}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iv), (c)-(iii), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iii), (d)-(iv)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f6mp0f",
    "question": "<p>The molar conductivity of a conductivity cell filled with 10 moles of 20 mL NaCl solution is $${\\Lambda _{m1}}$$ and that of 20 moles another identical cell heaving 80 mL NaCl solution is $${\\Lambda _{m2}}$$. The conductivities exhibited by these two cells are same. The relationship between $${\\Lambda _{m2}}$$ and $${\\Lambda _{m1}}$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${\\Lambda _{m2}}$$ = 2$${\\Lambda _{m1}}$$",
      "$${\\Lambda _{m2}}$$ = $${\\Lambda _{m1}}$$ / 2",
      "$${\\Lambda _{m2}}$$ = $${\\Lambda _{m1}}$$",
      "$${\\Lambda _{m2}}$$ = 4$${\\Lambda _{m1}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "$${\\Lambda _{m2}}$$ = 2$${\\Lambda _{m1}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kp7j97",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : For KI, molar conductivity increases steeply with dilution</p>\n<p>Statement II : For carbonic acid, molar conductivity increases slowly with dilution</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldo2veix",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R)</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : An aqueous solution of $$\\mathrm{KOH}$$ when used for volumetric analysis, its concentration should be checked before the use.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : On aging, $$\\mathrm{KOH}$$ solution absorbs atmospheric $$\\mathrm{CO}_{2}$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpp3x3f",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following statements is correct for electrolysis of brine solution?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ is formed at cathode",
      "$$\\mathrm{H}_{2}$$ is formed at anode",
      "$$\\mathrm{Cl}_{2}$$ is formed at cathode",
      "$$\\mathrm{OH}^{-}$$ is formed at cathode"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{OH}^{-}$$ is formed at cathode"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7d2mp",
    "question": "<p>Identify the factor from the following that does not affect electrolytic conductance of a solution.</p>",
    "options": [
      "The nature of solvent used.\n",
      "The nature of the electrolyte added.\n",
      "The nature of the electrode used.\n",
      "Concentration of the electrolyte."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "The nature of the electrode used.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg7uyu7",
    "question": "<p>Alkaline oxidative fusion of $$\\mathrm{MnO}_2$$ gives \"A\" which on electrolytic oxidation in alkaline solution produces B. A and B respectively are</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Mn}_2 \\mathrm{O}_3$$ and $$\\mathrm{MnO}_4^{2-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Mn}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7$$ and $$\\mathrm{MnO}_4^{-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{MnO}_4^{2-}$$ and $$\\mathrm{MnO}_4^{-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{MnO}_4^{2-}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Mn}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{MnO}_4^{2-}$$ and $$\\mathrm{MnO}_4^{-}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxzqiw7",
    "question": "<p>Which out of the following is a correct equation to show change in molar conductivity with respect to concentration for a weak electrolyte, if the symbols carry their usual meaning :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}-\\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}^{\\circ}+\\mathrm{AC}^{\\frac{1}{2}}=0$$",
      "$$\\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}^2 \\mathrm{C}+\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{a}} \\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}^{\\mathrm{o}^2}-\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{a}} \\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}} \\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}^{\\circ}=0$$",
      "$$\\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}-\\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}^{\\circ}-\\mathrm{AC}^{\\frac{1}{2}}=0$$",
      "$$\\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}^2 \\mathrm{C}-\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{a}} \\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}^{\\circ 2}+\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{a}} \\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}} \\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}^{\\circ}=0$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "$$\\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}^2 \\mathrm{C}-\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{a}} \\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}^{\\circ 2}+\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{a}} \\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}} \\Lambda_{\\mathrm{m}}^{\\circ}=0$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erz0j",
    "question": "<p>For a strong electrolyte, a plot of molar conductivity against (concentration) $${ }^{1 / 2}$$ is a straight line, with a negative slope, the correct unit for the slope is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{S} \\mathrm{cm}^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-3 / 2} \\mathrm{~L}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{S} \\mathrm{cm}{ }^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-3 / 2} \\mathrm{~L}^{-1 / 2}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{S} \\mathrm{cm}{ }^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1} \\mathrm{~L}^{1 / 2}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{S} \\mathrm{cm}^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-3 / 2} \\mathrm{~L}^{1 / 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{S} \\mathrm{cm}^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-3 / 2} \\mathrm{~L}^{1 / 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmbaj",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : Fusion of $$\\mathrm{MnO}_2$$ with $$\\mathrm{KOH}$$ and an oxidising agent gives dark green $$\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{MnO}_4$$.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : Manganate ion on electrolytic oxidation in alkaline medium gives permanganate ion.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v49ug",
    "question": "<p>Molar ionic conductivities of divalent cation and anion are $$57 \\mathrm{~S~cm}^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$ and $$73 \\mathrm{~S~cm}^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$ respectively. The molar conductivity of solution of an electrolyte with the above cation and anion will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$187 \\mathrm{~S} \\mathrm{~cm}^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$260 \\mathrm{~S} \\mathrm{~cm}^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$65 \\mathrm{~S} \\mathrm{~cm}^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$130 \\mathrm{~S} \\mathrm{~cm}^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "$$130 \\mathrm{~S} \\mathrm{~cm}^2 \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s2pv4",
    "question": "<p>The quantity of silver deposited when one coulomb charge is passed through $$\\mathrm{AgNO}_3$$ solution :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$0.1 \\mathrm{~g}$$ atom of silver\n",
      "1 chemical equivalent of silver\n",
      "$$1 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of silver\n",
      "1 electrochemical equivalent of silver"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "conductance-and-electrolysis",
    "solution": "1 electrochemical equivalent of silver"
  },
  {
    "id": "yTjIAY8xgsNZVa9N",
    "question": "For the following cell with hydrogen electrodes at two different pressure p<sub>1</sub> and p<sub>2</sub>. What will be the emf for the given cell :\n<br/><br/>$$\\eqalign{\n  &amp; Pt({H_2})|{H^ + }(aq)|Pt({H_2})  \\cr \n  &amp; \\,\\,\\,\\,\\,{p_1}\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,1M\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,{p_2} \\cr} $$",
    "options": [
      "$${{RT} \\over F}{\\log _e}{{{P_1}} \\over {{P_2}}}$$ ",
      "$${{RT} \\over 2F}{\\log _e}{{{P_1}} \\over {{P_2}}}$$",
      "$${{RT} \\over F}{\\log _e}{{{P_2}} \\over {{P_1}}}$$",
      "none of these"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$${{RT} \\over 2F}{\\log _e}{{{P_1}} \\over {{P_2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xp34ovlDlQwqPFEa",
    "question": "EMF of a cell in terms of reduction potential of its left and right electrodes is :",
    "options": [
      "E = E<sub>left</sub> - E<sub>right</sub>",
      "E = E<sub>left</sub> + E<sub>right</sub>",
      "E = E<sub>right</sub> - E<sub>left</sub>",
      "E = -(E<sub>right</sub> + E<sub>left</sub>)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "E = E<sub>right</sub> - E<sub>left</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "eghRs2hzUeGUNQrn",
    "question": "Which of the following reaction is possible at anode?",
    "options": [
      "2Cr<sup>3+</sup> + 7H<sub>2</sub>O $$\\to Cr_2O_7^{2-}$$ + 14H<sup>+</sup>",
      "F<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ 2F<sup>-</sup>",
      "(1/2) O<sub>2</sub> + 2H<sup>+</sup> $$\\to$$ H<sub>2</sub>O ",
      "none of these"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "2Cr<sup>3+</sup> + 7H<sub>2</sub>O $$\\to Cr_2O_7^{2-}$$ + 14H<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "PGFWnz6ubDo31DLQ",
    "question": "When the sample of copper with zinc impurity is to be purified by electrolysis, the appropriate\nelectrodes are :",
    "options": [
      "cathode = pure zinc, anode = pure copper",
      "cathode =  impure sample, anode = pure copper",
      "cathode =  impure zinc, anode = impure sample",
      "cathode =  pure copper, anode = impure sample"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "cathode =  pure copper, anode = impure sample"
  },
  {
    "id": "RcPjHXd5i8KNuZis",
    "question": "For a cell reaction involving a two-electron change, the standard e.m.f. of the cell is found to be 0.295 V at 25<sup>o</sup>C. The equilibrium constant of the reaction at 25<sup>o</sup>C will be",
    "options": [
      "29.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup>",
      "10",
      "1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup>",
      "1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-10</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "SoHEmoxCiUyAtlFp",
    "question": "For the redox reaction Zn(s) + Cu<sup>2+</sup>(0.1 M) $$\\to$$ Zn<sup>2+</sup>(1M) + Cu(s) taking place in a cell, $$E_{cell}^o$$  is 1.10 volt. E<sub>cell</sub> for the cell will be ($$2.303{{RT} \\over F}$$ = 0.0591)",
    "options": [
      "1.80 volt",
      "1.07 volt",
      "0.82 volt",
      "2.14 volt"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "1.07 volt"
  },
  {
    "id": "rXhD04mECCIdYnJU",
    "question": "Standard reduction electrode potentials of three metals A,B&amp;C are respectively +0.5 V, -3.0 V &amp; -1.2 V. The\nreducing, powers of these metals are",
    "options": [
      "A &gt; B &gt; C",
      "C &gt; B &gt; A",
      "A &gt; C &gt; B",
      "B &gt; C &gt; A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "B &gt; C &gt; A"
  },
  {
    "id": "JMgJztXuwIK7ythF",
    "question": "Consider the following E<sup>o</sup> values <br/>\n<br>$$E_{F{e^{3 + }}/F{e^{2 + }}}^o$$ = 0.77 V;<br/>\n<br>$$E_{S{n^{2 + }}/S{n}}^o$$ = -0.14 V<br/>\n<br>Under standard conditions the potential for the reaction <br/>\n<br>Sn(s) + 2Fe<sup>3+</sup>(aq) $$\\to$$ 2Fe<sup>2+</sup>(aq) + Sn<sup>2+</sup>(aq) is :</br></br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "1.68 V",
      "0.63 V ",
      "0.91 V ",
      "1.40 V "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "0.91 V "
  },
  {
    "id": "5M8pT6y7VOoRf7rT",
    "question": "The standard e.m.f of a cell, involving one electron change is found to be 0.591 V at 25<sup>o</sup>C.\nThe equilibrium constant of the reaction is (F = 96,500 C mol<sup>-1</sup>: R = 8.314 JK<sup>-1</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>1</sup>",
      "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>30</sup>",
      "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup>",
      "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "xjjIlFLTU5Mx54S4",
    "question": "In a cell that utilises the reaction Zn(s) + 2H<sup>+</sup>\n(aq) $$\\to$$ Zn2+(aq) + H2(g) addition of H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> to cathode compartment, will ",
    "options": [
      "lower the E and shift equilibrium to the left ",
      "increases the E and shift equilibrium to the left",
      "increase the E and shift equilibrium to the right ",
      "Lower the E and shift equilibrium to the right "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "increase the E and shift equilibrium to the right "
  },
  {
    "id": "0eHrZRrqDZ2WoZfL",
    "question": "The $$E_{{M^{3 + }}/{M^{2 + }}}^o$$  values for Cr, Mn, Fe and Co are – 0.41, +1.57, + 0.77 and +1.97 V\nrespectively. For which one of these metals the change in oxidation state form +2 to +3 is\neasiest? ",
    "options": [
      "Fe",
      "Mn",
      "Cr",
      "Co"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "Cr"
  },
  {
    "id": "lapmeFUNf98aZaDl",
    "question": "For a spontaneous reaction the ∆G , equilibrium constant (K) and $$E_{cell}^o$$ will be respectively",
    "options": [
      "-ve, &gt;1, +ve",
      "+ve, &gt;1, -ve ",
      "-ve, &lt;1, -ve ",
      "-ve, &gt;1, -ve "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "-ve, &gt;1, +ve"
  },
  {
    "id": "b2QNMOI2608D7ogn",
    "question": "Given the data at 25<sup>o</sup>C, <br/>\nAg + I<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$ AgI + e<sup>-</sup> , E<sup>o</sup> = 0.152 V<br/>\nAg $$\\to$$ Ag<sup>+</sup> + e<sup>-</sup>, E<sup>o</sup> = -0.800 V<br/>\nWhat is the value of log K<sub>sp</sub> for AgI? (2.303 RT/F = 0.059 V)",
    "options": [
      "–8.12",
      "+8.612",
      "–37.83",
      "–16.13"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "–16.13"
  },
  {
    "id": "D6we0EIVC1ykVqoS",
    "question": "The cell, Zn | Zn<sup>2+</sup> (1M) || Cu<sup>2+</sup> (1M) | Cu($$E_{cell}^o$$ = 1.10V)  was allowed to be completely discharged at 298 K. The relative concentration of Zn<sup>2+</sup> to Cu<sup>2+</sup> $$\\left[ {{{\\left[ {Z{n^{2 + }}} \\right]} \\over {\\left[ {C{u^{2 + }}} \\right]}}} \\right]$$ is",
    "options": [
      "antilog (24.08) ",
      "37.3",
      "10<sup>37.3</sup>",
      "9.65 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup>\n "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "10<sup>37.3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "uSB2XOq3OHyFIxIT",
    "question": "Given $$E_{C{r^{3 + }}/Cr}^o$$ = -0.72 V; $$E_{Fe^{2+}/Fe}^o$$ = -0.42V, The potential for the cell Cr | Cr<sup>3+</sup> (0.1M) || Fe<sup>2+</sup> (0.01 M) | Fe is",
    "options": [
      "0.26 V",
      "0.399 V",
      "−0.339 V",
      "−0.26 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "0.26 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "Z1oO3ob5geBBpWEe",
    "question": "Given : $$E_{F{e^{3 + }}/Fe}^o$$  = -0.036V; $$E_{F{e^{2 + }}/Fe}^o$$ = -0.439 V<br/>\nThe value of standard electrode potential for the change, <br/>\nFe<sup>3+</sup> (aq) + e<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$ Fe<sup>2+</sup> (aq) will be ",
    "options": [
      "-0.072 V",
      "0.385 V",
      "0.770 V ",
      "0.270"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "0.770 V "
  },
  {
    "id": "ZBWJikte7Qop5gW2",
    "question": "The correct order of $$E_{{M^{2 + }}/M}^o$$ values with negative sign for the four successive elements Cr, Mn, Fe\nand Co is :",
    "options": [
      "Mn &gt; Cr &gt; Fe &gt; Co",
      "Cr &gt; Fe &gt; Mn &gt; Co",
      "Fe &gt; Mn &gt; Cr &gt; Co",
      "Cr &gt; Mn &gt; Fe &gt; Co"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "Mn &gt; Cr &gt; Fe &gt; Co"
  },
  {
    "id": "k8IeHnDoD18NxFv3",
    "question": "The Gibbs energy for the decomposition of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> at 500<sup>o</sup>C is as follows :<br/>\n<br>$${2 \\over 3}A{l_2}{O_3}$$ $$\\to$$ $${4 \\over 3}Al + {O_2}$$, $${\\Delta _r}G$$ = + 966 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup><br/>\n<br>The potential difference needed for electrolytic reduction of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> at 500<sup>o</sup>C is at least :</br></br>",
    "options": [
      "4.5 V",
      "3.0 V",
      "2.5 V",
      "5.0 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "2.5 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "LWCyjCSw4AjHEKIr",
    "question": "The reduction potential of hydrogen half cell will be negative if :",
    "options": [
      "p(H<sub>2</sub>) = 1 atm and [H<sup>+</sup>] = 1.0 M",
      "p(H<sub>2</sub>) = 1 atm and [H<sup>+</sup>] = 2.0 M",
      "p(H<sub>2</sub>) = 2 atm and [H<sup>+</sup>] =1.0 M",
      "p(H<sub>2</sub>) = 2 atm and [H<sup>+</sup>] =2.0 M"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "p(H<sub>2</sub>) = 2 atm and [H<sup>+</sup>] =1.0 M"
  },
  {
    "id": "4fZCIsWjm9yNWayS",
    "question": "The standard reduction potentials for Zn<sup>2+</sup>/ Zn, Ni<sup>2+</sup>/ Ni, and Fe<sup>2+</sup>/ Fe are –0.76, –0.23 and –0.44 V respectively. The reaction <br/><br/>X + Y<sup>2+</sup> $$\\to$$ X<sup>2+</sup> + Y will be spontaneous when :",
    "options": [
      "X = Ni, Y = Fe",
      "X = Ni, Y = Zn",
      "X = Fe, Y = Zn",
      "X = Zn, Y = Ni"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "X = Zn, Y = Ni"
  },
  {
    "id": "l3DCdJawiACbkXOv",
    "question": "Given<br/>\n<br>$$E_{C{r^{2 + }}/Cr}^o$$ = -0.74 V; $$E_{MnO_4^ - /M{n^{2 + }}}^o$$ = 1.51 V<br/>\n<br>$$E_{C{r_2}O_7^{2 - }/C{r^{3 + }}}^o$$ = 1.33 V; $$E_{Cl/C{l^ - }}^o$$ = 1.36 V<br/>\n<br>Based on the data given above, strongest oxidising agent will be : </br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "Cr<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Mn<sup>2+</sup>",
      "$$MnO_4^ - $$ ",
      "Cl<sup>-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$$MnO_4^ - $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "1xD2pQDXx8XvRJBw",
    "question": "Given below are the half-cell reactions:<br/>\n<br>Mn<sup>2+</sup> + 2e<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$ Mn; E<sup>o</sup> = -1.18 V<br/>\n<br>2(Mn<sup>3+</sup> + e<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$ Mn<sup>2+</sup>); E<sup>o</sup> = +1.51 V<br/>\n<br>The E<sup>o</sup> for 3Mn<sup>2+</sup> $$\\to$$ Mn + 2Mn<sup>3+</sup> will be :</br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "– 0.33 V; the reaction will not occur",
      "– 0.33 V; the reaction will occur",
      "– 2.69 V; the reaction will not occur ",
      "– 2.69 V; the reaction will occur"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "– 2.69 V; the reaction will not occur "
  },
  {
    "id": "6FwE436nRDqSrw7iaxjfz",
    "question": "What will occur if a block of copper metal is dropped into a beaker containing a\nsolution of 1M ZnSO<sub>4</sub>?",
    "options": [
      "The copper metal will dissolve and zinc metal will be deposited.",
      "The copper metal will dissolve with evolution of hydrogen gas.",
      "The copper metal will dissolve with evolution of oxygen gas.",
      "No reaction will occur."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "No reaction will occur."
  },
  {
    "id": "glD0k4y2Jz1hSVqm",
    "question": "Given<br/>\n$$E_{C{l_2}/C{l^ - }}^o$$ = 1.36 V, $$E_{C{r^{3 + }}/Cr}^o$$ = - 0.74 V<br/>\n$$E_{C{r_2}{O_7}^{2 - }/C{r^{3 + }}}^o$$ = 1.33 V, $$E_{Mn{O_4}^ - /Mn ^{2+}}^o$$ = 1.51 V<br/>\nAmong the following, the strongest reducing agent is :",
    "options": [
      "Mn<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Cr<sup>3+</sup>\n",
      "Cl<sup>–</sup>",
      "Cr"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "Cr"
  },
  {
    "id": "3wm6goYMCAXUXRu8cIpOQ",
    "question": "What is the standard reduction potential (E<sup>o</sup>) for Fe<sup>3+</sup> $$ \\to $$ Fe ? \n<br/>Given that :\n<br/>Fe<sup>2+</sup> + 2e<sup>$$-$$</sup> $$ \\to $$ Fe; $$E_{F{e^{2 + }}/Fe}^o$$ = $$-$$0.47 V\n<br/>Fe<sup>3+</sup> + e<sup>$$-$$</sup> $$ \\to $$ Fe<sup>2+</sup>; $$E_{F{e^{3 + }}/F{e^{2 + }}}^o$$ = +0.77 V  ",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$ 0.057 V",
      "+ 0.057 V",
      "+ 0.30 V",
      "$$-$$ 0.30 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$$-$$ 0.057 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "c5du9JDLuSgRuPLqXGgPG",
    "question": "Consider the following standard electrode potentials (E<sup>o</sup> in volts) in aqueous solution :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-wv9z{font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-de48{font-weight:bold;font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\">Element</th>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\">M<sup>3+</sup> /M</th>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\">M<sup>+</sup> /M</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">A1</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">-1.66</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">+ 0.55</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">T1</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">+1.26</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">- 0.34</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>\n<br/><br/>Based on these data, which of the following statements is <b>correct</b> ?",
    "options": [
      "T1<sup>+</sup> is more stable than A1<sup>3+</sup>",
      "A1<sup>+</sup> is more stable than A1<sup>3+</sup> ",
      "T1 <sup>+</sup> is more stable than A1<sup>+</sup>",
      "T1<sup>3+</sup> is more stable than A1<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "T1 <sup>+</sup> is more stable than A1<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "rJ5MeXS6Q6ilnTsB6bQyr",
    "question": "To find the standard potential of M<sup>3+</sup>/M electrode,the following cell is constituted : Pt/M/M<sup>3+</sup>(0.001 mol L<sup>−1</sup> )/Ag<sup>+</sup>(0.01 mol L<sup>−1</sup> )/Ag \n<br/><br/>The emf of the cell is found to be 0.421 volt at 298 K. The standard potential of half reaction M3<sup>+ </sup> + 3e<sup>−</sup>$$ \\to $$ M at 298 K will be :\n<br/><br/>(Given $$E_{A{g^ + }\\,/\\,Ag}^ - $$ at 298 K = 0.80 Volt)",
    "options": [
      "0.38 Volt",
      "0.32 Volt ",
      "1.28 Volt",
      "0.66 Volt"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "0.32 Volt "
  },
  {
    "id": "Fu8Gl8B3LaApCw8cUnlNU",
    "question": "If the standard electrode potential for a cell is 2 V at 300 K, the equilibrium constant (K) for the reaction \n<br/><br>Zn(s) + Cu<sup>2+</sup> (aq) $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ Zn<sup>2+</sup>(aq) + Cu(s)  \n<br/><br>at 300 K is approximately,\n<br/><br>(R = 8 JK<sup>$$-$$1</sup>mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, F = 96000 C mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "e<sup>$$-$$80</sup>",
      "e<sup>$$-$$160</sup>",
      "e<sup>320</sup>",
      "e<sup>160</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "e<sup>160</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "zkv2z6czzaddipFUSZ3rsa0w2w9jx578xfo",
    "question": "Given\n<br/><br>CO<sup>3+</sup> + e<sup>–</sup> $$ \\to $$ CO<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup> ; E<sup>o</sup> = + 1.81 V\n<br/><br>Pb<sup>4+</sup>\n + 2e<sup>–</sup> $$ \\to $$ Pb<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup> ; E<sup>o</sup> = + 1.67 V\n<br/><br>Ce<sup>4+</sup>\n + e<sup>–</sup> $$ \\to $$ Ce<sup>3+</sup>\n ; E<sup>o</sup> = + 1.61 V\n<br/><br>Bi<sup>3+</sup> + 3e<sup>–</sup> $$ \\to $$ Bi ; E<sup>o</sup> = + 0.20 V\n<br/><br>Oxidizing power of the species will increase in the order :</br></br></br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "Co<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Ce<sup>4+</sup>\n &lt; Bi<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Pb<sup>4+</sup>",
      "Co<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Pb<sup>4+</sup> &lt; Ce<sup>4+</sup>\n &lt; Bi<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Ce<sup>4+</sup>\n &lt; Pb<sup>4+</sup> &lt; Bi<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Co<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Bi<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Ce<sup>4+</sup>\n &lt; Pb<sup>4+</sup> &lt; Co<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "Bi<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Ce<sup>4+</sup>\n &lt; Pb<sup>4+</sup> &lt; Co<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "XSCjtZy1GFblWZclEF6pD",
    "question": "The standard Gibbs energy for the given cell\nreaction in kJ mol<sup>–1</sup> at 298 K is :<br/>\n<br>Zn(s) + Cu<sup>2+</sup> (aq) $$ \\to $$ Zn<sup>2+</sup> (aq) + Cu (s),<br/>\n<br>E° = 2 V at 298 K<br/>\n<br>(Faraday's constant, F = 96000 C mol<sup>–1</sup>)</br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "384",
      "–192",
      "–384",
      "192"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "–384"
  },
  {
    "id": "XgMMmhs2mwwqfhqjxPgjn",
    "question": "Calculate the standard cell potential in (V) of the\ncell in which following reaction takes place :\n<br/><br/>Fe<sup>2+</sup>(aq) + Ag<sup>+</sup>(aq) $$ \\to $$ Fe<sup>3+</sup>(aq) + Ag (s)\n<br/><br/>Given that<br/>\n<br>$$E_{A{g^ + }/Ag}^o = xV$$<br/>\n<br>$$E_{Fe^{2+ }/Fe}^o = yV$$<br/>\n<br>$$E_{Fe^{3+ }/Fe}^o = zV$$</br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "x + 2y - 3z",
      "x - z",
      "x - y",
      "x + y - z"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "x + 2y - 3z"
  },
  {
    "id": "8A5KDTJeCT1IRGt6pCPIf",
    "question": "Given that $${E^\\Theta }_{{O_2}/{H_2}O} = 1.23\\,V$$ ;<br/>\n<br>$${E^\\Theta }_{{S_2}O_8^{2 - }/SO_4^{2 - }} = 2.05\\,V$$<br/>\n<br>$${E^\\Theta }_{B{r_2}/B{r^ - }} = 1.09\\,V$$<br/>\n<br>$${E^\\Theta }_{A{u^{3 + }}/Au} = 1.4\\,V$$<br/>\n<br/>The strongest oxidizing agent is :</br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "O<sub>2</sub>",
      "Au<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Br<sub>2</sub>",
      "$${S_2}O_8^{2 - }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$${S_2}O_8^{2 - }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "SmPXPFiVHnfPsRt3ygw24",
    "question": "Given the equilibrium constant: \n<br/><br/>K<sub>C</sub> of the reaction : \n<br/><br/>Cu(s) + 2Ag<sup>+</sup> (aq) $$ \\to $$ Cu<sup>2+</sup> (aq) + 2Ag(s) is <br/><br/>10 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>15</sup>,  calculate the E$$_{cell}^0$$ of this reaciton at 298 K <br/><br/>[2.303 $${{RT} \\over F}$$  at  298 K = 0.059V]",
    "options": [
      "0.4736 mV",
      "0.04736 V",
      "0.4736 V",
      "0.04736 mV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "0.4736 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "UAZ845NByQR9VWArvbOrp",
    "question": "For the cell Zn(s) |Zn<sup>2+</sup> (aq)| |M<sup>x+</sup> (aq)| M(s), different half cells and their standard electrode potentials are given below : \n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-a0j4{font-size:18px;text-align:left}\n.tg .tg-nx8p{font-size:18px;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-a0j4\">M<sup>x+</sup> (aq)/M(s)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-a0j4\">Au<sup>3+</sup>(aq)/Au(s)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-a0j4\">Ag<sup>+</sup>(aq)/Ag(s)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-a0j4\">Fe<sup>3+</sup>(aq)/Fe<sup>2+</sup> (aq)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-nx8p\">Fe<sup>2+</sup>(aq)/Fe(s)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-a0j4\">E<sup>0</sup><sub>M<sup>x+</sup></sub><sub>/M</sub>/(V)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-a0j4\">1.40</td>\n<td class=\"tg-a0j4\">0.80</td>\n<td class=\"tg-a0j4\">0.77</td>\n<td class=\"tg-nx8p\">$$-$$0.44</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>\n<br/><br/>If  $$E_{z{n^{2 + }}/zn}^0$$ = $$-$$ 0.76 V, which cathode will give maximum value of E<sup>o</sup><sub>cell</sub> per electron transferred?",
    "options": [
      "Ag<sup>+</sup>/Ag",
      "Fe<sup>3+</sup>/Fe<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Au<sup>3+</sup>/Au",
      "Fe<sup>2+</sup>/Fe"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "Ag<sup>+</sup>/Ag"
  },
  {
    "id": "swzda7kwskEWBbGApD9uc",
    "question": "In the cell \n<br/><br/>Pt$$\\left| {\\left( s \\right)} \\right|$$H<sub>2</sub>(g,  1 bar)$$\\left| {HCl\\left( {aq} \\right)} \\right|$$AgCl$$\\left| {\\left( s \\right)} \\right|$$Ag(s)|Pt(s) \n<br/><br/>the cell potential is 0.92 V when a 10<sup>–6</sup> molal HCl solution is used. The standard electrode potential of (AgCl/ AgCl<sup>–</sup> ) electrode is : \n<br/>$$\\left\\{ {} \\right.$$Given,  $${{2.303RT} \\over F} = 0.06V$$  at  $$\\left. {298} \\right\\}$$",
    "options": [
      "0.94 V",
      "0.40 V",
      "0.76 V",
      "0.20 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "0.20 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "5BVvstOicz7u7lLOaVjIi",
    "question": "Consider the following reduction processes :\n<br/>Zn<sup>2+</sup> + 2e<sup>–</sup> $$ \\to $$ Zn(s) ; E<sup>o</sup> = – 0.76 V\n<br/>Ca<sup>2+</sup> + 2e<sup>–</sup> $$ \\to $$ Ca(s); E<sup>o</sup> = –2.87 V\n<br/>Mg<sup>2+</sup> + 2e<sup>–</sup> $$ \\to $$ Mg(s) ; E<sup>o</sup> = – 2.36 V\n<br/>Ni<sup>2</sup> + 2e<sup>–</sup> $$ \\to $$ Ni(s) ; E<sup>o</sup> = – 0.25 \n<br/>The reducing power of the metals increases in the order :",
    "options": [
      "Ca &lt; Mg &lt; Zn &lt; Ni ",
      "Ni &lt; Zn &lt; Mg &lt; Ca",
      "Zn &lt; Mg &lt; Ni &lt; Ca",
      "Ca &lt; Zn &lt; Mg &lt; Ni "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "Ni &lt; Zn &lt; Mg &lt; Ca"
  },
  {
    "id": "cXdHzOQUqGMGQWniXAL7v",
    "question": "The anodic half-cell of lead-acid battery is recharged using electricity of 0.05 Faraday. The amount of PbSO<sub>4</sub> electrolyzed in g during the process is : (Molar mass of PbSO<sub>4</sub> = 303 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "22.8",
      "15.2",
      "7.6",
      "11.4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "7.6"
  },
  {
    "id": "Q79m4sOIjASt3kFMip39x",
    "question": "The standard electrode potential $${E^o }$$ and its temperature coefficient $$\\left( {{{d{E^o }} \\over {dT}}} \\right)$$ for a cell are 2V and $$-$$ 5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> VK<sup>$$-$$1</sup> at 300 K respectively. \n<br/>The cell reaction is \n<br/>Zn(s) + Cu<sup>2+</sup> (aq) $$\\buildrel \\, \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ Zn<sup>2+</sup> (aq) + Cu(s)\n<br/><br/>The standard reaction enthalpy ($$\\Delta $$<sub>r</sub>H$${^o }$$) at 300 K in kJ mol<sup>–1</sup> is, [Use R = 8 JK<sup>–1</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup> and F = 96,000C mol<sup>–1</sup>] ",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$ 412.8",
      "$$-$$ 384.0",
      "192.0",
      "206.4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$$-$$ 412.8"
  },
  {
    "id": "anp5e0kXk90TGWLSeijgy2xukg3eyne6",
    "question": "For the given cell :\n<br/><br/>Cu(s) | Cu<sup>2+</sup>(C<sub>1</sub>M) || Cu<sup>2+</sup>(C<sub>2</sub>M) | Cu(s)\n<br/><br/>change in Gibbs energy ($$\\Delta $$G) is negative, if :",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>2</sub> = $$\\sqrt 2 $$C<sub>1</sub>",
      "C<sub>2</sub> = $${{{C_1}} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "C<sub>1</sub> = 2C<sub>2</sub>",
      "C<sub>1</sub> = C<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "C<sub>2</sub> = $$\\sqrt 2 $$C<sub>1</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "pTx77IPXCWk30MCL097k9k2k5dztcnq",
    "question": "Given that the standard potentials (E<sup>o</sup>) of Cu<sup>2+</sup>/Cu and Cu<sup>+</sup>/Cu are 0.34 V and 0.522 V respectively, the E<sup>o</sup> of Cu<sup>2+</sup>/Cu<sup>+</sup> :\n",
    "options": [
      "- 0.182 V",
      "- 0.158 V",
      "0.182 V",
      "+0.158 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "+0.158 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "xyPs8aYT7ryGrF9KBW1klrd7vdi",
    "question": "The electrode potential of M<sup>2+</sup>/M of 3d-series elements shows positive value for :",
    "options": [
      "Zn",
      "Fe",
      "Cu",
      "Co"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "Cu"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56xkq8c",
    "question": "<p>In 3d series, the metal having the highest M<sup>2+</sup>/M standard electrode potential is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Cr",
      "Fe",
      "Cu",
      "Zn"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "Cu"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58dm2tw",
    "question": "<p>The $${\\left( {{{\\partial E} \\over {\\partial T}}} \\right)_P}$$ of different types of half cells are as follows:</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 378px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 84px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 96px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 96px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 102px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">A</th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">B</th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">C</th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">D</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$1 \\times {10^{ - 4}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$2 \\times {10^{ - 4}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$$0.1 \\times {10^{ - 4}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$0.2 \\times {10^{ - 4}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>(Where E is the electromotive force)</p>\n<p>Which of the above half cells would be preferred to be used as reference electrode?</p>",
    "options": [
      "A",
      "B",
      "C",
      "D"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59qx5vl",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of reduction potentials of the following pairs is</p>\n<p>A. Cl<sub>2</sub>/Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup></p>\n<p>B. I<sup>2</sup>/I<sup>$$-$$</sup></p>\n<p>C. Ag<sup>+</sup>/Ag</p>\n<p>D. Na<sup>+</sup>/Na</p>\n<p>E. Li<sup>+</sup>/Li</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "A > C > B > D > E",
      "A > B > C > D > E",
      "A > C > B > E > D",
      "A > B > C > E > D"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "A > C > B > D > E"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w5nm6m",
    "question": "<p>In which of the following half cells, electrochemical reaction is pH dependent?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$Pt\\,|\\,F{e^{3 + }},\\,F{e^{2 + }}$$",
      "$$MnO_4^ - \\,|M{n^{2 + }}$$",
      "$$Ag\\,|\\,AgCl\\,|C{l^{ - 1}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}{F_2}\\,|{F^ - }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$$MnO_4^ - \\,|M{n^{2 + }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldssd0qo",
    "question": "<p>The standard electrode potential $$\\mathrm{(M^{3+}/M^{2+})}$$ for V, Cr, Mn &amp; Co are $$-$$0.26 V, $$-$$0.41 V, + 1.57 V and + 1.97 V, respectively. The metal ions which can liberate $$\\mathrm{H_2}$$ from a dilute acid are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Mn^{2+}}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Co^{2+}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{V^{2+}}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Mn^{2+}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{V^{2+}}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cr^{2+}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Cr^{2+}}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Co^{2+}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{V^{2+}}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cr^{2+}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh03dlfs",
    "question": "<p>The reaction</p>\n<p>$$\\frac{1}{2} \\mathrm{H}_{2}(\\mathrm{~g})+\\mathrm{AgCl}(\\mathrm{s}) \\rightleftharpoons \\mathrm{H}^{+}(\\mathrm{aq})+\\mathrm{Cl}^{-}(\\mathrm{aq})+\\mathrm{Ag}(\\mathrm{s})$$</p>\n<p>occurs in which of the given galvanic cell.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Ag}|\\mathrm{AgCl}(\\mathrm{s})| \\mathrm{KCl}\\left(\\mathrm{sol}^{\\mathrm{n}}\\right)\\left|\\mathrm{AgNO}_{3}\\right| \\mathrm{Ag}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Pt}\\left|\\mathrm{H}_{2}(\\mathrm{~g})\\right| \\mathrm{HCl}\\left(\\mathrm{sol}^{\\mathrm{n}}\\right)|\\mathrm{AgCl}(\\mathrm{s})| \\mathrm{Ag}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Pt}\\left|\\mathrm{H}_{2}(\\mathrm{~g})\\right| \\mathrm{HCl}\\left(\\mathrm{sol}^{\\mathrm{n}}\\right)\\left|\\mathrm{AgNO}_{3}\\left(\\mathrm{sol}^{\\mathrm{n}}\\right)\\right| \\mathrm{Ag}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Pt}\\left|\\mathrm{H}_{2}(\\mathrm{~g})\\right| \\mathrm{KCl}\\left(\\mathrm{sol}^{\\mathrm{n}}\\right)|\\mathrm{AgCl}(\\mathrm{s})| \\mathrm{Ag}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Pt}\\left|\\mathrm{H}_{2}(\\mathrm{~g})\\right| \\mathrm{HCl}\\left(\\mathrm{sol}^{\\mathrm{n}}\\right)|\\mathrm{AgCl}(\\mathrm{s})| \\mathrm{Ag}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh27hyo5",
    "question": "<p>The standard electrode potential of $$\\mathrm{M}^{+} / \\mathrm{M}$$ in aqueous solution does not depend on</p>",
    "options": [
      "Ionisation of a gaseous metal atom",
      " Sublimation of a solid metal",
      "Ionisation of a solid metal atom",
      "Hydration of a gaseous metal ion"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "Ionisation of a solid metal atom"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg81ysc",
    "question": "<p>Reduction potential of ions are given below:</p>\n<p>$$\\begin{array}{ccc}\n\\mathrm{ClO}_4^{-} &amp; \\mathrm{IO}_4^{-} &amp; \\mathrm{BrO}_4^{-} \\\\\n\\mathrm{E}^{\\circ}=1.19 \\mathrm{~V} &amp; \\mathrm{E}^{\\circ}=1.65 \\mathrm{~V} &amp; \\mathrm{E}^{\\circ}=1.74 \\mathrm{~V}\n\\end{array}$$</p>\n<p>The correct order of their oxidising power is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{IO}_4^{-}>\\mathrm{BrO}_4^{-}>\\mathrm{ClO}_4^{-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{BrO}_4^{-}>\\mathrm{ClO}_4^{-}>\\mathrm{IO}_4^{-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{ClO}_4^{-}>\\mathrm{IO}_4^{-}>\\mathrm{BrO}_4^{-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{BrO}_4^{-}>\\mathrm{IO}_4^{-}>\\mathrm{ClO}_4^{-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{BrO}_4^{-}>\\mathrm{IO}_4^{-}>\\mathrm{ClO}_4^{-}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vyqtr",
    "question": "<p>One of the commonly used electrode is calomel electrode. Under which of the following categories, calomel electrode comes?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Metal ion - Metal electrodes\n",
      "Oxidation - Reduction electrodes\n",
      "Metal - Insoluble Salt - Anion electrodes\n",
      "Gas - Ion electrodes"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "Metal - Insoluble Salt - Anion electrodes\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vyr3r",
    "question": "<p>What pressure (bar) of $$\\mathrm{H}_2$$ would be required to make emf of hydrogen electrode zero in pure water at $$25^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.5",
      "$$10^{-14}$$",
      "1",
      "$$10^{-7}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$$10^{-14}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmaj6",
    "question": "<p>The emf of cell $$\\mathrm{Tl}\\left|\\underset{(0.001 \\mathrm{M})}{\\mathrm{Tl}^{+}}\\right| \\underset{(0.01 \\mathrm{M})}{\\mathrm{Cu}^{2+}} \\mid \\mathrm{Cu}$$ is $$0.83 \\mathrm{~V}$$ at $$298 \\mathrm{~K}$$. It could be increased by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "increasing concentration of $$\\mathrm{Tl}^{+}$$ ions\n",
      "increasing concentration of $$\\mathrm{Cu}^{2+}$$ ions\n",
      "increasing concentration of both $$\\mathrm{Tl}^{+}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cu}^{2+}$$ ions\n",
      "decreasing concentration of both $$\\mathrm{Tl}^{+}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cu}^{2+}$$ ions"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "increasing concentration of $$\\mathrm{Cu}^{2+}$$ ions\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmape",
    "question": "<p>The reaction;</p>\n<p>$$\\frac{1}{2} \\mathrm{H}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}+\\mathrm{AgCl}_{(\\mathrm{s})} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{H}_{(\\mathrm{aq})}^{+}+\\mathrm{Cl}_{(\\mathrm{aq})}^{-}+\\mathrm{Ag}_{(\\mathrm{s})}$$</p>\n<p>occurs in which of the following galvanic cell :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Pt}\\left|\\mathrm{H}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}\\right| \\mathrm{HCl}_{(\\text {soln.) }}\\left|\\mathrm{AgNO}_{3(\\mathrm{aq})}\\right| \\mathrm{Ag}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ag}\\left|\\mathrm{AgCl}_{(\\mathrm{s})}\\right| \\mathrm{KCl}_{\\text {(soln.) }}\\left|\\mathrm{AgNO}_{3 \\text { (aq.) }}\\right| \\mathrm{Ag}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Pt}\\left|\\mathrm{H}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}\\right| \\mathrm{KCl}_{(\\text {soln.) }}\\left|\\mathrm{AgCl}_{(\\mathrm{s})}\\right| \\mathrm{Ag}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Pt}\\left|\\mathrm{H}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}\\right| \\mathrm{HCl}_{(\\text {soln. })}\\left|\\mathrm{AgCl}_{(\\mathrm{s})}\\right| \\mathrm{Ag}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Pt}\\left|\\mathrm{H}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}\\right| \\mathrm{HCl}_{(\\text {soln. })}\\left|\\mathrm{AgCl}_{(\\mathrm{s})}\\right| \\mathrm{Ag}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s2pxi",
    "question": "<p>For the electro chemical cell</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{M}\\left|\\mathrm{M}^{2+}\\right||\\mathrm{X}| \\mathrm{X}^{2-}$$</p>\n<p>If $$\\mathrm{E}_{\\left(\\mathrm{M}^{2+} / \\mathrm{M}\\right)}^0=0.46 \\mathrm{~V}$$ and $$\\mathrm{E}_{\\left(\\mathrm{x} / \\mathrm{x}^{2-}\\right)}^0=0.34 \\mathrm{~V}$$.</p>\n<p>Which of the following is correct?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{E}_{\\mathrm{cell}}=0.80 \\mathrm{~V}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{M}+\\mathrm{X} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{M}^{2+}+\\mathrm{X}^{2-}$$ is a spontaneous reaction\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{E}_{\\text {cell }}=-0.80 \\mathrm{~V}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{M}^{2+}+\\mathrm{X}^{2-} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{M}+\\mathrm{X}$$ is a spontaneous reaction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{M}^{2+}+\\mathrm{X}^{2-} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{M}+\\mathrm{X}$$ is a spontaneous reaction"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2a269",
    "question": "<p>How can an electrochemical cell be converted into an electrolytic cell ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Applying an external opposite potential greater than $$\\mathrm{E}_{\\text {cell }}^0$$\n",
      "Exchanging the electrodes at anode and cathode.\n",
      "Applying an external opposite potential lower than $$\\mathrm{E}^0{ }_{\\text {cell }}$$\n",
      "Reversing the flow of ions in salt bridge."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrochemistry",
    "topic": "electrochemical-series,-cell-and-their-emf",
    "solution": "Applying an external opposite potential greater than $$\\mathrm{E}_{\\text {cell }}^0$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "DPHjNRp9HYMpCuwb",
    "question": "The smog is essentially caused by the presence of :",
    "options": [
      "O<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub>c",
      "O<sub>3</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>",
      "Oxides of sulphur and nitrogen",
      "O<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Oxides of sulphur and nitrogen"
  },
  {
    "id": "aQOztvgo4hbyAVSGQc4oN",
    "question": "Identify the pollutant gases largely responsible for the discoloured and\nlustreless nature of marble of the Taj Mahal. \n ",
    "options": [
      "O<sub>3</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "CO<sub>2</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> ",
      "SO<sub>2</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>",
      "SO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "SO<sub>2</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "QKEcqENtJnpSfcXvhegj4",
    "question": "The higher concentration of which gas in air can cause stiffness of flower buds?",
    "options": [
      "CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "SO<sub>2</sub>",
      "NO<sub>2</sub>",
      "CO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "SO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "4LJzstBfaeRJnHJOSuTIa",
    "question": "Taj Mahal is being slowly disfigured and discoloured. This is primarily due to : \n",
    "options": [
      "acid rain",
      "soil pollution",
      "global warming",
      "water pollution "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "acid rain"
  },
  {
    "id": "liHlouQwo3AJFRY2yHKo8",
    "question": "The molecule that has minimum /no role in the formation of photochemical smog, is :",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>2</sub> = O",
      "O<sub>3</sub>",
      "N<sub>2</sub>",
      "NO "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "N<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "CkxJwS2oCs8jm63Zy5fPu",
    "question": "Excessive release of CO<sub>2</sub> into the atomosphere\nresults in :",
    "options": [
      "depletion of ozone",
      "polar vortex",
      "global warming",
      "formation of smog"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "global warming"
  },
  {
    "id": "iYUBBDhoTwMCfsEkn53rsa0w2w9jx111j7y",
    "question": "Air pollution that occurs in sunlight is :",
    "options": [
      "oxidising smog",
      "reducing smog",
      "fog",
      "acid rain"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "oxidising smog"
  },
  {
    "id": "VaOZbTZwaxfCaaoPRD3rsa0w2w9jx4rhrq2",
    "question": "The correct set of species responsible for the photochemical smog is :",
    "options": [
      "NO, NO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub> and hydrocarbons",
      "N<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2 </sub>and hydrocarbons",
      "CO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub> and hydrocarbons",
      "N<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub> and hydrocarbons"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "NO, NO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub> and hydrocarbons"
  },
  {
    "id": "UvgCshfDcKHOwhQU5T3rsa0w2w9jx82y8m9",
    "question": "The primary pollutant that leads to photochemical smog is :",
    "options": [
      "acrolein",
      "ozone",
      "sulphur dioxide",
      "nitrogen oxides "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "nitrogen oxides "
  },
  {
    "id": "fp55glCcOI1w0uaeDPgFI",
    "question": "Peroxyacetyl nitrate (PAN), an eye irritant is produced by : ",
    "options": [
      "classical smog ",
      "acid rain ",
      "photochemical smog ",
      "organic waste "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "photochemical smog "
  },
  {
    "id": "QRHQxJBw8bwRj2HRehjgy2xukf2b9eyf",
    "question": "Thermal power plants can lead to :",
    "options": [
      "Ozone layer depletion",
      "Blue baby syndrome",
      "Eutrophication",
      "Acid rain"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Acid rain"
  },
  {
    "id": "Fbw4wlLdPmIA8b9Oxfjgy2xukf3imnr7",
    "question": "The incorrect statement(s) among (a) – (d)\nregarding acid rain is (are) :\n<br/><br/>(a) It can corrode water pipes.\n<br/>(b) It can damage structures made up of stone.\n<br/>(c) It cannot cause respiratory ailments in animals.\n<br/>(d) It is not harmful for trees",
    "options": [
      "(c) and (d)",
      "(a), (b) and (d)",
      "(c) only",
      "(a), (c) and (d)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "(c) and (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": "6LNV19yErXPc3smIjjjgy2xukevl1i6a",
    "question": "The statement that is not true about ozone is :",
    "options": [
      "In the stratosphere, CFCs release chlorine\nfree radicals (Cl) which reacts with O<sub>3</sub> to\ngive chlorine dioxide radicals",
      "It is a toxic gas and its reaction with NO\ngives NO<sub>2</sub>.",
      "In the atmosphere, it is depleted by CFCs",
      "In the stratosphere, it forms a protective\nshield against UV radiation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "In the stratosphere, CFCs release chlorine\nfree radicals (Cl) which reacts with O<sub>3</sub> to\ngive chlorine dioxide radicals"
  },
  {
    "id": "7NpjlPPfiMF7Sovh0x1kls8x5sw",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : An allotrope of oxygen is an important intermediate in the formation of reducing smog.<br/><br/>Statement II : Gases such as oxides of nitrogen and sulphur present in troposphere contribute to the formation of photochemical smog.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
  },
  {
    "id": "r4Ioich78qXNzBWHRx1klucy0ej",
    "question": "The presence of ozone in troposphere :",
    "options": [
      "protects us from greenhouse effect ",
      "protects us from the UV radiation",
      "protects us from the X-ray radiation",
      "generates photochemical smog"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "generates photochemical smog"
  },
  {
    "id": "UoAPF2DwyhLv80BZsm1kmhsmt0e",
    "question": "The type of pollution that gets increased during the day time and in the presence of O<sub>3</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "Oxidising smog",
      "Global warming",
      "Acid rain",
      "Reducing smog"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Oxidising smog"
  },
  {
    "id": "ixcHp5ekYX9kWuAXsQ1kmj7e1ma",
    "question": "Reducing smog is a mixture of :",
    "options": [
      "Smoke, fog and O<sub>3</sub>",
      "Smoke, fog and N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "Smoke, fog and CH<sub>2</sub> = CH $$-$$ CHO",
      "Smoke, fog and SO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Smoke, fog and SO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krx8sddp",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : Chlorofluoro breakdown by radiation in the visible energy region and release chlorine gas in the atmosphere which then reacts with stratospheric ozone.<br/><br/>Statement II : Atmospheric ozone reacts with nitric oxide to give nitrogen and oxygen gases, which add to the atmosphere.<br/><br/>For the above statements choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and II are false",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and II are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and II are false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktcnmexm",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R). <br/><br/>Assertion (A) : Photochemical smog causes cracking of rubber.<br/><br/>Reason (R) : Presence of ozone, nitric oxide, acrolein, formaldehyde and peroxyacetyl nitrate in photochemical smog makes it oxidizing.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the true explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true.",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false.",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the true explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the true explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktec57j8",
    "question": "The gas 'A' is having very low reactivity reaches to stratosphere. It is non-toxic and non-flammable but dissociated by UV-radiations in stratosphere. The intermediates formed initially from the gas 'A' are :",
    "options": [
      "$$Cl\\mathop O\\limits^ \\bullet   + \\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  {F_2}Cl$$",
      "$$Cl\\mathop O\\limits^ \\bullet   + C\\mathop {{H_3}}\\limits^ \\bullet  $$",
      "$$\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  {H_3} + C\\mathop {{F_2}}\\limits^ \\bullet  Cl$$",
      "$$\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  l + C\\mathop {{F_2}}\\limits^ \\bullet  Cl$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "$$\\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  l + C\\mathop {{F_2}}\\limits^ \\bullet  Cl$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfrst3j",
    "question": "In stratosphere most of the ozone formation is assisted by :",
    "options": [
      "cosmic rays",
      "$$\\gamma$$-rays",
      "ultraviolet radiation",
      "visible radiations"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "ultraviolet radiation"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjvhdl1",
    "question": "The deposition of X and Y on ground surfaces is referred as wet and dry depositions, respectively. X and Y are :",
    "options": [
      "X = Ammonium salts, Y = CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "X = SO<sub>2</sub>, Y = Ammonium salts",
      "X = Ammonium salts, Y = SO<sub>2</sub>",
      "X = CO<sub>2</sub>, Y = SO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "X = Ammonium salts, Y = SO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l549iaam",
    "question": "<p>The acid that is believed to be mainly responsible for the damage of Taj Mahal is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "sulfuric acid.",
      "hydrofluoric acid.",
      "phosphoric acid.",
      "hydrochloric acid."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "sulfuric acid."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55ne09g",
    "question": "<p>Correct statement about photo-chemical smog is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "It occurs in humid climate.",
      "It is a mixture of smoke, fog and SO<sub>2</sub>.",
      "It is reducing smog.",
      "It results from reaction of unsaturated hydrocarbons."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "It results from reaction of unsaturated hydrocarbons."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56xv6cq",
    "question": "<p>On the surface of polar stratospheric clouds, hydrolysis of chlorine nitrite gives A and B while its reaction with its reaction with HCl produces B and C. A, B and C are, respectively :</p>",
    "options": [
      "HOCl, HNO<sub>3</sub>, Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "Cl<sub>2</sub>, HNO<sub>3</sub>, HOCl",
      "HClO<sub>2</sub>, HNO<sub>2</sub>, HOCl",
      "HOCl, HNO<sub>2</sub>, Cl<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "HOCl, HNO<sub>3</sub>, Cl<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57s6my9",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two Statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Classical smog occurs in cool humid climate. It is a reducing mixture of smoke, fog and sulphur dioxide.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Photochemical smog has components, ozone, nitric oxide, acrolein, formaldehyde, PAN etc.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58dx8w3",
    "question": "<p>Polar stratospheric clouds facilitate the formation of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "ClONO<sub>2</sub>",
      "HOCl",
      "ClO",
      "CH<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "HOCl"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6e1c4y6",
    "question": "<p>The photochemical smog does not generally contain :</p>",
    "options": [
      "NO",
      "NO<sub>2</sub>",
      "SO<sub>2</sub>",
      "HCHO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "SO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldohn76e",
    "question": "<p>How can photochemical smog be controlled?</p>",
    "options": [
      "By using catalytic convertors in the automobiles/industry.",
      "By complete combustion of fuel.",
      "By using tall chimneys.",
      "By using catalyst."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "By using catalytic convertors in the automobiles/industry."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr3lqav",
    "question": "<p>Formation of photochemical smog involves the following reaction in which $$\\mathrm{A}, \\mathrm{B}$$ and $$\\mathrm{C}$$ are respectively.</p>\n<p>$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n&amp; \\text { i. } \\mathrm{NO}_{2} \\stackrel{\\mathrm{h} v}{\\longrightarrow} \\mathrm{A}+\\mathrm{B} \\\\\n&amp; \\text { ii. } \\mathrm{B}+\\mathrm{O}_{2} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{C} \\\\\n&amp; \\text { iii. } \\mathrm{A}+\\mathrm{C} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{NO}_{2}+\\mathrm{O}_{2}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{NO}, \\mathrm{O} ~\\& ~\\mathrm{O}_{3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{N}, \\mathrm{O}_{2} ~\\& ~\\mathrm{O}_{3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{O}, \\mathrm{N}_{2} \\mathrm{O} ~\\& ~\\mathrm{NO}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{O}, \\mathrm{NO} ~\\mathrm{\\&} ~\\mathrm{NO}_{3}^{-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{NO}, \\mathrm{O} ~\\& ~\\mathrm{O}_{3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsr2hjm",
    "question": "<p>Correct statement about smog is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "NO$$_2$$ is present in classical smog",
      "Both NO$$_2$$ and SO$$_2$$ are present in classical smog",
      "Photochemical smog has high concentration of oxidizing agents",
      "Classical smog also has high concentration of oxidizing agents"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Photochemical smog has high concentration of oxidizing agents"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwv3imz",
    "question": "<p>Correct statement is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "An average human being consumes more food than air",
      "An average human being consumes 100 times more air than food",
      "An average human being consumes nearly 15 times more air than food",
      "An average human being consumes equal amount of food and air"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "An average human being consumes nearly 15 times more air than food"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyfc02b",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following is true about freons?</p>",
    "options": [
      "These are radicals of chlorine and chlorine monoxide",
      "These are chemicals causing skin cancer",
      "All radicals are called freons",
      "These are chlorofluorocarbon compounds"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "These are chlorofluorocarbon compounds"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgo04s00",
    "question": "The possibility of photochemical smog formation will be minimum at :",
    "options": [
      "Mumbai in May",
      "Kolkata in October",
      "New-Delhi in August (Summer)",
      "Srinagar, Jammu and Kashmir in January"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Srinagar, Jammu and Kashmir in January"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp2n3ge",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following are the Green house gases?</p>\n<p>A. Water vapour</p>\n<p>B. Ozone</p>\n<p>C. I$$_2$$</p>\n<p>D. Molecular hydrogen</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and D only",
      "A and B only",
      "B and C only",
      "C and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "A and B only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq3usi7",
    "question": "<p>The radical which mainly causes ozone depletion in the presence of UV radiations is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{NO}^\\cdot$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{CH}_{3} ^\\cdot$$",
      "$$\\dot{\\mathrm{Cl}}$$",
      "$$\\dot{\\mathrm{O}} \\mathrm{H}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "$$\\dot{\\mathrm{Cl}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsy97rh",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following compounds is an example of Freon?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{F}_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{HF}_{3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{F}_{4}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{Cl}_{2} \\mathrm{F}_{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{Cl}_{2} \\mathrm{F}_{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvuqdzz",
    "question": "<p>The delicate balance of $$\\mathrm{CO}_{2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ is NOT disturbed by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Burning of Coal",
      "Burning of petroleum",
      "Respiration",
      "Deforestation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Respiration"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgys3sb4",
    "question": "<p>Which of these reactions is not a part of breakdown of ozone in stratosphere?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{C{F_2}C{l_2}(g)\\buildrel {uv} \\over\n \\longrightarrow \\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  l(g) + \\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  {F_2}Cl(g)}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{C\\mathop l\\limits^ \\bullet  (g) + {O_3}(g)\\buildrel {} \\over\n \\longrightarrow Cl\\mathop O\\limits^ \\bullet  (g) + {O_2}(g)}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{2Cl\\mathop O\\limits^ \\bullet  \\buildrel {} \\over\n \\longrightarrow Cl{O_2}(g) + C\\mathop l\\limits^ \\bullet  (g)}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Cl\\mathop O\\limits^ \\bullet  (g) + O(g)\\buildrel {} \\over\n \\longrightarrow C\\mathop l\\limits^ \\bullet  (g) + {O_2}(g)}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{2Cl\\mathop O\\limits^ \\bullet  \\buildrel {} \\over\n \\longrightarrow Cl{O_2}(g) + C\\mathop l\\limits^ \\bullet  (g)}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh29h51b",
    "question": "<p>The possibility of photochemical smog formation is more at :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Industrial areas",
      "Himalayan villages in winter",
      "The places with healthy vegetation",
      "Marshy lands"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "air-pollution",
    "solution": "Industrial areas"
  },
  {
    "id": "vl2JhFWgopJNPS0j",
    "question": "Identify the wrong statements in the following :",
    "options": [
      "Chlorofluorocarbons are responsible for ozone layer depletion",
      "Greenhouse effect is responsible for global warming",
      "Ozone layer does not permit infrared radiation from the sun to reach the earth ",
      "Acid rains is mostly because of oxides of nitrogen and sulphur "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "Ozone layer does not permit infrared radiation from the sun to reach the earth "
  },
  {
    "id": "a0rXrzsqTpw83J1Ujrmpe",
    "question": "Which one of the following substances used in dry cleaning is a better strategy to control environmental pollution?",
    "options": [
      "Tetrachloroethylene",
      "Carbon dioxide",
      "Sulphur dioxide",
      "Nitrogen dioxide"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "Carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "id": "50oaAYiPx3AP3qZTRO0LS",
    "question": "Which of the following is a set of greenhouse gases?",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>4</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub> ",
      "O<sub>3</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>, CO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>",
      "O<sub>3</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, Cl<sub>2</sub> ",
      "CO<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>4</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>O, O<sub>3</sub> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "CO<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>4</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>O, O<sub>3</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "RLNhRb6CX8I13lHht8oBi",
    "question": "The reaction that is NOT involved in the ozone layer depletion mechanism in the stratosphere is : \n",
    "options": [
      "$$Cl\\mathop O\\limits^ \\bullet  \\left( g \\right) + O\\left( g \\right) \\to \\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  l\\left( g \\right) + {O_2}(g)$$",
      "$$C{F_2}C{l_2}\\left( g \\right)\\,\\buildrel {uv} \\over\n \\longrightarrow \\mathop {\\,C}\\limits^ \\bullet  l\\left( g \\right) + \\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  {F_2}Cl\\left( g \\right)$$",
      "$$C{H_4} + 2{O_3}\\, \\to \\,3C{H_2} = O + 3{H_2}O$$",
      "$$HOCl\\left( g \\right)\\,\\buildrel {hv} \\over\n \\longrightarrow \\,\\mathop O\\limits^ \\bullet  H\\left( g \\right) + \\mathop C\\limits^ \\bullet  l\\left( g \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "$$C{H_4} + 2{O_3}\\, \\to \\,3C{H_2} = O + 3{H_2}O$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xhI9smiCG3gEv4KCfqC18",
    "question": "<b>Assertion :</b> Ozone is destroyed by CFCs in the upper stratosphere.<br/><br/>\n<b>Reason :</b> Ozone holes increase the amount of UV radiation the earth.",
    "options": [
      "Assertion and reason are both correct, and the reason is the correct explanation for the\nassertion.",
      "Assertion and reason are incorrect.",
      "Assertion and reason are correct but, the reason is not the explanation for the assertion",
      "Assertion is false, but the reason is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "Assertion and reason are correct but, the reason is not the explanation for the assertion"
  },
  {
    "id": "0IyyWxNjhEp6Ibjt9FEi3",
    "question": "Which is wrong with respect to our responsiblity as a human being to protect our environment?",
    "options": [
      "Restricting the use of vehicles",
      "Setting up compost tin in gardens.",
      "Avoiding the use of floodlighted facilities",
      "Using plastic bags."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "Using plastic bags."
  },
  {
    "id": "aoCftFz0i9yWjknXk36xp",
    "question": "The layer of atmosphere between 10 km to\n50 km above the sea level is called as :",
    "options": [
      "mesosphere",
      "thermosphere",
      "troposphere",
      "stratosphere"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "id": "TOm87Abp0qmvBD6ENE3rsa0w2w9jwv4lwq9",
    "question": "The regions of the atmosphere, where clouds form and where we live, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "Stratosphere and Stratosphere",
      "Stratosphere and Troposphere",
      "Troposphere and Stratosphere",
      "Troposphere and Troposphere "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "Troposphere and Troposphere "
  },
  {
    "id": "x2rERT9AylC8LmfMeU7k9k2k5h0xap0",
    "question": "Among the gases (a) – (e), the gases that cause greenhouse effect are :\n<br/>(a) CO<sub>2</sub>\n<br/>(b) H<sub>2</sub>O\n<br/>(c) CFCs\n<br/>(d) O<sub>2</sub>\n<br/>(e) O<sub>3</sub>",
    "options": [
      "(a), (b), (c) and (d)",
      "(a) and (d)",
      "(a), (b), (c) and (e)",
      "(a), (c), (d) and (e)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "(a), (b), (c) and (e)"
  },
  {
    "id": "GSvjWQ33GBjunUigovjgy2xukfc7hvig",
    "question": "The processes of calcination and roasting in\nmetallurgical industries, respectively, can Iead\nto :",
    "options": [
      "Global warming and photochemical smog",
      "Photochemical smog and ozone layer\ndepletion",
      "Photochemical smog and global warming",
      "Global warming and acid rain"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "Global warming and acid rain"
  },
  {
    "id": "z6OHnMskvVRYWd8YTWjgy2xukfjetv4g",
    "question": "The condition that indicates a polluted environment\nis :",
    "options": [
      "BOD value of 5 ppm",
      "eutrophication",
      "0.03% of CO<sub>2</sub> in the atmosphere",
      "pH of rain water to be 5.6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "eutrophication"
  },
  {
    "id": "NmeOuE6SmdsVKrRsK41klrdx8mx",
    "question": "The gas released during anaerobic degradation of vegetation may lead to :",
    "options": [
      "Ozone hole",
      "Corrosion of metals",
      "Acid rain",
      "Global warming and cancer"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "Global warming and cancer"
  },
  {
    "id": "ucnbCLjLiy3wI3QoNz1kltaup4t",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : The pH of rain water is normally 5.6.<br/><br/>Statement II : If the pH of rain water drops below 5.6, it is called acid rain.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
  },
  {
    "id": "UZAkLUdt9D9tnCL0ud1kmitc0bl",
    "question": "The green house gas/es is (are) :<br/><br/>(A) Carbon dioxide<br/><br/>(B) Oxygen<br/><br/>(C) Water vapour<br/><br/>(D) Methane<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A) and (C) only",
      "(A) and (B) only",
      "(A), (C) and (D) only",
      "(A) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "(A), (C) and (D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "6eWQrdaof7JXRWSDGY1kmlmun7v",
    "question": "The statements that are TRUE :<br/><br/>(A) Methane leads to both global warming and photochemical smog<br/><br/>(B) Methane is generated from paddy fields<br/><br/>(C) Methane is a stronger global warming gas than CO<sub>2</sub><br/><br/>(D) Methane is a part of reducing smog<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A), (B), (C) only",
      "(A) and (B) only",
      "(B), (C), (D) only",
      "(A), (B), (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "(A), (B), (C) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "mtBKU6RyqQW1aGlp4c1kmlzs6hv",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/><b>Statement I</b> : Non-biodegradable wastes are generated by the thermal power plants.<br/><br/><b>Statement II</b> : Bio-degradable detergents leads to eutrophication.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true.",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true.",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but statement is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "Both statement I and statement II are true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1krrjbrej",
    "question": "Which one of the following gases is reported to retard photosynthesis?",
    "options": [
      "CO",
      "CFCs",
      "CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "NO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "NO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfsctvl",
    "question": "Which one of the following is used to remove most of plutonium from spent nuclear fuel?",
    "options": [
      "ClF<sub>3</sub>",
      "O<sub>2</sub>F<sub>2</sub>",
      "I<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>",
      "BrO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "O<sub>2</sub>F<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bdctfh",
    "question": "<p>Some gases are responsible for heating of atmosphere (green house effect). Identify from the following the gaseous species which does not cause it.</p>",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>4</sub>",
      "O<sub>3</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "N<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "N<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i5d1dy",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I<br/><br/>Pollutant</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II<br/><br/>Source</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Microorganisms</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Strip mining</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Plant nutrients</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Domestic sewage</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Toxic heavy metals</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Chemical fertilizer</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Sediment</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Chemical factory</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV D-III",
      "A-I, B-IV, C-II, D-III",
      "A-I, B-IV, C-III, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kpwdea",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : The non bio-degradable fly ash and slag from steel industry can be used by cement industry.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The fuel obtained from plastic waste is lead free.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldo14hf1",
    "question": "<p>The industrial activity held least responsible for global warming is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "manufacturing of cement",
      "Electricity generation in thermal power plants",
      "steel manufacturing",
      "Industrial production of urea"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "Industrial production of urea"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrkihse",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 616px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 246px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 270px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Nitrogen oxides in air</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Eutrophication</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Methane in air</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">pH of rain water becomes 5.6</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Carbon dioxide</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Global warming</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Phosphate fertilisers in water</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Acid rain</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-III, D-I",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgygyxfc",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 625px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 267px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List I<br/>Industry</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List II<br/>Waste Generated</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Steel plants</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Gypsum</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Thermal power plants</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Fly ash</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Fertilizer industries</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Slag</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Paper mills</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Bio-degradable wastes</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(II), (C)-(I), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(III), (C)-(IV), (D)-(I)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "environmental-pollution",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(II), (C)-(I), (D)-(IV)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p7b23h",
    "question": "<p>Which among the following pairs has only herbicides?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Aldrin and Dieldrin",
      "Sodium chlorate and Aldrin",
      "Sodium arsinate and Dieldrin",
      "Sodium chlorate and sodium arsinite"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "soil-pollution",
    "solution": "Sodium chlorate and sodium arsinite"
  },
  {
    "id": "iW7XTRothg6P9RbLOTWOs",
    "question": "BOD stands for :",
    "options": [
      "Biological Oxygen Demand",
      "Bacterial Oxidation Demand",
      "Biochemical Oxygen Demand",
      "Biochemical Oxidation Demand"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "Biochemical Oxygen Demand"
  },
  {
    "id": "k1eF2Ps0qO9LFyR9",
    "question": "The concentration of fluoride, lead, nitrate and iron in a water sample from an underground lake was found\nto be 1000 ppb, 40 ppb, 100 ppm and 0.2 ppm, respectively. This water is unsuitable for drinking due to\nhigh concentration of :",
    "options": [
      "Lead",
      "Nitrate",
      "Iron",
      "Fluoride"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "Nitrate"
  },
  {
    "id": "S9yxTmxEHaHVB8Va",
    "question": "A water sample has ppm level concentration of following anions<br/>\nF<sup>-</sup> = 10; $$SO_4^{2-}$$ = 100; $$NO_3^-$$ = 50<br/>\nThe anion/anions that make/makes the water sample unsuitable for drinking is/are :",
    "options": [
      "both $$SO_4^{2-}$$ and $$NO_3^-$$",
      "only F<sup>-</sup>",
      "only $$SO_4^{2-}$$\n",
      "only $$NO_3^-$$\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "only F<sup>-</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "cp0XElnr3HAHyjDD",
    "question": "The recommended concentration of fluoride ion in drinking water is up to 1 ppm as fluoride ion is required\nto make teeth enamel harder by converting <br/>[3Ca<sub>3</sub> (PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>.Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>] to  ",
    "options": [
      "[3{Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>}. CaF<sub>2</sub>] ",
      "[CaF<sub>2</sub>] \n",
      "[3(CaF<sub>2</sub>). Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>] ",
      "[3Ca<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>. CaF<sub>2</sub>] "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "[3Ca<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>. CaF<sub>2</sub>] "
  },
  {
    "id": "GOLG0wmJiyEAm7QYJscUq",
    "question": "Biochemical Oxygen Demand (BOD) value can be a measure of water pollution caused by the organic matter. Which of the following statements is correct ? ",
    "options": [
      "Aerobic bacteria decrease the BOD value.",
      "Anaerobic bacteria increase the BOD value. ",
      "Clean water has BOD value higher than 10 ppm.",
      "Polluted water has BOD value higher than 10 ppm."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "Polluted water has BOD value higher than 10 ppm."
  },
  {
    "id": "QffYcH0xtL1fxMF01Zz7m",
    "question": "A water sample has ppm level concentration of the following metals : Fe = 0.2; Mn = 5.0; Cu = 3.0; Zn = 5.0. The metal that makes the water sample unsuitable for drinking is : ",
    "options": [
      "Cu",
      "Mn",
      "Fe",
      "Zn"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "Mn"
  },
  {
    "id": "niGPN9aBAYClqm1AZAyI9",
    "question": "Which of the following conditions in drinking water causes methemoglobinemia?",
    "options": [
      "&gt; 50 ppm of lead",
      "&gt; 50 ppm of chloride",
      "&gt; 50 ppm of nitrate",
      "&gt; 100 ppm of sulphate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "&gt; 50 ppm of nitrate"
  },
  {
    "id": "m1hf1bAWUFJwqwnq3byGL",
    "question": "Water filled in two glasses A and B have BOD values of 10 and 20, respectively. The correct statement regarding them, is :",
    "options": [
      "B is more polluted than A. ",
      "A is suitable for drinking, whereas B is not .",
      "Both A and B are suitable for dirnking ",
      "A is more polluted than B. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "B is more polluted than A. "
  },
  {
    "id": "YGp4iB1XX3gJaNtjH7ad1",
    "question": "The concentration of dissolved oxygen (DO) in cold water can go upto : ",
    "options": [
      "14 ppm",
      "16 ppm",
      "8 ppm",
      "10 ppm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "10 ppm"
  },
  {
    "id": "Qr5SrWsLd7DpZ1kbDrhtZ",
    "question": "Water samples with BOD values of 4 ppm and 18 ppm, respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "Clean and Highly polluted",
      "Highly polluted and Clean ",
      "Highly polluted and Highly polluted ",
      "Clean and Clean \n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "Clean and Highly polluted"
  },
  {
    "id": "AozPF8ZSoswuudQlJSMNk",
    "question": "The maximum prescribed concentration of\ncopper in drinking water is :",
    "options": [
      "3 ppm",
      "5 ppm",
      "0.5 ppm",
      "0.05 ppm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "3 ppm"
  },
  {
    "id": "Q1Y6jD3B7vnXND9zEC7k9k2k5lkyppv",
    "question": "Biochemical Oxygen Demand (BOD) is the\namount of oxygen required (in ppm) :",
    "options": [
      "for sustaining life in a water body.",
      "by anaerobic bacteria to breakdown\ninorganic waste present in a water body.",
      "for the photochemical breakdown of waste\npresent in 1 m<sup>3</sup> volume of a water body.",
      "by bacteria to break-down organic waste in\na certain volume of a water sample."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "by bacteria to break-down organic waste in\na certain volume of a water sample."
  },
  {
    "id": "8AdxD96kvH0Ab97gkxjgy2xukftduzpi",
    "question": "The presence of soluble fluoride ion upto\n1 ppm concentration in drinking water, is :",
    "options": [
      "safe for teeth",
      "harmful to skin",
      "harmful for teeth",
      "harmful to bones"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "safe for teeth"
  },
  {
    "id": "RJWVxmhQZc4lge6b0d1klrtvfmr",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : The value of the parameter \"Biochemical Oxygen Demand (BOD)\" is important for survival of aquatic life.<br/><br/>Statement II : The optimum value of BOD is 6.5 ppm.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "kwxRPiWONUdpfoDiLf1kmkiv11z",
    "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is (are) incorrect reason for eutrophication?<br/><br/>(A) excess usage of fertilisers<br/><br/>(B) excess usage of detergents<br/><br/>(C) dense plant population in water bodies<br/><br/>(D) lack of nutrients in water bodies that prevent plant growth<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A) Only",
      "(B) and (D) only",
      "(C) only",
      "(D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "(D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz0lrqx",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is NOT correct?",
    "options": [
      "Eutrophication indicates that water body is polluted",
      "The dissolved oxygen concentration below 6 ppm inhibits fish growth",
      "Eutrophication leads to increase in the oxygen level in water",
      "Eutrophication leads to anaerobic conditions"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "Eutrophication leads to increase in the oxygen level in water"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktb4hx27",
    "question": "The conversion of hydroxyapatite occurs due to presence of F<sup>$$-$$</sup> ions in water. The correct formula of hydroxyapatite is :",
    "options": [
      "[3Ca<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub> . Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[3Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub> . CaF<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[Ca<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub> . CaF<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[3Ca<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub> . CaF<sub>2</sub>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "[3Ca<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub> . Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktif4n8z",
    "question": "BOD values (in ppm) for clean water (A) and polluted water (B) are expected respectively :",
    "options": [
      "A &gt; 50, B &lt; 27",
      "A &gt; 25, B &lt; 17",
      "A &lt; 5, B &gt; 17",
      "A &gt; 15, B &gt; 47"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "A &lt; 5, B &gt; 17"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn009m1",
    "question": "Water sample is called cleanest on the basis of which one of the BOD values given below :",
    "options": [
      "11 ppm",
      "15 ppm",
      "3 ppm",
      "21 ppm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "3 ppm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58jlm5s",
    "question": "<p>The measured BOD values for four different water samples (A-D) are as follows: A = 3 ppm; B = 18 ppm; C = 21 ppm; D = 4 ppm. The water samples which can be called as highly polluted with organic wastes, are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and B",
      "A and D",
      "B and C",
      "B and D"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "B and C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59r386l",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Polluted water may have a value of BOD of the order of 17 ppm.</p>\n<p>Reason R : BOD is a measure of oxygen required to oxidise both the bio-degradable an non-biodegradable organic material in water.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is correct but R is not correct.",
      "A is not correct but R is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "A is correct but R is not correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5am0ld2",
    "question": "<p>The eutrophication of water body results in :</p>",
    "options": [
      "loss of Biodiversity.",
      "breakdown of organic matter.",
      "increase in biodiversity.",
      "decrease in BOD."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "loss of Biodiversity."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jlo7ik",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I<br/><br/>Pollutant</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II<br/><br/>Disease/sickness</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Sulphate (&gt;500 ppm)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Methemoglobinemia</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Nitrate (&gt;50 ppm)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Brown mottling of teeth</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Lead (&gt;50 ppb)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Laxative effect</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Fluoride (&gt;2 ppm)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Kidney damage</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III",
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mczllm",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : In polluted water values of both dissolved oxygen and $$\\mathrm{BOD}$$ are very low.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Eutrophication results in decrease in the amount of dissolved oxygen.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqwm6up",
    "question": "The water quality of a pond was analyzed and its BOD was found to be 4. The pond has :",
    "options": [
      "Very clean water",
      "Highly polluted water\n",
      "Water has high amount of fluoride compounds\n",
      "Slightly polluted water"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "Very clean water"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsd8lk5",
    "question": "<p>The concentration of dissolved Oxygen in water for growth of fish should be more than $$\\mathrm{\\underline X }$$ ppm and Biochemical Oxygen Demand in clean water should be less than $$\\mathrm{\\underline Y }$$ ppm. X and Y in ppm are, respectively.</p>",
    "options": [
      "<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 134px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 67px\">\n<col style=\"width: 67px\">\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{X}$$</th>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{Y}$$</th>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">4</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">15</td>\n  </tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
      "<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 134px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 67px\">\n<col style=\"width: 67px\">\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{X}$$</th>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{Y}$$</th>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">4</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">8</td>\n  </tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
      "<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 134px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 67px\">\n<col style=\"width: 67px\">\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{X}$$</th>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{Y}$$</th>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">6</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">12</td>\n  </tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
      "<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 134px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 67px\">\n<col style=\"width: 67px\">\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{X}$$</th>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{Y}$$</th>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">6</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">5</td>\n  </tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 134px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 67px\">\n<col style=\"width: 67px\">\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{X}$$</th>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\">$$\\mathrm{Y}$$</th>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">6</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">5</td>\n  </tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguznvso",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : If BOD is 4 ppm and dissolved oxygen is 8 ppm, then it is a good quality water.</p>\n<p>Statement II : If the concentration of zinc and nitrate salts are $$5 ~\\mathrm{ppm}$$ each, then it can be a good quality water.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Both the statements I and II are incorrect",
      "Both the statements I and II are correct",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "Both the statements I and II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh02vu8k",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II:</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 658px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 300px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Species)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Maximum allowed concentration in ppm in drinking water)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{F^-}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">&lt; 50 ppm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{SO_4^{2-}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">&lt; 5 ppm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{NO_3^-}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">&lt; 2 ppm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Zn}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">&lt; 500 ppm</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-I, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-IV C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "environmental-chemistry",
    "topic": "water-pollution",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV C-I, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktcno560",
    "question": "The interaction energy of London forces between two particles is proportional to r<sup>x</sup>, where r is the distance between the particles. The value of x is :",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "$$-$$3",
      "$$-$$6",
      "6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "critical-phenomenon-and-liquefaction",
    "solution": "$$-$$6"
  },
  {
    "id": "DMBvher3DUF68WQz",
    "question": "Equal masses of methane and oxygen are mixed in an empty container at 25<sup>o</sup>C. The fraction of the\ntotal pressure exerted by oxygen is ",
    "options": [
      "2/3",
      "1/2",
      "1/3 $$\\times$$ 273/298",
      "1/3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "dalton's-law-of-partial-pressure",
    "solution": "1/3"
  },
  {
    "id": "77nv9vOPrUaHclITGgjgy2xukf3isiq9",
    "question": "A mixture of one mole each of H<sub>2</sub>\n, He and O<sub>2</sub>\neach are enclosed in a cylinder of volume V at\ntemperature T. If the partial pressure of H<sub>2</sub>\n is 2 atm, the total pressure of the gases in the\ncylinder is :",
    "options": [
      "14 atm",
      "38 atm",
      "6 atm",
      "22 atm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "dalton's-law-of-partial-pressure",
    "solution": "6 atm"
  },
  {
    "id": "bnfpDkJBY2Dw8be5",
    "question": "Value of gas constant R is",
    "options": [
      "0.082 litre atm",
      "0.987 cal mol<sup>-1</sup> K<sup>-1</sup>",
      "8.3 J mol<sup>-1</sup> K<sup>-1</sup>",
      "83 erg mol<sup>-1</sup> K<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "ideal-gas-equation",
    "solution": "8.3 J mol<sup>-1</sup> K<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "2GzdbgvmtegiLSYz",
    "question": "For an ideal gas, number of moles per litre in terms of its pressure P, gas constant R and temperature T is",
    "options": [
      "PT/R",
      "PRT",
      "P/RT",
      "RT/P"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "ideal-gas-equation",
    "solution": "P/RT"
  },
  {
    "id": "3OZcQb16VIBDWDlM",
    "question": "If 10<sup>–4</sup> dm<sup>3</sup> of water is introduced into a 1.0 dm<sup>3</sup> flask to 300 K, how many moles of water are in the vapour phase when equilibrium is established ?<br/>\n(Given : Vapour pressure of H<sub>2</sub>O at 300 K is 3170 Pa ; R = 8.314 J K<sup>–1</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "5.56 x 10<sup>–3</sup> mol",
      "1.53 x 10<sup>–2</sup> mol",
      "4.46 x 10<sup>–2</sup> mol",
      "1.27 x 10<sup>–3</sup> mol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "ideal-gas-equation",
    "solution": "1.27 x 10<sup>–3</sup> mol"
  },
  {
    "id": "Oq5IzlRFMYv3tMatp6wxD",
    "question": "At 300 K, the density of a certain gaseous molecule at 2 bar is double to that of\ndinitrogen (N<sub>2</sub> ) at 4 bar. The molar mass of gaseous molecule is :",
    "options": [
      "28 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "56 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "112 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "224 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "ideal-gas-equation",
    "solution": "112 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "2Or9MoZos2yfEuzQOB9Zh",
    "question": "Assuming ideal gas behaviour, the ratio of density of ammonia to that of hydrogen chloride at same temperature and pressure is : (Atomic wt. of Cl = 35.5 u) ",
    "options": [
      "1.46",
      "0.46",
      "1.64",
      "0.64"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "ideal-gas-equation",
    "solution": "0.46"
  },
  {
    "id": "vE4bST8NYSTze4j45VUIN",
    "question": "0.5 moles of gas A and x moles of gas B exert a pressure of 200 Pa in a container of volume 10 m<sup>3</sup> at 1000 K. Given R is the gas constant in JK<sup>$$-$$1</sup>mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, x is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{2R} \\over {4 + R}}$$",
      "$${{2R} \\over {4 - R}}$$",
      "$${{4 + R} \\over {2R}}$$",
      "$${{4 - R} \\over {2R}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "ideal-gas-equation",
    "solution": "$${{4 - R} \\over {2R}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "BB3wHc6gG9Fb1ws3hlaTX",
    "question": "An open vessel at 27<sup>o</sup>C is heated until two fifth of the air (assumed as an ideal gas) it has escaped from the vessel assuming that the volume of the vessel remains constant, the temperature at which the vessel has been\nheated is - ",
    "options": [
      "750 K",
      "500<sup>o</sup>C",
      "750<sup>o</sup>C",
      "500 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "ideal-gas-equation",
    "solution": "500 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58dbw4q",
    "question": "<p>An evacuated glass vessel weighs 40.0 g when empty, 135.0 g when filled with a liquid of density 0.95 g mL<sup>$$-$$1</sup> and 40.5 g when filled with an ideal gas at 0.82 atm at 250 K. The molar mass of the gas in g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup> is :</p>\n<p>(Given : R = 0.082 L atm K<sup>$$-$$1</sup> mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "35",
      "50",
      "75",
      "125"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "ideal-gas-equation",
    "solution": "125"
  },
  {
    "id": "YNM112mAYUdTASsZ",
    "question": "Kinetic theory of gases proves",
    "options": [
      "only Boyle's law",
      "only Charle's law",
      "only Avogadro's law",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases",
    "solution": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "id": "rTopFGW9CaQ21Prc",
    "question": "According to the kinetic theory of gases, in an ideal gas, between two successive collisions of a gas molecule travels",
    "options": [
      "in a wavy path",
      "in a straight line path",
      "with an accelerated velocity",
      "in a circular path"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases",
    "solution": "in a straight line path"
  },
  {
    "id": "o4YK11wxjbidjZOg",
    "question": "As the temperature is raised from 20°C to 40°C, the average kinetic energy of neon atoms\nchanges by a factor of which of the following? ",
    "options": [
      "1/2",
      "2",
      "$$313\\over293$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{313\\over293}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases",
    "solution": "$$313\\over293$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "0QEESL1DkNne0soL",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is NOT true about the effect of an increase in\ntemperature on the distribution of molecular speeds in a gas? ",
    "options": [
      "The most probable speed increases",
      "The fraction of the molecules with the most probable speed increases ",
      "The distribution becomes broader",
      "The area under the distribution curve remains the same as under the lower temperature  "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "maxwell's-distribution-of-speed",
    "solution": "The fraction of the molecules with the most probable speed increases "
  },
  {
    "id": "BIFrcTtTLO9Ostri",
    "question": "For gaseous state, if most probable speed is denoted by C*, average speed by $$\\mathop C\\limits^{\\_\\_} $$  and mean square speed by\nC, then for a large number of molecules the ratios of these speeds are:",
    "options": [
      "C*: $$\\mathop C\\limits^{\\_\\_} $$  : C = 1.128 : 1.225 : 1",
      "C*: $$\\mathop C\\limits^{\\_\\_} $$  : C = 1.225 : 1.128  : 1",
      "C*: $$\\mathop C\\limits^{\\_\\_} $$  : C = 1 : 1.225 : 1.128",
      "C*: $$\\mathop C\\limits^{\\_\\_} $$  : C =  1 : 1.128 : 1.225 "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "maxwell's-distribution-of-speed",
    "solution": "C*: $$\\mathop C\\limits^{\\_\\_} $$  : C =  1 : 1.128 : 1.225 "
  },
  {
    "id": "0tp9tc6B8AmlToQxtzTqv",
    "question": "Initially, the <i>root mean square (rms)</i> velocity of N<sub>2</sub> molecules at certain temperature is $$u$$. If this temperature is doubled and all the nitrogen molecules dissociate into nitrogen atoms, then the new <i>rms</i> velocity will be :\n",
    "options": [
      "u/2",
      "2u",
      "4u",
      "14u"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "maxwell's-distribution-of-speed",
    "solution": "2u"
  },
  {
    "id": "x7HuWP5747KtQSI1",
    "question": "In Van der Waals equation of state of the gas law, the constant ‘b’ is a measure of ",
    "options": [
      "intermolecular repulsions",
      "intermolecular collisions per unit volume ",
      "Volume occupied by the molecules ",
      "intermolecular attraction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "Volume occupied by the molecules "
  },
  {
    "id": "gFsQR0V4Jf56mxih",
    "question": "'a’ and `b’ are van der Waals’ constants for gases. Chlorine is more easily liquefied than ethane because",
    "options": [
      "a and b for Cl<sub>2</sub> &lt; a and b for C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>",
      "a and b for Cl<sub>2</sub> &gt; a and b for C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>",
      "a for Cl<sub>2</sub> &gt; a for C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub> and b Cl<sub>2</sub> &lt; b for C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>",
      "a for Cl<sub>2</sub> &lt; a for C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub> and b Cl<sub>2</sub> &gt; b for C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "a for Cl<sub>2</sub> &gt; a for C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub> and b Cl<sub>2</sub> &lt; b for C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "i4gZ3uMYLOWd4C7v",
    "question": "The compressibility factor for a real gas at high pressure is :",
    "options": [
      "1 + RT/pb",
      "1",
      "1 + pb/RT",
      "1–pb/RT"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "1 + pb/RT"
  },
  {
    "id": "ak8xAvo1s8Cjz97o",
    "question": "If Z is a compressibility factor, van der Waals equation at low pressure can be written as:",
    "options": [
      "Z = 1 + $$RT \\over Pb$$",
      "Z = 1 - $$a \\over VRT$$",
      "Z = 1 - $$Pb \\over RT$$",
      "Z = 1 + $$Pb \\over RT$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "Z = 1 - $$a \\over VRT$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "qiBbj74PfU5N8QYN4g96q",
    "question": "At very high pressures, the compressibility factor of one mole of a gas is given by : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{pb} \\over {RT}}$$",
      "1 + $${{pb} \\over {RT}}$$",
      "1 $$-$$ $${{pb} \\over {RT}}$$",
      "1 $$-$$ $${b \\over {\\left( {VRT} \\right)}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "1 + $${{pb} \\over {RT}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "GpGK1lJCWYdi3xb80fgaT",
    "question": "Among the following, the incorrect statement is :",
    "options": [
      "At low pressure, real gases show ideal behaviour.",
      "At very low temperature, real gases show ideal behaviour.",
      "At very large volume, real gases show ideal behaviour.",
      "At Boyle’s temperature, real gases show ideal behaviour."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "At very low temperature, real gases show ideal behaviour."
  },
  {
    "id": "vIsgg4CaJHBxCcSkPQVT6",
    "question": "Consider the van der Waals constants, a and b,\nfor the following gases.<br/><br/>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:8px 12px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:8px 12px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-s6z2{text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\">Gas</th>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\">Ar</th>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\">Ne</th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">Kr</th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">Xe</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">a/ (atm dm<sup>6</sup> mol<sup>–2</sup>)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">1.3</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">0.2</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">5.1</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">4.1</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">b/ (10<sup>–2</sup> dm<sup>3</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">3.2</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">1.7</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">1.0</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">5.0</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>\n<br/>Which gas is expected to have the highest\ncritical temperature?",
    "options": [
      "Ne",
      "Kr",
      "Xe",
      "Ar"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "Kr"
  },
  {
    "id": "pclPmoSxC8nSmkWpQe3rsa0w2w9jwv9lvk5",
    "question": "Consider the following table :<br/><br/>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border-color:#9ABAD9;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#9ABAD9;color:#444;background-color:#EBF5FF;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#9ABAD9;color:#fff;background-color:#409cff;}\n.tg .tg-s6z2{text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\">Gas</th>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\">a/(k Pa dm<sup>6</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>) </th>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\">b/(dm<sup>3</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">A</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">642.32</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">0.05196</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">B</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">155.21</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">0.04136</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">C</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">431.91</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">0.05196</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">D</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">155.21</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">0.4382</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>\n<br/>a and b are vander Waals constants. The correct statement about the gases is :",
    "options": [
      "Gas C will occupy more volume than gas A; gas B will be more compressible than gas D",
      "Gas C will occupy lesser volume than gas A; gas B will be more compressible than gas D",
      "Gas C will occupy lesser volume than gas A; gas B will be lesser compressible than gas D",
      "Gas C will occupy more volume than gas A; gas B will be lesser compressible than gas D"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "Gas C will occupy more volume than gas A; gas B will be more compressible than gas D"
  },
  {
    "id": "O0U4zebzX3GWOMMTmksyG",
    "question": "At a given temperature T, gases Ne, Ar, Xe and\nKr are found to deviate from ideal gas\nbehaviour. Their equation of state is given as<br/><br/>\n$$p = {{RT} \\over {V - b}}$$ at T.<br/><br/>\nHere, b is the van der Waals constant. Which\ngas will exhibit steepest increase in the plot of\nZ (compression factor) vs p?",
    "options": [
      "Xe",
      "Ne",
      "Ar",
      "Kr"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "Xe"
  },
  {
    "id": "Exstt9D4roYvshgtVYkK6",
    "question": "The volume of gas A is twice than that of gas B. The compressibility factor of gas A is thrice than that of gas B at same temperature. The pressures of the gases for equal number of moles are - ",
    "options": [
      "2P<sub>A</sub> = 3P<sub>B</sub> ",
      "3P<sub>A</sub> = 2P<sub>B</sub> ",
      "P<sub>A</sub> = 3P<sub>B</sub> ",
      "P<sub>A</sub> = 2P<sub>B</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "2P<sub>A</sub> = 3P<sub>B</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktecqjv7",
    "question": "The unit of the van der Waals gas equation parameter 'a' in $$\\left( {P + {{a{n^2}} \\over {{V^2}}}} \\right)(V - nb) = nRT$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "kg m s<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "dm<sup>3</sup> mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "kg m s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "atm dm<sup>6</sup> mol<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "atm dm<sup>6</sup> mol<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyry0ih",
    "question": "<p>Arrange the following gases in increasing order of van der Waals constant 'a'</p>\n<p>A. Ar</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{CH}_{4}$$</p>\n<p>C. $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{C}_{6} \\mathrm{H}_{6}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct option from the following.</p>",
    "options": [
      "D, C, B and A",
      "A, B, C and D",
      "B, C, D and A",
      "C, D, B and A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gaseous-state",
    "topic": "real-gas-and-van-der-wall's-equation",
    "solution": "A, B, C and D"
  },
  {
    "id": "YhIafiSYsm9Ny31L",
    "question": "The reaction :<br/>\n$${(CH)_3}C - Br\\buildrel {{H_2}O} \\over\n \\longrightarrow {(CH)_3}C - OH$$",
    "options": [
      "elimination reaction",
      "substitution reaction",
      "free radical reaction",
      "displacement reaction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "substitution reaction"
  },
  {
    "id": "GhBslikI5bMiNL8W",
    "question": "Tertiary alkyl halides are practically inert to substitution by S<sub>N</sub>2 mechanism because of ",
    "options": [
      "insolubility",
      "instability",
      "inductive effect",
      "steric hindrance"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "steric hindrance"
  },
  {
    "id": "QFmlPkcfmI30FWXJ",
    "question": "Alkyl halides react with dialkyl copper reagents to give ",
    "options": [
      "alkenes",
      "alkyl copper halides",
      "alkanes",
      "alkenyl halides"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "alkanes"
  },
  {
    "id": "wPDTgc0fl8jSpE8V",
    "question": "Elimination of bromine from 2-bromobutane results in the formation of- ",
    "options": [
      "equimolar mixture of 1 and 2-butene",
      "predominantly 2-butene",
      "predominantly 1-butene",
      "predominantly 2-butyne "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "predominantly 2-butene"
  },
  {
    "id": "fp3riE18xnsMsA7D",
    "question": "Reaction of trans-2-phenyl-1-bromocyclopentane on reaction with alcoholic KOH produces",
    "options": [
      "4-phenylcyclopentene",
      "2-phenylcyclopentene",
      "1-phenylcyclopentene ",
      "3-phenylcyclopentene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "3-phenylcyclopentene"
  },
  {
    "id": "nuKrwIrs6tRqH8DK",
    "question": "Which of the following is the correct order of decreasing S<sub>N</sub>2 reactivity? ",
    "options": [
      "RCH<sub>2</sub>X &gt; R<sub>3</sub>CX &gt; R<sub>2</sub>CHX",
      "RCH<sub>2</sub>X &gt; R<sub>2</sub>CHX &gt;  \nR<sub>3</sub>CX",
      "R<sub>3</sub>CX &gt;  R<sub>2</sub>CHX &gt; RCH<sub>2</sub>X",
      "R<sub>2</sub>CHX &gt; R<sub>3</sub>CX &gt; RCH<sub>2</sub>X"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "RCH<sub>2</sub>X &gt; R<sub>2</sub>CHX &gt;  \nR<sub>3</sub>CX"
  },
  {
    "id": "kB4ViC44AFYSfszW",
    "question": "The organic chloro compound, which shows complete stereochemical inversion during a S<sub>N</sub>2 reaction,\nis",
    "options": [
      "(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CHC",
      "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>CCl ",
      "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CHCl ",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>Cl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>Cl"
  },
  {
    "id": "VRIH3zWFUwBDFFyq",
    "question": "How many chiral compounds are possible on monochlorination of 2–methyl butane ?",
    "options": [
      "8",
      "2",
      "4",
      "6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "LVPpCWM1PCNSfEFm",
    "question": "In S<sub>N</sub>2 reactions, the correct order of reactivity for the following compounds:<br/>\nCH<sub>3</sub>Cl, CH<sub>3</sub>CH\n<sub>2</sub>Cl, (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CHCl and (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>CCl is: ",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>Cl &gt; CH<sub>3</sub>Cl &gt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CHCl &gt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>CCl",
      "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CHCl &gt; CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>Cl &gt; CH<sub>3</sub>Cl &gt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>CCl",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>Cl &gt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CHCl &gt; CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>Cl &gt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>CCl",
      "CH3<sub></sub>Cl &gt; CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>Cl &gt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CHCl &gt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>CCl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "CH3<sub></sub>Cl &gt; CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>Cl &gt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CHCl &gt; (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>CCl"
  },
  {
    "id": "7dmKpmZoRmckHRGv",
    "question": "The synthesis of alkyl fluorides is best accomplished by:",
    "options": [
      "Sandmeyer’s reaction",
      "Finkelstein reaction",
      "Swarts reaction",
      "Free radical fluorination"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "Swarts reaction"
  },
  {
    "id": "ubQhYAu8evYWN8lF",
    "question": "3-Methyl-pent-2-ene on reaction with HBr in presence of peroxide forms an addition product. The number\nof possible stereoisomers for the product is :",
    "options": [
      "Zero",
      "Two",
      "Four",
      "Six"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "Four"
  },
  {
    "id": "yJbMVAdqAXHeDT2BqQ3rsa0w2w9jx97q3kk",
    "question": "Which one of the following is likely to give a precipitate with AgNO<sub>3</sub> solution ?",
    "options": [
      "CHCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>CCl",
      "CCl<sub>4</sub>",
      "CH<sub>2</sub>=CH–Cl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>CCl"
  },
  {
    "id": "Rv0T6OUeTQDAA8hp8m3rsa0w2w9jx7zp2mj",
    "question": "An 'Assertion' and a 'Reason' are given below. Choose the correct answer from the following options :\n<br/><b>Assertion (A) :</b> Vinyl halides do not undergo nucleophilic substitution easily.\n<br/><b>Reason (R) :</b> Even though the intermediate carbocation is stabilized by loosely held p-electrons, the cleavage\nis difficult because of strong bonding.",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct statements but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct statements and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is correct statement but (R) is a wrong statement",
      "Both (A) and (R) are wrong statements."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "(A) is correct statement but (R) is a wrong statement"
  },
  {
    "id": "lq85iCEuexDvaQkD2cVT6",
    "question": "Which one of the following alkenes when\ntreated with HCl yields majorly an anti\nMarkovnikov product?",
    "options": [
      "Cl – CH = CH<sub>2</sub>",
      "F<sub>3</sub>C – CH = CH<sub>2</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>O – CH = CH<sub>2</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>N – CH = CH<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "F<sub>3</sub>C – CH = CH<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "ToJZqAKvw1E2kWYbWfjgy2xukfotw2er",
    "question": "The major product formed in the following reaction is :\n<br/>CH<sub>3</sub>CH = CHCH(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> $$\\buildrel {HBr} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$",
    "options": [
      "Br(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH(Br)CH<sub>2</sub>CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH(Br)CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>C(Br)(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>C(Br)(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "uBw8ql4QsONZPxHM2K1kmki9q4m",
    "question": "The correct pair(s) of the ambident nucleophiles is(are)<br/><br/>(A) AgCN/KCN<br/><br/>(B) RCOOAg/RCOOK<br/><br/>(C) AgNO<sub>2</sub>/KNO<sub>2</sub><br/><br/>(D) AgI/KI",
    "options": [
      "(B) and (C) only",
      "(B) only",
      "(A) and (C) only",
      "(A) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "(A) and (C) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu0kss8",
    "question": "<p>The isomeric deuterated bromide with molecular formula $$\\mathrm{C_4H_8DBr}$$ having two chiral carbon atoms is</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 - Bromo - 1 - deuterobutane",
      "2 - Bromo - 1 - deutero - 2 - methylpropane",
      "2 - Bromo - 3 - deuterobutane",
      "2 - Bromo - 2 - deuterobutane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "2 - Bromo - 3 - deuterobutane"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyfs5ir",
    "question": "<p>Assertion A : Hydrolysis of an alkyl chloride is a slow reaction but in the presence of NaI, the rate of the hydrolysis increases.</p>\n<p>Reason R : I$$^{-}$$ is a good nucleophile as well as a good leaving group.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyhghbp",
    "question": "<p>The pair from the following pairs having both compounds with net non-zero dipole moment is</p>",
    "options": [
      "cis-butene, trans-butene",
      "CH$$_2$$Cl$$_2$$, CHCl$$_3$$",
      "Benzene, anisidine",
      "1,4-Dichlorobenzene, 1,3-Dichlorobenzene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "CH$$_2$$Cl$$_2$$, CHCl$$_3$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbmmtp5",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as <b>Assertion (A)</b> and the other is labelled as <b>Reason (R)</b>.<br/><br/>\n<b>Assertion (A)</b> : Haloalkanes react with KCN to form alkyl cyanides as a main product while with $\\mathrm{AgCN}$ form isocyanide as the main product.\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Reason (R)</b> : $\\mathrm{KCN}$ and $\\mathrm{AgCN}$ both are highly ionic compounds.<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below :\n",
    "options": [
      "(A) is correct but $(\\mathbf{R})$ is not correct",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "(A) is correct but $(\\mathbf{R})$ is not correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc6672b",
    "question": "<p>The correct statement regarding nucleophilic substitution reaction in a chiral alkyl halide is ;</p>",
    "options": [
      "Retention occurs in $$S_N 1$$ reaction and inversion occurs in $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2$$ reaction.\n",
      "Racemisation occurs in $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 1$$ reaction and retention occurs in $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2$$ reaction.\n",
      "Racemisation occurs in both $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 1$$ and $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2$$ reactions.\n",
      "Racemisation occurs in $$S_N 1$$ reaction and inversion occurs in $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2$$ reaction."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "Racemisation occurs in $$S_N 1$$ reaction and inversion occurs in $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2$$ reaction."
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7c0dv",
    "question": "<p>The product (C) in the below mentioned reaction is :</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{CH}_3-\\mathrm{CH}_2-\\mathrm{CH}_2-\\mathrm{Br} \\xrightarrow[\\Delta]{\\mathrm{KOH}_{(\\text {alc) }}} \\mathrm{A} \\xrightarrow{\\mathrm{HBr}} \\mathrm{B} \\xrightarrow[\\mathrm{KOH}_{(\\mathrm{aq})}]{\\Delta} \\mathrm{C}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "Propan-1-ol",
      "Propyne",
      "Propan-2-ol",
      "Propene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "Propan-2-ol"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfpev1i",
    "question": "<p>Alkyl halide is converted into alkyl isocyanide by reaction with</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{KCN}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{NH}_4 \\mathrm{CN}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{NaCN}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{AgCN}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{AgCN}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg7n4xi",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement - I: High concentration of strong nucleophilic reagent with secondary alkyl halides which do not have bulky substituents will follow $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}}{ }^2$$ mechanism.</p>\n<p>Statement - II: A secondary alkyl halide when treated with a large excess of ethanol follows $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}}{ }^1$$ mechanism.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgygvg4",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : $$\\mathrm{CH}_2=\\mathrm{CH}-\\mathrm{CH}_2-\\mathrm{Cl}$$ is an example of allyl halide.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Allyl halides are the compounds in which the halogen atom is attached to $$\\mathrm{sp}^2$$ hybridised carbon atom.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "(A) is true but (R) is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2ux53",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2$$ reaction of $$\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_5 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{Br}$$ occurs more readily than the $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2$$ reaction of $$\\mathrm{CH}_3 \\mathrm{CH}_2 \\mathrm{Br}$$.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : The partially bonded unhybridized p-orbital that develops in the trigonal bipyramidal transition state is stabilized by conjugation with the phenyl ring.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct",
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloalkanes",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "fatBMkjmuTnF5BLV",
    "question": "Bottles containing C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>l and C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>I lost their original labels. They were labelled A and B for testing A and B were separately taken in test tubes and boiled with NaOH solution. The end solution in each tube was made acidic with dilute HNO<sub>3</sub> and then some AgNO<sub>3</sub> solution was added. Substance B gave a yellow precipitate. Which one of the following statements is true for this experiment?",
    "options": [
      "A and C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>I",
      "B and C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>I",
      "Addition of HNO<sub>3</sub> was unnecessary",
      "A was C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloarenes",
    "solution": "A was C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>I"
  },
  {
    "id": "jTckFpJDgkfdLvSi",
    "question": "Fluorobenzene (C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>F) can be synthesized in the laboratory ",
    "options": [
      "by heating phenol with HF and KF ",
      "from aniline by diazotisation followed by heating the diazonium salt with HBF<sub>4</sub>",
      "by direct fluorination of benzene with F<sub>2</sub> gas",
      "by reacting bromobenzene with NaF solution"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloarenes",
    "solution": "from aniline by diazotisation followed by heating the diazonium salt with HBF<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Nxs37rOCozjzfqn4",
    "question": "A solution of (–$$l$$) – chloro –1 – phenylethane in toluene racemises slowly in the presence of a small\namount of SbCl<sub>5</sub>, due to the formation of :",
    "options": [
      "carbene",
      "carbocation",
      "free radical",
      "carbanion"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloarenes",
    "solution": "carbocation"
  },
  {
    "id": "7NudWE0Pd6VRZKz21W1kmj8cx36",
    "question": "Which of the following reaction is an example of ammonolysis?",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>COCl + C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>NH<sub>2</sub> $$ \\to $$ C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>CONHC<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CN $$\\buildrel {[H]} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CN $$\\buildrel {HCl} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>$$\\mathop N\\limits^ +  $$H<sub>3</sub>Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>Cl + NH<sub>3</sub> $$ \\to $$ C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloarenes",
    "solution": "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>Cl + NH<sub>3</sub> $$ \\to $$ C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "eYgdeMnpmJqMuzfVFA1kmm0j0rh",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH and AgCN both can generate nucleophile.<br/><br/>Statement II : KCN and AgCN both will generate nitrile nucleophile with all reaction conditions.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate option :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true.",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true.",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloarenes",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but statement II is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo9onxy",
    "question": "In the following halogenated organic compounds, the one with the maximum number of chlorine atoms in its structure is :",
    "options": [
      "Gammaxene",
      "Chloropicrin",
      "Chloral",
      "Freon-12"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloarenes",
    "solution": "Gammaxene"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjymym",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R :</p>\n<p><b>Assertion A</b> : Aryl halides cannot be prepared by replacement of hydroxyl group of phenol by halogen atom.</p>\n<p><b>Reason R</b> : Phenols react with halogen acids violently.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is true but R is false",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "haloarenes",
    "solution": "A is true but R is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "rktozxqKIS8O2y9i",
    "question": "The compound formed on heating chlorobenzene with chloral in the presence concentrated\nsulphuric acid is ",
    "options": [
      "gammexene",
      "hexachloroethane ",
      "Freon",
      "DDT"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "some-important-polyhalogens-compounds",
    "solution": "DDT"
  },
  {
    "id": "1NDiQGdoBtjRd5jW",
    "question": "Which of the following on heating with aqueous KOH, produces acetaldehyde ? ",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COCl",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>Cl",
      "CH<sub>2</sub>ClCH<sub>2</sub>Cl",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CHCl<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "some-important-polyhalogens-compounds",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>CHCl<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "uvAs196tZzWdZf85",
    "question": "What is DDT among the following?",
    "options": [
      "Greenhouse gas",
      "A fertilizer",
      "Biodegradable pollutant",
      "Non–biodegradable pollutant\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "some-important-polyhalogens-compounds",
    "solution": "Non–biodegradable pollutant\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "WRAcl0x7FhcNvp4Z",
    "question": "Iodoform can be prepared from all except :",
    "options": [
      "Ethyl methyl ketone",
      "Isopropyl alcohol",
      "3–Methyl – 2– butanone ",
      "Isobutyl alcohol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "some-important-polyhalogens-compounds",
    "solution": "Isobutyl alcohol"
  },
  {
    "id": "QKjkxVH5bPaZitm7",
    "question": "The major organic compound formed by the reaction of 1, 1, 1– trichloroethane with silver powder is:\n",
    "options": [
      "2- Butyne",
      "2- Butene",
      "Acetylene",
      "Ethene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "haloalkanes-and-haloarenes",
    "topic": "some-important-polyhalogens-compounds",
    "solution": "2- Butyne"
  },
  {
    "id": "pWmzH6l5zYAqGV3g",
    "question": "The reaction of toluene with Cl<sub>2</sub> in presence of FeCl<sub>3</sub> gives predominantly",
    "options": [
      "benzoyl chloride",
      "benzyl chloride",
      "o-and p-chlorotoluene",
      "m-chlorotoluene "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "aromatic-hydrocarbons",
    "solution": "o-and p-chlorotoluene"
  },
  {
    "id": "Upud2y2sCAOmjWB3",
    "question": "Toluene is nitrated and the resulting product is reduced with tin and hydrochloric acid. The product so\nobtained is diazotised and then heated with cuprous bromide. The reaction mixture so formed\ncontains ",
    "options": [
      "mixture of o− and p−bromotoluenes ",
      "mixture of o− and p−dibromobenzenes ",
      "mixture of o− and p−bromoanilines ",
      "mixture of o− and m−bromotoluenes"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "aromatic-hydrocarbons",
    "solution": "mixture of o− and p−bromotoluenes "
  },
  {
    "id": "utBkDDXbjbcMunnJIZVsx",
    "question": "Polysubstitution is a major drawback in:",
    "options": [
      "Reimer Tiemann reaction ",
      "Friedel Craft's alkylation",
      "Acetylation of aniline",
      "Friedel Craft's acylation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "aromatic-hydrocarbons",
    "solution": "Friedel Craft's alkylation"
  },
  {
    "id": "mmGUwBBHnUbWiqmGtM1kltac45k",
    "question": "The correct sequence of reagents used in the preparation of 4-bromo-2-nitroethyl benzene from benzene is :",
    "options": [
      "$$C{H_3}COCl/AlC{l_3},B{r_2}/AlB{r_3},HN{O_3}/{H_2}S{O_4},Zn/HCl$$",
      "$$C{H_3}COCl/AlC{l_3},Zn - Hg/HCl,B{r_2}/AlB{r_3},HN{O_3}/{H_2}S{O_4}$$",
      "$$B{r_2}/AlB{r_3},C{H_3}COCl/AlC{l_3},HN{O_3}/{H_2}S{O_4},Zn/HCl$$",
      "$$HN{O_3}/{H_2}S{O_4},B{r_2}/AlC{l_3},C{H_3}COCl/AlC{l_3},Zn - Hg/HCl$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "aromatic-hydrocarbons",
    "solution": "$$C{H_3}COCl/AlC{l_3},Zn - Hg/HCl,B{r_2}/AlB{r_3},HN{O_3}/{H_2}S{O_4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krrixp9z",
    "question": "Benzene on nitration gives nitrobenzene in presence of HNO<sub>3</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> mixture, where :",
    "options": [
      "both H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and HNO<sub>3</sub> act as a bases",
      "HNO<sub>3</sub> acts as an acid and H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> acts as a base",
      "both H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and HNO<sub>3</sub> act as an acids",
      "HNO<sub>3</sub> acts as a base and H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> acts as an acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "aromatic-hydrocarbons",
    "solution": "HNO<sub>3</sub> acts as a base and H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> acts as an acid"
  },
  {
    "id": "pe3VuSMjafKGXbUY",
    "question": "Which one of the following has the minimum boiling point?",
    "options": [
      "n-butane",
      "isobutane",
      "1- butene ",
      "1- butyne "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "isobutane"
  },
  {
    "id": "TbB49EEyllHLCA4I",
    "question": "Which branched chain isomer of the hydrocarbon with molecular mass 72u gives only one isomer of\nmono substituted alkyl halide ?",
    "options": [
      "Tertiary butyl chloride",
      "Neopentane",
      "Isohexane",
      "Neohexane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "Neopentane"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpowrdg",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct set of reagents for the following conversion.</p>\n<p>trans $$\\left(\\mathrm{Ph}-\\mathrm{CH}=\\mathrm{CH}-\\mathrm{CH}_{3}\\right) \\rightarrow \\operatorname{cis}\\left(\\mathrm{Ph}-\\mathrm{CH}=\\mathrm{CH}-\\mathrm{CH}_{3}\\right)$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Br_2,alc\\cdot KOH,NaNH_2,H_2}$$ Lindlar Catalyst",
      "$$\\mathrm{Br_2,aq\\cdot KOH,NaNH_2,Na}$$ (Liq NH$$_3$$)",
      "$$\\mathrm{Br_2,alc\\cdot KOH,NaNH_2,Na}$$ (Liq NH$$_3$$)",
      "$$\\mathrm{Br_2,aq\\cdot KOH,NaNH_2,H_2}$$ Lindlar Catalyst"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Br_2,alc\\cdot KOH,NaNH_2,H_2}$$ Lindlar Catalyst"
  },
  {
    "id": "TA3us7UrAp2iuloV",
    "question": "At 300 K and 1 atm, 15 mL of a gaseous hydrocarbon requires 375 mL air containing 20% O<sub>2</sub> by volume\nfor complete combustion. After combustion the gases occupy 345 mL. Assuming that the water formed is\nin liquid form and the volumes were measured at the same temperature and pressure, the formula of the hydrocarbon is:",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>8</sub>",
      "C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>8</sub>",
      "C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>10 </sub>",
      "C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>6</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>8</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "jJQuoLtlHQfjujXJ",
    "question": "The trans-alkenes are formed by the reduction of alkynes with",
    "options": [
      "Sn - HCl",
      "H<sub>2</sub> – Pd/C, BaSO<sub>4</sub>",
      "NaBH<sub>4</sub>",
      "Na/liq. NH<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "Na/liq. NH<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "y6j26Xr7oVlfOzKVQX7YF",
    "question": "When 2-butyne is treate with H<sub>2</sub>/Lindlar's catalyst,  compound X is produced as the major product and when treated with Na/liq. NH<sub>3</sub> it produces Y as the major product Which of the following statements is correct ? ",
    "options": [
      "X will have higher dipole moment and higher boiling point than Y. ",
      "Y will have higher dipole moment and higher boiling point than X. ",
      "X will have lower dipole moment and lower boiling point than Y. ",
      "Y will have higher dipole momet and lower boiling point than X. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "X will have higher dipole moment and higher boiling point than Y. "
  },
  {
    "id": "9JJzZ2SLzT2x9bknFG7k9k2k5dzm2gh",
    "question": "Consider the following reaction :<br/><br/>\n$${\\left( {C{H_3}} \\right)_3}CCH\\left( {OH} \\right)C{H_3}\\buildrel {conc.\\,\\,\\,{H_2}S{O_4}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$<br/><br/>\n$${\\left( {C{H_3}} \\right)_2}CHCH\\left( {Br} \\right)C{H_3}\\buildrel {alc.\\,\\,KOH} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$<br/><br/>\n$${\\left( {C{H_3}} \\right)_2}{\\rm{ }}CHCH\\left( {Br} \\right)C{H_3}\\buildrel {{{(C{H_3})}_3}{O^\\Theta }{K^ \\oplus }} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$<br/><br/>\n$${\\left( {C{H_3}} \\right)_2}\\mathop C\\limits_{\\mathop |\\limits_{OH} }  - C{H_2} - CHO\\buildrel \\Delta  \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$<br/><br/>\nWhich of these reaction(s) will not produce Saytzeff product ?",
    "options": [
      "(d) only",
      "(b) and (d)",
      "(a), (c) and (d) ",
      "(c) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "(c) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "mdQud17aY3e3WX6XcB1klurfm78",
    "question": "In $$\\mathop C\\limits^1 {H_2} = \\mathop C\\limits^2  = \\mathop C\\limits^3 H - \\mathop C\\limits^4 {H_3}$$ molecule, the hybridization of carbon 1, 2, 3 and 4 respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "sp<sup>2</sup>, sp, sp<sup>2</sup>, sp<sup>3</sup>",
      "sp<sup>2</sup>, sp<sup>2</sup>, sp<sup>2</sup>, sp<sup>3</sup>",
      "sp<sup>3</sup>, sp, sp<sup>3</sup>, sp<sup>3</sup>",
      "sp<sup>2</sup>, sp<sup>3</sup>, sp<sup>2</sup>, sp<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "sp<sup>2</sup>, sp, sp<sup>2</sup>, sp<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bdfzjg",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The presence of weaker $$\\pi$$-bonds make alkenes less stable than alkanes.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The strength of the double bond is greater than that of carbon-carbon single bond.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "89W1LZPiizn2R1Zs",
    "question": "The hydrocarbon which can react with sodium in liquid ammonia is ",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>C≡CCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>3</sub> ",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>C≡CH",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH=CHCH<sub>3</sub> ",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>C≡CCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>C≡CH"
  },
  {
    "id": "E2dXvNkNpXK7JVZ3Sf1Mn",
    "question": "The correct order for acid strength of compounds : <br/><br/>CH $$ \\equiv $$ CH, CH<sub>3</sub>–C $$ \\equiv $$ CH and CH<sub>2</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub> is as follows ",
    "options": [
      "CH $$ \\equiv $$ CH &gt; CH<sub>2</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub> &gt; CH<sub>3</sub> – C $$ \\equiv $$ CH ",
      "CH<sub>3</sub> – C $$ \\equiv $$ CH &gt; CH<sub>2</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub> &gt; HC $$ \\equiv $$ CH",
      "HC $$ \\equiv $$ CH &gt; CH<sub>3</sub> – C $$ \\equiv $$ CH &gt; CH<sub>2</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub> ",
      "CH<sub>3</sub> – CH $$ \\equiv $$ CH &gt; CH $$ \\equiv $$ CH &gt; CH<sub>2</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "HC $$ \\equiv $$ CH &gt; CH<sub>3</sub> – C $$ \\equiv $$ CH &gt; CH<sub>2</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "vhxIvDxZuBdZYxUw5w1kmlmskfq",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II :<br/><br/><b>List - I (Chemicals)</b><br/><br/>(a) Alcoholic potassium hydroxide<br/><br/>(b) Pd/BaSO<sub>4</sub><br/><br/>(c) BHC (Benzene hexachloride)<br/><br/>(d) Polyacetylene<br/><br/><b>List - II (Use / Preparation / Constituent)</b><br/><br/>(i) Electrodes in batteries<br/><br/>(ii) Obtained by addition reaction<br/><br/>(iii) Used for $$\\beta$$ - elimination reaction<br/><br/>(iv) Lindlar's catalyst<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate match :",
    "options": [
      "(a) - (ii), (b) - (i), (c) - (iv), (d) - (iii)",
      "(a) - (iii), (b) - (iv), (c) - (ii), (d) - (i)",
      "(a) - (iii), (b) - (i), (c) - (iv), (d) - (ii)",
      "(a) - (ii), (b) - (iv), (c) - (i), (d) - (iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "(a) - (iii), (b) - (iv), (c) - (ii), (d) - (i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxzq9jw",
    "question": "<p>The incorrect statement regarding ethyne is</p>",
    "options": [
      "The carbon - carbon bonds in ethyne is weaker than that in ethene\n",
      "Both carbons are sp hybridised\n",
      "The $$\\mathrm{C}-\\mathrm{C}$$ bonds in ethyne is shorter than that in ethene\n",
      "Ethyne is linear"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "properties-and-preparation-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "The carbon - carbon bonds in ethyne is weaker than that in ethene\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZQ3aov898q3p028i",
    "question": "On mixing a certain alkane with chlorine and irradiating it with ultravioletlight, it forms only one\nmonochloroalkane. This alkane could be",
    "options": [
      "pentane",
      "isopentane",
      "neopentane",
      "propane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "neopentane"
  },
  {
    "id": "tNKGNwWii5UKiC2h",
    "question": "Of the five isomeric hexanes, the isomer which can give two monochlorinated\ncompounds is ",
    "options": [
      "n-hexane",
      "2, 3-dimethylbutane ",
      "2,2-dimethylbutane",
      "2-methylpentane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "2, 3-dimethylbutane "
  },
  {
    "id": "hWTepb6yo1U6lbU2",
    "question": "2 methylbutane on reacting with bromine in the presence of sunlight gives mainly",
    "options": [
      "1 – bromo -2 - methylbutane",
      "2 – bromo -2 - methylbutane ",
      "2 – bromo -3 - methylbutane",
      "1 – bromo -3 – methylbutane "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "2 – bromo -2 - methylbutane "
  },
  {
    "id": "lgZ0ZnOGvoPshY5c2Oqdb",
    "question": "5 L of an alkane requires 25 L of oxygen for its complete combustion. If all volumes are measured at constant temperature and pressure, the alkane is :",
    "options": [
      "Ethane ",
      "Propane ",
      "Butane",
      "Isobutane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "Propane "
  },
  {
    "id": "V3gZMChucf9b9KzhZ91kmkicf5x",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : 2-methylbutane on oxidation with KMnO<sub>4</sub> gives 2-methylbutan-2-ol.<br/><br/>Statement II : n-alkanes can be easily oxidised to corresponding alcohols with KMnO<sub>4</sub>.<br/><br/>Choose the correct option :",
    "options": [
      "Both statement I and statement II are incorrect",
      "Both statement I and statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz0y1js",
    "question": "Presence of which reagent will affect the reversibility of the following reaction, and change it to a irreversible reaction :<br/><br/>CH<sub>4</sub> + I<sub>2</sub> $$\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\rightleftharpoons}\n\\limits_{{\\mathop{\\rm Re}\\nolimits} versible}^{hv}} $$ CH<sub>3</sub> $$-$$ I + HI",
    "options": [
      "HOCl",
      "dilute HNO<sub>2</sub>",
      "Liquid NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "Concentrated HIO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "Concentrated HIO<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gqjxu9",
    "question": "<p>$$\n\\stackrel{\\bullet}{\\mathrm{Cl}}+\\mathrm{CH}_{4} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{A}+\\mathrm{B}\n$$</p>\n<p>A and B in the above atmospheric reaction step are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{H}_{6}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cl}_{2}$$",
      "$$\\stackrel{\\bullet}{\\mathrm{C}} \\mathrm{HCl}_{2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{H}_{2}$$",
      "$$\\stackrel{\\bullet}{\\mathrm{C}}\\mathrm{H}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{HCl}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{H}_{6}$$ and $$\\mathrm{HCl}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "$$\\stackrel{\\bullet}{\\mathrm{C}}\\mathrm{H}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{HCl}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsd4e3j",
    "question": "<p>The one giving maximum number of isomeric alkenes on dehydrohalogenation reaction is (excluding rearrangement)</p>",
    "options": [
      "2-Bromo-3,3-dimethylpentane",
      "2-Bromopropane",
      "1-Bromo-2-methylbutane",
      "2-Bromopentane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "2-Bromopentane"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmagm",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 2$$ reactions are 'stereospecific', indicating that they result in the formation of only one stereo-isomer as the product.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : $$\\mathrm{S}_{\\mathrm{N}} 1$$ reactions generally result in formation of product as racemic mixtures.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkanes",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "xUYAEGRuMSmmUT7a",
    "question": "Butene-1 may be converted to butane by reaction with",
    "options": [
      "Sn - HCI",
      "Zn - Hg",
      "Pd/H<sub>2</sub>",
      "Zn - HCI"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "Pd/H<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "5vKOozcg75TnU5tc",
    "question": "Reaction of one molecule of HBr with one molecule of 1,3-butadiene at 40<sup>o</sup>C gives\npredominantly ",
    "options": [
      "3-bromobutene under kinetically controlled conditions",
      "1-bromo-2-butene under thermodymically controlled conditions",
      "3-bromobutene under thermodynamically controlled conditions",
      "1-bromo-2-butene under kinetically controlled conditions "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "1-bromo-2-butene under thermodymically controlled conditions"
  },
  {
    "id": "L9a44ahQMNwobucN",
    "question": "Which types of isomerism is shown by 2,3-dichlorobutane? ",
    "options": [
      "Diastereo ",
      "Optical ",
      "Geometric ",
      "Structural "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "Optical "
  },
  {
    "id": "St0IILnMneZTu0Ou",
    "question": "The reaction of propene with HOCl (Cl<sub>2</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>O) proceeds through the intermediate:",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{CH}_{3}-\\mathrm{CH}^{+}-\\mathrm{CH}_{2}-\\mathrm{OH}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{CH}_{3}-\\mathrm{CHCl}-\\mathrm{CH}_{2}^{+}$$",
      "CH<sub>3</sub> - CH<sup>+</sup> - CH<sub>2</sub> - OH",
      "$$\\mathrm{CH}_{3}-\\mathrm{CH}^{+}-\\mathrm{CH}_{2}-\\mathrm{Cl}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{CH}_{3}-\\mathrm{CH}^{+}-\\mathrm{CH}_{2}-\\mathrm{Cl}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krutcjxz",
    "question": "An organic compound 'A' C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>8</sub> on treatment with KMnO<sub>4</sub>/H<sup>+</sup> yields compound 'B' C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>6</sub>O.<br/><br/>Compound 'A' also yields compound 'B' an ozonolysis. Compound 'A' is :",
    "options": [
      "2-Methylpropene",
      "1-Methylcyclopropane",
      "But-2-ene",
      "Cyclobutane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "2-Methylpropene"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn113za",
    "question": "The stereoisomers that are formed by electrophilic addition of bromine to trans-but-2-ene is/are :",
    "options": [
      "2 enantiomers and 2 mesomers",
      "2 identical mesomers",
      "2 enantiomers",
      "1 racemic and 2 enantiomers"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "2 identical mesomers"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l549k6lc",
    "question": "<p>Two isomers 'A' and 'B' with molecular formula C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>8</sub> give different products on oxidation with KMnO<sub>4</sub> in acidic medium. Isomer 'A' on reaction with KMnO<sub>4</sub>/H<sup>+</sup> results in effervescence of a gas and gives ketone. The compound 'A' is</p>",
    "options": [
      "But-1-ene.",
      "cis-But-2-ene.",
      "trans-But-2-ene.",
      "2-methyl propene."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "2-methyl propene."
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo9kl4l",
    "question": "A hydrocarbon ' $\\mathrm{X}$ ' with formula $\\mathrm{C}_{6} \\mathrm{H}_{8}$ uses two moles of $\\mathrm{H}_{2}$ on catalytic hydrogenation of its one mole. On ozonolysis, ' $\\mathrm{X}$ ' yields two moles of methane dicarbaldehyde. The hydrocarbon ' $\\mathrm{X}$ ' is:",
    "options": [
      "hexa-1, 3, 5-triene",
      "cyclohexa-1, 4-diene",
      "cyclohexa - 1,3 - diene",
      "1-methylcyclopenta-1, 4-diene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkenes",
    "solution": "cyclohexa-1, 4-diene"
  },
  {
    "id": "OR4TrBhIdxazt1Iy",
    "question": "Which of these will not react with acetylene ?",
    "options": [
      "NaOH",
      "ammonical AgNO<sub>3</sub>\n ",
      "Na",
      "HCl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "NaOH"
  },
  {
    "id": "WSTuR3sLMiCXMB7g",
    "question": "What is the product when acetylene reacts with hypochlorous acid ?",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COCI",
      "ClCH<sub>2</sub>CHO",
      "Cl<sub>2</sub>CHCHO",
      "ClCHCOOH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "Cl<sub>2</sub>CHCHO"
  },
  {
    "id": "lkk68ldp",
    "question": "Acetylene does not react with :",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{Na}$",
      "ammoniacal $\\mathrm{AgNO}_3$",
      "$\\mathrm{HCl}$",
      "$\\mathrm{NaOH}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{NaOH}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "EdtroXvb7mZHiUJT",
    "question": "Which of the following reactions will yield 2, 2-dibromopropane? ",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub> - CH = CH<sub>2</sub> + HBr $$\\to$$",
      "CH<sub>3</sub> - C $$\\equiv$$ CH + 2HBr $$\\to$$",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH = CHBr + HBr $$\\to$$",
      "CH $$\\equiv$$ CH + 2HBr $$\\to$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub> - C $$\\equiv$$ CH + 2HBr $$\\to$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "OKLyIwI4cqJQbksy",
    "question": "In the following sequence of reactions, the alkene affords the compound ‘B’ <br/>\nCH<sub>3</sub> - CH = CH - CH<sub>3</sub> $$\\buildrel {{O_3}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ A $$\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{Zn}^{H{}_2O}} $$ B<br/>\nThe compound B is",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CHO ",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COCH<sub>3</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COCH<sub>3</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CHO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>CHO"
  },
  {
    "id": "MjCtO8sCU6fKyleK",
    "question": "Ozonolysis of an organic compound gives formaldehyde as one of the products. This confirms the\npresence of :",
    "options": [
      "a vinyl group",
      "an isopropyl group ",
      "an acetylenic triple bond",
      "two ethylenic double bonds"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "a vinyl group"
  },
  {
    "id": "87dWb2mHmAAnL6oz",
    "question": "2–Hexyne gives trans–2–Hexene on treatment with :",
    "options": [
      "Pt/H<sub>2</sub>",
      "Li/NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "Pd/BaSO<sub>4</sub>",
      "LiAlH<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "Li/NH<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "ditAYlp468Ihw58lXJ1kmhtjw42",
    "question": "Which of the following is Lindlar catalyst?",
    "options": [
      "Partially deactivated palladised charcoal",
      "Zinc chloride and HCl",
      "Sodium and Liquid NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "Cold dilute solution of KMnO<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "Partially deactivated palladised charcoal"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krrhtybh",
    "question": "Metallic sodium does not react normally with :",
    "options": [
      "gaseous ammonia",
      "But-2-yne",
      "Ethyne",
      "tert-butyl alcohol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrocarbons",
    "topic": "reaction-of-alkynes",
    "solution": "But-2-yne"
  },
  {
    "id": "c3vmcQ1iVZostSCZ",
    "question": "Which one of the following process will produce hard water?",
    "options": [
      "Saturation of water with MgCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "Saturation of water with CaSO<sub>4</sub>",
      "Addition of Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> to water",
      "Saturation of water with CaCO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "Saturation of water with CaSO<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "kOa1aT8CRLRZ215l0FAUI",
    "question": "The temporary hardness of water is due to : ",
    "options": [
      "Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>",
      "NaCl",
      "Ca(HCO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "CaCl<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "Ca(HCO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "NQGlTHHx9VEEWpXPmf4hW",
    "question": "100 mL of a water sample contains 0.81 g of calcium bicrabonate and 0.73 g of magnesium\nbicarbonate. The hardness of this water sample expressed in terms of equivalents of CaCO<sub>3</sub> is :\n(Molar mass of calcium bicarbonate is 162 g mol<sup>–1</sup> and magnesium bicarbonate is 146 g mol<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "1,000 ppm",
      "100 ppm",
      "10,000 ppm",
      "5,000 ppm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "10,000 ppm"
  },
  {
    "id": "6iRo5dnzEeuyoRpq0c3rsa0w2w9jx96rnbl",
    "question": "The temporary hardness of a water sample is due to compound X. Boiling this sample converts X to\ncompound Y. X and Y, respectively, are : ",
    "options": [
      "Mg(HCO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> and MgCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "Ca(HO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> and CaO",
      "Ca(HCO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> and Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Mg(HCO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> and Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "Mg(HCO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> and Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "8tUg0a63BEI8RgQVDz7k9k2k5dz9yug",
    "question": "In comparison to the zeolite process for the removal of permanent hardness, the synthetic resins\nmethod is :",
    "options": [
      "less efficient as the resins cannot be regenerated.\n",
      "more efficient as it can exchange only cations.",
      "more efficient as it can exchange both cations as well as anions.",
      "less efficient as it exchanges only anions."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "more efficient as it can exchange both cations as well as anions."
  },
  {
    "id": "PcWvMCMNeubZ4zLLhF7k9k2k5ll1ljd",
    "question": "Amongst the following, the form of water with\nthe lowest ionic conductance at 298 K is :",
    "options": [
      "saline water used for intravenous injection",
      "sea water",
      "distilled water",
      "water from a well"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "distilled water"
  },
  {
    "id": "b5cISs9PJ06j8bHwi2jgy2xukfq9375d",
    "question": "The one that is NOT suitable for the removal of permanent hardness of water is :",
    "options": [
      "Ion-exchange method\n",
      "Calgon's method",
      "Treatment with sodium carbonate",
      "Clark's method"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "Clark's method"
  },
  {
    "id": "vy6NV8ZSTBj9CClRPS1kmkj63r6",
    "question": "The functional groups that are responsible for the ion-exchange property of cation and anion exchange resins, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$SO<sub>3</sub>H and $$-$$NH<sub>2</sub>",
      "$$-$$NH<sub>2</sub> and COOH",
      "$$-$$NH<sub>2</sub> and $$-$$SO<sub>3</sub>H",
      "$$-$$SO<sub>3</sub>H and $$-$$COOH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "$$-$$SO<sub>3</sub>H and $$-$$NH<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktb4suyg",
    "question": "Which one of the following methods is most suitable for preparing deionized water?",
    "options": [
      "Synthetic resin method",
      "Clark's method",
      "Calgon's method",
      "Permutit method"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "Synthetic resin method"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58j0204",
    "question": "<p>Boiling of hard water is helpful in removing the temporary hardness by converting calcium hydrogen carbonate and magnesium hydrogen carbonate to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "CaCO<sub>3</sub> and Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>",
      "CaCO<sub>3</sub> and MgCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub> and MgCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub> and Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "CaCO<sub>3</sub> and Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mcmljt",
    "question": "<p>The metal salts formed during softening of hardwater using Clark's method are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Ca}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Mg}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{CaCO}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Mg}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ca}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{MgCO}_{3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{CaCO}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{MgCO}_{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{CaCO}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Mg}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nurw6e",
    "question": "<p>The products obtained during treatment of hard water using Clark's method are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{CaCO}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{MgCO}_{3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ca}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Mg}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{CaCO}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Mg}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ca}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{MgCO}_{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{CaCO}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Mg}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq4rjwx",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Permutit process is more efficient compared to the synthetic resin method for the softening of water.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Synthetic resin method results in the formation of soluble sodium salts.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Both the Statements I and II are correct",
      "Both the Statements I and II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hard-and-soft-water",
    "solution": "Both the Statements I and II are incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "OZQViQPXbBBLnjHlB8Ejp",
    "question": "NaH is an example of : ",
    "options": [
      "metallic hydride ",
      "saline hydride ",
      "electron-rich hydrid",
      "molecular hydride "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrides",
    "solution": "saline hydride "
  },
  {
    "id": "KfmkbZ65PpvhypcD983rsa0w2w9jx0xwv5f",
    "question": "The correct statements among (a) to (d) are :\n<br/>(a) saline hydrides produce H<sub>2</sub> gas when reacted with H<sub>2</sub>O.\n<br/>(b) reaction of LiAlH<sub>4</sub> with BF<sub>3</sub> leads to B<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>.\n<br/>(c) PH<sub>3</sub> and CH<sub>4</sub> are electron - rich and electron - precise hydrides, respectively.\n<br/>(d) HF and CH<sub>4</sub> are called as molecular ",
    "options": [
      "(a), (b), (c) and (d)",
      "(a), (c) and (d) only",
      "(c) and (d) only",
      "(a), (b) and (c) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrides",
    "solution": "(a), (b), (c) and (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": "HNVd3S1YbCv2BOjNMejgy2xukf25wpua",
    "question": "If the boiling point of H<sub>2</sub>O is 373 K, the boiling point of H<sub>2</sub>S will be :",
    "options": [
      "greater than 300 K but less than 373 K",
      "equal to 373 K",
      "more than 373 K",
      "less than 300 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrides",
    "solution": "less than 300 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrkancd",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 529px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 159px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 270px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>Type of Hydride</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>Example</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Electron deficient hydride</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{MgH_2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Electron rich hydride</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{HF}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Electron precise hydride</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{B_2H_6}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Saline hydride</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{CH_4}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrides",
    "solution": "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsykyp6",
    "question": "<p>Which hydride among the following is less stable?</p>",
    "options": [
      "NH$$_3$$",
      "HF",
      "LiH",
      "BeH$$_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrides",
    "solution": "BeH$$_2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "OQa1Mcp1hT6VIlMQ",
    "question": "From the following statements regarding H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, choose the incorrect statement :",
    "options": [
      "It decomposes on exposure to light",
      "It has to be stored in plastic or wax lined glass bottles in dark",
      "It has to be kept away from dust",
      "It can act only as an oxidizing agent"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "It can act only as an oxidizing agent"
  },
  {
    "id": "yrgkBJFJ6Qz9z5ePwjGca",
    "question": "In which of the following reactions, hydrogen peroxide acts as an oxidizing\nagent ?\n",
    "options": [
      "HOCl + H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> $$ \\to $$ H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup> +  Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup> + O<sub>2</sub> ",
      "I<sub>2</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> + 2OH<sup>$$-$$</sup> $$ \\to $$ 2I<sup>$$-$$</sup> + 2H<sub>2</sub>O + O<sub>2</sub> ",
      "2Mn$$O_4^ - $$ + 3H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> $$ \\to $$ 2 MnO<sub>2</sub> + 3O<sub>2</sub> + 2H<sub>2</sub>O + 2OH<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "PbS + 4H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> $$ \\to $$ PbSO<sub>4</sub> + 4H<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "PbS + 4H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> $$ \\to $$ PbSO<sub>4</sub> + 4H<sub>2</sub>O"
  },
  {
    "id": "TOD1Gaj0R3gvAPLK",
    "question": "Hydrogen peroxide oxidises [Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>4-</sup> to [Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3-</sup> in acidic medium but reduces [Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3-</sup> to [Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>4-</sup> in alkaline medium. The other products formed are, respectively :",
    "options": [
      "H<sub>2</sub>O and (H<sub>2</sub>O + OH<sup>-</sup>)",
      "(H<sub>2</sub>O + O<sub>2</sub>) and H<sub>2</sub>O ",
      "(H<sub>2</sub>O + O<sub>2</sub>) and (H<sub>2</sub>O + OH<sup>-</sup>) ",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O and (H<sub>2</sub>O + O<sub>2</sub>)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "H<sub>2</sub>O and (H<sub>2</sub>O + O<sub>2</sub>)"
  },
  {
    "id": "dm7wW2oRfHtzNqhlYUHTY",
    "question": "The chemical nature of hydrogen peroxide is : ",
    "options": [
      "Oxidising agent in acidic medium, but not in basic medium \n",
      "Oxidising and reducing agent in both acidic and basic medium ",
      "Reducing agent in basic medium, but not in acidic medium \n",
      "Oxidising and reducing agent in acidic medium, but not in basic medium."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "Oxidising and reducing agent in both acidic and basic medium "
  },
  {
    "id": "SmnNezRPW9d5vcknhFbsq",
    "question": "The volume strength of 1M H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is : (Molar mass of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> = 34 g mol<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "5.6",
      "22.4",
      "11.35",
      "16.8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "11.35"
  },
  {
    "id": "JH206oKrKCRWvilJzg1Eh",
    "question": "The strength of 11.2 volume solution of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>\nis : [Given that molar mass of H = 1 g mol–1\nand O = 16 g mol<sup>–1</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "3.4%",
      "34%",
      "13.6%",
      "1.7%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "3.4%"
  },
  {
    "id": "A7oVDyPzjGlUB86OlH7k9k2k5eq49tx",
    "question": "Among the statements (a) - (d), the correct ones are :<br/>\n(a) Decomposition of hydrogen peroxide gives dioxygen.<br/>\n(b) Like hydrogen peroxide, compounds, such as KCIO<sub>3</sub>, Pb(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> and NaNO<sub>3</sub> when heated liberate dioxygen.<br/>\n(c) 2-Ethylanthraquinone is useful for the industrial preparation of hydrogen peroxide.<br/>\n(d) Hydrogen peroxide is used for the manufacture of sodium perborate.\n",
    "options": [
      "(a), (b), (c) and (d)",
      "(a) and (c) only",
      "(a), (b) and (c) only",
      "(a), (c) and (d) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "(a), (b), (c) and (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": "6fwOTAPELwjXkPxFoEjgy2xukfou07q6",
    "question": "Hydrogen peroxide, in the pure state, is :",
    "options": [
      "Linear and blue in color",
      "Linear and almost colorless",
      "Non-planar and almost colorless",
      "Planar and bluein color"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "Non-planar and almost colorless"
  },
  {
    "id": "GXqryxS0xhyJ5m3Wlr1klrey98z",
    "question": "(A) HOCI + H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> → H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup> + Cl<sup>-</sup> + O<sub>2</sub><br/><br/>\n(B) I<sub>2</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> + 2OH<sup>-</sup> → 2I<sup>-</sup> + 2H<sub>2</sub>O + O<sub>2</sub><br/><br/>\nChoose the correct option.",
    "options": [
      "H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> acts as reducing and oxidising agent respectively in equations (A) and (B).",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> act as oxidizing and reducing agent respectively in equations (A) and (B).",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> acts as oxidising agent in equations (A) and (B).",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> acts as reducing agent in equations (A) and (B)."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> acts as reducing agent in equations (A) and (B)."
  },
  {
    "id": "tOHfo9m5uYuHHqApqs1kls86rv7",
    "question": "Which of the following equation depicts the oxidizing nature of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>?",
    "options": [
      "$$C{l_2} + {H_2}{O_2} \\to 2HCl + {O_2}$$",
      "$$KI{O_4} + {H_2}{O_2} \\to KI{O_3} + {H_2}O + {O_2}$$",
      "$$2{I^ - } + {H_2}{O_2} + 2{H^ + } \\to {I_2} + 2{H_2}O$$",
      "$${I_2} + {H_2}{O_2} + 2O{H^ - } \\to 2{I^ - } + 2{H_2}O + {O_2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "$$2{I^ - } + {H_2}{O_2} + 2{H^ + } \\to {I_2} + 2{H_2}O$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "4PTJQ9ebT7K3DbcBeX1kmht8l9e",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can act as both oxidising and reducing agent in basic medium.<br/><br/>Statement II : In the hydrogen economy, the energy is transmitted in the form of dihydrogen.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both statement I and statement II are false",
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "Both statement I and statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "Y4nmZCOwnfT7sUjyZt1kmitok74",
    "question": "The correct statements about H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> are :<br/><br/>(A) used in the treatment of effluents.<br/><br/>(B) used as both oxidising and reducing agents.<br/><br/>(C) the two hydroxyl groups lie in the same plane.<br/><br/>(D) miscible with water.<br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A), (C) and (D) only",
      "(A), (B), (C) and (D)",
      "(A), (B) and (D) only",
      "(B), (C) and (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "(A), (B) and (D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "UgCEw3uj8wcz5LZsJZ1kmm0x15k",
    "question": "In basic medium, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> exhibits which of the following reactions?<br/><br/>(A) Mn<sup>2+</sup> $$ \\to $$ Mn<sup>4+</sup><br/><br/>(B) I<sup>2</sup> $$ \\to $$ I<sup>$$-$$</sup><br/><br/>(C) PbS $$ \\to $$ PbSO<sub>4</sub><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(B) only",
      "(A), (B) only",
      "(A) only",
      "(A), (C) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "(A), (B) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq5ooxa",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion A and other is labelled as Reason R. <br/><br/>Assertion A : The dihedral angles in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in gaseous phase is 90.2$$^\\circ$$ and in solid phase is 111.5$$^\\circ$$.<br/><br/>Reason R : The change in dihedral angle in solid and gaseous phase is due to the difference in the intermolecular forces.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below for A and R.",
    "options": [
      "A is correct but R is not correct.",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is not the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is not correct but R is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "A is not correct but R is correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfs0i0h",
    "question": "The oxide that gives H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> most readily on treatment with H<sub>2</sub>O is :",
    "options": [
      "PbO<sub>2</sub>",
      "Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>",
      "SnO<sub>2</sub>",
      "BaO<sub>2</sub> . 8H<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn136xd",
    "question": "Hydrogen peroxide reacts with iodine in basic medium to give :",
    "options": [
      "IO$$_4^ - $$",
      "IO<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "I<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "IO$$_3^ - $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "I<sup>$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5497wu2",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following reactions indicates the reducing ability of hydrogen peroxide in basic medium?</p>",
    "options": [
      "HOCl + H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup> + Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup> + O<sub>2</sub>",
      "PbS + 4H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ PbSO<sub>4</sub> + 4H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "2MnO$$_4^ - $$ + 3H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ 2MnO<sub>2</sub> + 3O<sub>2</sub> + 2H<sub>2</sub>O + 2OH<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "Mn<sup>2+</sup> + H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ Mn<sup>4+</sup> + 2OH<sup>$$-$$</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "2MnO$$_4^ - $$ + 3H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ 2MnO<sub>2</sub> + 3O<sub>2</sub> + 2H<sub>2</sub>O + 2OH<sup>$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58dsdel",
    "question": "<p>Consider the following reaction:</p>\n<p>$$2HSO_4^ - (aq)\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{(2)\\,Hydrolysis}^{(1)\\,Electrolysis}} 2HSO_4^ -  + 2{H^ + } + A$$</p>\n<p>The dihedral angle in product A in its solid phase at 110 K is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "104$$^\\circ$$",
      "111.5$$^\\circ$$",
      "90.2$$^\\circ$$",
      "111.0$$^\\circ$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "90.2$$^\\circ$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6e17bvb",
    "question": "<p>The reaction of $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ with potassium permanganate in acidic medium leads to the formation of mainly :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Mn<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Mn<sup>4+</sup>",
      "Mn<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Mn<sup>6+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "Mn<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gpvqxv",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following can be used to prevent the decomposition of $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Urea",
      "Formaldehyde",
      "Formic acid",
      "Ethanol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "Urea"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i4wimo",
    "question": "The products obtained from a reaction of hydrogen peroxide and acidified potassium permanganate are :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Mn}^{4+}, \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$ only",
      "$$\\mathrm{Mn}^{2+}, \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$ only",
      "$$\\mathrm{Mn}^{4+}, \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}, \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ only",
      "$$\\mathrm{Mn}^{2+}, \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}, \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Mn}^{2+}, \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}, \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jkxzf3",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements.</p>\n<p>Statement I : Hydrogen peroxide can act as an oxidizing agent in both acidic and basic conditions.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Density of hydrogen peroxide at $$298 \\mathrm{~K}$$ is lower than that of $$\\mathrm{D}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldo1b3b9",
    "question": "<p>The starting material for convenient preparation of deuterated hydrogen peroxide ($$\\mathrm{D_{2}O_{2}}$$) in :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{BaO_{2}}$$",
      "2-ethylanthraquinol",
      "$$\\mathrm{BaO}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K_{2}S_{2}O_{8}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{K_{2}S_{2}O_{8}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo8gu9e",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p><b>Statement I :</b> $ \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}$ is used in the synthesis of Cephalosporin</p>\n<p><b>Statement II : </b>$ \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}$ is used for the restoration of aerobic conditions to sewage wastes.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement $\\mathbf{I}$ is incorrect but Statement $\\mathbf{II}$ is correct",
      "Statement $\\mathbf{I}$ is correct but Statement $\\mathbf{II}$ is incorrect",
      "Both Statement $\\mathbf{I}$ and Statement $\\mathbf{II}$ are incorrect",
      "Both Statement $\\mathbf{I}$ and Statement $\\mathbf{II}$ are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "Both Statement $\\mathbf{I}$ and Statement $\\mathbf{II}$ are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpp2gu2",
    "question": "<p>$$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ acts as a reducing agent in :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Mn}^{2+}+2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{MnO}_{2}+2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{Fe}^{2+}+2 \\mathrm{H}^{+}+\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}+2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Na}_{2} \\mathrm{S}+4 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{Na}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}+4 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{NaOCl}+\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{NaCl}+\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}+\\mathrm{O}_{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "$$2 \\mathrm{NaOCl}+\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{NaCl}+\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}+\\mathrm{O}_{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwsg1tx",
    "question": "<p>In which of the following reactions the hydrogen peroxide acts as a reducing agent?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{M{n^{2 + }} + {H_2}{O_2} \\to M{n^{4 + }} + 2O{H^ - }}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{HOCl + {H_2}{O_2} \\to {H_3}{O^ + } + C{l^ - } + {O_2}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{PbS + 4{H_2}{O_2} \\to PbS{O_4} + 4{H_2}O}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{2F{e^{2 + }} + {H_2}{O_2} \\to 2F{e^{3 + }} + 2O{H^ - }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{HOCl + {H_2}{O_2} \\to {H_3}{O^ + } + C{l^ - } + {O_2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgysddu1",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following can reduce decomposition of $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ on exposure to light :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Urea",
      "Glass containers",
      "Alkali",
      "Dust"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "hydrogen-peroxide",
    "solution": "Urea"
  },
  {
    "id": "lIQJkeyT6xd94hgZ",
    "question": "Which of the following could act as a propellant for rockets?",
    "options": [
      "Liquid oxygen + liquid argon",
      "Liquid hydrogen + liquid oxygen",
      "Liquid nitrogen + liquid oxygen",
      "Liquid hydrogen + liquid nitrogen"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Liquid hydrogen + liquid oxygen"
  },
  {
    "id": "hNhpxUhQTXgY5mqw",
    "question": "Which of the following statements in relation to the hydrogen atom is correct? ",
    "options": [
      "3s orbital is lower in energy than 3p orbital ",
      "3p orbital is lower in energy than 3d orbital ",
      "3s and 3p orbitals are of lower energy than 3d orbital ",
      "3s, 3p and 3d orbitals all have the same energy"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "3s, 3p and 3d orbitals all have the same energy"
  },
  {
    "id": "Pb0T5Vn72NAtuQbl",
    "question": "In context with the industrial preparation of hydrogen from water gas (CO + H<sub>2</sub>), which of the following\nis the correct statement? ",
    "options": [
      "CO and H<sub>2</sub> are fractionally separated using differences in their densities ",
      "CO is removed by absorption in aqueous Cu<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> solution",
      "H<sub>2</sub> is removed through occlusion with Pd ",
      "CO is oxidised to CO<sub>2</sub> with steam in the presence of a catalyst followed by absorption of CO<sub>2</sub> in\nalkali "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "CO is oxidised to CO<sub>2</sub> with steam in the presence of a catalyst followed by absorption of CO<sub>2</sub> in\nalkali "
  },
  {
    "id": "OjczRswB80lQ5rfW",
    "question": "Very pure hydrogen (99.9%) can be made by which of the following processes?",
    "options": [
      "Reaction of methane with steam",
      "Mixing natural hydrocarbons of high molecular weight",
      "Electrolysis of water",
      "Reaction of salt like hydrides with water"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Reaction of salt like hydrides with water"
  },
  {
    "id": "s8JGgbIMivCxhixyIwIjv",
    "question": "Identify the reaction which does not liberate hydrogen :",
    "options": [
      "Reaction of zinc with aqueous alkali. ",
      "Electrolysis of acidified water using Pt electrodes.",
      "Allowing a solution of sodium in liquid ammonia to stand.",
      "Reaction of lithium hydride with B<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Reaction of lithium hydride with B<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>."
  },
  {
    "id": "jAqvOS12W6QA8qORv9Ziy",
    "question": "The isotopes of hydrogen are : ",
    "options": [
      "Tritium and protium only ",
      "Protium and Deuterium only",
      "Protium, deuterium and tritium",
      "Deuterium and tritium only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Protium, deuterium and tritium"
  },
  {
    "id": "Erp4lcv6q8cGy8GtWsyLU",
    "question": "The total number of isotopes of hydrogen and number of radioactive isotopes among them, respectively, are : ",
    "options": [
      "3 and 2",
      "2 and 1",
      "2 and 0",
      "3 and 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "3 and 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "uJDjQd4uHzRfviVfeoHTV",
    "question": "The correct statements among (a) to (d) regarding H<sub>2</sub> as a fuel are :\n<br/><br/>(a)   It produces less pollutants than petrol.\n<br/><br/>(b)   A cylinder of compressed dihydrogen weighs $$ \\sim $$ 30 times more than a petrol tank producing the same amount of energy. \n<br/><br/>(c)   Dihydrogen is stored in tanks of metal alloys like NaNi<sub>5</sub>.\n\n<br/><br/>(d)   On combustion, values of energy released per gram of liquid dihydrogen and LPG are 50 and 142 KJ, respectively.",
    "options": [
      "(a) and (c) only",
      "(b) and (d) only",
      "(a), (b) and (c) only",
      "(b), (c) and (d) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "(a), (b) and (c) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "78cPXCPgjcL30DM0653rsa0w2w9jx57b9mn",
    "question": "The metal that gives hydrogen gas upon treatment with both acid as well as base is :",
    "options": [
      "mercury",
      "zinc",
      "iron ",
      "magnesium"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "zinc"
  },
  {
    "id": "Zc7TuIRNK7nsXw8tSVjgy2xukg4mzfju",
    "question": "Dihydrogen of high purity (&gt; 99.95%) is\nobtained through :",
    "options": [
      "the electrolysis of acidified water using Pt\nelectrodes",
      "the electrolysis of warm Ba(OH)<sub>2</sub> solution\nusing Ni electrodes",
      "the electrolysis of brine solution",
      "the reaction of Zn with dilute HCl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "the electrolysis of warm Ba(OH)<sub>2</sub> solution\nusing Ni electrodes"
  },
  {
    "id": "wwebbpFAL2ol43iBh31klrtqm9p",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.<br/><br/>Assertion A : Hydrogen is the most abundant element in the Universe, but it is not the most abundant gas in the troposphere.<br/><br/>Reason R : Hydrogen is the lightest element.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krrhat72",
    "question": "The single largest industrial application of dihydrogen is :",
    "options": [
      "Manufacture of metal hybrides",
      "Rocket fuel in space research",
      "In the synthesis of ammonia",
      "In the synthesis of nitric acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "In the synthesis of ammonia"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krus1mpm",
    "question": "At 298.2 K the relationship between enthalpy of bond dissociation (in kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>) for hydrogen (E<sub>H</sub>) and its isotope, deuterium (E<sub>D</sub><sub></sub>), is best described by :",
    "options": [
      "$${E_H} = {1 \\over 2}{E_D}$$",
      "$${E_H} = {E_D}$$",
      "$${E_H} \\simeq {E_D} - 7.5$$",
      "$${E_H} = 2{E_D}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "$${E_H} \\simeq {E_D} - 7.5$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1gqond",
    "question": "The number of neutrons and electrons, respectively, present in the radioactive isotope of hydrogen is :",
    "options": [
      "1 and 1",
      "3 and 1",
      "2 and 1",
      "2 and 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "2 and 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktea7gyg",
    "question": "Deuterium resembles hydrogen in properties but :",
    "options": [
      "reacts slower than hydrogen",
      "reacts vigorously than hydrogen",
      "reacts just as hydrogen",
      "emits $$\\beta$$<sup>+</sup> particles"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "reacts slower than hydrogen"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktiaoh2u",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : The process of producing syn-gas is called gasification of coal.<br/><br/>Statement II : The composition of syn-gas is CO + CO<sub>2</sub> + H<sub>2</sub> (1 : 1 : 1)<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjvxej8",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is incorrect?",
    "options": [
      "Atomic hydrogen is produced when H<sub>2</sub> molecules at a high temperature are irradiated with UV radiation.",
      "At around 2000 K, the dissociation of dihydrogen into its atoms is nearly 8.1%",
      "Bond dissociation enthalpy of H<sub>2</sub> is highest among diatomic gaseous molecules which contain a single bond.",
      "Dihydrogen is produced on reacting zinc with HCl as well as NaOH<sub>(aq)</sub>."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "At around 2000 K, the dissociation of dihydrogen into its atoms is nearly 8.1%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55n9j37",
    "question": "<p>Hydrogen has three isotopes : protium (<sup>1</sup>H), deuterium (<sup>2</sup>H or D) and tritium (<sup>3</sup>H or T). They have nearly same chemical properties but different physical properties. They differ in :</p>",
    "options": [
      "number of protons.",
      "atomic number.",
      "electronic configuration.",
      "atomic mass."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "atomic mass."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56apdvs",
    "question": "<p>Dihydrogen reacts with CuO to give :</p>",
    "options": [
      "CuH<sub>2</sub>",
      "Cu",
      "Cu<sub>2</sub>O",
      "Cu(OH)<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Cu"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c6hz9b",
    "question": "<p>The highest industrial consumption of molecular hydrogen is to produce compounds of element :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Carbon",
      "Nitrogen",
      "Oxygen",
      "Chlorine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Nitrogen"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f6u0xy",
    "question": "<p>High purity (&gt; 99.95%) dihydrogen is obtained by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "reaction of zinc with aqueous alkali.",
      "electrolysis of acidified water using platinum electrodes.",
      "electrolysis of warm aqueous barium hydroxide solution between nickel electrodes.",
      "reaction of zinc with dilute acid."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "electrolysis of warm aqueous barium hydroxide solution between nickel electrodes."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldoiprbs",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Hydrogen is an environment friendly fuel.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Atomic number of hydrogen is 1 and it is a very light element.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsrijii",
    "question": "<p>Which of the given compounds can enhance the efficiency of hydrogen storage tank?</p>",
    "options": [
      "SiH$$_4$$",
      "Li/P$$_4$$",
      "NaNi$$_5$$",
      "Di-isobutylaluminium hydride"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "NaNi$$_5$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu0q01a",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 669px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Cobalt catalyst</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{(H_2+Cl_2)}$$ production</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Syngas</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Water gas production</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Nickel catalyst</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Coal gasification</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Brine solution</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Methanol production</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp2ll7k",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements, one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Isotopes of hydrogen have almost same chemical properties, but difference in their rates of reaction.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Isotopes of hydrogen have different enthalpy of bond dissociation.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguz6w0o",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement-I : Methane and steam passed over a heated $$\\mathrm{Ni}$$ catalyst produces hydrogen gas.</p>\n<p>Statement-II : Sodium nitrite reacts with $$\\mathrm{NH}_{4} \\mathrm{Cl}$$ to give $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}, \\mathrm{N}_{2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{NaCl}$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Both the statements I and II are incorrect",
      "Both the statements I and II are correct",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Both the statements I and II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvtrmob",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Physical properties of isotopes of hydrogen are different.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Mass difference between isotopes of hydrogen is very large.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is false",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is true",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgygojv0",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two reactions, involved in the commercial production of dihydrogen (H$$_2$$). The two reactions are carried out at temperature \"T$$_1$$\" and \"T$$_2$$\", respectively</p>\n<p>$$C(s) + {H_2}O(g)\\buildrel {{T_1}} \\over\n \\longrightarrow CO(g) + {H_2}(g)$$</p>\n<p>$$CO(g) + {H_2}O(g)\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{Catalyst}^{{T_2}}} C{O_2}(g) + {H_2}(g)$$</p>\n<p>The temperatures T$$_1$$ and T$$_2$$ are correctly related as :</p>",
    "options": [
      "T$$_1$$ < T$$_2$$",
      "T$$_1$$ = T$$_2$$",
      "T$$_1$$ = 100 K, T$$_2$$ = 1270 K",
      "T$$_1$$ > T$$_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "T$$_1$$ > T$$_2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh27my4y",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements, one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Loss of electron from hydrogen atom results in nucleus of $$\\sim 1.5 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{pm}$$ size.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Proton $$\\left(\\mathrm{H}^{+}\\right)$$ always exists in combined form.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "preparation-and-properties-of-hydrogen",
    "solution": "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "uIyQIg8dZMaxri67",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements about water is FALSE?",
    "options": [
      "Water is oxidized to oxygen during photosynthesis",
      "Water can act both as an acid and as a base.",
      "There is extensive intramolecular hydrogen bonding in the condensed phase. ",
      "Ice formed by heavy water sinks in normal water"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "water-and-heavy-water",
    "solution": "There is extensive intramolecular hydrogen bonding in the condensed phase. "
  },
  {
    "id": "STHwuGYJJPFlImZWCGuMU",
    "question": "Identify the <b>incorrect</b> statement regarding heavy water :",
    "options": [
      "It reacts with Al<sub>4</sub>C<sub>3</sub> to produce CD<sub>4</sub> and Al(OD)<sub>3</sub>\n.",
      "It is used as a coolant in nuclear reactors.",
      "It reacts with CaC<sub>2</sub> to produce C<sub>2</sub>D<sub>2</sub> and Ca(OD)<sub>2</sub>\n.",
      "It reacts with SO<sub>3</sub> to form deuterated sulphuric acid (D<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>)."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "water-and-heavy-water",
    "solution": "It is used as a coolant in nuclear reactors."
  },
  {
    "id": "Yrn6AmEckCM9wHxSTwOeB",
    "question": "The number of water molecule(s) not\ncoordinated to copper ion directly in\nCuSO<sub>4</sub>.5H<sub>2</sub>O, is :",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "4",
      "3",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "water-and-heavy-water",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZZUuqVeJd1zHz4hd6Y3rsa0w2w9jwwe2x42",
    "question": "The synonym for water gas when used in the production of methanol is :",
    "options": [
      "fuel gas\n",
      "laughing gas",
      "syn gas",
      "natural gas "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "water-and-heavy-water",
    "solution": "syn gas"
  },
  {
    "id": "rHodv5IEGs1I9NXtf5jgy2xukfi6dkjr",
    "question": "The equation that represents the water-gas shift\nreaction is :",
    "options": [
      "CO(g) + H<sub>2</sub>O(g) $$\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{Catalyst}^{673K}} $$ CO<sub>2</sub>(g) + H<sub>2</sub>(g)",
      "CH<sub>4</sub>(g) + H<sub>2</sub>O(g) $$\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{Ni}^{1270K}} $$ CO(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub>(g)",
      "C(s) + H<sub>2</sub>O(g) $$\\buildrel {1270K} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ CO(g) + H<sub>2</sub>(g)",
      "2C(s) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) + 4N<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\buildrel {1273K} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ 2CO(g) + 4N<sub>2</sub>(g)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "water-and-heavy-water",
    "solution": "CO(g) + H<sub>2</sub>O(g) $$\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{Catalyst}^{673K}} $$ CO<sub>2</sub>(g) + H<sub>2</sub>(g)"
  },
  {
    "id": "TTZObNnBixyownou5G1kltaoghd",
    "question": "Water does not produce CO on reacting with :",
    "options": [
      "C",
      "CH<sub>4</sub>",
      "C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>8</sub>",
      "CO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "water-and-heavy-water",
    "solution": "CO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "3dkcKHthI3ZfuQI5mk1kluct6a6",
    "question": "Statements about heavy water are given below :<br/><br/>A. Heavy water is used in exchange reactions for the study of reaction mechanisms.<br/><br/>B. Heavy water is prepared by exhaustive electrolysis of water.<br/><br/>(C) Heavy water has higher boiling point than ordinary water.<br/><br/>(D) Viscosity of H<sub>2</sub>O is greater than D<sub>2</sub>O.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "A, B, and C only",
      "A and C only",
      "A and D only",
      "A and B only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "water-and-heavy-water",
    "solution": "A, B, and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "PAgw0KDStIacoEbhuH1kmj8ey0p",
    "question": "The INCORRECT statement(s) about heavy water is (are)<br/><br/>(A) used as a moderator in nuclear reactor<br/><br/>(B) obtained as a by-product in fertilizer industry<br/><br/>(C) used for the study of reaction mechanism<br/><br/>(D) has a higher dielectric constant than water<br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(D) only",
      "(B) and (D) only",
      "(B) only",
      "(C) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "water-and-heavy-water",
    "solution": "(D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt32bz5",
    "question": "The water having more dissolved O<sub>2</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "boiling water",
      "water at 80$$^\\circ$$C",
      "polluted water",
      "water at 4$$^\\circ$$C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "water-and-heavy-water",
    "solution": "water at 4$$^\\circ$$C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktcqygaz",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).<br/><br/>Assertion (A) : Heavy water is used for the study of reaction mechanism.<br/><br/>Reason (R) : The rate of reaction for the cleavage of O - H bond is slower than that of O - D bond.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the true explanation of (A).",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the true explanation of (A).",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true.",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "water-and-heavy-water",
    "solution": "(A) is true but (R) is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo85213",
    "question": "The normal rain water is slightly acidic and its $\\mathrm{pH}$ value is $5.6$ because of which one of the following?",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{N}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{5}+\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{HNO}_{3}$",
      "$2 \\mathrm{SO}_{2}+\\mathrm{O}_{2}+2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$",
      "$4 \\mathrm{NO}_{2}+\\mathrm{O}_{2}+2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow 4 \\mathrm{HNO}_{3}$",
      "$\\mathrm{CO}_{2}+\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{CO}_{3}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "hydrogen",
    "topic": "water-and-heavy-water",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{CO}_{2}+\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{CO}_{3}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "5VhUNGZC3Ih0M1jv",
    "question": "Species acting as both Bronsted acid and base is :",
    "options": [
      "(HSO<sub>4</sub>)<sup>-1</sup>",
      "Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>",
      "NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "OH<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "(HSO<sub>4</sub>)<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "BjNHwlQ1smZPuAsw",
    "question": "The conjugate base of H<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub><sup>-</sup> is :",
    "options": [
      "$$PO_4^{3-}$$",
      "$$HPO_4^{2-}$$",
      "H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> ",
      "P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "$$HPO_4^{2-}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "vckZKHCipEfA0nTp",
    "question": "What is the conjugate base of OH<sup>-</sup>?",
    "options": [
      "O<sub>2</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O ",
      "O<sup>-</sup>",
      "O<sup>-2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "O<sup>-2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "QKKG3pWkKH2YvftO",
    "question": "The first and second dissociation constants of an acid H<sub>2</sub>A are 1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>−5</sup>\n and 5.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>−10</sup> respectively. The overall dissociation constant of the acid will be :",
    "options": [
      "5.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>−5</sup>",
      "5.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup>",
      "5.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>−15</sup>",
      "5.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "5.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>−15</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "JC7Yq9RbskMJSRmo",
    "question": "Four species are listed below <br/>\ni. $$HCO_3^−$$<br/> \nii. $$H_3O^+$$<br/>\niii. $$HSO_4^−$$<br/>\niv. $$HSO_3F$$<br/>\nWhich one of the following is the correct sequence of their acid strength?",
    "options": [
      "iv &lt; ii &lt; iii &lt; I ",
      "ii &lt; iii &lt; i &lt; iv ",
      "i &lt; iii &lt; ii &lt; iv ",
      "iii &lt; i &lt; iv &lt; ii "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "i &lt; iii &lt; ii &lt; iv "
  },
  {
    "id": "0uLOaBC4G2UrdrHb",
    "question": "Three reactions involving $$H_2PO_4^−$$ are given below :<br/><br>\n(i) H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>O $$\\to$$ H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup> + $$H_2PO_4^−$$<br/><br>\n(ii) $$H_2PO_4^−$$ + H<sub>2</sub>O $$\\to$$ $$HPO_4^{2−}$$ + H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup><br/><br>\n(iii) $$H_2PO_4^−$$ + OH<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> + O<sup>2-</sup><br/><br>\nIn which of the above does $$H_2PO_4^−$$ act as an acid?</br></br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "(ii) only",
      "(i) and (ii)",
      "(iii) only",
      "(i) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "(ii) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "vEHsVLPLszmhK22W",
    "question": "Which of the following are Lewis acids?\n",
    "options": [
      "BCl<sub>3</sub> and AlCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "PH<sub>3</sub> and BCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "AlCl<sub>3</sub> and SiCl<sub>4</sub> ",
      "PH<sub>3</sub> and SiCl<sub>4</sub>\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "BCl<sub>3</sub> and AlCl<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "aYVW7FnWxEC4TOAkuok7v",
    "question": "Which of the following is a Lewis acid?",
    "options": [
      "PH<sub>3</sub>",
      "B(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>",
      "NaH",
      "NF<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "B(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "AujBC42nW8tnVlF4WP3rsa0w2w9jx80i0yx",
    "question": "The decreasing order of electrical conductivity of the following aqueous solutions is :\n<br/><br>0.1 M Formic acid (A),\n<br/><br>0.1 M Acetic acid (B),\n<br/><br>0.1 M Benzoic acid (C)</br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "A &gt; B &gt; C",
      "C &gt; B &gt; A",
      "A &gt; C &gt; B",
      "C &gt; A &gt; B"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "A &gt; C &gt; B"
  },
  {
    "id": "xTuVm5bTakukx8E7331kmj7glkn",
    "question": "Which of the following compound CANNOT act as a Lewis base?",
    "options": [
      "SF<sub>4</sub>",
      "NF<sub>3</sub>",
      "ClF<sub>3</sub>",
      "PCl<sub>5</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "PCl<sub>5</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59quy18",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R :</p>\n<p>Assertion A : The amphoteric nature of water is explained by using Lewis acid/base concept.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Water acts as an acid with NH<sub>3</sub> and as a base with H<sub>2</sub>S.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "A is false but R is true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f6gtvc",
    "question": "<p>$${K_{{a_1}}}$$, $${K_{{a_2}}}$$ and $${K_{{a_3}}}$$ are the respective ionization constants for the following reactions (a), (b) and (c).</p>\n<p>(a) $${H_2}{C_2}{O_4} \\mathbin{\\lower.3ex\\hbox{$\\buildrel\\textstyle\\rightarrow\\over\n {\\smash{\\leftarrow}\\vphantom{_{\\vbox to.5ex{\\vss}}}}$}} {H^ + } + H{C_2}O_4^ - $$</p>\n<p>(b) $$H{C_2}O_4^ -  \\mathbin{\\lower.3ex\\hbox{$\\buildrel\\textstyle\\rightarrow\\over\n {\\smash{\\leftarrow}\\vphantom{_{\\vbox to.5ex{\\vss}}}}$}} {H^ + } + {C_2}O_4^{2 - }$$</p>\n<p>(c) $${H_2}{C_2}O_4^{} \\mathbin{\\lower.3ex\\hbox{$\\buildrel\\textstyle\\rightarrow\\over\n {\\smash{\\leftarrow}\\vphantom{_{\\vbox to.5ex{\\vss}}}}$}} 2{H^ + } + {C_2}O_4^{2 - }$$</p>\n<p>The relationship between $${K_{{a_1}}}$$, $${K_{{a_2}}}$$ and $${K_{{a_3}}}$$ is given as :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${K_{{a_3}}}$$ $$=$$ $${K_{{a_1}}}$$ $$+$$ $${K_{{a_2}}}$$",
      "$${K_{{a_3}}}$$ $$=$$ $${K_{{a_1}}}$$ $$-$$ $${K_{{a_2}}}$$",
      "$${K_{{a_3}}}$$ $$=$$ $${K_{{a_1}}}$$ $$/$$ $${K_{{a_2}}}$$",
      "$${K_{{a_3}}}$$ $$=$$ $${K_{{a_1}}}$$ $$\\times$$ $${K_{{a_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "$${K_{{a_3}}}$$ $$=$$ $${K_{{a_1}}}$$ $$\\times$$ $${K_{{a_2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nwijti",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Permanganate titrations are not performed in presence of hydrochloric acid.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Chlorine is formed as a consequence of oxidation of hydrochloric acid.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathrm{A}$$",
      "Both $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ are true but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathrm{A}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is false",
      "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ostwald's-dilution-law-and-concept-of-acid-and-base",
    "solution": "Both $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathrm{A}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "RUQ483f9Av4JbQrM",
    "question": "1 M NaCL and 1 M HCL are present in an aqueous solution. The solution is",
    "options": [
      "not a buffer solution with pH &lt; 7",
      "not a buffer solution with pH &gt; 7",
      "a buffer solution with pH &lt; 7",
      "a buffer solution with pH &gt; 7"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "not a buffer solution with pH &lt; 7"
  },
  {
    "id": "ddKU1xjGhcvug3uI",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is not true?",
    "options": [
      "pH + pOH = 14 for all aqueous solutions",
      "The pH of 1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-8</sup> M HCl is 8",
      "96,500 coulombs of electricity when passed through a CuSO<sub>4</sub> solution deposits 1 gram equivalent of copper at the cathode",
      "The conjugate base of $$H_2PO_4^-$$ is $$HPO_4^{2-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "The pH of 1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-8</sup> M HCl is 8"
  },
  {
    "id": "36fILz6BGvxDNX8F",
    "question": "When rain is accompanied by a thunderstorm, the collected rain water will have a pH value :",
    "options": [
      "slightly higher than that when the thunderstorm is not there",
      "uninfluenced by occurence of thunderstorm",
      "which depends on the amount of dust in air",
      "slightly lower than that of rain water without thunderstorm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "slightly lower than that of rain water without thunderstorm"
  },
  {
    "id": "lhdzuk8TeyLzVzDI",
    "question": "Hydrogen ion concentration in mol / L in a solution of pH = 5.4 will be :",
    "options": [
      "3.98 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-6</sup>",
      "3.68 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-6</sup>",
      "3.88 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>6</sup>",
      "3.98 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "3.98 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-6</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "RE5uolgWBFOkWdLk",
    "question": "The pK<sub>a</sub> of a weak acid (HA) is 4.5. The pOH of an aqueous buffered solution of HA in which 50% of\nthe acid is ionized is :",
    "options": [
      "7.0",
      "4.5",
      "2.5",
      "9.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "9.5"
  },
  {
    "id": "jqWGX93OB4i4nQKN",
    "question": "The pK<sub>a</sub> of a weak acid, HA, is 4.80. The pK<sub>b</sub> of a weak base, BOH, is 4.78. The pH of an aqueous\nsolution of the corresponding salt, BA, will be",
    "options": [
      "9.58",
      "4.79",
      "7.01",
      "9.22"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "7.01"
  },
  {
    "id": "qCGfhtpBGQHYly6m",
    "question": "At 25°C, the solubility product of Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> is 1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–11</sup>. At which pH, will Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions start precipitating in the form of Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> from a solution of 0.001 M Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions?",
    "options": [
      "9",
      "10",
      "11",
      "8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "10"
  },
  {
    "id": "qGVWK1MZRBzzwjhZ",
    "question": "The pH of a 0.1 molar solution of the acid HQ is 3. The value of the ionization constant, K<sub>a</sub> of this acid is :",
    "options": [
      "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–1</sup>",
      "1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–3</sup>",
      "1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–5</sup>",
      "1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–7</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–5</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "RKYX99CCwQPpDEDk",
    "question": "How many litres of water must be added to 1 litre of an aqueous solution of HCl with a pH of 1 to create an\naqueous solution with pH of 2? ",
    "options": [
      "0.1 L",
      "0.9 L",
      "2.0 L",
      "9.0 L"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "9.0 L"
  },
  {
    "id": "puIn3AAAmkL0Nj6f",
    "question": "pK<sub>a</sub> of a weak acid (HA) and pK<sub>b</sub> of a weak base (BOH) are 3.2 and 3.4, respectively. The pH of their salt (AB) solution is :",
    "options": [
      "6.9",
      "7.0",
      "1.0",
      "7.2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "6.9"
  },
  {
    "id": "a665nN8laO2C2GPNZPZfO",
    "question": "Additin of sodium hydroxide solution to a weak acid (HA)results in a buffer of pH 6. If ionition constant of HA is 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup>, the ratio of salt to acid concentration in the buffer solution will be :",
    "options": [
      "4 : 5",
      "1 : 10",
      "10 : 1",
      "5 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "10 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "u3GyVK3XHCtIrlBEQI6r5",
    "question": "50 mL of 0.2 M ammonia solution is treated with 25 mL of 0.2 M HCl. If pK<sub>b</sub> of ammonia solution is 4.75, the pH of the mixture will be :\n",
    "options": [
      "3.75",
      "4.75",
      "8.25",
      "9.25"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "9.25"
  },
  {
    "id": "6kCnP3DxcB1v9UKL",
    "question": "An alkali is titrated against an acid with methyl orange as indicator, which of the following is a correct combination?",
    "options": [
      "<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n  <tr>\n    <th class=\"tg-amwm\">Base</th>\n    <th class=\"tg-amwm\">Acid</th>\n    <th class=\"tg-amwm\">End point</th>\n  </tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">Weak</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">Strong</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">Colourless to pink</td>\n  </tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
      "<table class=\"tg\">\n  <tbody><tr>\n    <th class=\"tg-uys7\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Base</span></th>\n    <th class=\"tg-uys7\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Acid</span></th>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">End point</span></th>\n  </tr>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-uys7\">Strong</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-uys7\">Strong</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">Pinkish red to yellow</td>\n  </tr>\n</tbody></table>",
      "<table class=\"tg\">\n  <tbody><tr>\n    <th class=\"tg-uys7\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Base</span></th>\n    <th class=\"tg-uys7\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Acid</span></th>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">End point</span></th>\n  </tr>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-uys7\">Weak</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-uys7\">Strong</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">Yellow to pinkish red</td>\n  </tr>\n</tbody></table>",
      "<table class=\"tg\">\n  <tbody><tr>\n    <th class=\"tg-uys7\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Base</span></th>\n    <th class=\"tg-uys7\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Acid</span></th>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">End point</span></th>\n  </tr>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-uys7\">Strong</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-uys7\">Strong</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">Pink to colourless</td>\n  </tr>\n</tbody></table>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "<table class=\"tg\">\n  <tbody><tr>\n    <th class=\"tg-uys7\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Base</span></th>\n    <th class=\"tg-uys7\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Acid</span></th>\n    <th class=\"tg-baqh\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">End point</span></th>\n  </tr>\n  <tr>\n    <td class=\"tg-uys7\">Weak</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-uys7\">Strong</td>\n    <td class=\"tg-baqh\">Yellow to pinkish red</td>\n  </tr>\n</tbody></table>"
  },
  {
    "id": "5kVpUgJHVoUaEKV1H9Noc",
    "question": "Following four solutions are prepared by mixing different volumes of NaOH and HCl of different concentrations, pH of which one of them will be equal to 1 ? ",
    "options": [
      "100 mL $${M \\over {10}}$$ HCl + 100 mL $${M \\over {10}}$$ NaOH",
      "75 mL $${M \\over {5}}$$ HCl + 25 mL $${M \\over {5}}$$ NaOH",
      "60 mL $${M \\over {10}}$$ HCl + 40 mL $${M \\over {10}}$$ NaOH",
      "55 mL $${M \\over {10}}$$ HCl + 45 mL $${M \\over {10}}$$ NaOH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "75 mL $${M \\over {5}}$$ HCl + 25 mL $${M \\over {5}}$$ NaOH"
  },
  {
    "id": "zbTfltnQSROPCkwZIOezy",
    "question": "20 mL of 0.1 M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> solution is added to 30 mL of of 0.2 M NH<sub>4</sub>OH solution. The pH of the resultant mixture is : [pk<sub>b</sub> of NH<sub>4</sub>OH = 4.7].",
    "options": [
      "5.2",
      "9.0",
      "5.0",
      "9.4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "9.0"
  },
  {
    "id": "Kc2R8r4GVp3kehsCOm3rsa0w2w9jwvcw3hj",
    "question": "Consider the following statements\n<br/>(a) The pH of a mixture containing 400 mL of 0.1 M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and 400 mL of 0.1 M NaOH will be approximately 1.3\n<br/>(b) Ionic product of water is temperature dependent.\n<br/>(c) A monobasic acid with Ka = 10<sup>–5</sup>\n has pH = 5. The degree of dissociation of this acid is 50 %.\n<br/>(d) The Le Chatelier's principle is not applicable to common-ion effect. \n<br/><br/>The correct statements are :",
    "options": [
      "(a) and (b)",
      "(a), (b) and (c)",
      "(a), (b) and (d)",
      "(b) and (c)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "(a), (b) and (c)"
  },
  {
    "id": "66N4haRBTOcgD7A54JVS7",
    "question": "The pH of rain water, is approximately : ",
    "options": [
      "5.6 ",
      "7.5",
      "7.0",
      "6.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "5.6 "
  },
  {
    "id": "uG8oesPo5DsDJYyhEn7k9k2k5h5xstn",
    "question": "The strength of an aqueous NaOH solution is most accurately determined by titrating : <br/>(Note : consider that\nan appropriate indicator is used)",
    "options": [
      "Aq. NaOH in a pipette and aqueous oxalic acid in a burette",
      "Aq. NaOH in a burette and aqueous oxalic acid in a conical flask",
      "Aq. NaOH in a volumetric flask and concentrated H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> in a conical flask",
      "Aq. NaOH in a burette and concentrated H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> in a conical flask"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "Aq. NaOH in a burette and aqueous oxalic acid in a conical flask"
  },
  {
    "id": "MMirQN7QrUQSFVzilK7k9k2k5hlglgv",
    "question": "For the following Assertion and Reason, the\ncorrect option is :\n<br/><br/><b>Assertion :</b> The pH of water increases with\nincrease in temperature.<br/>\n<br/><b>Reason :</b> The dissociation of water into H<sup>+</sup> and\nOH<sup>–</sup> is an exothermic reaction.",
    "options": [
      "Both assertion and reason are false.",
      "Both assertion and reason are true, but the\nreason is not the correct explanation for the\nassertion.",
      "Both assertion and reason are true, and the\nreason is the correct explanation for the\nassertion.",
      "Assertion is not true, but reason is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "Both assertion and reason are false."
  },
  {
    "id": "B4iZSjmdcOHx6CvPr6jgy2xukf25kmue",
    "question": "An acidic buffer is obtained on mixing :",
    "options": [
      "100 mL of 0.1 M HCl and 200 mL of 0.1 M CH<sub>3</sub>COONa",
      "100 mL of 0.1 M HCl and 200 mL of 0.1 M NaCl",
      "100 mL of 0.1 M CH<sub>3</sub>COOH and 100 mL of 0.1 M NaOH",
      "100 mL of 0.1 M CH<sub>3</sub>COOH and 200 mL of 0.1 M NaOH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "100 mL of 0.1 M HCl and 200 mL of 0.1 M CH<sub>3</sub>COONa"
  },
  {
    "id": "wEIHpXzK3AHH7ZEofjjgy2xukft77oy5",
    "question": "Arrange the following solutions in the\ndecreasing order of pOH :\n<br/><br/>(A) 0.01 M HCl\n<br/>(B) 0.01 M NaOH\n<br/>(C) 0.01 M CH<sub>3</sub>COONa\n<br/>(D) 0.01 M NaCl\n",
    "options": [
      "(B) &gt; (C) &gt; (D) &gt; (A)",
      "(A) &gt; (D) &gt; (C) &gt; (B)",
      "(A) &gt; (C) &gt; (D) &gt; (B)",
      "(B) &gt; (D) &gt; (C) &gt; (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "(A) &gt; (D) &gt; (C) &gt; (B)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktb4nsec",
    "question": "Given below are two statements.<br/><br/>Statement I : In the titration between strong acid and weak base methyl orange is suitable as an indicator.<br/><br/>Statement II : For titration of acetic acid with NaOH phenolphthalein is not a suitable indicator.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55mylff",
    "question": "<p>A student needs to prepare a buffer solution of propanoic acid and its sodium salt with pH 4. The ratio of $${{[C{H_3}C{H_2}CO{O^ - }]} \\over {[C{H_3}C{H_2}COOH]}}$$ required to make buffer is ___________.</p>\n<p>Given : $${K_a}(C{H_3}C{H_2}COOH) = 1.3 \\times {10^{ - 5}}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.03",
      "0.13",
      "0.23",
      "0.33"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "0.13"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i4j1yd",
    "question": "<p>Class XII students were asked to prepare one litre of buffer solution of $$\\mathrm{pH} \\,8.26$$ by their Chemistry teacher: The amount of ammonium chloride to be dissolved by the student in $$0.2\\, \\mathrm{M}$$ ammonia solution to make one litre of the buffer is :</p>\n<p>(Given: $$\\mathrm{pK}_{\\mathrm{b}}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)=4.74$$</p>\n<p>Molar mass of $$\\mathrm{NH}_{3}=17 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$</p>\n<p>Molar mass of $$\\mathrm{NH}_{4} \\mathrm{Cl}=53.5 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "53.5 g",
      "72.3 g",
      "107.0 g",
      "126.0 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "107.0 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rjgnmc",
    "question": "<p>$$200 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ of $$0.01 \\,\\mathrm{M} \\,\\mathrm{HCl}$$ is mixed with $$400 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ of $$0.01 \\,\\mathrm{M} \\,\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$$. The $$\\mathrm{pH}$$ of the mixture is _________.</p>\n<p>Given: $$\\log {2}=0.30, \\log 3=0.48, \\log 5=0.70, \\log 7=0.84, \\log 11=1.04$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.14",
      "1.78",
      "2.34",
      "3.02"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "1.78"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo9pvcf",
    "question": "The incorrect statement for the use of indicators in acid-base titration is :",
    "options": [
      "Phenolphthalein is a suitable indicator for a weak acid vs strong base titration.",
      "Methyl orange may be used for a weak acid vs weak base titration.",
      "Methyl orange is a suitable indicator for a strong acid vs weak base titration.",
      "Phenolphthalein may be used for a strong acid vs strong base titration."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "Methyl orange may be used for a weak acid vs weak base titration."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu0alpt",
    "question": "<p>When the hydrogen ion concentration [H$$^+$$] changes by a factor of 1000, the value of pH of the solution __________</p>",
    "options": [
      "decreases by 2 units",
      "increases by 2 units",
      "decreases by 3 units",
      "increases by 1000 units"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "decreases by 3 units"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnzrkr2",
    "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct?<br/><br/>\n(A) The $\\mathrm{pH}$ of $1 \\times 10^{-8}~ \\mathrm{M} ~\\mathrm{HCl}$ solution is 8 .<br/><br/>\n(B) The conjugate base of $\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{PO}_{4}^{-}$ is $\\mathrm{HPO}_{4}^{2-}$.<br/><br/>\n(C) $\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{w}}$ increases with increase in temperature.<br/><br/>\n(D) When a solution of a weak monoprotic acid is titrated against a strong base at half neutralisation point, $\\mathrm{pH}=\\frac{1}{2} \\mathrm{pK}_{\\mathrm{a}}$<br/><br/>\n\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below:",
    "options": [
      "$(\\mathrm{A}),(\\mathrm{B}),(\\mathrm{C})$",
      "(B), (C)",
      "(B), (C), (D)",
      "(A), (D)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "(B), (C)"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmb5f",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : A Buffer solution is the mixture of a salt and an acid or a base mixed in any particular quantities</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : Blood is naturally occurring buffer solution whose $$\\mathrm{pH}$$ is maintained by $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{CO}_3 / \\mathrm{HCO}_3{ }^{\\ominus}$$ concentrations.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmaun",
    "question": "<p>The equilibrium $$\\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7^{2-} \\rightleftharpoons 2 \\mathrm{CrO}_4^{2-}$$ is shifted to the right in :</p>",
    "options": [
      "a weakly acidic medium\n",
      "a basic medium\n",
      "a neutral medium\n",
      "an acidic medium"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "ph,-buffer-and-indicators",
    "solution": "a basic medium\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "Foi0Nvb4HaCq16QX",
    "question": "An aqueous solution contains 0.10 M H<sub>2</sub>S and 0.20 M HCl. If the equilibrium constants for the formation of HS<sup>–</sup> from H<sub>2</sub>S is 1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–7</sup> and that of S<sup>2-</sup> from HS<sup>–</sup> ions is 1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–13</sup> then the concentration of S<sup>2-</sup> ions in aqueous solution is :",
    "options": [
      "5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–19</sup>",
      "5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–8</sup>",
      "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–20</sup>",
      "6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–21</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "salt-hydrolysis",
    "solution": "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–20</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "jAMoJTWC2nSpjGEc",
    "question": "Which of the following salts is the most basic in aqueous solution?",
    "options": [
      "Pb(CH<sub>3</sub>COO)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Al(CN)<sub>3</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COOK",
      "FeCl<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "salt-hydrolysis",
    "solution": "CH<sub>3</sub>COOK"
  },
  {
    "id": "cmYmpm6gdsmzUDxsCn3rsa0w2w9jx0xo7lv",
    "question": "The pH of a 0.02 M NH<sub>4</sub>Cl solution will be :\n<br/> [given K<sub>b</sub> (NH<sub>4</sub>OH) = 10<sup>–5</sup>\n and log 2 = 0.301]",
    "options": [
      "2.56",
      "5.35",
      "4.35",
      "4.65"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "salt-hydrolysis",
    "solution": "5.35"
  },
  {
    "id": "1yIt1yVHzptcjID1Jm1kmlnapae",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion A and the other labelled as reason R<br/><br/>Assertion A : During the boiling of water having temporary hardness, Mg(HCO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> is converted to MgCO<sub>3</sub>.<br/><br/>Reason R : The solubility product of Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> is greater than that of MgCO<sub>3</sub>.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true but R is not the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is false but R is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "salt-hydrolysis",
    "solution": "A is false but R is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6e0t4v9",
    "question": "<p>$$20 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ of $$0.1\\, \\mathrm{M} \\,\\mathrm{NH}_{4} \\mathrm{OH}$$ is mixed with $$40 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ of $$0.05 \\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{HCl}$$. The $$\\mathrm{pH}$$ of the mixture is nearest to :</p>\n<p>(Given : $$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{b}}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{4} \\mathrm{OH}\\right)=1 \\times 10^{-5}, \\log 2=0.30, \\log 3=0.48, \\log 5=0.69, \\log 7=0.84, \\log 11= 1.04)$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "3.2",
      "4.2",
      "5.2",
      "6.2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "salt-hydrolysis",
    "solution": "5.2"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc5ys78",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : Aqueous solution of ammonium carbonate is basic.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : Acidic/basic nature of salt solution of a salt of weak acid and weak base depends on $$K_a$$ and $$K_b$$ value of acid and the base forming it.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct\n",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect\n",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "salt-hydrolysis",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "P0hxinWVAB203vL9",
    "question": "Let the solubility of an aqueous solution of Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> be x then its K<sub>sp</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "4x<sup>3</sup>",
      "108x<sup>5</sup>",
      "27x<sup>4</sup>",
      "9x"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "4x<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "h4URh3UyijpeHvTH",
    "question": "The solubility in water of a sparingly soluble salt AB<sub>2</sub> is 1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-5</sup> mol L<sup>-1</sup>. Its solubility product number will be :",
    "options": [
      "4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-10</sup>",
      "1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-15</sup>",
      "1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-10</sup>",
      "4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-15</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-15</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "xxqL8L3VO9oz19IW",
    "question": "The molar solubility (in ol L<sup>-1</sup>) of a sparingly soluble salt MX<sub>4</sub> is \"s\". The corresponding solubility product is K<sub>sp</sub>. 's' is given in term of K<sub>sp</sub> by the relation :",
    "options": [
      "s = (256 K<sub>sp</sub>)<sup>1/5</sup>",
      "s = (128 K<sub>sp</sub>)<sup>1/4</sup>",
      "s = ( K<sub>sp</sub> / 128)<sup>1/4</sup>",
      "s = (K<sub>sp</sub> / 256)<sup>1/5</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "s = (K<sub>sp</sub> / 256)<sup>1/5</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "rnHtJcU7gKFAqmjU",
    "question": "The solubility product of a salt having general formula MX<sub>2</sub>, in water is: 4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-12</sup> . The\nconcentration of M<sup>2+</sup> ions in the aqueous solution of the salt is :",
    "options": [
      "2.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-6</sup> M",
      "4.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-10</sup> M",
      "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-4</sup> M",
      "1.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-4</sup> M"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-4</sup> M"
  },
  {
    "id": "MyppAjJ3G6Ufgaoa",
    "question": "In a sautrated solution of the sparingly soluble strong electrolyte AgIO<sub>3</sub> (Molecular mass = 283) the\nequilibrium which sets in is <br/>\nAgIO<sub>3(s)</sub> $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ Ag<sup>+</sup>(aq) + $$IO_3^-$$<br/>\nIf the solubility product constant K<sub>sp</sub> of AgIO<sub>3</sub> at a given temperature is 1.0 $$\\times$$10<sup>−8</sup>, what is the mass of AgIO<sub>3</sub> contained in 100 ml of its saturated solution?",
    "options": [
      "28.3 × 10<sup>−2</sup> g",
      "2.83 × 10<sup>−3</sup> g",
      "1.0 × 10<sup>−7</sup> g",
      "1.0 × 10<sup>−4</sup> g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "2.83 × 10<sup>−3</sup> g"
  },
  {
    "id": "4dFsBO6B8XgokkaY",
    "question": "Solid Ba(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> is gradually dissolved in a 1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-4</sup> M Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> solution. At what concentration of Ba<sup>2+</sup> will a precipitate begin to form ?<br/>\n(K<sub>sp</sub> for BaCO<sub>3</sub> = 5.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>−9</sup> )",
    "options": [
      "5.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-5</sup> M",
      "8.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-8</sup> M",
      "8.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-7</sup> M",
      "4.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-5</sup> M"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "5.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-5</sup> M"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZYnlp6BhJXpGc1fB",
    "question": "Solubility product of silver bromide is 5.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–13</sup>. The quantity of potassium bromide (molar mass taken as 120g of mol<sup>–1</sup>) to be added to 1 litre of 0.05 M solution of silver nitrate to start the\nprecipitation of AgBr is :",
    "options": [
      "1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–10</sup> g",
      "1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–9</sup> g",
      "6.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–5</sup> g",
      "5.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–8</sup> g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–9</sup> g"
  },
  {
    "id": "4REoJPtiRGdnZEXE",
    "question": "An aqueous solution contains an unknown concentration of Ba<sup>2+</sup>. When 50 mL of a 1 M solution of Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> is added, BaSO<sub>4</sub> just begins to precipitate. The final volume is 500 mL. The solubility product of BaSO<sub>4</sub> is 1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–10</sup>. What is the original concentration of Ba<sup>2+</sup>? ",
    "options": [
      "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–10</sup> M ",
      "5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–9</sup> M ",
      "2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–9</sup> M ",
      "1.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–9</sup> M "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "1.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>–9</sup> M "
  },
  {
    "id": "9L2veFGDZcPzQu5zUJcko",
    "question": "The minimum volume of water required to dissolve 0.1 g lead (II) chloride to get a saturated solution  (K<sub>sp</sub> of PbCl<sub>2</sub> = 3.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-8</sup> atomic mass of Pb = 207 u ) is :",
    "options": [
      "0.36 L",
      "17.98 L",
      "0.18 L",
      "1.798 L"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "0.18 L"
  },
  {
    "id": "XKkoVifHAJVoOa8Ft3d36",
    "question": "If solublity product of Zr<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>4</sub> is denoted by K<sub>sp</sub> and its molar solubility is denoted by S, then\nwhich of the following relation between S and K<sub>sp</sub> is correct ?",
    "options": [
      "$$S = {\\left( {{{{K_{sp}}} \\over {929}}} \\right)^{1/9}}$$",
      "$$S = {\\left( {{{{K_{sp}}} \\over {6912}}} \\right)^{1/7}}$$",
      "$$S = {\\left( {{{{K_{sp}}} \\over {144}}} \\right)^{1/6}}$$",
      "$$S = {\\left( {{{{K_{sp}}} \\over {216}}} \\right)^{1/7}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "$$S = {\\left( {{{{K_{sp}}} \\over {6912}}} \\right)^{1/7}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "KsBz03C1PotsX2wqbW3rsa0w2w9jx96xbuz",
    "question": "The molar solubility of Cd(OH)<sub>2</sub> is 1.84 × 10<sup>–5</sup>\n M in water. The expected solubility of Cd(OH)<sub>2</sub> in a buffer\nsolution of pH = 12 is : ",
    "options": [
      "2.49 × 10<sup>–10</sup> M",
      "1.84 × 10<sup>–9</sup>\n M",
      "6.23 × 10<sup>–11</sup> M",
      "$${{2.49} \\over {1.84}} \\times {10^{ - 9}}M$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "2.49 × 10<sup>–10</sup> M"
  },
  {
    "id": "pUfa4Ym8y6Xfaym8PQ3rsa0w2w9jx4yequb",
    "question": "What is the molar solubility of Al(OH)<sub>3</sub> in 0.2 M NaOH solution ? Given that, solubility product of Al(OH)<sub>3</sub> = 2.4 × 10<sup>–24</sup>\n :",
    "options": [
      "3 × 10<sup>–22</sup>",
      "3 × 10<sup>–19</sup>",
      "12 × 10<sup>–21</sup>",
      "12 × 10<sup>–22</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "3 × 10<sup>–22</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "ruSuuwhZ7iwJLKmaGKODQ",
    "question": "If K<sub>sp</sub> of Ag<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> is 8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–12</sup>, the molar solubility of Ag<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> in 0.1 M AgNO<sub>3</sub> is - ",
    "options": [
      "8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–12</sup> M ",
      "8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–10</sup> M ",
      "8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–13</sup> M ",
      "8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–11</sup> M "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–10</sup> M "
  },
  {
    "id": "utgcehQJcUzIbmHTinyGy",
    "question": "A mixture of 100 m mol of Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub> and 2 g of sodium sulphate was dissolved in water and the volume was made up to 100 mL. The mass of calcium sulphate formed and the concentration of OH<sup>–</sup> in resulting solution, respectively, are : (Molar mass of Ca (OH)<sub>2</sub>, Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and CaSO<sub>4</sub> are 74, 143 and 136 g mol<sup>–1</sup>\n , respectively; K<sub>sp</sub> of Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub> is 5.5 × 10<sup>–6</sup>\n) \n",
    "options": [
      "13.6g, 0.28 mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "13.6g, 0.14  mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "1.9g, 0.28 mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "1.9g, 0.14 mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "1.9g, 0.28 mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "CBU1jR4sZy8Hyhtey57k9k2k5icemzm",
    "question": "The K<sub>sp</sub> for the following dissociation is\n1.6 × 10<sup>–5</sup><br/><br/>\n$$PbC{l_{2(s)}} \\leftrightharpoons Pb_{(aq)}^{2 + } + 2Cl_{(aq)}^ - $$<br/><br/>\nWhich of the following choices is correct for\na mixture of 300 mL 0.134 M Pb(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> and\n100 mL 0.4 M NaCl ?",
    "options": [
      "Q &gt; K<sub>sp</sub>",
      "Not enough data provided",
      "Q &lt; K<sub>sp</sub>",
      "Q = K<sub>sp</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "Q &gt; K<sub>sp</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "iJn3IKg7Pnd9s0V1vS7k9k2k5lla8rp",
    "question": "The solubility product of Cr(OH)<sub>3</sub> at 298 K is\n6.0 × 10<sup>–31</sup>. The concentration of hydroxide ions\nin a saturated solution of Cr(OH)<sub>3</sub> will be :",
    "options": [
      "(2.22 × 10<sup>–31</sup>)<sup>1/4</sup>",
      "(4.86 × 10<sup>–29</sup>)<sup>1/4</sup>",
      "(18 × 10<sup>–31</sup>)<sup>1/4</sup>",
      "(18 × 10<sup>–31</sup>)<sup>1/2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "(18 × 10<sup>–31</sup>)<sup>1/4</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "H2zZyPaYCYEshked6Gjgy2xukevfq7al",
    "question": "For the following <b>Assertion</b> and <b>Reason</b>, the\ncorrect option is\n<br/><br/><b>Assertion (A):</b> When Cu (II) and sulphide ions\nare mixed, they react together\nextremely quickly to give a\nsolid.\n<br/><br/><b>Reason (R):</b> The equilibrium constant of\n<br/>Cu<sup>2+</sup>(aq) + S<sup>2–</sup>(aq) ⇌ CuS(s) is\nhigh because the solubility\nproduct is low.",
    "options": [
      "(A) is false and (R) is true.",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the\nexplanation for (A).",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the\nexplanation for (A).",
      "Both (A) and (R) are false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the\nexplanation for (A)."
  },
  {
    "id": "9tluPF7LC9EBRnfOeF1kls7vr2v",
    "question": "The solubility of AgCN in a buffer solution of pH = 3 is x. The value of x is : [Assume : No cyano complex is formed; K<sub>sp</sub>(AgCN) = 2.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$16</sup> and K<sub>a</sub>(HCN) = 6.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$10</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "1.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup>",
      "1.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup>",
      "2.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$16</sup>",
      "0.625 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "1.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "d5nZSxCsVC9CoGEX1N1kltas7ex",
    "question": "The solubility of Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub> in water is :<br/><br/>[Given : The solubility product of Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub> in water = 5.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "1.11 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup>",
      "1.11 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "1.77 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup>",
      "1.77 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "1.11 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krrhnxhk",
    "question": "A solution is 0.1 M in Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup> and 0.001 M in CrO$$_4^{2 - }$$. Solid AgNO<sub>3</sub> is gradually added to it. Assuming that the addition does not change in volume and K<sub>sp</sub>(AgCl) = 1.7 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$10</sup> M<sup>2</sup> and K<sub>sp</sub>(Ag<sub>2</sub>CrO<sub>4</sub>) = 1.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$12</sup> M<sup>3</sup>.<br/><br/>Select correct statement from the following :\n",
    "options": [
      "AgCl precipitates first because its K<sub>sp</sub> is high.",
      "Ag<sub>2</sub>CrO<sub>4</sub> precipitates first as its K<sub>sp</sub> is low.",
      "Ag<sub>2</sub>CrO<sub>4</sub> precipitates first because the amount of Ag<sup>+</sup> needed is low.",
      "AgCl will precipitate first as the amount of Ag<sup>+</sup> needed to precipitate is low."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "AgCl will precipitate first as the amount of Ag<sup>+</sup> needed to precipitate is low."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l548kqa9",
    "question": "<p>The solubility of AgCl will be maximum in which of the following?</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.01 M KCl",
      "0.01 M HCl",
      "0.01 M AgNO<sub>3</sub>",
      "Deionised water"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "Deionised water"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59qmg9d",
    "question": "<p>The K<sub>sp</sub> for bismuth sulphide (Bi<sub>2</sub>S<sub>3</sub>) is 1.08 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$73</sup>. The solubility of Bi<sub>2</sub>S<sub>3</sub> in mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup> at 298 K is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$15</sup>",
      "2.7 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$12</sup>",
      "3.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$10</sup>",
      "4.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$15</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguzjr9b",
    "question": "<p>$$25 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ of silver nitrate solution (1M) is added dropwise to $$25 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ of potassium iodide $$(1.05 \\mathrm{M})$$ solution. The ion(s) present in very small quantity in the solution is/are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{I^-}$$ only",
      "$$\\mathrm{K^+}$$ only",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ag^+}$$ and $$\\mathrm{I^-}$$ both",
      "$$\\mathrm{NO_3^-}$$ only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Ag^+}$$ and $$\\mathrm{I^-}$$ both"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsanzb5m",
    "question": "Solubility of calcium phosphate (molecular mass, M) in water is $\\mathrm{W_{g}}$ per $100 \\mathrm{~mL}$ at $25^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$. Its solubility product at $25^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$ will be approximately.",
    "options": [
      "$10^7\\left(\\frac{W}{M}\\right)^3$",
      "$10^3\\left(\\frac{\\mathrm{W}}{\\mathrm{M}}\\right)^5$",
      "$10^7\\left(\\frac{W}{M}\\right)^5$",
      "$10^5\\left(\\frac{\\mathrm{W}}{\\mathrm{M}}\\right)^5$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "$10^7\\left(\\frac{W}{M}\\right)^5$"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxzq6c0",
    "question": "<p>For a sparingly soluble salt $$\\mathrm{AB}_2$$, the equilibrium concentrations of $$\\mathrm{A}^{2+}$$ ions and $$B^{-}$$ ions are $$1.2 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{M}$$ and $$0.24 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{M}$$, respectively. The solubility product of $$\\mathrm{AB}_2$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$0.069 \\times 10^{-12}$$\n",
      "$$0.276 \\times 10^{-12}$$\n",
      "$$6.91 \\times 10^{-12}$$\n",
      "$$27.65 \\times 10^{-12}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "ionic-equilibrium",
    "topic": "solubility-product-and-common-ion-effect",
    "solution": "$$6.91 \\times 10^{-12}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "i4GqcPX1rTNDDfuk",
    "question": "Which one of the following ores is best concentrated by froth – floatation method?",
    "options": [
      "Magnetite",
      "Malachite ",
      "Galena",
      "Cassiterite"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "Galena"
  },
  {
    "id": "QHtu3F3jR3nmee7n",
    "question": "Which of the following factors is of <b>no significance</b> for roasting sulphide ores to the oxides and not\nsubjecting the sulphide ores to carbon reduction directly?  ",
    "options": [
      "Metal sulphides are thermodynamically more stable than CS<sub>2</sub>",
      "CO<sub>2</sub> is thermodynamically more stable than CS<sub>2</sub>",
      "Metal sulphides are less stable than the corresponding oxides",
      "CO<sub>2</sub> is more volatile than CS<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "Metal sulphides are less stable than the corresponding oxides"
  },
  {
    "id": "QPpBDaEXy72VYavK",
    "question": "Which one of the following ores is best concentrated by froth floatation method?",
    "options": [
      "Siderite",
      "Galena",
      "Malachite",
      "Magnetite"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "Galena"
  },
  {
    "id": "1fM0uOKXgH77sdhdAcrUU",
    "question": "In the leaching method, bauxite ore is digested with a concentrated solution of NaOH that produces 'X'.  When CO<sub>2</sub> gas is passed through the aqueous solution of 'X', a hydrated compound 'Y' is precipitated. 'X' and 'Y' respectively are : ",
    "options": [
      "NaAlO<sub>2</sub> &nbsp; and &nbsp; Al<sub>2</sub>(CO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>.x H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "A(OH)<sub>3</sub> &nbsp; and &nbsp; Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.x H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "Na[Al(OH)<sub>4</sub>] &nbsp; and &nbsp; Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.x H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "Na[Al(OH)<sub>4</sub>] &nbsp; and &nbsp; Al<sub>2</sub>(CO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>.x H<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "Na[Al(OH)<sub>4</sub>] &nbsp; and &nbsp; Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.x H<sub>2</sub>O"
  },
  {
    "id": "8kOTKOq3hXvrPlSSSm3rsa0w2w9jx4z8tme",
    "question": "The idea of froth floatation method came from a person X and this method is related to the process Y of ores. X and Y, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "washer woman and concentration",
      "fisher woman and concentration",
      "wisher man and reduction",
      "fisher man and reduction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "washer woman and concentration"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krrhf5dt",
    "question": "Consider two chemical reactions (A) and (B) that take place during metallurgical process:<br/><br/>(A) $$ZnC{O_{3(s)}}\\buildrel \\Delta  \\over\n \\longrightarrow Zn{O_{(s)}} + C{O_{2(g)}}$$<br/><br/>(B) $$2Zn{S_{(s)}} + 3{O_{2(g)}}\\buildrel \\Delta  \\over\n \\longrightarrow 2Zn{O_{(s)}} + 2S{O_{2(g)}}$$<br/><br/>The correct option of names given to them respectively is :",
    "options": [
      "(A) is calcination and (B) is roasting",
      "Both (A) and (B) are producing same product so both are roasting",
      "Both (A) and (B) are producing same product so both are calcination",
      "(A) is roasting and (B) is calcination"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "(A) is calcination and (B) is roasting"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krutaldk",
    "question": "In the leaching of alumina from bauxite, the ore expected to leach out in the process by reacting with NaOH is :",
    "options": [
      "TiO<sub>2</sub>",
      "Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "ZnO",
      "SiO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "SiO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krx5bn0e",
    "question": "Match List I with List II : (Both having metallurgical terms)<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(a)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Concentration of Ag ore</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(i)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Reverberatory furnace</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(b)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Blast furnace</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(ii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Pig iron</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(c)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Blister copper</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(iii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Leaching with dilute NaCN solution</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(d)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Froth floatation method</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(iv)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Sulfide ores</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(i), (c)-(iii), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56wthv6",
    "question": "<p>Statement I : Leaching of gold with cyanide ion in absence of air / O<sub>2</sub> leads to cyano complex of Au(III).</p>\n<p>Statement II : Zinc is oxidized during the displacement reaction carried out for gold extraction.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57rrclh",
    "question": "<p>Match List-I with List-II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 582px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 44px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 313px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 42px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 183px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Concentration of gold ore</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Aniline</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Leaching of alumina</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">NaOH</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Froth stabiliser</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">SO$$_2$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Blister copper</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">NaCN</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - (IV), (B) - (III), (C) - (II), (D) - (I)",
      "(A) - (IV), (B) - (II), (C) - (I), (D) - (III)",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (II), (C) - (I), (D) - (IV)",
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (IV), (C) - (III), (D) - (I)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "(A) - (IV), (B) - (II), (C) - (I), (D) - (III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58iyg9y",
    "question": "<p>The role of depressants in 'Froth Flotation method' is to</p>",
    "options": [
      "selectively prevent one component of the ore from coming to the froth.",
      "reduce the consumption of oil for froth formation.",
      "stabilize the froth.",
      "enhance non-wettability of the mineral particles."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "selectively prevent one component of the ore from coming to the froth."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5altec2",
    "question": "<p>Leaching of gold with dilute aqueous solution of NaCN in presence of oxygen gives complex [A], which on reaction with zinc forms the elemental gold and another complex [B]. [A] and [B], respectively are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${[Au{(CN)_4}]^ - }$$ and $${[Zn{(CN)_2}{(OH)_2}]^{2 - }}$$",
      "$${[Au{(CN)_2}]^ - }$$ and $${[Zn{(OH)_4}]^{2 - }}$$",
      "$${[Au{(CN)_2}]^{ - }}$$ and $${[Zn{(CN)_4}]^{2 - }}$$",
      "$${[Au{(CN)_4}]^{2 - }}$$ and $${[Zn{(CN)_6}]^{4 - }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "$${[Au{(CN)_2}]^{ - }}$$ and $${[Zn{(CN)_4}]^{2 - }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mckl7d",
    "question": "<p>Which of the reaction is suitable for concentrating ore by leaching process ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\n2 \\mathrm{Cu}_{2} \\mathrm{~S}+3 \\mathrm{O}_{2} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{Cu}_{2} \\mathrm{O}+2 \\mathrm{SO}_{2}\n$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Fe}_{3} \\mathrm{O}_{4}+\\mathrm{CO} \\rightarrow 3 \\mathrm{FeO}+\\mathrm{CO}_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Al}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{3}+2 \\mathrm{NaOH}+3 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{Na}\\left[\\mathrm{Al}(\\mathrm{OH})_{4}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Al}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{3}+6 \\mathrm{Mg} \\rightarrow 6 \\mathrm{MgO}+4 \\mathrm{Al}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Al}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{3}+2 \\mathrm{NaOH}+3 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{Na}\\left[\\mathrm{Al}(\\mathrm{OH})_{4}\\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpnixu8",
    "question": "<p>The methods NOT involved in concentration of ore are</p>\n<p>A. Liquation</p>\n<p>B. Leaching</p>\n<p>C. Electrolysis</p>\n<p>D. Hydraulic washing</p>\n<p>E. Froth floatation</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and C only",
      "C, D and E only",
      "B, D and C only",
      "B, D and E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "A and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu0nanv",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : In froth floatation method of rotating paddle agitates the mixture to drive air out of it.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Iron pyrites and generally avoided for extraction of iron due to environmental reasons.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnzhs7y",
    "question": "Which one of the following is not an example of calcination?\n",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{CaCO}_{3} \\cdot \\mathrm{MgCO}_{3} \\stackrel{\\Delta}{\\longrightarrow} \\mathrm{CaO}+\\mathrm{MgO}+2 \\mathrm{CO}_{2}$",
      "$2 \\mathrm{PbS}+3 \\mathrm{O}_{2} \\stackrel{\\Delta}{\\longrightarrow} 2 \\mathrm{PbO}+2 \\mathrm{SO}_{2}$",
      "$\\mathrm{CaCO}_{3} \\stackrel{\\Delta}{\\longrightarrow} \\mathrm{CaO}+\\mathrm{CO}_{2}$",
      "$\\mathrm{Fe}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{3} \\cdot \\mathrm{xH}_{2} \\mathrm{O} \\stackrel{\\Delta}{\\longrightarrow} \\mathrm{Fe}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{3}+\\mathrm{xH}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "$2 \\mathrm{PbS}+3 \\mathrm{O}_{2} \\stackrel{\\Delta}{\\longrightarrow} 2 \\mathrm{PbO}+2 \\mathrm{SO}_{2}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsxytzu",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : In the metallurgy process, sulphide ore is converted to oxide before reduction.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Oxide ores in general are easier to reduce.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyg7v84",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following is used as a stabilizer during the concentration of sulphide ores?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Cresols",
      "Xanthates",
      "Fatty acids",
      "Pine oils"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "concentration-of-ore",
    "solution": "Cresols"
  },
  {
    "id": "3aMFytgPWP5T3vn5B7Hhm",
    "question": "With respect to an ore, Ellingham diagram helps to predict the feasibility of its.",
    "options": [
      "Electrolysis",
      "Thermal reducation",
      "Vapour phase refining",
      "Zone refining"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "ellingham-diagram",
    "solution": "Thermal reducation"
  },
  {
    "id": "5ZWNUw5xBZyL610W1Tjgy2xukfja5umg",
    "question": "An Ellingham diagram provides information\nabout :",
    "options": [
      "the temperature dependence of the\nstandard Gibbs energies of formation of\nsome metal oxides",
      "the pressure dependence of the standard\nelectrode potentials of reduction reactions\ninvolved in the extraction of metals",
      "the conditions of pH and potential under\nwhich a species is thermodynamically\nstable",
      "the kinetics of the reduction process"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "ellingham-diagram",
    "solution": "the temperature dependence of the\nstandard Gibbs energies of formation of\nsome metal oxides"
  },
  {
    "id": "en8KxGfA8e01Wp6oft1klsbki4q",
    "question": "Ellingham diagram is a graphical representation of :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta$$G vs P",
      "$$\\Delta$$G vs T",
      "($$\\Delta$$G $$-$$ T$$\\Delta$$S) vs T",
      "$$\\Delta$$H vs T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "ellingham-diagram",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta$$G vs T"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz18yvs",
    "question": "The statement is incorrect about Ellingham diagram is ",
    "options": [
      "provides idea about the reaction rate.",
      "provides idea about free energy change.",
      "provides idea about changes in the phases during the reaction.",
      "provides idea about reduction of metal oxide."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "ellingham-diagram",
    "solution": "provides idea about the reaction rate."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktb50g0y",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : The choice of reducing agents for metals extraction can be made by using Ellingham diagram, a plot of $$\\Delta$$G vs temperature.<br/><br/>Statement II : The value of $$\\Delta$$S increases from left to right in Ellingham diagram.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "ellingham-diagram",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58dpl6l",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : According to Ellingham diagram, any metal oxide with higher $$\\Delta$$G$$^\\circ$$ is more stable than the one with lower $$\\Delta$$G$$^\\circ$$.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The metal involved in the formation of oxide placed lower in the Ellingham diagram can reduce the oxide of a metal placed higher in the diagram.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "ellingham-diagram",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldoia26j",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A: In an Ellingham diagram, the oxidation of carbon to carbon monoxide shows a negative slope with respect to temperature.</p>\n<p>Reason R: CO tends to get decomposed at higher temperature.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "ellingham-diagram",
    "solution": "A is correct but R is not correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp2vpwg",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements related to Ellingham diagram:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Ellingham diagrams can be constructed for formation of oxides, sulfides and halides of metals.</p>\n<p>Statement II : It consists of plots of $$\\Delta_{\\mathrm{f}} \\mathrm{H}^{0}$$ vs $$\\mathrm{T}$$ for formation of oxides of elements.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>\n<p></p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "ellingham-diagram",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrkermy",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : In the Ellingham diagram, a sharp change in slope of the line is observed for $$\\mathrm{Mg} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{MgO}$$ at $$\\sim 1120^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$</p>\n<p>Reason R: There is a large change of entropy associated with the change of state</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is true",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "ellingham-diagram",
    "solution": "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "TnyU78xKvWYnv0Hv",
    "question": "Aluminium is extracted by the electrolysis of",
    "options": [
      "bauxite",
      "alumina",
      "alumina mixed with molten cryolite",
      "molten cryolite"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "alumina mixed with molten cryolite"
  },
  {
    "id": "wHgo9N84n61Kzqkz",
    "question": "The metal extracted by leaching with a cyanide is",
    "options": [
      "Mg",
      "Ag",
      "Cu",
      "Na"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Ag"
  },
  {
    "id": "iVORBt4a2dAC3T1vsAi9N",
    "question": "Extraction of copper by smelting uses silica as an additive to remove :",
    "options": [
      "Cu<sub>2</sub>S",
      "FeO",
      "FeS",
      "Cu<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "FeO"
  },
  {
    "id": "7dRN57D3UpRkLSOYZyvET",
    "question": "In the extraction of copper from its sulphate ore, metal is finally obtained by the oxidation of cuprous sulphide with : ",
    "options": [
      "Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> ",
      "Cu<sub>2</sub>O",
      "SO<sub>2</sub> ",
      "CO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Cu<sub>2</sub>O"
  },
  {
    "id": "ObIp8z72OiwR9tsWjXi30",
    "question": "Hall- Heroult's process is given by :",
    "options": [
      "Cu<sup>2+</sup> (aq) + H<sub>2</sub>(g)&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;Cu(s) + 2H<sup>+</sup> (aq)",
      "Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> + 2AI &nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> + 2Cr",
      "2Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> + 3C &nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;4Al + 3CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "ZnO + C &nbsp; $$\\buildrel {Coke,\\,1673\\,K} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$&nbsp;Zn + CO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "2Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> + 3C &nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;4Al + 3CO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ndqg2KPW3H8RC9m7UEqfj",
    "question": "In the Hall-Heroult process, aluminium is formed at the cathode. The cathode is made out of - ",
    "options": [
      "Copper ",
      "Platinum ",
      "Carbon",
      "Pure aluminium "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Carbon"
  },
  {
    "id": "DeCVT3bOXyRFMsxPWSsH2",
    "question": "The pair that does NOT require calcination is - ",
    "options": [
      "Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and CaCO<sub>3</sub>⋅MgCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "ZnCO<sub>3</sub> and CaO ",
      "ZnO and Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>⋅xH<sub>2</sub>O",
      "ZnO and MgO "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "ZnO and MgO "
  },
  {
    "id": "OyCo4tb0bZEABK8UBzOr8",
    "question": "<b>Assertion: </b>For the extraction of iron, haematite\nore is used.<br/><br/>\n<b>Reason:</b> Haematite is a carbonate ore of iron.",
    "options": [
      "Both the assertion and reason are correct\nand the reason is the correct explanation for\nthe assertion.",
      "Only the reason is correct.",
      "Both the assertion and reason are correct,\nbut the reason is not the correct explanation\nfor the assertion.",
      "Only the assertion is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Only the assertion is correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "JREybSne4o6KDMU9XW3rsa0w2w9jx85286e",
    "question": "The correct statement is :",
    "options": [
      "leaching of bauxite using concentrated NaOH solution gives sodium aluminate and sodium silicate",
      "the Hall-Heroult process is used for the production of aluminium and iron",
      "pig iron is obtained from cast iron",
      "the blistered appearance of copper during the metallurgical process is due to the evolution of CO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "leaching of bauxite using concentrated NaOH solution gives sodium aluminate and sodium silicate"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ai04AzSxUr31JHozPm7k9k2k5dz6ppd",
    "question": "The purest from of commercial iron is :\n",
    "options": [
      "pig iron",
      "wrought iron ",
      "cast iron",
      "scrap iron and pig iron"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "wrought iron "
  },
  {
    "id": "yGuymlnZ8QqbaYboGe7k9k2k5hkj969",
    "question": "Among the reactions (a) - (d), the reaction(s)\nthat does/do not occur in the blast furnace\nduring the extraction of iron is/are :<br/>\n(a) CaO + SiO<sub>2</sub> $$ \\to $$ CaSiO<sub>3</sub><br/>\n(b) 3Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> + CO $$ \\to $$ 2Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> + CO<sub>2</sub><br/>\n(c) FeO + SiO<sub>2</sub> $$ \\to $$ FeSiO<sub>3</sub><br/>\n(d) FeO $$ \\to $$ Fe + $${{1 \\over 2}}$$O<sub>2</sub>",
    "options": [
      "(a) and (d)",
      "(c) and (d)",
      "(a)",
      "(d)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "(c) and (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": "7imRerkDmrKVkYWsFbjgy2xukexzdnpf",
    "question": "Cast iron is used for the manufacture of :",
    "options": [
      "wrought iron, pig iron and steel",
      "wrought iron and pig iron",
      "wrought iron and steel",
      "pig iron, scrap iron and steel"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "wrought iron and steel"
  },
  {
    "id": "WN4UCaO02aiJMbBB2S1klurlmb0",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I </th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Sodium Carbonate</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Deacon</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Titanium</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Castner-Kellner</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Chlorine</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>van-Arkel</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Sodium hydroxide</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Solvay</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (i), (d) $$ \\to $$ (ii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (b) $$ \\to $$ (i), (c) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (i), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iv)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (i), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (ii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (i), (d) $$ \\to $$ (ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "igxsI4p6NuXqY3PNOp1klusni8h",
    "question": "Calgon is used for water treatment. Which of the following statement is NOT true about Calgon?",
    "options": [
      "It is also known as Graham's salt. ",
      "It is polymeric compound and is water soluble.",
      "It does not remove Ca<sup>2+</sup> ion by precipitation.",
      "Calgon contains the 2<sup>nd</sup> most abundant element by weight in the Earth's crust."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Calgon contains the 2<sup>nd</sup> most abundant element by weight in the Earth's crust."
  },
  {
    "id": "piPmrb97jTRvovoAqn1kmhtoobd",
    "question": "The process that involves the removal of sulphur from the ores is :",
    "options": [
      "Roasting",
      "Smelting",
      "Leaching",
      "Refining"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Roasting"
  },
  {
    "id": "NDKD4oPlCMkymvn4261kmiup4ww",
    "question": "Which of the following reduction reaction CANNOT be carried out with coke?",
    "options": [
      "ZnO $$ \\to $$ Zn",
      "Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> $$ \\to $$ Fe",
      "Cu<sub>2</sub>O $$ \\to $$ Cu",
      "Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> $$ \\to $$ Al"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> $$ \\to $$ Al"
  },
  {
    "id": "4xv3ylxzIWHghwSi411kmlnjabg",
    "question": "The chemical that is added to reduce the melting point of the reaction mixture during the extraction of aluminium is :",
    "options": [
      "Cryolite",
      "Bauxite",
      "Calamine",
      "Kaolite"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Cryolite"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1gnx25",
    "question": "Which one of the following set of elements can be detected using sodium fusion extract?",
    "options": [
      "Sulfur, Nitrogen, Phosphorous, Halogens",
      "Phosphorous, Oxygen, Nitrogen, Halogens",
      "Nitrogen, Phosphorous, Carbon, Sulfur",
      "Halogens, Nitrogen, Oxygen, Sulfur"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Sulfur, Nitrogen, Phosphorous, Halogens"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1ir1k8",
    "question": "The addition of silica during the extraction of copper from its sulphide ore :-",
    "options": [
      "converts copper sulphide into copper silicate",
      "converts iron oxide into iron silicate",
      "reduces copper sulphide into metallic copper",
      "reduces the melting point of the reaction mixture"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "converts iron oxide into iron silicate"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktiainee",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).<br/><br/>Assertion (A) : Aluminium is extracted from bauxite by the electrolysis of molten mixture of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> with cryolite.<br/><br/>Reason (R) : The oxidation state of Al in cryolite is +3.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A) is true but (R) is false.",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true.",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l548p1rl",
    "question": "<p>In isolation of which one of the following metals from their ores, the use of cyanide salt is not commonly involved?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Zinc",
      "Gold",
      "Silver",
      "Copper"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Copper"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55n81ek",
    "question": "<p>In the metallurgical extraction of copper, following reaction is used :</p>\n<p>FeO + SiO<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ FeSiO<sub>3</sub></p>\n<p>FeO and FeSiO<sub>3</sub> respectively are.</p>",
    "options": [
      "gangue and flux.",
      "flux and slag.",
      "slag and flux.",
      "gangue and slag."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "gangue and slag."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56aonz6",
    "question": "<p>Given are two statements one is labelled as Assertion A and other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Magnesium can reduce Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> at a temperature below 1350$$^\\circ$$C, while above 1350$$^\\circ$$C, while above 1350$$^\\circ$$C aluminium can reduce MgO.</p>\n<p>Reason R : The melting and boiling points of magnesium are lower than those of aluminium.</p>\n<p>n light of the above statements, choose most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct, and R is correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are correct, but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is correct R is not correct.",
      "A is not correct, R is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct, but R is NOT the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bd6zfn",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following chemical reactions represents Hall-Heroult Process?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> + 2Al $$\\to$$ Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> + 2Cr",
      "2Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> + 3C $$\\to$$ 4Al + 3CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "FeO + CO $$\\to$$ Fe + CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "2[Au(CN)<sub>2</sub>]$$_{(aq)}^ - $$ + Zn(s) $$\\to$$ 2Au(s) + [Zn(CN<sub>4</sub>)]<sup>2$$-$$</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "2Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> + 3C $$\\to$$ 4Al + 3CO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6e15u5y",
    "question": "<p>The compound(s) that is (are) removed as slag during the extraction of copper is :</p>\n<p>(A) CaO</p>\n<p>(B) FeO</p>\n<p>(C) Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></p>\n<p>(D) ZnO</p>\n<p>(E) NiO</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "(C), (D) only",
      "(A), (B), (E) only",
      "(A), (B) only",
      "(B) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "(B) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f6s3ba",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements.</p>\n<p>Statement I : Pig iron is obtained by heating cast iron with scrap iron.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Pig iron has a relatively lower carbon content than that of cast iron.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are not correct.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is not correct.",
      "Statement I is not correct but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are not correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gpudl0",
    "question": "<p>Refining using liquation method is the most suitable for metals with :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Low melting point",
      "High boiling point",
      "High electrical conductivity",
      "Less tendency to be soluble in melts than impurities"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Low melting point"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i4t5ww",
    "question": "<p>The metal that is not extracted from its sulfide ore is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Aluminium",
      "Iron",
      "Lead",
      "Zinc"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Aluminium"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo9f3sx",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is incorrect?",
    "options": [
      "Cast iron is obtained by melting pig iron with scrap iron and coke using hot air blast.",
      "The malleable iron is prepared from cast iron by oxidising impurities in a reverberatory furnace.",
      "van Arkel method is used to purify tungsten.",
      "Boron and Indium can be purified by zone refining method."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "van Arkel method is used to purify tungsten."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr3x8ky",
    "question": "<p>In the extraction of copper, its sulphide ore is heated in a reverberatory furnace after mixing with silica to:</p>",
    "options": [
      "remove $$\\mathrm{FeO}$$ as $$\\mathrm{FeSiO}_{3}$$",
      "remove calcium as $$\\mathrm{CaSiO}_{3}$$",
      "decrease the temperature needed for roasting of $$\\mathrm{Cu}_{2} \\mathrm{~S}$$",
      "separate $$\\mathrm{CuO}$$ as $$\\mathrm{CuSiO}_{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "remove $$\\mathrm{FeO}$$ as $$\\mathrm{FeSiO}_{3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduk6sjw",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following reactions does not occur during extraction of copper?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{2FeS + 3{O_2} \\to 2FeO + 2S{O_2}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{FeO + Si{O_2} \\to FeSi{O_3}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{CaO + Si{O_2} \\to CaSi{O_3}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{2C{u_2}s + 3{O_2} \\to 2C{u_2}O + 2S{O_2}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{CaO + Si{O_2} \\to CaSi{O_3}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwshc7f",
    "question": "<p>The metal which is extracted by oxidation and subsequent reduction from its ore is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Al",
      "Cu",
      "Ag",
      "Fe"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Ag"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyfwkvx",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 668px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 248px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List-I<br/></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List-II<br/></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Reverberatory furnace</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Pig Iron</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Electrolytic cell</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Aluminium</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Blast furnace</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Silicon</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Zone Refining furnace</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Copper</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-I, D-III",
      "A-I, B-IV, C-II, D-III",
      "A-I, B-III, C-II, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-II, C-I, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguz8a9u",
    "question": "<p>In the extraction process of copper, the product obtained after carrying out the reactions</p>\n<p>(i) $$2 \\mathrm{Cu}_{2} \\mathrm{~S}+3 \\mathrm{O}_{2} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{Cu}_{2} \\mathrm{O}+2 \\mathrm{SO}_{2}$$</p>\n<p>(ii) $$2 \\mathrm{Cu}_{2} \\mathrm{O}+\\mathrm{Cu}_{2} \\mathrm{~S} \\rightarrow 6 \\mathrm{Cu}+\\mathrm{SO}_{2}$$ is called</p>",
    "options": [
      "Copper matte",
      "Blister copper",
      "Reduced copper",
      "Copper scrap"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Blister copper"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgys775m",
    "question": "<p>In Hall - Heroult process, the following is used for reducing $$\\mathrm{Al}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{3}$$ :-</p>",
    "options": [
      "Magnesium",
      "$$\\mathrm{CaF}_{2}$$",
      "Graphite",
      "$$\\mathrm{Na}_{3} \\mathrm{AlF}_{6}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "Graphite"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh04k0wi",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following metals can be extracted through alkali leaching technique?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Sn}$$",
      "Cu",
      "$$\\mathrm{Au}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Pb}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "extractions-of-metals",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Au}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "z9dSEikS79hDzKZwzC99I",
    "question": "Match the ores (column A) with the metals (column B) : \n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-wrg0{font-size:22px;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-wv9z{font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-wv9z\" colspan=\"2\">(Column A) ores</th>\n<th class=\"tg-wv9z\" colspan=\"2\">(Column B) Metals</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Siderite</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">(a)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Zinc </td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">Kaolinite</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(b)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">Copper</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">Malachite</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(c)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">Iron</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">Calamine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(d)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">Aluminium</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "(I)-(c); (II)-(d); (III)-(b); (IV)-(a)",
      "(I)-(a); (II)-(b); (III)-(c); (IV)-(d)",
      "(I)-(b); (II)-(c); (III)-(d); (IV)-(a)",
      "(I)-(c); (II)-(d); (III)-(a); (IV)-(b)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "(I)-(c); (II)-(d); (III)-(b); (IV)-(a)"
  },
  {
    "id": "hOg1N4YomLFSwYPHhY20M",
    "question": "The ore that contains the metal in the form of\nfluoride is :",
    "options": [
      "sphalerite",
      "magnetite",
      "malachite",
      "cryolite"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "cryolite"
  },
  {
    "id": "rf9wZRwudY6vHrcF02cFc",
    "question": "The one that is not a carbonate ore is :",
    "options": [
      "siderite",
      "bauxite",
      "malachite",
      "calamine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "bauxite"
  },
  {
    "id": "NHVXzELQCCoA5dE6wGWQd",
    "question": "The ore that contains both iron and copper is : ",
    "options": [
      "Copper Pyrites ",
      "Malachite ",
      "Dolomite ",
      "Azurite"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "Copper Pyrites "
  },
  {
    "id": "oixba3aIu7eJHah4WJjgy2xukft6tb4m",
    "question": "The incorrect statement is :",
    "options": [
      "bronze is an alloy of copper and tin",
      "cast iron is used to manufacture wrought\niron",
      "german silver is an alloy of zinc, copper\nand nickel",
      "brass is an alloy of copper and nickel"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "brass is an alloy of copper and nickel"
  },
  {
    "id": "LfHcemjLzca9VDQAZU1klree9wm",
    "question": "The major components in \"Gun Metal” are :",
    "options": [
      "Al, Cu, Mg and Mn",
      "Cu, Ni and Fe",
      "Cu, Sn and Zn",
      "Cu, Zn and Ni"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "Cu, Sn and Zn"
  },
  {
    "id": "LXfPQaqOoarjlPYReg1klrf28tb",
    "question": "Which of the following ore is concentrated using group 1 cyanide salt ?",
    "options": [
      "Sphalerite",
      "Malachite",
      "Siderite",
      "Calamine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "Sphalerite"
  },
  {
    "id": "AN5PkS5wV7BMDC8WZ01klruje7f",
    "question": "Math List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List I (Metal)</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List II (Ores)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Aluminium</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Siderite</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Iron</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Calamine</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Copper</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Kaolinite</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Zinc</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Malachite</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "C52PlhrgVGu0gMepqf1kltb4lt4",
    "question": "The major components of German Silver are :",
    "options": [
      "Zn, Ni and Ag",
      "Cu, Zn and Ni",
      "Cu, Zn and Ag",
      "Ge, Cu and Ag"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "Cu, Zn and Ni"
  },
  {
    "id": "NtlZbcMBpWbWIcmR3Z1kludhrdn",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I (Ore)</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II (Element Present)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Kernite</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Tin</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Cassiterite</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Boron</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Calamine</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Fluorine</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Cryolite</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Zinc</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (i), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (ii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (i), (c) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iv)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (i), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (c) $$ \\to $$ (i), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "(a) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (i), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "Sa6sfv0GfGqEaNmSFw1kluseg2r",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I </th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Siderite</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Cu</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Calamine</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Ca</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Malachite</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Fe</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Cryolite</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Al</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td></td>\n<td></td>\n<td>(v)</td>\n<td>Zn</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (i), (b) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iv)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (i), (c) $$ \\to $$ (v), (d) $$ \\to $$ (ii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (i), (b) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (v), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (v), (c) $$ \\to $$ (i), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iv)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (v), (c) $$ \\to $$ (i), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iv)"
  },
  {
    "id": "rIKTcJJFLOhvDIhTVB1kmkih0yv",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II :<br/><br/><table style=\"width:100%\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Haematite</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>$$A{l_2}{O_3}\\,.\\,x{H_2}O$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Bauxite</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>$$F{e_2}{O_3}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Magnetite</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>$$CuC{O_3}\\,.\\,Cu{(OH)_2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Malachite</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>$$F{e_3}{O_4}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(i), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(iii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt5a4n2",
    "question": "Sulphide ion is soft base and its ores are common for metals.<br/><br/>(a) Pb (b) Al (c) Ag (d) Mg",
    "options": [
      "(a) and (c) only",
      "(a) and (d) only",
      "(a) and (b) only",
      "(c) and (d) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "(a) and (c) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktcqv88a",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : Sphalerite is a sulphide or of zinc and copper glance is a sulphide ore of copper.<br/><br/>Statement II : It is possible to separate two sulphide ores by adjusting proportion of oil to water or by using 'depressants' in a forth flotation method.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktft0hl2",
    "question": "Match List-I with List-II :<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I<br/>(Name of ore/mineral)</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II<br/>(Chemical formula)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Calmine</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>$$Zns$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Malachite</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>$$FeC{O_3}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Siderite</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>$$ZnC{O_3}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Sphalerite</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>$$CuC{O_3}.Cu{(OH)_2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn022ft",
    "question": "Calamine and Malachite, respectively, are the ores of : ",
    "options": [
      "Nickel and Aluminium",
      "Zinc and Copper",
      "Copper and Iron",
      "Aluminium and Zinc"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "Zinc and Copper"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54yd40r",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 404px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 43px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 104px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 205px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-I<br/>Ore</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-II<br/>Composition</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Siderite</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">FeCO$$_3$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Malachite</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">CuCO$$_3$$ . Cu(OH)$$_2$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Sphalerite</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">ZnS</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Calamine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">ZnCO$$_3$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II",
      "A-I, B-II, C-IV, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c6h70d",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 505px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 62px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 195px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 80px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 168px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\">List -II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Sphalerite</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">FeCO$$_3$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Calamine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">PbS</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Galena</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">ZnCO$$_3$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Siderite</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">ZnS</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p71vbf",
    "question": "<p>In metallurgy the term \"gangue\" is used for :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Contamination of undesired earthy materials.",
      "Contamination of metals, other than desired metal.",
      "Minerals which are naturally occurring in pure form",
      "Magnetic impurities in an ore."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "Contamination of undesired earthy materials."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldscw4jc",
    "question": "<p>The major component of which of the following ore is sulphide based mineral?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Sphalerite",
      "Siderite",
      "Malachite",
      "Calamine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "Sphalerite"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh27ikq0",
    "question": "<p>The setting time of Cement is increased by adding :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Gypsum",
      "Limestone",
      "Clay",
      "Silica"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "minerals-and-ores",
    "solution": "Gypsum"
  },
  {
    "id": "I47jeIDqs18cVPFh",
    "question": "During the process of electrolytic refining of copper, some metals present as impurity\nsettle as ‘anode mud’ These are ",
    "options": [
      "Sn and Ag",
      "Pb and Zn",
      "Ag and Au",
      "Fe and Ni "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "Ag and Au"
  },
  {
    "id": "mL2j8pBkmkP9cMEn",
    "question": "Which method of purification is represented by the following equation :<br/>\nTi (s) + 2I<sub>2</sub> (g) $$\\buildrel {523K} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ TiI<sub>4</sub> (g) $$\\buildrel {1700K} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ Ti (s) + 2I<sub>2</sub> (g)",
    "options": [
      "zone refining",
      "cupellation",
      "Poling",
      "Van Arkel"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "Van Arkel"
  },
  {
    "id": "A2grdNtvtG8yy0iA",
    "question": "In the context of the Hall-Heroult process for the extraction of Al, which of the following statements is\n<b>false</b>? ",
    "options": [
      "Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is mixed with CaF<sub>2</sub> which lowers the melting point of the mixture and brings conductivity",
      "Al<sup>3+</sup> is reduced at the cathode to form Al",
      "Na<sub>3</sub>AlF<sub>6</sub> serves as the electrolyte",
      "CO and CO<sub>2</sub> are produced in this process"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "Na<sub>3</sub>AlF<sub>6</sub> serves as the electrolyte"
  },
  {
    "id": "sL3Wqf6NXIKx1ozazaNyl",
    "question": "The electrolytes usually used in the electroplating of gold and silver, respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "[Au(CN)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>–</sup> and [Ag(CN)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>–</sup>",
      "[Au(CN)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>–</sup> and  [Ag(Cl)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>–</sup>",
      "[Au(OH)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>–</sup> and  [Ag(OH)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>–</sup>",
      "[Au(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>–</sup> and  [Ag(CN)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>–</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "[Au(CN)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>–</sup> and [Ag(CN)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>–</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "9AMvJXPku3YEXKskzlQlU",
    "question": "The Mond process is used for the",
    "options": [
      "Extraction of Zn",
      "extraction of Mo",
      "Purification of Zr and Ti",
      "Purification of Ni"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "Purification of Ni"
  },
  {
    "id": "hv76feNJffydU1HoTX3rsa0w2w9jwvgw3py",
    "question": "Match the refining methods (Column I) with metals (Column II).\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-s6z2{text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Column I</span><br/><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">(Refining Methods)</span></th>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Column II</span><br/><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">(Metals)</span></th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(I) Liquation</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(a) Zr</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(II) Zone Refining</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(b) Ni</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(III) Mond Process</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(c) Sn</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(IV) Van Arkel Method</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(d) Ga</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "(I)-(c) ; (II)-(a) ; (III)-(b) ; (IV)-(d)",
      "(I)-(c) ; (II)-(d) ; (III)-(b) ; (IV)-(a)",
      "(I)-(b) ; (II)-(d) ; (III)-(a) ; (IV)-(c)",
      "(I)-(b) ; (II)-(c) ; (III)-(d) ; (IV)-(a)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "(I)-(c) ; (II)-(d) ; (III)-(b) ; (IV)-(a)"
  },
  {
    "id": "zIuBER3XpInZQNVlY23rsa0w2w9jx0u47iw",
    "question": "The correct statement is :",
    "options": [
      "zincite is a carbonate ore.",
      "Sodium cyanide cannot be used in the metallurgy of silver.",
      "aniline is a froth stabilizer.",
      "zone refining process is used for the refining of titanium. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "aniline is a froth stabilizer."
  },
  {
    "id": "xTDvUOECR0kp4Jkkhj7k9k2k5epyfz6",
    "question": "The refining method used when the metal and the impurities have low and high melting temperatures, respectively, is :",
    "options": [
      "liquation\n",
      "vapour phase refining ",
      "distillation",
      "zone refining "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "liquation\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "hen9l4BAyaMZUbuVNFjgy2xukf91u1jb",
    "question": "Among statements (a) - (d), the correct ones are\n<br/>(a) Lime stone is decomposed to CaO during\nthe extraction of iron from its oxides.\n<br/>(b) In the extraction of silver, silver is extracted\nas an anionic complex.\n<br/>(c) Nickel is purified by Mond’s process.\n<br/>(d) Zr and Ti are purified by Van Arkel method.",
    "options": [
      "(a), (c) and (d) only",
      "(c) and (d) only",
      "(b), (c) and (d) only",
      "(a), (b), (c) and (d)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "(a), (b), (c) and (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": "DA3hWpnc9Oe508G6Uljgy2xukg4ma8fm",
    "question": "The element that can be refined by distillation\nis :",
    "options": [
      "gallium",
      "nickel",
      "zinc",
      "tin"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "zinc"
  },
  {
    "id": "p2zSlIsnk8VOy8cdoo1kltbbc68",
    "question": "The method used for the purification of Indium is :",
    "options": [
      "zone refining",
      "vapour phase refining",
      "liquation",
      "van Arkel method"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "zone refining"
  },
  {
    "id": "eFXLuoFAiwIYzL3Anm1kmm17ar7",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II :<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Mercury</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Vapour phase refining</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Copper</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Distillation refining</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Silicon</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Electrolytic refining</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Nickel</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Zone refining</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the option given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(iii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq60xrp",
    "question": "The metal that can be purified economically by fractional distillation method is :",
    "options": [
      "Fe",
      "Zn",
      "Cu",
      "Ni"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "Zn"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktea98xy",
    "question": "Which refining process is generally used in the purification of low melting metals?",
    "options": [
      "Chromatographic method",
      "Liquation",
      "Electrolysis",
      "Zone refining"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "Liquation"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59qs5a3",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements.</p>\n<p>Statement I : During electrolytic refining, blister copper deposits precious metals.</p>\n<p>Statement II : In the process of obtaining pure copper by electrolysis method, copper blister is used to make the anode.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jkscmu",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following methods are not used to refine any metal?</p>\n<p>A. Liquation</p>\n<p>B. Calcination</p>\n<p>C. Electrolysis</p>\n<p>D. Leaching</p>\n<p>E. Distillation</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "B and D only",
      "A, B, D and E only",
      "B, D and E only",
      "A, C and E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "B and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqwflt5",
    "question": "Given below are two statements:\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement I</b>: During Electrolytic refining, the pure metal is made to act as anode and its impure metallic form is used as cathode.\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement I</b>I: During the Hall-Heroult electrolysis process, purified $\\mathrm{Al}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{3}$ is mixed with $\\mathrm{Na}_{3} \\mathrm{AlF}_{6}$ to lower the melting point of the mixture.\n<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below:",
    "options": [
      "Statement $\\mathrm{I}$ is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldssidu2",
    "question": "<p>The reaction representing the Mond process for metal refining is _________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{ZnO+C\\buildrel \\Delta  \\over\n \\longrightarrow Zn+CO}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{2K[Au(CN)_2]+Zn\\buildrel \\Delta  \\over\n \\longrightarrow K_2[Zn(CN)_4]+2Au}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Zr+2I_2 \\buildrel \\Delta  \\over\n \\longrightarrow ZrI_4}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ni+4CO\\buildrel \\Delta  \\over\n \\longrightarrow Ni(CO)_4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Ni+4CO\\buildrel \\Delta  \\over\n \\longrightarrow Ni(CO)_4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq433g9",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following is most likely a mismatch ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Titanium - van Arkel Method",
      "Zinc - Liquation",
      "Nickel - Mond process",
      "Copper - Electrolysis"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "isolation-of-elements",
    "topic": "refining-or-purification-of-metal",
    "solution": "Zinc - Liquation"
  },
  {
    "id": "wUH8fPw4KKtGrgFg",
    "question": "Beryllium and aluminium exhibit many properties which are similar. But the two elements\ndiffer in :",
    "options": [
      "exhibiting maximum covalency in compound ",
      "exhibiting amphoteric nature in their oxides ",
      "forming covalent halides ",
      "forming polymeric hydrides "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "exhibiting maximum covalency in compound "
  },
  {
    "id": "pYUtcySZjPJ4w1HX",
    "question": "Which one of the following is the correct statement?",
    "options": [
      "Boric acid is a protonic acid ",
      "Beryllium exhibits coordination number of six ",
      "Chlorides of both beryllium and aluminium have bridged chloride structures in solid phase",
      "B<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>.2NH<sub>3</sub> is known as ‘inorganic benzene’"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "Chlorides of both beryllium and aluminium have bridged chloride structures in solid phase"
  },
  {
    "id": "YNKUz0vHr32WvL7ebJTXB",
    "question": "The correct statements among I to III regarding\ngroup 13 element oxides are,<br/>\n(I) Boron trioxide is acidic.<br/>\n(II) Oxides of aluminium and gallium are\namphoteric.<br/>\n(III) Oxides of indium and thalliumare basic.",
    "options": [
      "(II) and (III) only",
      "(I), (II) and (III)",
      "(I) and (III) only",
      "(I) and (II) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "(I), (II) and (III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "eHmVE8SCvxX0Dv4LEp7k9k2k5lljc6c",
    "question": "The reaction of H<sub>3</sub>N<sub>3</sub>B<sub>3</sub>Cl<sub>3</sub> (A) with LiBH<sub>4</sub> in\ntetrahydrofuran gives inorganic benzene (B).\nFurther, the reaction of (A) with (C) leads to\nH<sub>3</sub>N<sub>3</sub>B<sub>3</sub>(Me)<sub>3</sub>. Compounds (B) and (C)\nrespectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "Borazine and MeBr",
      "Diborane and MeMgBr",
      "Boron nitride and MeBr",
      "Borazine and MeMgBr"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "Borazine and MeMgBr"
  },
  {
    "id": "QkTgo0X5HYLS0AjoYajgy2xukfou2rt1",
    "question": "Boron and silicon of very high purity can be obtained through :",
    "options": [
      "Liquation",
      "Electrolytic refining",
      "Zone refining",
      "Vapour phase refining"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "Zone refining"
  },
  {
    "id": "YPcyEMpOikMymQMZSC1klurumfk",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.<br/><br/>Assertion A : In TlI<sub>3</sub>, isomorphous to CsI<sub>3</sub>, the metal is present in +1 oxidation state.<br/><br/>Reason R : Tl metal has fourteen f electrons in its electronic configuration.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58dn3qk",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct stability order of group 13 elements in their + 1 oxidation state :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Al < Ga < In < Tl",
      "Tl < In < Ga < Al",
      "Al < Ga < Tl < In",
      "Al < Tl < Ga < In"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "Al < Ga < In < Tl"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo9ndvf",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement I:</b> Upon heating a borax bead dipped in cupric sulphate in a luminous flame, the colour of the bead becomes green<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement II:</b> The green colour observed is due to the formation of copper(I) metaborate<br/><br/>\nIn light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu1e4ik",
    "question": "<p>Potassium dichromate acts as a strong oxidizing agent in acidic solution. During this process, the oxidation state changes from :</p>",
    "options": [
      "+ 2 to + 1",
      "+ 6 to + 2",
      "+ 6 to + 3",
      "+ 3 to + 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "+ 6 to + 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp2wtkg",
    "question": "<p>The covalency and oxidation state respectively of boron in $$\\left[\\mathrm{BF}_{4}\\right]^{-}$$, are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 and 4",
      "4 and 3",
      "4 and 4",
      "3 and 5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "4 and 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrk11j3",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Boron is extremely hard indicating its high lattice energy.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Boron has highest melting and boiling point compared to its other group members.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Both statement I and Statement II are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "Both statement I and Statement II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguzuyn8",
    "question": "<p>For compound having the formula $$\\mathrm{GaAlCl}_{4}$$, the correct option from the following is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Cl}$$ forms bond with both $$\\mathrm{Al}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Ga}$$ in $$\\mathrm{GaAlCl}_{4}$$",
      "Oxidation state of $$\\mathrm{Ga}$$ in the salt $$\\mathrm{GaAlCl}_{4}$$ is +3 .",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ga}$$ is coordinated with $$\\mathrm{Cl}$$ in $$\\mathrm{GaAlCl}_{4}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ga}$$ is more electronegative than $$\\mathrm{Al}$$ and is present as a cationic part of the salt $$\\mathrm{GaAlCl}_{4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Ga}$$ is more electronegative than $$\\mathrm{Al}$$ and is present as a cationic part of the salt $$\\mathrm{GaAlCl}_{4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc5mr0e",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : Melting point of Boron (2453 K) is unusually high in group 13 elements.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Solid Boron has very strong crystalline lattice.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below ;</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) Is not the correct explanation of (A)\n",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)\n",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false\n",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd8uv19",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p><b>Statement I</b> : Group 13 trivalent halides get easily hydrolyzed by water due to their covalent nature.</p>\n<p><b>Statement II</b> : $$\\mathrm{AlCl}_3$$ upon hydrolysis in acidified aqueous solution forms octahedral $$\\left[\\mathrm{Al}\\left(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\\right)_6\\right]^{3+}$$ ion.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true\n",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true\n",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "Both statement I and statement II are true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5grwn0",
    "question": "<p>Give below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R:</p>\n<p>Assertion A: The stability order of +1 oxidation state of $$\\mathrm{Ga}$$, In and $$\\mathrm{Tl}$$ is Ga &lt; In &lt; Tl.</p>\n<p>Reason R: The inert pair effect stabilizes the lower oxidation state down the group.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is false but R is true.",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3qs2",
    "question": "<p>The number of neutrons present in the more abundant isotope of boron is '$$x$$'. Amorphous boron upon heating with air forms a product, in which the oxidation state of boron is '$$y$$'. The value of $$x+y$$ is _________ .</p>",
    "options": [
      "9",
      "6",
      "4",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "9"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s2kn9",
    "question": "<p>The correct statements from the following are :</p>\n<p>(A) The decreasing order of atomic radii of group 13 elements is $$\\mathrm{Tl}&gt;\\mathrm{In}&gt;\\mathrm{Ga}&gt;\\mathrm{Al}&gt;\\mathrm{B}$$.</p>\n<p>(B) Down the group 13 electronegativity decreases from top to bottom.</p>\n<p>(C) $$\\mathrm{Al}$$ dissolves in dil. $$\\mathrm{HCl}$$ and liberates $$\\mathrm{H}_2$$ but conc. $$\\mathrm{HNO}_3$$ renders $$\\mathrm{Al}$$ passive by forming a protective oxide layer on the surface.</p>\n<p>(D) All elements of group 13 exhibits highly stable +1 oxidation state.</p>\n<p>(E) Hybridisation of $$\\mathrm{Al}$$ in $$[\\mathrm{Al}(\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O})_6]^{3+}$$ ion is $$\\mathrm{sp}^3 \\mathrm{d}^2$$.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A), (B), (C) and (E) only\n",
      "(C) and (E) only\n",
      "(A), (C) and (E) only\n",
      "(A) and (C) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "(C) and (E) only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57i3i",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Gallium is used in the manufacturing of thermometers.</p>\n<p>Statement II : A thermometer containing gallium is useful for measuring the freezing point $$(256 \\mathrm{~K})$$ of brine solution.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-13-elements-(boron-family)",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "FuLwmcsZROGsOpFW",
    "question": "Glass is a :",
    "options": [
      "super-cooled liquid",
      "gel",
      "polymeric mixture",
      "micro-crystalline solid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "super-cooled liquid"
  },
  {
    "id": "3jVFwhFxVWmQOkdd",
    "question": "The stability of dihalides of $$Si,Ge,Sn$$ and $$Pb$$ increases steadily in the sequence :",
    "options": [
      "$$Pb{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Sn{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Ge{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Si{X_2}$$ ",
      "$$Ge{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Si{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Sn{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Pb{X_2}$$ ",
      "$$Si{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Ge{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Pb{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Sn{X_2}$$ ",
      "$$Si{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Ge{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Sn{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Pb{X_2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "$$Si{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Ge{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Sn{X_2} &lt;  &lt; Pb{X_2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "gRS8kXRuqpLanVm0o2AzJ",
    "question": "In graphite and diamond, the percentage of p-characters of the hybrid orbitals in hybridisation are respectively : ",
    "options": [
      "33 and 25 ",
      "33 and 75 ",
      "50 and 75",
      "67 and 75 "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "67 and 75 "
  },
  {
    "id": "58XuRNVqrRQYyuaWlJMiT",
    "question": "The one that is extensively used as a piezoelectric material is : ",
    "options": [
      "tridymite",
      "amorphous silica",
      "quartz",
      "mica"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "quartz"
  },
  {
    "id": "7XuuEwZHdouWCRqaWVD5q",
    "question": "The element that does NOT show catenation is :",
    "options": [
      "Ge",
      "Si",
      "Sn",
      "Pb"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "Pb"
  },
  {
    "id": "1qEOSDHc3sD3CwppBMeZr",
    "question": "The element that shows greater ability to form p$$\\pi $$-p$$\\pi $$ multiple bonds, is :",
    "options": [
      "Si",
      "Ge",
      "C",
      "Sn"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krusnay7",
    "question": "Which one of the following compounds of Group-14 elements is not known?",
    "options": [
      "[GeCl<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup>",
      "[Sn(OH)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup>",
      "[SiCl<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup>",
      "[SiF<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "[SiCl<sub>6</sub>]<sup>2$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rjlgq1",
    "question": "<p>In liquation process used for tin (Sn), the metal :</p>",
    "options": [
      "is reacted with acid.",
      "is dissolved in water.",
      "is brought to molten form which is made to flow on a slope.",
      "is fused with NaOH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "is brought to molten form which is made to flow on a slope."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rjnx5s",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements.</p>\n<p>Statement I : Stannane is an example of a molecular hydride.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Stannane is a planar molecule.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statement, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnz9975",
    "question": " During water-gas shift reaction",
    "options": [
      "water is evaporated in presence of catalyst.",
      "carbon monoxide is oxidized to carbon dioxide.",
      "carbon is oxidized to carbon monoxide.",
      "carbon dioxide is reduced to carbon monoxide."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "carbon monoxide is oxidized to carbon dioxide."
  },
  {
    "id": "lsao7fl5",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :\n<br/><br/><b>Statement (I) </b>: $\\mathrm{SiO}_2$ and $\\mathrm{GeO}_2$ are acidic while $\\mathrm{SnO}$ and $\\mathrm{PbO}$ are amphoteric in nature.\n<br/><br/><b>Statement (II)</b> : Allotropic forms of carbon are due to property of catenation and $\\mathrm{p} \\pi-\\mathrm{d} \\pi$ bond formation.\n<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse739kk",
    "question": "<p>Consider the oxides of group 14 elements\n$$\\mathrm{SiO}_2, \\mathrm{GeO}_2, \\mathrm{SnO}_2, \\mathrm{PbO}_2, \\mathrm{CO}$$ and $$\\mathrm{GeO}$$. The amphoteric oxides are</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{SnO}_2, \\mathrm{CO}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{SiO}_2, \\mathrm{GeO}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{SnO}_2, \\mathrm{PbO}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{GeO}, \\mathrm{GeO}_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{SnO}_2, \\mathrm{PbO}_2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse73zy3",
    "question": "<p>The compound that is white in color is</p>",
    "options": [
      "ammonium sulphide\n",
      "ammonium arsinomolybdate\n",
      "lead iodide\n",
      "lead sulphate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "lead sulphate"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2a2db",
    "question": "<p>Evaluate the following statements related to group 14 elements for their correctness.</p>\n<p>(A) Covalent radius decreases down the group from $$\\mathrm{C}$$ to $$\\mathrm{Pb}$$ in a regular manner.</p>\n<p>(B) Electronegativity decreases from $$\\mathrm{C}$$ to $$\\mathrm{Pb}$$ down the group gradually.</p>\n<p>(C) Maximum covalance of $$\\mathrm{C}$$ is 4 whereas other elements can expand their covalance due to presence of d orbitals.</p>\n<p>(D) Heavier elements do not form $$\\mathrm{p} \\pi-\\mathrm{p} \\pi$$ bonds.</p>\n<p>(E) Carbon can exhibit negative oxidation states.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A), (B) and (C) Only\n",
      "(A) and (B) Only\n",
      "(C), (D) and (E) Only\n",
      "(C) and (D) Only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "(C), (D) and (E) Only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57i90",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following material is not a semiconductor.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Copper oxide\n",
      "Graphite\n",
      "Silicon\n",
      "Germanium"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-14-elements-(carbon-family)",
    "solution": "Graphite\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "MqWmPgL8oGjxUdMh",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true? ",
    "options": [
      "H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>3</sub> is a stronger acid than H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>",
      "In aqueous medium HF is a stronger acid than HCl ",
      "HClO<sub>4</sub> is a weaker acid than HClO<sub>3</sub>",
      "HNO<sub>3</sub> is a stronger acid than HNO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "HNO<sub>3</sub> is a stronger acid than HNO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "jHp4xGIzjwmEpdkG",
    "question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?",
    "options": [
      "Nitrogen cannot form $$d\\pi - p\\pi$$ bond. ",
      "Single N – N bond is weaker than the single P – P bond",
      "N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> has two resonance structures",
      "The stability of hydrides increases from NH<sub>3</sub> to BiH<sub>3</sub> in group 15 of the periodic table"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "The stability of hydrides increases from NH<sub>3</sub> to BiH<sub>3</sub> in group 15 of the periodic table"
  },
  {
    "id": "A3mCPKshMHixEWNJ",
    "question": "The molecule having smallest bond angle is :",
    "options": [
      "NCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "AsCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "SbCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "PCl<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "SbCl<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "kwY9Syty88M5QITK",
    "question": "Which one of the following properties is not shown by NO?",
    "options": [
      "It combines with oxygen to form nitrogen dioxide",
      "It’s bond order is 2.5",
      "It is diamagnetic in gaseous state",
      "It is a neutral oxide"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "It is diamagnetic in gaseous state"
  },
  {
    "id": "QNJhOxqVGyg3czDJWfoj1",
    "question": "A metal ‘M’ reacts with nitrogen gas to afford ‘M<sub>3</sub>N’. ‘M<sub>3</sub>N’ on heating at high temperature gives back ‘M’ and on\nreaction with water produces a gas ‘B’. Gas ‘B’ reacts with aqueous \n solution of CuSO<sub>4</sub> to form a deep blue compound. ‘M’ and\n‘B’ respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "Li and NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "Ba and N<sub>2</sub>",
      "Na and NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "Al and N<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "Li and NH<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "178I7rci04rGxd9T",
    "question": "The compound that does not produce nitrogen gas by the thermal decomposition is :",
    "options": [
      "(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>",
      "Ba(N<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>",
      "NH<sub>4</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "A2m7JRQYhDBKsgWl7L7k9k2k5hlej38",
    "question": "A metal (A) on heating in nitrogen gas gives\ncompound B. B on treatment with H<sub>2</sub>O gives\na colourless gas which when passed through\nCuSO<sub>4</sub> solution gives a dark blue-violet\ncoloured solution. A and B respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "Na and NaNO<sub>3</sub>",
      "Na and Na<sub>3</sub>N",
      "Mg and Mg<sub>3</sub>N<sub>2</sub>",
      "Mg and Mg(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "Mg and Mg<sub>3</sub>N<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "6VwjX0BZ6jok6Cp1MWjgy2xukfte5gjk",
    "question": "The correct statement with respect to\ndinitrogen is :",
    "options": [
      "N<sub>2</sub> is paramagnetic in nature",
      "it can be used as an inert diluent for\nreactive chemicals",
      "it can combine with dioxygen at 25<sup>o</sup>C",
      "liquid dinitrogen is not used in cryosurgery"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "it can be used as an inert diluent for\nreactive chemicals"
  },
  {
    "id": "BINwkByPwnFMgGtH8Q1kluce9ld",
    "question": "Find A, B and C in the following reactions :<br/><br/>$$N{H_3} + A + C{O_2} \\to {(N{H_4})_2}C{O_3}$$<br/><br/>$${(N{H_4})_2}C{O_3} + {H_2}O + B \\to N{H_4}HC{O_3}$$<br/><br/>$$N{H_4}HC{O_3} + NaCl \\to N{H_4}Cl + C$$",
    "options": [
      "$$A - {O_2};B - C{O_2};C - N{a_2}C{O_3}$$",
      "$$A - {H_2}O;B - {O_2};C - NaHC{O_3}$$",
      "$$A - {H_2}O;B - {O_2};C - N{a_2}C{O_3}$$",
      "$$A - {H_2}O;B - C{O_2};C - NaHC{O_3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "$$A - {H_2}O;B - C{O_2};C - NaHC{O_3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "7WCoZ43jUqQDISg2wd1kmht9z0m",
    "question": "A group of 15 element, which is a metal and forms a hydride with strongest reducing power among group 15 hydrides. The element is :",
    "options": [
      "As",
      "Sb",
      "Bi",
      "P"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "Bi"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt4w7z2",
    "question": "Which one of the following group-15 hydride is the strongest reducing agent?",
    "options": [
      "AsH<sub>3</sub>",
      "BiH<sub>3</sub>",
      "PH<sub>3</sub>",
      "SbH<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "BiH<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56aq6vq",
    "question": "<p>Nitrogen gas is obtained by thermal decomposition of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Ba(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Ba(N<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "NaNO<sub>2</sub>",
      "NaNO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "Ba(N<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58j1wco",
    "question": "<p>The oxide which contains an odd electron at the nitrogen atom is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "N<sub>2</sub>O",
      "NO<sub>2</sub>",
      "N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "NO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bda415",
    "question": "PCl<sub>5</sub> is well known, but NCl<sub>5</sub> is not. because,",
    "options": [
      "nitrogen is less reactive than phosphorus.",
      "nitrogen doesn't have d-orbitals in its valence shell.",
      "catenation tendency is weaker in nitrogen than phosphorus.",
      "size of phosphorus is larger than nitrogen."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "nitrogen doesn't have d-orbitals in its valence shell."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c6o6y5",
    "question": "<p>The most stable trihalide of nitrogen is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "NF<sub>3</sub>",
      "NCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "NBr<sub>3</sub>",
      "NI<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "NF<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w5zzdh",
    "question": "<p>A $$\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{}^{573\\,K}} $$ Red phosphorus $$\\mathrel{\\mathop{\\kern0pt\\longrightarrow}\n\\limits_{under\\,pressure}^{heat\\,;\\,803\\,K}} $$ B</p>\n<p>Red phosphorus is obtained by heating \"A\" at 573 K, and can be converted to \"B\" by heating at 803 K under pressure.</p>\n<p>A and B, respectively, are</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\beta$$-black phosphorus and white phosphorus.",
      "white phosphorus and $$\\beta$$-black phosphorus.",
      "$$\\alpha$$-black phosphorus and white phosphorus.",
      "white phosphorus and $$\\alpha$$-black phosphorus."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "white phosphorus and $$\\alpha$$-black phosphorus."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gp8zm2",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I<br/>(Processes / Reactions)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II<br/>(Catalyst)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">2SO$$_2$$(g) + O$$_2$$(g) $$ \\to $$ 2SO$$_3$$(g)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Fe(s)</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">4NH$$_3$$(g) + 5O$$_2$$(g) $$ \\to $$ 4NO(g) + 6H$$_2$$O(g)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Pt(s) $$ - $$ Rh(s)</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">N$$_2$$(g) + 3H$$_2$$(g) $$ \\to $$ 2NH$$_3$$(g)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">V$$_2$$O$$_5$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Vegetable oil(l) + H$$_2$$ $$ \\to $$ Vegetable ghee(s)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ni(s)</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{II})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{I})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nwpyh4",
    "question": "<p>Dinitrogen and dioxygen, the main constituents of air do not react with each other  in atmosphere to form oxides of nitrogen because :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{N}_{2}$$ is unreactive in the condition of atmosphere.",
      "Oxides of nitrogen are unstable.",
      "Reaction between them can occur in the presence of a catalyst.",
      "The reaction is endothermic and require very high temperature."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "The reaction is endothermic and require very high temperature."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrl2jd4",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : $$\\mathrm{SbCl}_{5}$$ is more covalent than $$\\mathrm{SbCl}_{3}$$</p>\n<p>Statement II: The higher oxides of halogens also tend to be more stable than the lower ones.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "Both statement I and Statement II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaopfne",
    "question": "The strongest reducing agent among the following is :",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{SbH}_3$",
      "$\\mathrm{NH}_3$",
      "$\\mathrm{BiH}_3$",
      "$\\mathrm{PH}_3$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{BiH}_3$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfmftc2",
    "question": "<p>On passing a gas, '$$\\mathrm{X}$$', through Nessler's regent, a brown precipitate is obtained. The gas '$$\\mathrm{X}$$' is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Cl}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CO}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{NH}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{S}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{NH}_3$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg7qzxc",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct statements about the hydrides of group 15 elements.</p>\n<p>A. The stability of the hydrides decreases in the order $$\\mathrm{NH}_3&gt;\\mathrm{PH}_3&gt;\\mathrm{AsH}_3&gt; \\mathrm{SbH}_3&gt;\\mathrm{BiH}_3$$.</p>\n<p>B. The reducing ability of the hydride increases in the order $$\\mathrm{NH}_3&lt;\\mathrm{PH}_3&lt;\\mathrm{AsH}_3 &lt;\\mathrm{SbH}_3&lt;\\mathrm{BiH}_3$$.</p>\n<p>C. Among the hydrides, $$\\mathrm{NH}_3$$ is strong reducing agent while $$\\mathrm{BiH}_3$$ is mild reducing agent.</p>\n<p>D. The basicity of the hydrides increases in the order $$\\mathrm{NH}_3&lt;\\mathrm{PH}_3&lt;\\mathrm{AsH}_3&lt; \\mathrm{SbH}_3&lt;\\mathrm{BiH}_3$$.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "C and D only",
      "A and D only",
      "A and B only",
      "B and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "A and B only"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv40va43",
    "question": "<p>Identify the incorrect statements about group 15 elements :</p>\n<p>(A) Dinitrogen is a diatomic gas which acts like an inert gas at room temperature.</p>\n<p>(B) The common oxidation states of these elements are $$-3,+3$$ and +5.</p>\n<p>(C) Nitrogen has unique ability to form $$\\mathrm{p} \\pi-\\mathrm{p} \\pi$$ multiple bonds.</p>\n<p>(D) The stability of +5 oxidation states increases down the group.</p>\n<p>(E) Nitrogen shows a maximum covalency of 6.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A), (C), (E) only\n",
      "(D) and (E) only\n",
      "(A), (B), (D) only\n",
      "(B), (D), (E) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "(D) and (E) only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv40v8yq",
    "question": "<p>In qualitative test for identification of presence of phosphorous, the compound is heated with an oxidising agent. Which is further treated with nitric acid and ammonium molybdate respectively. The yellow coloured precipitate obtained is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Na}_3 \\mathrm{PO}_4 \\cdot 12 \\mathrm{MoO}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_4\\right)_3 \\mathrm{PO}_4 \\cdot 12\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_4\\right)_2 \\mathrm{MoO}_4$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{MoPO}_4 \\cdot 21 \\mathrm{NH}_4 \\mathrm{NO}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_4\\right)_3 \\mathrm{PO}_4 \\cdot 12 \\mathrm{MoO}_3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-15-elements-(nitrogen-family)",
    "solution": "$$\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_4\\right)_3 \\mathrm{PO}_4 \\cdot 12 \\mathrm{MoO}_3$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "9LasynDnRjTSq5LU",
    "question": "Which one of the following substances has the highest proton affinity?",
    "options": [
      "H<sub>2</sub>S",
      "NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "PH<sub>3</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "NH<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "RlatqLtie51tfsoJ",
    "question": "Regular use of which of the following fertilizer increases the acidity of soil? ",
    "options": [
      "Potassium nitrate",
      "Urea ",
      "Superphosphate of lime",
      "Ammonium sulphate "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "Ammonium sulphate "
  },
  {
    "id": "mkBnXGogUTYq8ycE",
    "question": "Which of the following statements regarding sulphur is incorrect?",
    "options": [
      "The vapour at 200<sup>o</sup>C consists mostly of S<sub>8</sub> rings ",
      "At 600<sup>o</sup>C the gas mainly consists of S<sub>2</sub> molecules ",
      "The oxidation state of sulphur is never less than +4 in its compounds ",
      "S<sub>2</sub> molecule is paramagnetic. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "The oxidation state of sulphur is never less than +4 in its compounds "
  },
  {
    "id": "Fkyt13wViFAxUzyK",
    "question": "<b>Assertion :</b> Nitrogen and Oxygen are the main components in the atmosphere but these do not react to\nform oxides of nitrogen.<br/><br>\n<b>Reason :</b> The reaction between nitrogen and oxygen requires high temperature. </br>",
    "options": [
      "Both assertion and reason are correct, and the reason is the correct explanation for the assertion",
      "Both assertion and reason are correct, but the reason is not the correct explanation for the assertion",
      "The assertion is incorrect, but the reason is correct",
      "Both the assertion and reason are incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "Both assertion and reason are correct, and the reason is the correct explanation for the assertion"
  },
  {
    "id": "KSVWysahybEDSogYTHXlu",
    "question": "In KO<sub>2</sub>, the nature of oxygen species and the oxydation state of oxygen atom are,  respectively : ",
    "options": [
      "Oxide and $$-$$ 2",
      "Superoxide and $$-$$ 1/2",
      "Peroxide and $$-$$ 1/2",
      "Superoxide and $$-$$ 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "Superoxide and $$-$$ 1/2"
  },
  {
    "id": "e0DGPaqfKBSF9y7rmD1kmln75qn",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I<br/>(process)</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II<br/>(catalyst)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Deacron's process</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>ZSM-5</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Contact process</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>$$CuC{l_2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Cracking of hydrocarbons</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Particles 'Ni'</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Hydrogenation of vegetable oils</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>$${V_2}{O_5}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(ii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1h1zpk",
    "question": "Given below are two statement : one is labelled as Assertion  A and the other is labelled as Reason R. <br/><br/><b>Assertion A</b> : SO<sub>2</sub>(g) is absorbed to a large extent than H<sub>2</sub>(g) on activated charcoal.<br/><br/><b>Reason R</b> : SO<sub>2</sub>(g) has a higher critical temperature than H<sub>2</sub>(g).<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct but R is not the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is not correct but R is correct.",
      "A is correct but R is not correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1iajmp",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II :<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - I<br/>(compound)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - II<br/>(effect/affected species)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(a)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Carbon monoxide</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(i)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Carcinogenic</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(b)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Sulphur dioxide</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(ii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Metabolized by pyrus plants</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(c)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Polychlorinated biphenyls</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(iii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">haemoglobin</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(d)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Oxides of Nitrogen</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(iv)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Stiffness of flower buds</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a) - (iii), (b) - (iv), (c) - (i), (d) - (ii)",
      "(a) - (iv), (b) - (i), (c) - (iii), (d) - (ii)",
      "(a) - (i), (b) - (ii), (c) - (iii), (d) - (iv)",
      "(a) - (iii), (b) - (iv), (c) - (ii), (d) - (i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "(a) - (iii), (b) - (iv), (c) - (i), (d) - (ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktecrru0",
    "question": "In polythionic acid, H<sub>2</sub>S<sub>x</sub>O<sub>6</sub> (x = 3 to 5) the oxidation state(s) of sulphur is/are :",
    "options": [
      "+ 5 only",
      "+ 6 only",
      "+ 3 and + 5 only",
      "0 and + 5 only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "0 and + 5 only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54yldjx",
    "question": "<p>Sulphur dioxide is one of the components of polluted air. SO<sub>2</sub> is also a major contributor to acid rain. The correct and complete reaction to represent acid rain caused by SO<sub>2</sub> is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2SO<sub>2</sub> + O<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ 2SO<sub>3</sub>",
      "SO<sub>2</sub> + O<sub>3</sub> $$\\to$$ SO<sub>3</sub> + O<sub>2</sub>",
      "SO<sub>2</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>",
      "2SO<sub>2</sub> + O<sub>2</sub> + 2H<sub>2</sub>O $$\\to$$ 2H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "2SO<sub>2</sub> + O<sub>2</sub> + 2H<sub>2</sub>O $$\\to$$ 2H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56yklkt",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 672px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 43px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 207px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 370px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-I <br/>(Anion)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-II <br/>(gas evolved on reaction with dil.H$$_2$$SO$$_2$$)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">CO$${_3^{2 - }}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Colourless gas which turns lead acetate paper black.</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">S$$^{2 - }$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Colourless gas which turns acidified potassium dichromate solution green.</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">SO$${_3^{2 - }}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Brown fumes which turns acidified KI solution containing starch blue.</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">NO$${_2^ - }$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Colourless gas evolved with brisk effervescence, which turns lime water milky.</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58iwm7j",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following elements is considered as a metalloid?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Sc",
      "Pb",
      "Bi",
      "Te"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "Te"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f72be0",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II:</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Sulphate</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Pesticide</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Fluoride</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Bending of bones</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Nicotine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Laxative effect</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Sodium arsinite</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Herbicide</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jki5g8",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements. One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Activated charcoal adsorbs SO<sub>2</sub> more efficiently than CH<sub>4</sub>.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Gases with lower critical temperatures are readily adsorbed by activated charcoal.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is correct but R is not correct.",
      "A is not correct but R is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "A is correct but R is not correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwuzqem",
    "question": "<p>$$\\mathrm{K_2Cr_2O_7}$$ paper acidified with dilute $$\\mathrm{H_2SO_4}$$ turns green when exposed to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Sulphur dioxide",
      "Sulphur trioxide",
      "Hydrogen sulphide",
      "Carbon dioxide"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "Sulphur dioxide"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsy0dph",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following pairs is an example of polar molecular solids?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{HCl}(\\mathrm{s}), \\mathrm{AlN}(\\mathrm{s})$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{MgO}(\\mathrm{s}), \\mathrm{SO}_{2}(\\mathrm{s})$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{SO}_{2}(\\mathrm{s}), \\mathrm{NH}_{3}(\\mathrm{s})$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{SO}_{2}(\\mathrm{s}), \\mathrm{CO}_{2}(\\mathrm{s})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{SO}_{2}(\\mathrm{s}), \\mathrm{NH}_{3}(\\mathrm{s})$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscqftga",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : Oxygen being the first member of group 16 exhibits only -2 oxidation state.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : Down the group 16 stability of +4 oxidation state decreases and +6 oxidation state increases.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect\n",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd90kdd",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p><b>Statement I</b> : $$\\mathrm{S}_8$$ solid undergoes disproportionation reaction under alkaline conditions to form $$\\mathrm{S}^{2-}$$ and $$\\mathrm{S}_2 \\mathrm{O}_3{ }^{2-}$$.</p>\n<p><b>Statement II</b> : $$\\mathrm{ClO}_4^{-}$$ can undergo disproportionation reaction under acidic condition.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect\n",
      "Both statement I and statement II are incorrect\n",
      "Statement I is incorrect but statement II is correct\n",
      "Both statement I and statement II are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd93acx",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct statements from the following</p>\n<p>A. All group 16 elements form oxides of general formula $$\\mathrm{EO}_2$$ and $$\\mathrm{EO}_3$$, where $$\\mathrm{E}=\\mathrm{S}, \\mathrm{Se}, \\mathrm{Te}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Po}$$. Both the types of oxides are acidic in nature.</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{TeO}_2$$ is an oxidising agent while $$\\mathrm{SO}_2$$ is reducing in nature.</p>\n<p>C. The reducing property decreases from $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{~S}$$ to $$\\mathrm{H}_2$$ Te down the group.</p>\n<p>D. The ozone molecule contains five lone pairs of electrons.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and B only",
      "C and D only",
      "A and D only",
      "B and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "A and B only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg7hu98",
    "question": "<p>A and B formed in the following reactions are:</p>\n<p>$$\\begin{aligned}\n&amp; \\mathrm{CrO}_2 \\mathrm{Cl}_2+4 \\mathrm{NaOH} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{A}+2 \\mathrm{NaCl}+2 \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}, \\\\\n&amp; \\mathrm{A}+2 \\mathrm{HCl}+2 \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}_2 \\rightarrow \\mathrm{B}+3 \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}\n\\end{aligned}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{A}=\\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7, \\mathrm{~B}=\\mathrm{CrO}_5$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{A}=\\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{CrO}_4, \\mathrm{~B}=\\mathrm{CrO}_5$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{A}=\\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_4, \\mathrm{~B}=\\mathrm{CrO}_4$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{A}=\\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7, \\mathrm{~B}=\\mathrm{CrO}_3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{A}=\\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{CrO}_4, \\mathrm{~B}=\\mathrm{CrO}_5$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgxplqk",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : The gas liberated on warming a salt with dil $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{SO}_4$$, turns a piece of paper dipped in lead acetate into black, it is a confirmatory test for sulphide ion.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : In statement-I the colour of paper turns black because of formation of lead sulphite. In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2uzrj",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : Both rhombic and monoclinic sulphur exist as $$\\mathrm{S}_8$$ while oxygen exists as $$\\mathrm{O}_2$$.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Oxygen forms $$p \\pi-p \\pi$$ multiple bonds with itself and other elements having small size and high electronegativity like $$\\mathrm{C}, \\mathrm{N}$$, which is not possible for sulphur.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)\n",
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct\n",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct\n",
      "Both $$(\\mathbf{A})$$ and $$(\\mathbf{R})$$ are correct and $$(\\mathbf{R})$$ is the correct explanation of $$(\\mathbf{A})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "Both $$(\\mathbf{A})$$ and $$(\\mathbf{R})$$ are correct and $$(\\mathbf{R})$$ is the correct explanation of $$(\\mathbf{A})$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2ux88",
    "question": "<p>On reaction of Lead Sulphide with dilute nitric acid which of the following is not formed?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Sulphur\n",
      "Nitric oxide\n",
      "Lead nitrate\n",
      "Nitrous oxide"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "Nitrous oxide"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmazc",
    "question": "<p>Identify the correct statements about p-block elements and their compounds.</p>\n<p>(A) Non metals have higher electronegativity than metals.</p>\n<p>(B) Non metals have lower ionisation enthalpy than metals.</p>\n<p>(C) Compounds formed between highly reactive nonmetals and highly reactive metals are generally ionic.</p>\n<p>(D) The non-metal oxides are generally basic in nature.</p>\n<p>(E) The metal oxides are generally acidic or neutral in nature.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(B) and (D) only\n",
      "(B) and (E) only\n",
      "(D) and (E) only\n",
      "(A) and (C) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-16-elements-(oxygen-family)",
    "solution": "(A) and (C) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "GXWI3vRQPRPREhET",
    "question": "Oxidation number of Cl in CaOCl<sub>2</sub> (bleaching powder) is :",
    "options": [
      "zero, since it contains Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "-1, since it contains Cl<sup>-</sup>",
      "+1, since it contains ClO<sup>-</sup>",
      "+1 and -1 since it contains ClO<sup>-</sup> and Cl<sup>-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "+1 and -1 since it contains ClO<sup>-</sup> and Cl<sup>-</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "KY82dAZgEvXWviOs",
    "question": "The correct statement for the molecule, CsI<sub>3</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "it contains Cs<sup>3+</sup> and I<sup>-</sup> ions.",
      "it contains Cs<sup>+</sup>, I<sup>-</sup> and lattice I<sub>2</sub> molecule.",
      "it is a covalent molecule",
      "it contains Cs<sup>+</sup> and $$I_3^-$$ ions"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "it contains Cs<sup>+</sup> and $$I_3^-$$ ions"
  },
  {
    "id": "pXwqIEIZisW3YuevRoBHt",
    "question": "The non-metal that does <b>not</b> exhibit positive oxidation state is :",
    "options": [
      "Oxygen",
      "Iodine",
      "Chlorine",
      "Fluorine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "Fluorine"
  },
  {
    "id": "pmp5nPrrzoRq1nDAYsV10",
    "question": "Aqueous solution of which salt will not contain ions with the electronic\nconfiguration 1s<sup>2</sup>2s<sup>2</sup>2p<sup>6</sup>3s<sup>2</sup>3p<sup>6</sup> ?",
    "options": [
      "NaF",
      "NaCl",
      "KBr",
      "CaI<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "NaF"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq5fcfe",
    "question": "The species given below that does NOT show disproportionation reaction is :",
    "options": [
      "$$BrO_4^ - $$",
      "$$Br{O^ - }$$",
      "$$BrO_2^ - $$",
      "$$BrO_3^ - $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "$$BrO_4^ - $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56xjz72",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Fluorine forms one oxoacid.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Fluorine has smallest size amongst all halogens and is highly electronegative.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is correct but R is not correct.",
      "A is not correct but R is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5alxjao",
    "question": "<p>White precipitate of AgCl dissolves in aqueous ammonia solution due to formation of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "[Ag(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>]Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "[Ag(Cl)<sub>2</sub>(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]",
      "[Ag(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]Cl",
      "[Ag(NH<sub>3</sub>)Cl]Cl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "[Ag(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]Cl"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldo2rv99",
    "question": "<p>For electron gain enthalpies of the elements denoted as $$\\Delta_{\\mathrm{eg}} \\mathrm{H}$$, the incorrect option is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta_{\\mathrm{eg}} \\mathrm{H}(\\mathrm{I})<\\Delta_{\\mathrm{eg}} \\mathrm{H}(\\mathrm{At})$$",
      "$$\\Delta_{\\mathrm{eg}} \\mathrm{H}(\\mathrm{Te})<\\Delta_{\\mathrm{eg}} \\mathrm{H}(\\mathrm{Po})$$",
      "$$\\Delta_{\\mathrm{eg}} \\mathrm{H}(\\mathrm{Cl})<\\Delta_{\\mathrm{eg}} \\mathrm{H}(\\mathrm{F})$$",
      "$$\\Delta_{\\mathrm{eg}} \\mathrm{H}(\\mathrm{Se})<\\Delta_{\\mathrm{eg}} \\mathrm{H}(\\mathrm{S})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta_{\\mathrm{eg}} \\mathrm{H}(\\mathrm{Cl})<\\Delta_{\\mathrm{eg}} \\mathrm{H}(\\mathrm{F})$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu0v1gb",
    "question": "<p>A. Ammonium salts produce haze in atmosphere.</p>\n<p>B. Ozone gets produced when atmospheric oxygen reacts with chlorine radicals.</p>\n<p>C. Polychlorinated biphenyls act as cleansing solvents.</p>\n<p>D. 'Blue baby' syndrome occurs due to the presence of excess of sulphate ions in water.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "B and C only",
      "A and D only",
      "A, B and C only",
      "A and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "A and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc4tvpg",
    "question": "<p>Element not showing variable oxidation state is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Bromine\n",
      "Iodine\n",
      "Chlorine\n",
      "Fluorine"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "Fluorine"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfj8sve",
    "question": "<p>Identify the incorrect pair from the following :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Fluoroapatite $$-3 \\mathrm{Ca}_3\\left(\\mathrm{PO}_4\\right)_2 \\cdot \\mathrm{CaF}_2$$\n",
      "Carnallite $$-\\mathrm{KCl} \\cdot \\mathrm{MgCl}_2 \\cdot 6 \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}$$\n",
      "Cryolite $$-\\mathrm{Na}_3 \\mathrm{AlF}_6$$\n",
      "Fluorspar $$-\\mathrm{BF}_3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "Fluorspar $$-\\mathrm{BF}_3$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgy6q5x",
    "question": "<p>The Lassiagne's extract is boiled with dil $$\\mathrm{HNO}_3$$ before testing for halogens because,</p>",
    "options": [
      "Silver halides are soluble in $$\\mathrm{HNO}_3$$.\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{AgCN}$$ is soluble in $$\\mathrm{HNO}_3$$.\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{S}$$ and $$\\mathrm{NaCN}$$ are decomposed by $$\\mathrm{HNO}_3$$.\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ag}_2 \\mathrm{S}$$ is soluble in $$\\mathrm{HNO}_3$$."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{S}$$ and $$\\mathrm{NaCN}$$ are decomposed by $$\\mathrm{HNO}_3$$.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gt1te",
    "question": "<p>Among the following halogens</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{F}_2, \\mathrm{Cl}_2, \\mathrm{Br}_2 \\text { and } \\mathrm{I}_2$$</p>\n<p>Which can undergo disproportionation reactions?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{F}_2$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cl}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Cl}_2, \\mathrm{Br}_2$$ and $$\\mathrm{I}_2$$\n",
      "Only $$\\mathrm{I}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{F}_2, \\mathrm{Cl}_2$$ and $$\\mathrm{Br}_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-17-elements-(halogen-family)",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Cl}_2, \\mathrm{Br}_2$$ and $$\\mathrm{I}_2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "VpItfWawj53nnHJ9",
    "question": "Which one the following statement regarding helium is incorrect? ",
    "options": [
      "It is used to fill gas balloons instead of hydrogen because it is lighter and non–inflammable ",
      "It is used in gas – cooled nuclear reactors",
      "It is used to produce and sustain powerful superconducting reagents ",
      "It is used as cryogenic agent for carrying out experiments at low temperatures "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-18-elements-(inert-or-noble-gases)",
    "solution": "It is used to fill gas balloons instead of hydrogen because it is lighter and non–inflammable "
  },
  {
    "id": "Ut5uj1dVpqLXtlWr",
    "question": "Which one has the highest boiling point?",
    "options": [
      "Ne",
      "Kr",
      "Xe",
      "He"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-18-elements-(inert-or-noble-gases)",
    "solution": "Xe"
  },
  {
    "id": "fEIuz17rr6XPqPBBuX2nZ",
    "question": "Which intermolecular force is most responsible in allowing xenon gas to liquefy?",
    "options": [
      "Dipole - dipole",
      "Ion - dipole",
      "Instantaneous dipole - induced dipole",
      "Ionic"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-18-elements-(inert-or-noble-gases)",
    "solution": "Instantaneous dipole - induced dipole"
  },
  {
    "id": "W50NsUwBBAgAFpPgKe3rsa0w2w9jx0u14hm",
    "question": "The noble gas that does not occur in the atmosphere is : ",
    "options": [
      "Ne",
      "He",
      "Kr",
      "Ra"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-18-elements-(inert-or-noble-gases)",
    "solution": "Ra"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse755kb",
    "question": "<p>Give below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement - I: Noble gases have very high boiling points.</p>\n<p>Statement - II: Noble gases are monoatomic gases. They are held together by strong dispersion forces. Because of this they are liquefied at very low temperature. Hence, they have very high boiling points.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true.\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "p-block-elements",
    "topic": "group-18-elements-(inert-or-noble-gases)",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "kehmuOXmvgF5gUxE",
    "question": "The correct order of ionic radius is ",
    "options": [
      "$$Ce &gt; Sm &gt; Tb &gt; Lu$$ ",
      "$$Lu &gt; Tb &gt; Sm &gt; Ce$$ ",
      "$$Tb &gt; Lu &gt; Sm &gt; Ce$$ ",
      "$$Sm &gt; Tb &gt; Lu &gt; Ce$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "$$Ce &gt; Sm &gt; Tb &gt; Lu$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "1LuevMRepxZ1WOcw",
    "question": "$$C{e^{ + 3}},\\,\\,L{a^{ + 3}},\\,\\,P{m^{ + 3}}\\,\\,$$  and $$Y{b^{ + 3}}\\,\\,$$  have ionic radial in the increasing order as ",
    "options": [
      "$$L{a^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; C{e^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; P{m^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; Y{b^{ + 3}}$$ ",
      "$$Y{b^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; P{m^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; C{e^{ + 3}}\\,&lt;\\,L{a^{ + 3}}$$ ",
      "$$L{a^{ + 3}}\\,\\, = C{e^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; P{m^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; Y{b^{ + 3}}$$ ",
      "$$Y{b^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; P{m^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; L{a^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; C{e^{ + 3}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "$$Y{b^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; P{m^{ + 3}}\\,\\, &lt; C{e^{ + 3}}\\,&lt;\\,L{a^{ + 3}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "E0SAifZYxVY6q7b3",
    "question": "The reduction in atomic size with increase in atomic number  is a characteristic of elements of ",
    "options": [
      "$$d$$ - block",
      "$$f$$ - block",
      "Radioactive series ",
      "High atomic masses."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "High atomic masses."
  },
  {
    "id": "WaYwgdseGSFeCX4V",
    "question": "Which one of the following ions has the highest value of ionic radius?",
    "options": [
      "O<sup>2-</sup>",
      "B<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Li<sup>+</sup>",
      "F<sup>-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "O<sup>2-</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "cxG1Jkrc0jF1DGni",
    "question": "The set representing the correct order of ionic radius is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$N{a^ + } &gt; L{i^ + } &gt; M{g^{2 + }} &gt; B{e^{2 + }}$$ ",
      "$$L{i^ + } &gt; N{a^ + } &gt; M{g^{2 + }} &gt; B{e^{2 + }}$$ ",
      "$$M{g^{2 + }} &gt; B{e^{2 + }} &gt; L{i^ + } &gt; N{a^ + }$$ ",
      "$$L{i^ + } &gt; B{e^{2 + }} &gt; N{a^ + } &gt; M{g^{2 + }}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "$$N{a^ + } &gt; L{i^ + } &gt; M{g^{2 + }} &gt; B{e^{2 + }}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "dhtRg8os4yuGgIZG",
    "question": "The correct sequence which shows decreasing order of the ionic radii of the elements is",
    "options": [
      "Al<sup>3+</sup> &gt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; F<sup>-</sup> &gt; O<sup>2-</sup>",
      "Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Al<sup>3+</sup> &gt; O<sup>2–</sup> &gt; F<sup>–</sup>",
      "Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; F<sup>–</sup> &gt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &gt; O<sup>2–</sup> &gt; Al<sup>3+</sup>",
      "O<sup>2–</sup> &gt; F<sup>–</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Al<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "O<sup>2–</sup> &gt; F<sup>–</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Al<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "MBshRPbtzuPwmK3h",
    "question": "The increasing order of the ionic radii of the given isoelectronic species is :",
    "options": [
      "Cl<sup>–</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup> , K<sup>+</sup> , S<sup>2–</sup>",
      "S<sup>2–</sup>, Cl<sup>–</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup> , K<sup>+</sup>",
      "Ca<sup>2+</sup> , K<sup>+</sup> , Cl<sup>–</sup> , S<sup>2–</sup>",
      "K<sup>+</sup>, S<sup>2–</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Cl<sup>–</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "Ca<sup>2+</sup> , K<sup>+</sup> , Cl<sup>–</sup> , S<sup>2–</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "mon03lcV7SBvYiyy",
    "question": "The ionic radii (in Å) of N<sup>3–</sup>, O<sup>2–</sup> and F<sup>–</sup> are respectively:",
    "options": [
      "1.36, 1.71 and 1.40",
      "1.71, 1.40 and 1.36",
      "1.71, 1.36 and 1.40",
      "1.36, 1.40 and 1.71"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "1.71, 1.40 and 1.36"
  },
  {
    "id": "3ag9pN67AkMkjaOTqOykP",
    "question": "For Na<sup>+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>, F<sup>-</sup> and O<sup>2-</sup>; the correct order of increasing ionic radii is :",
    "options": [
      "O<sup>2-</sup> &lt; F<sup>-</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; F<sup>-</sup> &lt; O<sup>2-</sup>",
      "Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; F<sup>-</sup> &lt; O<sup>2-</sup>",
      "Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; O<sup>2-</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; F<sup>-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; F<sup>-</sup> &lt; O<sup>2-</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "FIPtNdY8hkCMpNOBONkFM",
    "question": "The correct order of the atomic radii of C, Cs, Al, and S is : ",
    "options": [
      "S &lt; C &lt; Al &lt; Cs ",
      "S &lt; C &lt; Cs &lt; Al",
      "C &lt; S &lt; Al &lt; Cs ",
      "C &lt; S &lt; Cs &lt; Al \n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "C &lt; S &lt; Al &lt; Cs "
  },
  {
    "id": "a4s1MRUaAsAzEitw5Tjgy2xukfp2zk7a",
    "question": "The correct order of the ionic radii of<br/> O<sup>2–</sup>, N<sup>3–</sup>, F<sup>–</sup>\n, Mg<sup>2+</sup>, Na<sup>+</sup> and Al<sup>3+</sup> is :",
    "options": [
      "N<sup>3–</sup> &lt; O<sup>2–</sup> &lt; F<sup>–</sup>\n &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Al<sup>3+</sup>",
      "N<sup>3–</sup> &lt; F<sup>–</sup>\n &lt; O<sup>2–</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; Al<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Al<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; O<sup>2–</sup> &lt; F<sup>–</sup>\n &lt; N<sup>3–</sup>",
      "Al<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; F<sup>–</sup>\n &lt; O<sup>2–</sup> &lt; N<sup>3–</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "Al<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; F<sup>–</sup>\n &lt; O<sup>2–</sup> &lt; N<sup>3–</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "LcSov41YJlz8ZZIt3Hjgy2xukf93pib6",
    "question": "The ionic radii of O<sup>2–</sup>, F<sup>–</sup>, Na<sup>+</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup> are in\nthe order :",
    "options": [
      "F<sup>–</sup> &gt; O<sup>2–</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; Mg<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Mg<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; F<sup>–</sup> &gt; O<sup>2–</sup>",
      "O<sup>2–</sup> &gt; F<sup>–</sup> &gt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup>\n",
      "O<sup>2–</sup> &gt; F<sup>–</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; Mg<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "O<sup>2–</sup> &gt; F<sup>–</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; Mg<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "sIztGaiqvF5GydHqwh7k9k2k5hl6qft",
    "question": "The increasing order of the atomic radii of the\nfollowing elements is :-<br/>\n(a) C (b) O<br/> (c) F (d) Cl<br/>\n(e) Br",
    "options": [
      "(a) &lt; (b) &lt; (c) &lt; (d) &lt; (e)",
      "(c) &lt; (b) &lt; (a) &lt; (d) &lt; (e)",
      "(b) &lt; (c) &lt; (d) &lt; (a) &lt; (e)",
      "(d) &lt; (c) &lt; (b) &lt; (a) &lt; (e)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "(c) &lt; (b) &lt; (a) &lt; (d) &lt; (e)"
  },
  {
    "id": "trsye3E6Ydxm0hUECg1kmlm9w9n",
    "question": "The ionic radius of Na<sup>+</sup> ions is 1.02 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$. The ionic radii (in $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$) of Mg<sup>2+</sup> and Al<sup>3+</sup>, respectively, are ",
    "options": [
      "1.05 and 0.99",
      "0.72 and 0.54",
      "0.85 and 0.99",
      "0.68 and 0.72"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "0.72 and 0.54"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krusl2pj",
    "question": "The ionic radii of K<sup>+</sup>, Na<sup>+</sup>, Al<sup>3+</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup> are in the order:",
    "options": [
      "Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; K<sup>+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Al<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Al<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; K<sup>+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup>",
      "Al<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; K<sup>+</sup>",
      "K<sup>+</sup> &lt; Al<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "Al<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; K<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krx5jphv",
    "question": "The ionic radii of F<sup>$$-$$</sup> and O<sup>2$$-$$</sup> respectively are 1.33$$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$ and 1.4$$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$, while the covalent radius of N is 0.74$$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$.<br/><br/>The correct statement for the ionic radius of N<sup>3$$-$$</sup> from the following is :",
    "options": [
      "It is smaller than F<sup>$$-$$</sup> and N",
      "It is bigger than O2<sup>$$-$$</sup> and F<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "It is bigger than F<sup>$$-$$</sup> and N, but smaller than of O<sup>2$$-$$</sup>",
      "It is smaller than O<sup>2$$-$$</sup> and F<sup>$$-$$</sup>, but bigger than of N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "It is bigger than O2<sup>$$-$$</sup> and F<sup>$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktcoupty",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).<br/><br/>Assertion (A) : Barium carbonate is insoluble in water and is highly stable.<br/><br/>Reason (R) : The thermal stability of the carbonates increases with increasing cationic size.",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the true explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the true explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the true explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfs8ty7",
    "question": "The correct order of ionic radii for the ions, P<sup>3$$-$$</sup>, S<sup>2$$-$$</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, K<sup>+</sup>, Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup> is :",
    "options": [
      "P<sup>3$$-$$</sup> &gt; S<sup>2$$-$$</sup> &gt; Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Ca<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup> &gt; S<sup>2$$-$$</sup> &gt; P<sup>3$$-$$</sup> &gt; Ca<sup>2+</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup>",
      "P<sup>3$$-$$</sup> &gt; S<sup>2$$-$$</sup> &gt; Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup> &gt; Ca<sup>2+</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup>",
      "K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Ca<sup>2+</sup> &gt; P<sup>3$$-$$</sup> &gt; S<sup>2$$-$$</sup> &gt; Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "P<sup>3$$-$$</sup> &gt; S<sup>2$$-$$</sup> &gt; Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Ca<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56wx7p2",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of increasing ionic radii is</p>",
    "options": [
      "Mg<sup>2+</sup> < Na<sup>+</sup> < F<sup>$$-$$</sup> < O<sup>2$$-$$</sup> < N<sup>3$$-$$</sup>",
      "N<sup>3$$-$$</sup> < O<sup>2$$-$$</sup> < F<sup>$$-$$</sup> < Na<sup>+</sup> < Mg<sup>2+</sup>",
      "F<sup>$$-$$</sup> < Na<sup>+</sup> < O<sup>2$$-$$</sup> < Mg<sup>2+</sup> < N<sup>3$$-$$</sup>",
      "Na<sup>+</sup> < F<sup>$$-$$</sup> < Mg<sup>2+</sup> < O<sup>2$$-$$</sup> < N<sup>3$$-$$</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "Mg<sup>2+</sup> < Na<sup>+</sup> < F<sup>$$-$$</sup> < O<sup>2$$-$$</sup> < N<sup>3$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57ro17g",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : The ionic radii of O<sup>2$$-$$</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup> are same.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Both O<sup>2$$-$$</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup> are isoelectronic species.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A).",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false.",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "(A) is false but (R) is true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gpsf7v",
    "question": "<p>Given two statements below :</p>\n<p>Statement I : In $$\\mathrm{Cl}_{2}$$ molecule the covalent radius is double of the atomic radius of chlorine.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Radius of anionic species is always greater than their parent atomic radius.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpofadj",
    "question": "<p>The correct increasing order of the ionic radii is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Cl^- < Ca^{2+} < K^+ < S^{2-}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K^+ < S^{2-} < Ca^{2+} < Cl^-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ca^{2+} < K^+ < Cl^- < S^{2-}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{S^{2-} < Cl^- < Ca^{2+} < K^+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Ca^{2+} < K^+ < Cl^- < S^{2-}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3u1a",
    "question": "<p>The statement(s) that are correct about the species $$\\mathrm{O}^{2-}, \\mathrm{F}^{-}, \\mathrm{Na}^{+}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Mg}^{2+}$$.</p>\n<p>(A) All are isoelectronic</p>\n<p>(B) All have the same nuclear charge</p>\n<p>(C) $$\\mathrm{O}^{2-}$$ has the largest ionic radii</p>\n<p>(D) $$\\mathrm{Mg}^{2+}$$ has the smallest ionic radii</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(C) and (D) only\n",
      "(A), (C) and (D) only\n",
      "(B), (C) and (D) only\n",
      "(A), (B), (C) and (D)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "(A), (C) and (D) only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s2pz5",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The metallic radius of $$\\mathrm{Na}$$ is $$1.86 \\mathrm{~A}^{\\circ}$$ and the ionic radius of $$\\mathrm{Na}^{+}$$ is lesser than $$1.86 \\mathrm{~A}^{\\circ}$$</p>\n<p>Statement II : Ions are always smaller in size than the corresponding elements.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "atomic-and-ionic-radius",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "eso2oclGrXSeMCidWb1LU",
    "question": "The size of the iso-electronic species Cl<sup>–</sup>,  Ar and Ca<sup>2+</sup> is affected by :",
    "options": [
      "electron-electron interaction in the outer orbitals",
      "Principal quantum number of valence shell",
      "nuclear charge",
      "azimuthal quantum number of valence shell"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "effective-nuclear-charge",
    "solution": "nuclear charge"
  },
  {
    "id": "kwJYsjrMpmHiDMjZf83rsa0w2w9jx80b28u",
    "question": "Among the following, the energy of 2s orbital is lowest in :",
    "options": [
      "Li",
      "H",
      "Na",
      "K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "effective-nuclear-charge",
    "solution": "K"
  },
  {
    "id": "34hIZ7U2TMLlH4Gj",
    "question": "In which of the following arrangements the order is NOT according to the property\nindicated against it? ",
    "options": [
      "Li &lt; Na &lt; K &lt; Rb Increasing metallic radius",
      "I &lt; Br &lt; F &lt; Cl Increasing electron gain enthalpy (with negative sign) ",
      "B &lt; C &lt; N &lt; O Increasing first ionization enthalpy",
      "Al<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Mg<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; F<sup>- </sup> Increasing ionic size "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "B &lt; C &lt; N &lt; O Increasing first ionization enthalpy"
  },
  {
    "id": "TmgEqBkT5dQNbcARJZ4nf",
    "question": "The correct order of electron affinity is : ",
    "options": [
      "F &gt; Cl &gt; O",
      "F &gt; O &gt; Cl",
      "Cl &gt; F &gt; O",
      "O &gt; F &gt; Cl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "Cl &gt; F &gt; O"
  },
  {
    "id": "xGTiBQSTwqlHk9EiI3sKk",
    "question": "When the first electron gain enthalpy $$\\left( {{\\Delta _{eg}}H} \\right)$$ of oxygen is $$-$$ 141 kJ/mol, its second electron gain enthalpy is : ",
    "options": [
      "a more negative value than the first",
      "almost the same as that of the first",
      "negative, but less negative than the first",
      "a positive value"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "a positive value"
  },
  {
    "id": "bymMlZOak3pTMyxTzM7k9k2k5dz3vg6",
    "question": "The electron gain enthalpy (in KJ/mol) of fluorine, chlorine, bromine and iodine, respectively are:",
    "options": [
      "-296, -325, -333 and -349",
      "349, -333, -325 and -296 ",
      "-333, -349, -325 and -296",
      "-333, -325, -349 and -296\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "-333, -349, -325 and -296"
  },
  {
    "id": "hZFvmUgreGYpgoXGSz7k9k2k5eq0i7i",
    "question": "Within each pair of elements F &amp; Cl, S &amp; Se, and Li &amp; Na, respectively, the elements that release\nmore energy upon and electron gain are :",
    "options": [
      "F, S and Li",
      "Cl, Se and Na",
      "Cl, S and Li ",
      "F, Se and Na"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "Cl, S and Li "
  },
  {
    "id": "d3hIRdXrR1rAdv98XH1klusfda4",
    "question": "The correct order of electron gain enthalpy is :",
    "options": [
      "Te &gt; Se &gt; S &gt; O",
      "S &gt; Se &gt; Te &gt; O",
      "S &gt; O &gt; Se &gt; Te",
      "O &gt; S &gt; Se &gt; Te"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "S &gt; Se &gt; Te &gt; O"
  },
  {
    "id": "5MXK0IIzT59kN5CVrU1kmj67h8f",
    "question": "The absolute value of the electron gain enthalpy of halogens satisfies :",
    "options": [
      "Cl &gt; Br &gt; F &gt; I",
      "Cl &gt; F &gt; Br &gt; I",
      "I &gt; Br &gt; Cl &gt; F",
      "F &gt; Cl &gt; Br &gt; I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "Cl &gt; F &gt; Br &gt; I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktid2aao",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).<br/><br/>Assertion (A) : Metallic character decreases and non-metallic character increases on moving from left to right in a period.<br/><br/>Reason (R) : It is due to increase in ionisation enthalpy and decrease in electron gain enthalpy, when one moves from left to right in a period.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A) is false but (R) is true.",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "(A) is true but (R) is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59qpre3",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of electron gain enthalpies of Cl, F, Te and Po is</p>",
    "options": [
      "F < Cl < Te < Po",
      "Po < Te < F < Cl",
      "Te < Po < Cl < F",
      "Cl < F < Te < Po"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "Po < Te < F < Cl"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w5pi97",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of electron gain enthalpy ($$-$$ ve value) is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "O > S > Se > Te",
      "O < S < Se < Te",
      "O < S > Se > Te",
      "O < S > Se < Te"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "O < S > Se > Te"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mcidmt",
    "question": "<p>In which of the following pairs, electron gain enthalpies of constituent elements are nearly the same or identical?</p>\n<p>(A) Rb and Cs</p>\n<p>(B) Na and K</p>\n<p>(C) Ar and Kr</p>\n<p>(D) I and At</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) and (B) only",
      "(B) and (C) only",
      "(A) and (C) only",
      "(C) and (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "(A) and (C) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldujxa7o",
    "question": "<p>Inert gases have positive electron gain enthalpy. Its correct order is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "He < Ne < Kr < Xe",
      "He < Xe < Kr < Ne",
      "Xe < Kr < Ne < He",
      "He < Kr < Xe < Ne"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "He < Xe < Kr < Ne"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh28surs",
    "question": "<p>The difference between electron gain enthalpies will be maximum between :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Ar and Cl",
      "Ne and Cl",
      "Ne and F",
      "Ar and F"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "Ne and Cl"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse8akex",
    "question": "<p>The correct sequence of electron gain enthalpy of the elements listed below is</p>\n<p>A. Ar</p>\n<p>B. Br</p>\n<p>C. F</p>\n<p>D. S</p>\n<p>Choose the <b>most appropriate</b> from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{A>D>C>B}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{A}>\\mathrm{D}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{C}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{D}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{A}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{D}>\\mathrm{A}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{A}>\\mathrm{D}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{C}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfmk12q",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Fluorine has most negative electron gain enthalpy in its group.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Oxygen has least negative electron gain enthalpy in its group.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2usqx",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : The oxidation state of an element in a particular compound is the charge acquired by its atom on the basis of electron gain enthalpy consideration from other atoms in the molecule.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : $$\\mathrm{p} \\pi-\\mathrm{p} \\pi$$ bond formation is more prevalent in second period elements over other periods.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct\n",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc584o4",
    "question": "<p>The electron affinity value are negative for</p>\n<p>A. $$\\mathrm{Be} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{Be}^{-}$$</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{N} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{N}^{-}$$</p>\n<p>C. $$\\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{O}^{2-}$$</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{Na} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{Na}^{-}$$</p>\n<p>E. $$\\mathrm{Al} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{Al}^{-}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B, D and E only\n",
      "D and E only\n",
      "A and D only\n",
      "A, B and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electron-gain-enthalpy",
    "solution": "A, B and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "czSLorwmhSeJucEt",
    "question": "The formation of the oxide ion O<sup>2-</sup>(g) requires first an exothermic and then an endothermic\nstep as shown below <br/><br/>\nO<sub>(g)</sub> + e<sup>-</sup> = $$O_{(g)}^{-}$$ $$\\Delta $$H<sup>o</sup>  = -142 kJmol<sup>-1</sup><br/><br/>\n$$O_{(g)}^{-}$$ + e<sup>-</sup> = $$O_{(g)}^{2-}$$ $$\\Delta $$H<sup>o</sup> = 844 kJmol<sup>-1</sup><br/><br/> \nThis because ",
    "options": [
      "O<sup>-</sup> ion will tend to resist the addition of another electron ",
      "Oxygen has high electron affinity",
      "Oxygen is more electronegative ",
      "O<sup>-</sup> ion has comparatively larger size than oxygen atom "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electronegativity",
    "solution": "O<sup>-</sup> ion will tend to resist the addition of another electron "
  },
  {
    "id": "zt41lVfktVcLf4z4SxX2r",
    "question": "In general, the properties that decrease and increase down a group in the periodic table, respectively, are : ",
    "options": [
      "Atomic Radius and Electronegativity",
      "Electron Gain Enthalpy and Electronegativity. ",
      "Electronegativity and Atomic Radius.",
      "Electronegativity and Electron Gain Enthalpy."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electronegativity",
    "solution": "Electronegativity and Atomic Radius."
  },
  {
    "id": "SYfp09gAHw5vszkNGPdPk",
    "question": "The electronegativity of aluminium is similar to : ",
    "options": [
      "Beryllium",
      "Carbon",
      "Boron",
      "Lithium"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electronegativity",
    "solution": "Beryllium"
  },
  {
    "id": "1NYoLvdsw8RDFpOlqJnUx",
    "question": "The correct option with respect to the Pauling electronegativity values of the element is : ",
    "options": [
      "Ga &lt; Ge",
      "Si &lt; Al",
      "Te &gt; Se",
      "P &gt; S"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electronegativity",
    "solution": "Ga &lt; Ge"
  },
  {
    "id": "kUkJbCnwVC6Xpxdirgjgy2xukevlra8w",
    "question": "In general the property (magnitudes only) that\nshow an opposite trend in comparison to other\nproperties across a period is",
    "options": [
      "Electron gain enthalpy",
      "Electronegativity",
      "Ionization enthalpy",
      "Atomic radius"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electronegativity",
    "solution": "Atomic radius"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh02wxn8",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of electronegativity for given elements is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$ \\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{P}>\\mathrm{At}>\\mathrm{Br}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Br}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{At}>\\mathrm{P}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Br}>\\mathrm{P}>\\mathrm{At}>\\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{P}>\\mathrm{Br}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{At}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electronegativity",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Br}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{At}>\\mathrm{P}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfje1xt",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p><b>Statement I </b>: The electronegativity of group 14 elements from $$\\mathrm{Si}$$ to $$\\mathrm{Pb}$$, gradually decreases.</p>\n<p><b>Statement II</b> : Group 14 contains non-metallic, metallic, as well as metalloid elements.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "electronegativity",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ik8bdwg3HEN3lvci",
    "question": "The atomic numbers of Vanadium (V), Chromium (cr), Manganese (Mn) and Iron (Fe), respectively, $$23,24,25$$ and $$26$$. Which one of these may be expected to have the higher second ionization enthalpy? ",
    "options": [
      "Cr",
      "Mn",
      "Fe",
      "V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "Cr"
  },
  {
    "id": "fiVb9ZmMM2eIsnsx",
    "question": "The increasing order of the first ionization enthalpies of the elements B, P, S and F (lowest first) is :",
    "options": [
      "F &lt; S &lt; P &lt; B ",
      "P &lt; S &lt; B &lt; F",
      "B &lt; P &lt; S &lt; F ",
      "B &lt; S &lt; P &lt; F "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "B &lt; S &lt; P &lt; F "
  },
  {
    "id": "hwqnaLtz64pNGhiP",
    "question": "The first ionization potential of Na is 5.1 eV. The value of electron gain enthalpy of Na+\n will be: ",
    "options": [
      "– 5.1 eV ",
      "–10.2 eV",
      "+ 2.55 eV",
      "– 2.55 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "– 5.1 eV "
  },
  {
    "id": "0L67JQ4Hlh6dXi0w",
    "question": "Which of the following represents the correct order of increasing first ionization enthalpy for Ca, Ba, S, Se\nand Ar?",
    "options": [
      "S &lt; Se &lt; Ca &lt; Ba &lt; Ar ",
      "Ba &lt; Ca &lt; Se &lt; S &lt; Ar ",
      "Ca &lt; Ba &lt; S &lt; Se &lt; Ar ",
      "Ca &lt; S &lt; Ba &lt; Se &lt; Ar "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "Ba &lt; Ca &lt; Se &lt; S &lt; Ar "
  },
  {
    "id": "EFht6grTUGVQ7GXkQErPQ",
    "question": "Consider the following ionization enthalpies of two elements 'A' and 'B' .\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-p7ly{font-weight:bold;font-size:20px;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-4kyz{font-size:20px;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-p7ly\">Element</th>\n<th class=\"tg-p7ly\" colspan=\"3\">Ionization enthalpy (kJ/mol)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">1<sup>st</sup></td>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">2<sup>nd</sup></td>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">3<sup>rd</sup></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">A</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">899</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">1757</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">14847</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">B</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">737</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">1450</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">7731</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>\n<br/><br/>Which of the following statements is <b>correct</b>  ?\n",
    "options": [
      "Both ‘A’ and ‘B’ belong to group-1where ‘B’ comes below ‘A’.\n",
      "Both ‘A’ and ‘B’ belong to group-1 where ‘A’ comes below ‘B’.",
      "Both ‘A’ and ‘B’ belong to group-2 where ‘B’ comes below ‘A’.",
      "Both ‘A’ and ‘B’ belong to group-2 where ‘A’ comes below ‘B’."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "Both ‘A’ and ‘B’ belong to group-2 where ‘B’ comes below ‘A’."
  },
  {
    "id": "ZKx2nRw6gDyMaNAe8vJou",
    "question": "The electronic configuration with the highest ionization enthalpy is :",
    "options": [
      "[Ne] 3s<sup>2</sup> 3p<sup>1</sup>",
      "[Ne] 3s<sup>2</sup> 3p<sup>2</sup> ",
      "[Ne] 3s<sup>2</sup> 3p<sup>3</sup>",
      "[Ar] 3d<sup>10</sup> 4s<sup>2</sup> 4p<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "[Ne] 3s<sup>2</sup> 3p<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "aWEoBg2Pl5wdFEL7xEISy",
    "question": "The element having greatest difference between\nits first and second ionization energies, is :",
    "options": [
      "Ba",
      "Ca",
      "Sc",
      "K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "K"
  },
  {
    "id": "vdQzSMKy5Al82WwiLQ3rsa0w2w9jx926uap",
    "question": "In comparison to boron, berylium has :",
    "options": [
      "lesser nuclear charge and greater first ionisation enthalpy",
      "greater nuclear charge and greater first ionisation enthalpy",
      "greater nuclear charge and lesser first ionisation enthalpy",
      "lesser nuclear charge and lesser first ionisation ethalpy"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "lesser nuclear charge and greater first ionisation enthalpy"
  },
  {
    "id": "EWBol1WNgzzZ5s6rgu7k9k2k5h10ay2",
    "question": "The third ionization enthalpy is minimum for :",
    "options": [
      "Ni",
      "Co",
      "Mn",
      "Fe"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "Fe"
  },
  {
    "id": "2Mg8RHzSwYaiLtI0ly7k9k2k5h6kkpk",
    "question": "The first ionization energy (in kJ/mol) of Na, Mg, Al and Si respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "496, 577, 786, 737",
      "496, 737, 577, 786",
      "786, 737, 577, 496",
      "496, 577, 737, 786"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "496, 737, 577, 786"
  },
  {
    "id": "u6IfqVf6tbK40x16DG7k9k2k5icsuaf",
    "question": "B has a smaller first ionization enthalpy than\nBe. Consider the following statements :<br/><br/>\n(I) It is easier to remove 2p electron than 2s\nelectron<br/><br/>\n(II) 2p electron of B is more shielded from the\nnucleus by the inner core of electrons than\nthe 2s electrons of Be.<br/><br/>\n(III) 2s electron has more penetration power\nthan 2p electron.<br/><br/>\n(IV) atomic radius of B is more than Be\n(Atomic number B = 5, Be = 4)<br/><br/>\nThe correct statements are :",
    "options": [
      "(I), (III) and (IV)",
      "(II), (III) and (IV)",
      "(I), (II) and (IV)",
      "(I), (II) and (III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "(I), (II) and (III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "PNpMWKAgPnACxm6HWa7k9k2k5lfq2nr",
    "question": "The first and second ionisation enthalpies of a\nmetal are 496 and 4560 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>, respectively.\nHow many moles of HCl and H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>,\nrespectively, will be needed to react completely\nwith 1 mole of the metal hydroxide ?",
    "options": [
      "1 and 2",
      "1 and 0.5",
      "1 and 1",
      "2 and 0.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "1 and 0.5"
  },
  {
    "id": "Pf3572QMbuiI5itClajgy2xukf2e5jkx",
    "question": "Among the statements (I – IV), the correct ones\nare:\n<br/>(I) Be has smaller atomic radius compared to\nMg.\n<br/>(II) Be has higher ionization enthalpy than Al.\n<br/>(III) Charge/radius ratio of Be is greater than\nthat of Al.\n<br/>(IV) Both Be and Al form mainly covalent\ncompounds.",
    "options": [
      "(I), (II) and (IV)",
      "(II), (III) and (IV)",
      "(I), (III) and (IV)",
      "(I), (II) and (III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "(I), (II) and (IV)"
  },
  {
    "id": "287GCn5IPHqKhcuBwBjgy2xukf3ipq51",
    "question": "The five successive ionization enthalpies of an\nelement are 800, 2427, 3658, 25024 and 32824\nkJ mol<sup>–1</sup>. The number of valence electrons in\nthe element is :",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "3",
      "4",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "s1BB1rArLsvSgZvLU51klre8bvz",
    "question": "Consider the elements Mg, Al, S, P and Si, the correct increasing order of their first ionization\nenthalpy is :",
    "options": [
      "Al &lt; Mg &lt; Si &lt; S &lt; P",
      "Al &lt; Mg &lt; S &lt; Si &lt; P",
      "Mg &lt; Al &lt; Si &lt; S &lt; P",
      "Mg &lt; Al &lt; Si &lt; P &lt; S"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "Al &lt; Mg &lt; Si &lt; S &lt; P"
  },
  {
    "id": "vw5UG91COQjGHgYD0k1klucntlw",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List I<br/> Electronic configuration</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List II<br/> $${\\Delta _i}H$$ in kJ $$mo{l^{ - 1}}$$</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>$$1{s^2}2{s^2}$$</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>801</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>$$1{s^2}2{s^2}2{p^4}$$</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>899</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>$$1{s^2}2{s^2}2{p^3}$$</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>1314</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>$$1{s^2}2{s^2}2{p^1}$$</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>1402</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (i), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (b) $$ \\to $$ (i), (c) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (i)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (i), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (d) $$ \\to $$ (ii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "(a) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "rweUtYFJ4i6wJFXbRw1kmitzd6m",
    "question": "Identify the elements X and Y using the ionisation energy values given below :<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>Ionization energy (kJ/mol)</th>\n<th></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td></td>\n<td>1$${st}$$</td>\n<td>2$${nd}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>X</td>\n<td>495</td>\n<td>4563</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>Y</td>\n<td>731</td>\n<td>1450</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "X = F; Y = Mg",
      "X = Mg; Y = F",
      "X = Na; Y = Mg",
      "X = Mg; Y = Na"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "X = Na; Y = Mg"
  },
  {
    "id": "2hTGONkgwIUqTCaGI31kmm13av5",
    "question": "The first ionization energy of magnesium is smaller as compared to that of elements X and Y, but higher than that of Z. The elements X, Y and Z, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "neon, sodium and chlorine",
      "argon, chlorine and sodium",
      "chlorine, lithium and sodium",
      "argon, lithium and sodium"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "argon, chlorine and sodium"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1h93un",
    "question": "The correct order of first ionisation enthalpy is :",
    "options": [
      "Mg &lt; S &lt; Al &lt; P",
      "Mg &lt; Al &lt; S &lt; P",
      "Al &lt; Mg &lt; S &lt; P",
      "Mg &lt; Al &lt; P &lt; S"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "Al &lt; Mg &lt; S &lt; P"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54y9cxc",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements. One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : The first ionization enthalpy for oxygen is lower than that of nitrogen.</p>\n<p>Reason R : The four electrons in 2p orbitals of oxygen experience more electron-electron repulsion.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are are correct and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is correct but R is not correct.",
      "A is not correct but R is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "Both A and R are are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f6p8di",
    "question": "<p>The first ionization enthalpies of Be, B, N and O follow the order</p>",
    "options": [
      "O < N < B < Be",
      "Be < B < N < O",
      "B < Be < N < O",
      "B < Be < O < N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "B < Be < O < N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jkoy8d",
    "question": "<p>The incorrect statement is</p>",
    "options": [
      "The first ionization enthalpy of K is less than that of Na and Li.",
      "Xe does not have the lowest first ionization enthalpy in its group.",
      "The first ionization enthalpy of element with atomic number 37 is lower than that of the element with atomic number 38.",
      "The first ionization enthalpy of Ga is higher than that of the d-block element with atomic number 30."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "The first ionization enthalpy of Ga is higher than that of the d-block element with atomic number 30."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p70irf",
    "question": "<p>The first ionization enthalpy of Na, Mg and Si, respectively, are : 496, 737 and $$786 \\mathrm{~kJ} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$. The first ionization enthalpy ($$\\mathrm{kJ} \\,\\mathrm{mol}^{-1}$$) of $$\\mathrm{Al}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "487",
      "768",
      "577",
      "856"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "577"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo9jka5",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as <b>Assertion (A)</b> and the other is labelled as <b>Reason (R)</b>\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Assertion (A):</b> The first ionization enthalpy of $3 \\mathrm{~d}$ series elements is more than that of group 2 metals\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Reason (R):</b> In 3d series of elements successive filling of d-orbitals takes place.\n<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below : ",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but $(\\mathbf{R})$ is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "(A) is false but (R) is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsc2o1m",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The decrease in first ionization enthalpy from B to Al is much larger than that from Al to Ga.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The d orbitals in Ga are completely filled.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but statement II is correct",
      "Both the statements I and II are correct",
      "Both the statements I and II are incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "Both the statements I and II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguzhffg",
    "question": "<p>For elements $$\\mathrm{B}, \\mathrm{C}, \\mathrm{N}, \\mathrm{Li}, \\mathrm{Be}, \\mathrm{O}$$ and $$\\mathrm{F}$$, the correct order of first ionization enthalpy is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Li}<\\mathrm{Be}<\\mathrm{B}<\\mathrm{C}<\\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{N}<\\mathrm{F}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{Li}>\\mathrm{Be}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{N}>\\mathrm{O}>\\mathrm{F}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Li}<\\mathrm{Be}<\\mathrm{B}<\\mathrm{C}<\\mathrm{N}<\\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{F}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Li}<\\mathrm{B}<\\mathrm{Be}<\\mathrm{C}<\\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{N}<\\mathrm{F}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Li}<\\mathrm{B}<\\mathrm{Be}<\\mathrm{C}<\\mathrm{O}<\\mathrm{N}<\\mathrm{F}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvu0oop",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A : The energy required to form $$\\mathrm{Mg}^{2+}$$ from $$\\mathrm{Mg}$$ is much higher than that required to produce $$\\mathrm{Mg}^+$$</p>\n<p>Reason $$\\mathbf{R}: \\mathrm{Mg}^{2+}$$ is small ion and carry more charge than $$\\mathrm{Mg}^{+}$$</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaoc9af",
    "question": "The transition metal having highest $3^{\\text {rd }}$ ionisation enthalpy is :",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{Mn}$",
      "$\\mathrm{Fe}$",
      "$\\mathrm{Cr}$",
      "$V$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{Mn}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjay38",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$ :</p>\n<p>Assertion A : The first ionisation enthalpy decreases across a period.</p>\n<p>Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$ : The increasing nuclear charge outweighs the shielding across the period.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is true\n",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$\n",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfmotns",
    "question": "<p>The element having the highest first ionization enthalpy is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{C}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Al}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Si}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{N}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{N}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxzq97n",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 572px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 160px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 262px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Melting Point $$[\\mathrm{K}]$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{T} 1&gt;\\mathrm{In}&gt;\\mathrm{Ga}&gt;\\mathrm{A} 1&gt;\\mathrm{B}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ionic Radius $$[\\mathrm{M}^{+3} / \\mathrm{pm}]$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{B}&gt;\\mathrm{T} 1&gt;\\mathrm{Al} \\approx \\mathrm{Ga}&gt;\\mathrm{In}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\Delta_{\\mathrm{i}} \\mathrm{H}_1[\\mathrm{~kJ} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}]$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{T} 1&gt;\\mathrm{In}&gt;\\mathrm{Al}&gt;\\mathrm{Ga}&gt;\\mathrm{B}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Atomic Radius [pm]</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{B}&gt;\\mathrm{A} 1&gt;\\mathrm{T} 1&gt;\\mathrm{In}&gt;\\mathrm{Ga}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III\n",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV\n",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vyqw9",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of first ionization enthalpy values of the following elements is :</p>\n<p>(A) O</p>\n<p>(B) N</p>\n<p>(C) Be</p>\n<p>(D) F</p>\n<p>(E) B</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{A}<\\mathrm{B}<\\mathrm{D}<\\mathrm{C}<\\mathrm{E}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}<\\mathrm{E}<\\mathrm{A}<\\mathrm{B}<\\mathrm{D}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{E}<\\mathrm{C}<\\mathrm{A}<\\mathrm{B}<\\mathrm{D}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{B}<\\mathrm{D}<\\mathrm{C}<\\mathrm{E}<\\mathrm{A}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{E}<\\mathrm{C}<\\mathrm{A}<\\mathrm{B}<\\mathrm{D}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erzas",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of the first ionization enthalpy is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Ga}>\\mathrm{Al}>\\mathrm{B}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Tl}>\\mathrm{Ga}>\\mathrm{Al}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Al}>\\mathrm{Ga}>\\mathrm{Tl}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{Al}>\\mathrm{Ga}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Tl}>\\mathrm{Ga}>\\mathrm{Al}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erj91",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The correct order of first ionization enthalpy values of $$\\mathrm{Li}, \\mathrm{Na}, \\mathrm{F}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cl}$$ is $$\\mathrm{Na}&lt;\\mathrm{Li}&lt;\\mathrm{Cl}&lt;\\mathrm{F}$$.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The correct order of negative electron gain enthalpy values of $$\\mathrm{Li}, \\mathrm{Na}, \\mathrm{F}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cl}$$ is $$\\mathrm{Na}&lt;\\mathrm{Li}&lt;\\mathrm{F}&lt;\\mathrm{Cl}$$</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "ionization-energy",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "BhhYY8pJsndQGssB",
    "question": "Which one of the following is an amphoteric oxide?",
    "options": [
      "Na<sub>2</sub>O",
      "SO<sub>2</sub>",
      "B<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "ZnO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "ZnO"
  },
  {
    "id": "OXnfgb75B5dClK6j",
    "question": "Among Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, SiO<sub>2</sub>, P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and SO<sub>2</sub> the correct order of acid strength is",
    "options": [
      "SO<sub>2</sub> &lt; P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; SiO<sub>2</sub> &lt; Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; SiO<sub>2</sub> &lt; <sub>P2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; SO<sub>2</sub>",
      "Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; SiO<sub>2</sub> &lt; SO<sub>2</sub> &lt; P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "SiO<sub>2</sub> &lt; SO<sub>2</sub> &lt; Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; SiO<sub>2</sub> &lt; <sub>P2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; SO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "fsvUXCFmmtl2cjfY",
    "question": "Which of the following oxides is amphoteric in character? ",
    "options": [
      "CaO",
      "CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "SiO<sub>2</sub> ",
      "SnO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "SnO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "c26y3YHeSZn6k4re",
    "question": "In which of the following arrangements, the sequence is not strictly according to the property written against it",
    "options": [
      "CO<sub>2</sub> &lt; SiO<sub>2</sub> &lt;  SnO<sub>2</sub> &lt; PbO<sub>2</sub> : increasing oxidising power",
      "HF &lt; HCl &lt; HBr, HI : increasing acid strength",
      "NH<sub>3</sub> &lt; PH<sub>3</sub> &lt; AsH<sub>3</sub> &lt; SbH<sub>3</sub> : increasing basic strength",
      "B &lt; C &lt; O &lt; N : increasing first ionization enthalpy"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "NH<sub>3</sub> &lt; PH<sub>3</sub> &lt; AsH<sub>3</sub> &lt; SbH<sub>3</sub> : increasing basic strength"
  },
  {
    "id": "9BvtDiokWWAJbNgs",
    "question": "Which one of the following order represents the correct sequence of the increasing basic nature of the\ngiven oxides ?",
    "options": [
      "MgO &lt; K<sub>2</sub>O &lt; Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; Na<sub>2</sub>O",
      "Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; MgO &lt; Na<sub>2</sub>O &lt; K<sub>2</sub>O",
      "Na<sub>2</sub>O &lt; K<sub>2</sub>O &lt; MgO &lt; Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "K<sub>2</sub>O &lt; Na<sub>2</sub>O &lt; Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; MgO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; MgO &lt; Na<sub>2</sub>O &lt; K<sub>2</sub>O"
  },
  {
    "id": "hWos1QbD2o6pGJCQcMXfX",
    "question": "Which one of the following is an oxide?",
    "options": [
      "KO<sub>2</sub>  ",
      "BaO<sub>2</sub> ",
      "SiO<sub>2</sub> ",
      "CsO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "SiO<sub>2</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "OqdbyXIPmG3ZzYVE4t7k9k2k5icuagp",
    "question": "The acidic, basic and amphoteric oxides,\nrespectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "Cl<sub>2</sub>O, CaO, P<sub>4</sub>O<sub>10</sub>",
      "N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, Li<sub>2</sub>O, Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "MgO, Cl<sub>2</sub>O, Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "Na<sub>2</sub>O, SO<sub>3</sub>, Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, Li<sub>2</sub>O, Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "0B5292oiL6TvmutB9Ejgy2xukexzkfno",
    "question": "Three elements X, Y and Z are in the 3<sup>rd</sup> period\nof the periodic table. The oxides of X, Y and Z,\nrespectively, are basic, amphoteric and acidic.\nThe correct order of the atomic numbers of X,\nY and Z is :",
    "options": [
      "X &lt; Z &lt; Y",
      "Y &lt; X &lt; Z",
      "Z &lt; Y &lt; X",
      "X &lt; Y &lt; Z"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "X &lt; Y &lt; Z"
  },
  {
    "id": "qzdhwGRhNUgj6Phwnq1kluryl24",
    "question": "Which pair of oxides is acidic in nature?",
    "options": [
      "CaO, SiO<sub>2</sub>",
      "B<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, CaO",
      "B<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, SiO<sub>2</sub>",
      "N<sub>2</sub>O, BaO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "B<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, SiO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz1ky52",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II :<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>NaOH</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Acidic</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>$$Be{(OH)_2}$$</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Basic</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>$$Ca{(OH)_2}$$</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Amphoteric</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>$$B{(OH)_3}$$</td>\n<td></td>\n<td></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(e)</td>\n<td>$$Al{(OH)_3}$$</td>\n<td></td>\n<td></td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below ",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iii), (d)-(ii), (e)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i), (e)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iii), (d)-(i), (e)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iii), (e)-(iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i), (e)-(iii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55n6t8x",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 478px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 43px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 178px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 205px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-I (Oxide)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-II (Nature)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$C{l_2}{O_7}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Amphoteric</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$N{a_2}O$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Basic</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$A{l_2}{O_3}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Neutral</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${N_2}O$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Acidic</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - (IV), (B) - (III), (C) - (I), (D) - (II)",
      "(A) - (IV), (B) - (II), (C) - (I), (D) - (III)",
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (IV), (C) - (III), (D) - (I)",
      "(A) - (I), (B) - (II), (C) - (III), (D) - (IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "(A) - (IV), (B) - (II), (C) - (I), (D) - (III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55naceb",
    "question": "<p>Among the following, basic oxide is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "SO<sub>3</sub>",
      "SiO<sub>2</sub>",
      "CaO",
      "Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "CaO"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c6d6n1",
    "question": "<p>Given below are the oxides:</p>\n<p>Na<sub>2</sub>O, As<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>O, NO and Cl<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub></p>\n<p>Number of amphoteric oxides is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0",
      "1",
      "2",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq3y68n",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following statements are not correct?</p>\n<p>A. The electron gain enthalpy of $$\\mathrm{F}$$ is more negative than that of $$\\mathrm{Cl}$$.</p>\n<p>B. Ionization enthalpy decreases in a group of periodic table.</p>\n<p>C. The electronegativity of an atom depends upon the atoms bonded to it.</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{Al}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{NO}$$ are examples of amphoteric oxides.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B, C and D",
      "A, C and D Only",
      "A, B and D Only",
      "B and D Only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "A, C and D Only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh3266hc",
    "question": "<p>Group-13 elements react with $$\\mathrm{O}_{2}$$ in amorphous form to form oxides of type $$\\mathrm{M}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{3}~(\\mathrm{M}=$$ element). Which among the following is the most basic oxide?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Al$$_2$$O$$_3$$",
      "TI$$_2$$O$$_3$$",
      "B$$_2$$O$$_3$$",
      "Ga$$_2$$O$$_3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "TI$$_2$$O$$_3$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg836jo",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement - I: Along the period, the chemical reactivity of the elements gradually increases from group 1 to group 18 .</p>\n<p>Statement - II: The nature of oxides formed by group 1 elements is basic while that of group 17 elements is acidic.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is False but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are False\n",
      "Statement I is True But Statement II is False\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are True"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "nature-of-oxide",
    "solution": "Statement I is False but Statement II is true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "RmAad1XKRBKGo82A",
    "question": "According to the Periodic Law of elements, the variation in properties of elements is related to their",
    "options": [
      "nuclear masses",
      "atomic numbers",
      "nuclear neutron-proton number ratios",
      "atomic masses"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "atomic numbers"
  },
  {
    "id": "Oq7FrqXUGCyfiyFr",
    "question": "Following statements regarding the periodic trends of chemical reactivity of the alkali metals and the\nhalogens are given. Which of these statements gives the correct picture? ",
    "options": [
      "The reactivity decreases in the alkali metals but increases in the halogens with increase in atomic\nnumber down the group ",
      "In both the alkali metals and the halogens the chemical reactivity decreases with increase in\natomic number down the group",
      "Chemical reactivity increases with increase in atomic number down the group in both the alkali\nmetals and halogens ",
      "In alkali metals the reactivity increases but in the halogens it decreases with increase in atomic\nnumber down the group "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "In alkali metals the reactivity increases but in the halogens it decreases with increase in atomic\nnumber down the group "
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrI6PKBEmtwbZP",
    "question": "Outer electronic configuration of Gd (Atomic no : 64) is -",
    "options": [
      "4f<sup>8</sup>5d<sup>0</sup>6s<sup>2</sup>",
      "4f<sup>4</sup>5d<sup>4</sup>6s<sup>2</sup>",
      "4f<sup>7</sup>5d<sup>1</sup>6s<sup>2</sup>",
      "4f<sup>3</sup>5d<sup>5</sup>6s<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "4f<sup>7</sup>5d<sup>1</sup>6s<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "e7847wQT5m3tOcaK9JXhZ",
    "question": "The following statements concern elements in the periodic table. Which of the following is true ?",
    "options": [
      "All the elements in Group 17 are gases.",
      "The Group 13 elements are all metals.",
      "Elements of Group 16 have lower ionization enthalpy values compared\nto those of Group 15 in the corresponding periods.",
      "For Group 15 elements, the stability of + 5 oxidation state increases down\nthe group."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "Elements of Group 16 have lower ionization enthalpy values compared\nto those of Group 15 in the corresponding periods."
  },
  {
    "id": "VF0l4Bnb6dMOXU2M6l1CM",
    "question": "Aluminium is usually found in +3 oxidation state. In contrast, thallium exists in + 1 and + 3 oxidation states. This is due to : ",
    "options": [
      "inert pair effect ",
      "diagonal relationship ",
      "lattice structure",
      "lanthanoid contraction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "inert pair effect "
  },
  {
    "id": "IjGNobifF4qvC7wUtigt0",
    "question": "The element with Z = 120 (not yet discovered) will be an/a - ",
    "options": [
      "Alkaline earth metal",
      "Alkali metal ",
      "Transition metal ",
      "Inner transition metal "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "Alkaline earth metal"
  },
  {
    "id": "gCYe4UHRQA58hYaW4OMVT",
    "question": "The lathanide ion that would show colour is :",
    "options": [
      "Sm<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Gd<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Lu<sup>3+</sup>",
      "La<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "Sm<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "xHFNpBdzLG5c0XnCu5seX",
    "question": "The IUPAC symbol for the element with atomic\nnumber 119 would be :",
    "options": [
      "uun",
      "une",
      "uue",
      "unh"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "uue"
  },
  {
    "id": "Sv6vXzQkXSGQA5qck57k9k2k5idpeyw",
    "question": "The electronic configurations of bivalent\neuropium and trivalent cerium are<br/>\n(atomic number : Xe = 54, Ce = 58, Eu = 63)",
    "options": [
      "[Xe] 4f<sup>7</sup> 6s<sup>2</sup> and [Xe] 4f<sup>2</sup> 6s<sup>2</sup>",
      "[Xe] 4f<sup>2</sup> and [Xe] 4f<sup>7</sup>",
      "[Xe] 4f<sup>4</sup> and [Xe] 4f<sup>9</sup>",
      "[Xe] 4f<sup>7</sup> and [Xe] 4f<sup>1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "[Xe] 4f<sup>7</sup> and [Xe] 4f<sup>1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "mMnYC6nuD5wVAQcDgWjgy2xukf2bqnap",
    "question": "The atomic number of the element unnilennium is :",
    "options": [
      "109",
      "102",
      "119",
      "108"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "109"
  },
  {
    "id": "ovC6k9firpCEcLpHUT1kltbtw7l",
    "question": "The correct order of bond dissociation enthalpy of halogens is :",
    "options": [
      "F<sub>2</sub> &gt; Cl<sub>2</sub> &gt; Br<sub>2</sub> &gt; I<sub>2</sub>",
      "Cl<sub>2</sub> &gt; Br<sub>2</sub> &gt; F<sub>2</sub> &gt; I<sub>2</sub>",
      "I<sub>2</sub> &gt; Br<sub>2</sub> &gt; Cl<sub>2</sub> &gt; F<sub>2</sub>",
      "Cl<sub>2</sub> &gt; F<sub>2</sub> &gt; Br<sub>2</sub> &gt; I<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "Cl<sub>2</sub> &gt; Br<sub>2</sub> &gt; F<sub>2</sub> &gt; I<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "940D1wmXBAMZmuPmmK1kmitht5n",
    "question": "The characteristics of elements X, Y and Z with atomic numbers, respectively, 33, 53 and 83 are :",
    "options": [
      "X and Y are metalloids and Z is a metal.",
      "X and Z are non-metals and Y is a metalloid.",
      "X is a metalloid, Y is a non-metal and Z is a metal.",
      "X, Y and Z are metals."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "X is a metalloid, Y is a non-metal and Z is a metal."
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt34xum",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements for D.I. Mendeleeff, is incorrect?",
    "options": [
      "He authored the textbook - Principles of Chemistry",
      "At the time, he proposed Periodic Table of elements structure of atom was known.",
      "Element with atomic number 101 is named after him.",
      "He invented accurate barometer."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "At the time, he proposed Periodic Table of elements structure of atom was known."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjxabk7",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II :<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I<br/>(Metal Ion)</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II<br/>(Group of Qualitative analysis)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>$$M{n^{2 + }}$$</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Group - III</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>$$A{s^{3 + }}$$</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Group - IIA</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>$$C{u^{2 + }}$$</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Group - IV</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>$$A{l^{3 + }}$$</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Group - IIB</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iii), (d)-(i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56akmkw",
    "question": "<p>Element \"E\" belongs to the period 4 and group 16 of the periodic table. The valence shell electron configuration of the element, which is just above \"E\" in the group is</p>",
    "options": [
      "3s<sup>2</sup>, 3p<sup>4</sup>",
      "3d<sup>10</sup>, 4s<sup>2</sup>, 4p<sup>4</sup>",
      "4d<sup>10</sup>, 5s<sup>2</sup>, 5p<sup>4</sup>",
      "2s<sup>2</sup>, 2p<sup>4</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "3s<sup>2</sup>, 3p<sup>4</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6e13hl0",
    "question": "<p>The IUPAC nomenclature of an element with electronic configuration [Rn] $$5 \\mathrm{f}^{14} 6 \\mathrm{d}^{1} 7 \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Unnilbium",
      "Unnilunium",
      "Unnilquadium",
      "Unniltrium"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "Unniltrium"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo95c7k",
    "question": "Which of the following elements have half-filled f-orbitals in their ground state?\n<br/><br/>\n(Given : atomic number $\\mathrm{Sm}=62 ; \\mathrm{Eu}=63 ; \\mathrm{Tb}=65 ; \\mathrm{Gd}=64, \\mathrm{Pm}=61$ )<br/><br/>\nA. $\\mathrm{Sm}$<br/><br/>\nB. Eu<br/><br/>\nC. $\\mathrm{Tb}$<br/><br/>\nD. Gd<br/><br/>\nE. $\\mathrm{Pm}$\n<br/><br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      " B and D only",
      "A and $B$ only",
      "$C$ and $\\mathrm{D}$ only",
      "A and E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": " B and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqxee3e",
    "question": "Bond dissociation energy of \"E-H\" bond of the \"$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{E}$ \" hydrides of group 16 elements (given below), follows order.<br/><br/>\nA. $\\mathrm{O}$<br/><br/>\nB. $\\mathrm{S}$<br/><br/>\nC. Se<br/><br/>\nD. $\\mathrm{Te}$\n<br/><br/>\nChoose the correct from the options given below:",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{A}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{D}$",
      "$\\mathrm{D}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{A}$\n",
      "$\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{A}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{D}$",
      "$\\mathrm{A}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{D}>\\mathrm{C}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{A}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{D}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr4anoy",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 607px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 263px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I<br/>(Atomic number)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II<br/>(Block of periodic table)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">37</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">p-block</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">78</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">d-block</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">52</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">f-block</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">65</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">s-block</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A - II, B - IV, C - I, D - III",
      "A - IV, B - III, C - II, D - I",
      "A - IV, B - II, C - I, D - III",
      "A - I, B - III, C - IV, D - II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "A - IV, B - II, C - I, D - III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh322ick",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following elements will remain as liquid inside pure boiling water?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Li",
      "Br",
      "Cs",
      "Ga"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "Ga"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaoyqb0",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (I)</b> : Both metals and non-metals exist in p and d-block elements.<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (II)</b> : Non-metals have higher ionisation enthalpy and higher electronegativity than the metals.\n<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc5d4na",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : The $$4 \\mathrm{f}$$ and $$5 \\mathrm{f}$$ - series of elements are placed separately in the Periodic table to preserve the principle of classification.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : S-block elements can be found in pure form in nature. \n<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfp8dv0",
    "question": "<p>Anomalous behavior of oxygen is due to its</p>",
    "options": [
      "large size and low electronegativity\n",
      "small size and high electronegativity\n",
      "small size and low electronegativity\n",
      "large size and high electronegativity"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "small size and high electronegativity\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg7tdbj",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R:</p>\n<p>Assertion A: $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{Te}$$ is more acidic than $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{~S}$$.</p>\n<p>Reason R: Bond dissociation enthalpy of $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{Te}$$ is lower than $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{~S}$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both $$A$$ and $$R$$ are true and $$R$$ is the correct explanation of $$A$$.\n",
      "Both $$A$$ and $$R$$ are true but $$R$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$A$$.\n",
      "$$A$$ is false but $$R$$ is true.\n",
      "$$A$$ is true but $$R$$ is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "Both $$A$$ and $$R$$ are true and $$R$$ is the correct explanation of $$A$$.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgy4z4q",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 551px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 74px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 179px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 82px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 216px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List I<br/>Species</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List II<br/>Electronic distribution</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Cr^{+2}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{3d^8}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Mn^+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{3d^34s^1}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Ni^{+2}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{3d^4}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{V^+}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{3d^54s^1}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(II), (C)-(III), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwem87",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST I<br/>(Element)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST II<br/>(Electronic Configuration)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{N}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$[\\mathrm{Ar}] 3 \\mathrm{~d}^{10} 4 \\mathrm{~s}^2 4 \\mathrm{p}^5$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{S}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$[\\mathrm{Ne}] 3 \\mathrm{~s}^2 3 \\mathrm{p}^4$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Br}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$[\\mathrm{He}] 2 \\mathrm{~s}^2 2 \\mathrm{p}^3$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Kr}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$[\\mathrm{Ar}] 3 \\mathrm{~d}^{10} 4 \\mathrm{~s}^2 4 \\mathrm{p}^6$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-I, B-IV, C-III, D-II\n",
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV\n",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vyr68",
    "question": "<p>Number of elements from the following that CANNOT form compounds with valencies which match with their respective group valencies is ________. B, C, N, S, O, F, P, Al, Si</p>",
    "options": [
      "7",
      "3",
      "5",
      "6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5grwf0",
    "question": "Match List I with List II\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 664px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 262px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Elements)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Properties in their respective groups)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Cl,S}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Elements with highest electronegativity </td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Ge,As}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Elements with largest atomic size</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Fr,Ra}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Elements which show properties of both metals and non-metal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{F,O}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Elements with highest negative electron gain enthalpy</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV\n",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III\n",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I\n",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3yys",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I: In group 13, the stability of +1 oxidation state increases down the group.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The atomic size of gallium is greater than that of aluminium.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct\n",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "periodic-table-and-periodicity",
    "topic": "periodic-table-and-its-features",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "YeX4D66ntKuoZcBd",
    "question": "Which of the following is fully fluorinated polymer? ",
    "options": [
      "Neoprene ",
      "Teflon ",
      "Thiokol",
      "PVC "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Teflon "
  },
  {
    "id": "QwvPIUuSCTHSZtrX",
    "question": "Bakelite is obtained from phenol by reacting with ",
    "options": [
      "(CH<sub>2</sub>OH)<sub>2</sub>",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>CHO ",
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COCH<sub>3</sub>",
      "HCHO "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "HCHO "
  },
  {
    "id": "q3SJXeeeF6hgjUcR",
    "question": "The polymer containing strong intermolecular forces e.g. hydrogen bonding, is",
    "options": [
      "teflon",
      "nylon 6,6",
      "polystyrene",
      "natural rubber"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "nylon 6,6"
  },
  {
    "id": "WP3xzSnO7nC81kA7",
    "question": "The species which can best serve as an initiator for the cationic polymerization is :",
    "options": [
      "LiAlH<sub>4</sub>",
      "HNO<sub>3</sub>",
      "AlCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "BuLi"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "AlCl<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "TkSb5tPYSS5MarRm",
    "question": "Which one is classified as a condensation polymer?",
    "options": [
      "Teflon",
      "Acrylonitrile",
      "Dacron",
      "Neoprene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Dacron"
  },
  {
    "id": "R4DHlOg4ZAVTTAw644EHm",
    "question": "<b>Assertion : </b>\n<br/>Rayon is a semisynthetic polymer whose properties are better than natural cotton.\n<br/><br/><b>Reason :</b>\n<br/>Mechanical and aesthetic properties of cellulose can be improved by acetylation.",
    "options": [
      "Both assertion and reason are correct, and the reason is the correct explanation for the assertion.",
      "Both assertion and reason are correct, but the reason is not the correct explanation for the assertion.\n",
      "Assertion is incorrect statement, but the reason is correct.",
      "Both assertion and reason are incorrect."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Both assertion and reason are correct, but the reason is not the correct explanation for the assertion.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "EvOftvbUZrCOCLi0E1JLf",
    "question": "Which of the following polymers is synthesized using a free radical\npolymerization technique ?",
    "options": [
      "Teflon",
      "Terylene",
      "Melamine polymer",
      "Nylon 6, 6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Teflon"
  },
  {
    "id": "9jSxvfgu9skxsFOV",
    "question": "The formation of which of the following polymers involves hydrolysis reaction?",
    "options": [
      "Bakelite\n",
      "Nylon 6, 6",
      "Terylene",
      "Nylon 6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Nylon 6"
  },
  {
    "id": "FOHd2K8fzioZHEExWmxdW",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is <b>not</b> true ? ",
    "options": [
      "Step growth polymerisation requires a bifunctional monomer.",
      "Nylon 6 is an example of step-growth polymerisation. ",
      "Chain growth polymerisation includes both homopolymerisation and copylymerisation.",
      "Chain growth polymerisation involves homopolymerisation only. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Chain growth polymerisation involves homopolymerisation only. "
  },
  {
    "id": "dWsN3Ze14gktg3rXT63rsa0w2w9jx4r5vl5",
    "question": "Which of the following is a thermosetting polymer?",
    "options": [
      "Buna-N",
      "PVC",
      "NyIon6",
      "Bakelite"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Bakelite"
  },
  {
    "id": "w0uRUdnIaxuWxq6IIu3rsa0w2w9jx0wn5ui",
    "question": "The correct match between Item-I and Item-II is : \n<br/><br/>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-s6z2{text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-s268{text-align:left}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Item - I</span></th>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-s6z2\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Item - II</span></th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(a)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s268\">High density polythene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s268\">Peroxide catalyst</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(b)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Polyacrylonitrile</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Condensation at high<br/>temperature &amp; pressure</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(c)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Novolac</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Ziegler-Natta Catalyst</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(d)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Nylon 6</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Acid or base catalyst</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (IV), (b) $$ \\to $$ (II), (c) $$ \\to $$ (I), (d) $$ \\to $$ (III)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (III), (b) $$ \\to $$ (I), (c) $$ \\to $$ (IV), (d) $$ \\to $$ (II)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (II), (b) $$ \\to $$ (IV), (c) $$ \\to $$ (I), (d) $$ \\to $$ (III)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (III), (b) $$ \\to $$ (I), (c) $$ \\to $$ (II), (d) $$ \\to $$ (IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "(a) $$ \\to $$ (III), (b) $$ \\to $$ (I), (c) $$ \\to $$ (IV), (d) $$ \\to $$ (II)"
  },
  {
    "id": "kwwaCPcbNad8FyurI03rsa0w2w9jwwerfzj",
    "question": "Which of the following is a condensation polymer?",
    "options": [
      "Neoprene",
      "Buna-S ",
      "Nylon 6, 6",
      "Teflon"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Nylon 6, 6"
  },
  {
    "id": "NmD6Lln5x3n1f3ojnrtoJ",
    "question": "Poly $$\\beta $$ –hydroxybutyrate-co-$$\\beta $$-hydroxyvalerate (PHBV) is a copolymer of ",
    "options": [
      "2-hydroxybutanoic acid and 3-hydroxypentanoic acid",
      "3-hydroxybutanoic acid and 2-hydroxypentanoic acid",
      "3-hydroxybutanoic acid and 3-hydroxypentanoic acid ",
      "3-hydroxybutanoic acid and 4-hydroxypentanoic acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "3-hydroxybutanoic acid and 3-hydroxypentanoic acid "
  },
  {
    "id": "xz5XA6Uy8Yx5c65wuEqWB",
    "question": "The two monomers for the synthesis of Nylon 6, 6 are",
    "options": [
      "HOOC(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>6</sub>COOH, H<sub>2</sub>N(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>4</sub>NH<sub>2</sub> ",
      "HOOC(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>4</sub>COOH, H<sub>2</sub>N(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>6</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>",
      "HOOC(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>4</sub>COOH, H<sub>2</sub>N(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>4</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>",
      "HOOC(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>6</sub>COOH, H<sub>2</sub>N(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>6</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "HOOC(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>4</sub>COOH, H<sub>2</sub>N(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>6</sub>NH<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "3Uc01RPfHvBUTEYJ5Gjgy2xukfp2ocze",
    "question": "Which one of the following polymers is not obtained by condensation polymerisation?",
    "options": [
      "Bakelite",
      "Nylon 6",
      "Buna-N",
      "Nylon 6, 6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Buna-N"
  },
  {
    "id": "4pxrTp0MvVuPb93jNJjgy2xukg0n52mw",
    "question": "The correct match between Item - I and Item - II\nis :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\"><b>Item - I</b></th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\"><b>Item - II</b></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(a) Natural rubber</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(I) 1, 3-butadiene\n+ styrene</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(b) Neoprene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(II) 1, 3-butadiene\n+ acrylonitrile</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(c) Buna-N</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(III) Chloroprene</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(d) Buna-S</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(IV) Isoprene</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "(a) - (IV), (b) - (III), (c) - (II), (d) - (I)",
      "(a) - (III), (b) - (IV), (c) - (I), (d) - (II)",
      "(a) - (III), (b) - (IV), (c) - (II), (d) - (I)",
      "(a) - (IV), (b) - (III), (c) - (I), (d) - (II)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "(a) - (IV), (b) - (III), (c) - (II), (d) - (I)"
  },
  {
    "id": "RDgdTViEFKoqMHR4ZSjgy2xukfupb477",
    "question": "Consider the Assertion and Reason given\nbelow.\n<br/><br/>Assertion (A) : Ethene polymerized in the\npresence of Ziegler Natta Catalyst at high\ntemperature and pressure is used to make\nbuckets and dustbins.\n<br/><br/>Reason (R) : High density polymers are closely\npacked and are chemically inert.\n<br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the following:",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the\ncorrect explanation of (A).",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not\nthe correct explanation of (A).",
      "(A) is correct but (R) is wrong.",
      "(A) and (R) both are wrong."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the\ncorrect explanation of (A)."
  },
  {
    "id": "B8frC15krJkPnwFBdf7k9k2k5lkxwrs",
    "question": "Which polymer has 'chiral' monomer(s) ?",
    "options": [
      "Nylon 6,6",
      "Buna-N",
      "PHBV",
      "Neoprene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "PHBV"
  },
  {
    "id": "W9iW02p231FVoeLQMR7k9k2k5hlu26t",
    "question": "Preparation of Bakelite proceeds via reactions.",
    "options": [
      "Electrophilic substitution and dehydration",
      "Condensation and elimination",
      "Nucleophilic addition and dehydration",
      "Electrophilic addition and dehydration"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Electrophilic substitution and dehydration"
  },
  {
    "id": "mVNWmmA8w3jSuVLJMb1klrens2x",
    "question": "Match <b>List I</b> with <b>List II</b>.<br/><br/>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List I <br/>(Monomer Unit)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List II<br/>(Polymer)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(a) Caprolactum</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(i) Natural rubber</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(b) 2-Chloro-1, 3-butadiene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(ii) Buna-N</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(c) Isoprene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(iii) Nylon 6</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(d) Acrylonitrile</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(iv) Neoprene</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below:",
    "options": [
      "(a) → (iv), (b) → (iii), (c) → (ii), (d) → (i)",
      "(a) → (iii), (b) → (iv), (c) → (i), (d) → (ii)",
      "(a) → (ii), (b) → (i), (c) → (iv), (d) → (iii)",
      "(a) → (i), (b) → (ii), (c) → (iii), (d) → (iv)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "(a) → (iii), (b) → (iv), (c) → (i), (d) → (ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "b9RT4YAVDThny2AXZx1klrtm24v",
    "question": "In polymer Buna-S : 'S' stands for :",
    "options": [
      "Sulphur",
      "Styrene",
      "Strength",
      "Sulphonation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Styrene"
  },
  {
    "id": "SoMqm4ToKUcx0J8LuX1klsbnov6",
    "question": "Which statement is correct?",
    "options": [
      "Buna-N is a natural polymer.",
      "Synthesis of Buna-S needs nascent oxygen.",
      "Buna-S is a synthetic and linear thermosetting polymer.",
      "Neoprene is an addition copolymer used in plastic bucket manufacturing."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Synthesis of Buna-S needs nascent oxygen."
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq5j8cu",
    "question": "Orlon fibres are made up of :",
    "options": [
      "Polyacrylonitrile",
      "Polyesters",
      "Polyamide",
      "Cellulose"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Polyacrylonitrile"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krrira42",
    "question": "Bakelite is a cross-linked polymer of formaldehyde and :",
    "options": [
      "PHBV",
      "Buna-S",
      "Novolac",
      "Dacron"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Novolac"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krx4v5by",
    "question": "A biodegradable polyamide can be made from :",
    "options": [
      "Glycine and isoprene",
      "Hexamethylene diamine and adipic acid",
      "Glycine and aminocaproic acid",
      "Styrene and caproic acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Glycine and aminocaproic acid"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktb3yln3",
    "question": "The polymer formed on heating Novolac with formaldehyde is :",
    "options": [
      "Bakelite",
      "Polyester",
      "Melamine",
      "Nylon 6, 6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Bakelite"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktial1be",
    "question": "Monomer of Novolac is :",
    "options": [
      "3-Hydroxybutanoic acid",
      "phenol and melamine",
      "o-Hydroxymethylphenol",
      "1, 3-Butadiene and styrene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "o-Hydroxymethylphenol"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjvz633",
    "question": "Which among the following is not a polyester?",
    "options": [
      "Novolac",
      "PHBV",
      "Dacron",
      "Glyptal"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Novolac"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktn0labb",
    "question": "Monomer units of Dacron polymer are :",
    "options": [
      "ethylene glycol and phthalic acid",
      "ethylene glycol and terephthalic acid",
      "glycerol and terephthalic acid",
      "glycerol and phthalic acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "ethylene glycol and terephthalic acid"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l549paa8",
    "question": "<p>The polymer, which can be stretched and remains its original status on releasing the force is</p>",
    "options": [
      "Bakelite.",
      "Nylon 6, 6.",
      "Buna-N.",
      "Terylene."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Buna-N."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54yu147",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p><b>Assertion A</b> : Dacron is an example of polyester polymer.</p>\n<p><b>Reason R</b> : Dacron is made up of ethylene glycol and terephthalic acid monomers.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is correct but R is not correct.",
      "A is not correct but R is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55nog1e",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements, one is Assertion (A) and other is Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : Natural rubber is a linear polymer of isoprene called cis-polyisoprene with elastic properties.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : The cis-polyisoprene molecules consist of various chains held together by strong polar interactions with coiled structure.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct one from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A).",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false.",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "(A) is true but (R) is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56b7da8",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following is NOT a copolymer?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Buna-S",
      "Neoprene",
      "PHBV",
      "Butadiene-styrene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Neoprene"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56y6k1k",
    "question": "<p>Which is true about Buna-N?</p>",
    "options": [
      "It is a linear polymer of 1, 3-butadiene.",
      "It is obtained by copolymerization of 1, 3-butadiene and styrene.",
      "It is obtained by copolymerization of 1, 3-butadiene and acrylonitrile.",
      "The suffix N in Buna-N stands for its natural occurrence."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "It is obtained by copolymerization of 1, 3-butadiene and acrylonitrile."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58e8t8z",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following sets are correct regarding polymer?</p>\n<p>(A) Copolymer : Buna-S</p>\n<p>(B) Condensation polymer : Nylon-6,6</p>\n<p>(C) Fibres : Nylon-6,6</p>\n<p>(D) Thermosetting polymer : Terylene</p>\n<p>(E) Homopolymer : Buna-N</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from given options below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A), (B) and (C) are correct",
      "(B), (C) and (D) are correct",
      "(A), (C) and (E) are correct",
      "(A), (B) and (D) are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "(A), (B) and (C) are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bdm9ky",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following is not an example of a condensation polymer?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Nylon 6,6",
      "Dacron",
      "Buna-N",
      "Silicone"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Buna-N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c6v0eg",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following is an example of polyester?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Butadiene-styrene copolymer",
      "Melamine polymer",
      "Neoprene",
      "Poly-$$\\beta$$-hydroxybutyrate-co-$$\\beta$$-hydroxyvalerate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Poly-$$\\beta$$-hydroxybutyrate-co-$$\\beta$$-hydroxyvalerate"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i5ne6q",
    "question": "<p>Vulcanization of rubber is carried out by heating a mixture of</p>",
    "options": [
      "isoprene and styrene",
      "neoprene and sulphur",
      "isoprene and sulphur",
      "neoprene and styrene"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "isoprene and sulphur"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jlzhn2",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I<br/><br/>Polymers</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II<br/><br/>Commercial names</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Phenol-formaldehyde resin</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Glyptal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Copolymer of 1,3-butadiene and sterene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Novolac</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Polyester of glycol and phthalic acid</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Buna-S</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Polyester of glycol and terephthalic acid</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Dacron</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-I, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kq9u25",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 445px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 53px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 156px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 40px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 196px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - I<br/>(Polymer)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - II<br/>(Monomer)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Neoprene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Acrylonitrile</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Teflon</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Chloroprene</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Acrilan</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Tetrafluoroethene</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Natural rubber</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Isoprene</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{III})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mdmsag",
    "question": "<p>Terylene polymer is obtained by condensation of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Ethane-1,2-diol and Benzene-1,3 dicarboxylic acid",
      "Propane-1, 2-diol and Benzene-1, 4 dicarboxylic acid",
      "Ethane-1,2-diol and Benzene-1, 4 dicarboxylic acid",
      "Ethane-1,2-diol and Benzene-1, 2 dicarboxylic acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Ethane-1,2-diol and Benzene-1, 4 dicarboxylic acid"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rky5ms",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following is NOT a natural polymer?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Protein",
      "Starch",
      "Rubber",
      "Rayon"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Rayon"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr3aqxm",
    "question": "<p>Caprolactam when heated at high temperature in presence of water, gives</p>",
    "options": [
      "Dacron",
      "Nylon 6",
      "Teflon",
      "Nylon 6,6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Nylon 6"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsdegdx",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 607px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 263px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Elastomeric polymer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Urea formaldehyde resin</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Fibre Polymer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Polystyrene</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Thermosetting Polymer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Polyester</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Thermoplastic Polymer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Neoprene</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgo03g3a",
    "question": "Match <b>List I</b> with <b>List II</b>:<br/><br/>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I - (Monomer)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II - (Polymer)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A) Tetrafluoroethene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I) Orlon</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B) Acrylonitrile</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II) Natural rubber</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C) Caprolactam</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III) Teflon</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D) Isoprene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV) Nylon-6</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(III), (C)-(IV), (D)-(I)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(II), (D)-(I) "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp278cc",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 689px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 62px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 58px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 320px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Weak intermolecular forces of attraction</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Hexamethylenediamine + adipic acid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Hydrogen bonding</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{AlEt_3+TiCl_4}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Heavily branched polymer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">2 - chloro - 1, 3 - butadiene</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">High density polymer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Phenol + formaldehyde</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-III, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq4dln7",
    "question": "<p>Match the following</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 554px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 159px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 295px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">Column A</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">Column B</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(a)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Nylon 6</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Natural Rubber</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(b)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Vulcanized Rubber</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Cross Linked</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(c)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">cis-1, 4-polyisoprene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Caprolactam</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(d)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Polychloroprene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Neoprene</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{a} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{III}, \\mathrm{b} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{II}, \\mathrm{c} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{I}, \\mathrm{d} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{IV}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{a} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{II}, \\mathrm{b} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{III}, \\mathrm{c} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{IV}, \\mathrm{d} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{I}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{a} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{IV}, \\mathrm{b} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{III}, \\mathrm{c} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{I}, \\mathrm{d} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{II}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{a} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{III}, \\mathrm{b} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{IV}, \\mathrm{c} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{I}, \\mathrm{d} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{II}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{a} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{III}, \\mathrm{b} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{II}, \\mathrm{c} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{I}, \\mathrm{d} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{IV}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrkw6du",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 616px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 246px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 270px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Examples)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Type)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">2-chloro-1,3- butadiene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Biodegradable polymer</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Nylon 2-nylon 6</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Synthetic Rubber</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Polyacrylonitrile</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Polyester</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Dacron</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Addition Polymer</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsyobzp",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Ethene at 333 to $$343 \\mathrm{~K}$$ and $$6$$-$$7$$ atm pressure in the presence of $$\\mathrm{AlEt}_{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{TiCl}_{4}$$ undergoes addition polymerization to give LDP.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Caprolactam at $$533$$-$$543 \\mathrm{~K}$$ in $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$ through step growth polymerizes to give Nylon 6.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguz063i",
    "question": "<p>The polymer $$\\mathrm{X}$$ - consists of linear molecules and is closely packed. It is prepared in the presence of triethylaluminium and titanium tetrachloride under low pressure. The polymer $$\\mathrm{X}$$ is-</p>",
    "options": [
      "High density polythene",
      "Polytetrafluoroethane",
      "Low density polythene",
      "Polyacrylonitrile"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "High density polythene"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyhdhmk",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 625px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 267px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List I<br/>Polymer</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List II<br/>Type/Class</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Nylon-2-Nylon-6</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Thermosetting polymer</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Buna-N</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Biodegradable polymer</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Urea-formaldehyde resin</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Synthetic rubber</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Dacron</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Polyester</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(III), (D)-(II)",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "classification,-preparations-and-properties-of-polymers",
    "solution": "(A)-(II), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(IV)"
  },
  {
    "id": "vhJVbf2rlZLlPeos",
    "question": "Polymer formation from monomers starts by",
    "options": [
      "condensation reaction between monomers",
      "coordinate reaction between monomers",
      "conversion of monomer to monomer ions by protons",
      "hydrolysis of monomers"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "uses-of-polymers",
    "solution": "condensation reaction between monomers"
  },
  {
    "id": "7vtBlxotvksJ3qLS",
    "question": "Nylon threads are made of",
    "options": [
      "polyester polymer",
      "polyamide polymer",
      "polyethylene polymer ",
      "polyvinyl polymer"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "uses-of-polymers",
    "solution": "polyamide polymer"
  },
  {
    "id": "vMVc3aRBBP4U9DRt",
    "question": "Which of the following is a polyamide? ",
    "options": [
      "Teflon",
      "Nylon – 6, 6",
      "Terylene",
      "Bakelite "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "uses-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Nylon – 6, 6"
  },
  {
    "id": "amiGoRZdojHHmnxp",
    "question": "Which polymer is used in the manufacture of paints and lacquers?",
    "options": [
      "Glyptal",
      "Polypropene",
      "Poly vinyl chloride",
      "Bakelite"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "uses-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Glyptal"
  },
  {
    "id": "l6bdUCEYmVkKcIs2",
    "question": "Which of the following statements about low density polythene is <b>FALSE</b> ?",
    "options": [
      "Its synthesis requires high pressure.",
      "It is a poor conductor of electricity.",
      "Its synthesis requires dioxygen or a peroxide initiator as a catalyst.",
      "It is used in the manufacture of buckets, dust-bins etc."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "uses-of-polymers",
    "solution": "It is used in the manufacture of buckets, dust-bins etc."
  },
  {
    "id": "P51W5qDE01xXE33Lf01kmitscfs",
    "question": "Which of the following polymer is used in the manufacture of wood laminates?",
    "options": [
      "Melamine formaldehyde resin",
      "Urea formaldehyde resin",
      "cis-poly isoprene",
      "Phenol and formaldehyde resin"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "uses-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Urea formaldehyde resin"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57si1mt",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 584px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 44px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 241px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 42px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 257px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - I <br/>(Polymer)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - II<br/>(Used in)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Bakelite</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Radio and television cabinets</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Glyptal</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Electrical switches</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">PVC</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Paints and Lacquers</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Polystyrene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Water pipes</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (III), (C) - (IV), (D) - (I)",
      "(A) - (I), (B) - (II), (C) - (III), (D) - (IV)",
      "(A) - (IV), (B) - (III), (C) - (II), (D) - (I)",
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (III), (C) - (I), (D) - (IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "uses-of-polymers",
    "solution": "(A) - (II), (B) - (III), (C) - (IV), (D) - (I)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f7cmkk",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Nylon 6, 6</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Buckets</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Low density polythene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Non-stick utensils</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">High density polythene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Bristles of brushes</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Teflon</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Toys</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "uses-of-polymers",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu0ix5b",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 669px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I (Name of polymer)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II (Uses)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Glyptal</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Flexible pipes</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Neoprene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Synthetic wool</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Acrilan</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Paints and Lacquers</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">LDP</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Gaskets</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II",
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "uses-of-polymers",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh27c4zz",
    "question": "<p>Polymer used in orlon is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Polyethene",
      "Polyacrylonitrile",
      "Polycarbonate",
      "Polyamide"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "polymers",
    "topic": "uses-of-polymers",
    "solution": "Polyacrylonitrile"
  },
  {
    "id": "vWJP5CEhPwDZ6pFu",
    "question": "The compound formed in the positive test for nitrogen with the Lassaigne solution of an\norganic compound is",
    "options": [
      "Fe<sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sub>3</sub> ",
      "Na<sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>5</sub>NOS] ",
      "Fe(CN)<sub>3</sub>",
      "Na<sub>3</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>] "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "Fe<sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sub>3</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "YDElZ5AcFtk5IWMd",
    "question": "29.5 mg of an organic compound containing nitrogen was digested according to Kjeldahl’s method\nand the evolved ammonia was absorbed in 20 mL of 0.1 M HCl solution. The excess of the acid\nrequired 15 mL of 0.1 M NaOH solution for complete neutralization. The percentage of nitrogen in\nthe compound is",
    "options": [
      "59.0",
      "47.4",
      "23.7",
      "29.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "23.7"
  },
  {
    "id": "4e0uOE2k00zUIZ3eVaKLW",
    "question": "The correct match between Item-I and Item-II is : \n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border:none;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:0px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:0px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-bzci{font-size:20px;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-p7ly{font-weight:bold;font-size:20px;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-fbrz{font-weight:bold;font-size:20px;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-4kyz{font-size:20px;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-p7ly\" colspan=\"2\">Item-I (drug)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-fbrz\" colspan=\"2\">Item-II (test)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">A</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">Chloroxylenol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-fbrz\">P</td>\n<td class=\"tg-bzci\">Carbylamine test</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">B</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">Norethindrone</td>\n<td class=\"tg-fbrz\">Q</td>\n<td class=\"tg-bzci\">Sodium hydrogen carbonet test</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">C</td>\n<td class=\"tg-4kyz\">Sulphapyridine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-fbrz\">R</td>\n<td class=\"tg-bzci\">Ferric chloride test</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-fbrz\">D</td>\n<td class=\"tg-bzci\">Penicillin</td>\n<td class=\"tg-fbrz\">S</td>\n<td class=\"tg-bzci\">Bayer's test</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "A&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;R;&nbsp;&nbsp;B&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;P;&nbsp;&nbsp;C&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;S;&nbsp;&nbsp;D&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;Q",
      "A&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;Q;&nbsp;&nbsp;B&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;S;&nbsp;&nbsp;C&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;P;&nbsp;&nbsp;D&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;R",
      "A&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;R;&nbsp;&nbsp;B&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;S;&nbsp;&nbsp;C&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;P;&nbsp;&nbsp;D&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;Q",
      "A&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;Q;&nbsp;&nbsp;B&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;P;&nbsp;&nbsp;C&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;S;&nbsp;&nbsp;D&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;R"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "A&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;R;&nbsp;&nbsp;B&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;S;&nbsp;&nbsp;C&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;P;&nbsp;&nbsp;D&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;Q"
  },
  {
    "id": "vbaXCPN3LsEMzZwTEp3rsa0w2w9jx4ziqff",
    "question": "An organic compound 'A' is oxidizod with Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> followed by boiling with HNO<sub>3</sub>. The resultant solution is\nthen treated with ammonium molybdate to yield a yellow precipitate. \n<br/>Based on above observation, the\nelement present in the given compound is:",
    "options": [
      "Fluorine",
      "Phosphorus",
      "Nitrogen",
      "Sulphur"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "Phosphorus"
  },
  {
    "id": "O8ENJyXKVDcOCmuJPqjgy2xukey8w164",
    "question": "If you spill a chemical toilet cleaning liquid on\nyour hand, your first aid would be",
    "options": [
      "aqueous NaOH",
      "aqueous NaHCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "aqueous NH<sub>3</sub>",
      "vinegar"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "aqueous NaHCO<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "eJAPTCE9w0uar3r1Yi1kltbrhig",
    "question": "Which of the following compound is added to the sodium extract before addition of silver nitrate for testing of halogens?",
    "options": [
      "Nitric acid",
      "Sodium hydroxide",
      "Ammonia",
      "Hydrochloric acid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "Nitric acid"
  },
  {
    "id": "jQeKAfN0dgQh2Avyxi1kluc9c0i",
    "question": "Which of the following is 'a' FALSE statement ?",
    "options": [
      "Carius method is used for the estimation of nitrogen in an organic compound.",
      "Kjeldahl's method is used for the estimation of nitrogen in an organic compound.",
      "Carius tube is used in the estimation of sulphur in an organic compound.",
      "Phosphoric acid produced on oxidation of phosphorus present in an organic compound is precipitated as Mg<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub> by adding magnesia mixture."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "Carius method is used for the estimation of nitrogen in an organic compound."
  },
  {
    "id": "oi6jDGS4mmZ38RLMZ61klusopw1",
    "question": "Seliwanoff test and Xanthoproteic test are used for the identification of ___________ and ________ respectively.",
    "options": [
      "ketoses, proteins",
      "proteins, ketoses",
      "aldoses, ketoses",
      "ketoses, aldoses"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "ketoses, proteins"
  },
  {
    "id": "6WdStJs5fRbJn8o16t1kmirt2bc",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II :<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I <br/>Test/Reagents/Observation(s)</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II <br/>Species detected</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Lassaigne's Test</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Carbon</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Cu(II) oxide</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Sulphur</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Silver nitrate</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>N, S, P, and halogen</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>The sodium fusion extract<br/> gives black precipitate with<br/> acetic acid and lead acetate</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Halogen Specifically</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>The correct match is :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iv), (c)-(iii), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktb3l6le",
    "question": "Which one of the following complexes is violet in colour?",
    "options": [
      "[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>4$$-$$</sup>",
      "[Fe(SCN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>4$$-$$</sup>",
      "Fe<sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN<sub>6</sub>)]<sub>3</sub> . H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "[Fe(CN)<sub>5</sub>NOS]<sup>4$$-$$</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "[Fe(CN)<sub>5</sub>NOS]<sup>4$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktebydcv",
    "question": "Acidic ferric chloride solution on treatment with excess of potassium ferrocyanide gives a Prussian blue coloured colloidal species. It is :",
    "options": [
      "Fe<sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sub>3</sub>",
      "K<sub>5</sub>Fe[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sub>2</sub>",
      "HFe[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]",
      "KFe[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "Fe<sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbm5rqa",
    "question": "In Kjeldahl's method for estimation of nitrogen, $\\mathrm{CuSO}_4$ acts as :",
    "options": [
      "catalytic agent",
      "hydrolysis agent",
      "reducing agent",
      "oxidising agent"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "catalytic agent"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscqgzqj",
    "question": "<p>The technique used for purification of steam volatile water immiscible substances is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Fractional distillation\n",
      "Distillation\n",
      "Fractional distillation under reduced pressure\n",
      "Steam distillation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "Steam distillation"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd9lkhd",
    "question": "<p>The fragrance of flowers is due to the presence of some steam volatile organic compounds called essential oils. These are generally insoluble in water at room temperature but are miscible with water vapour in vapour phase. A suitable method for the extraction of these oils from the flowers is -</p>",
    "options": [
      "distillation\n",
      "steam distillation\n",
      "distillation under reduced pressure\n",
      "crystallisation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "steam distillation\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxzq9e3",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 572px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 160px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 262px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Test)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Observation)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Br_2}$$ water test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Yellow orange or orange red precipitate formed</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ceric ammonium nitrate test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Reddish orange colour disappears</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ferric chloride test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Red colour appears</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">2, 4 - DNP test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Blue, Green, Violet or Red colour appear</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I\n",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV\n",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57nu2",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following statements are correct?</p>\n<p>A. Glycerol is purified by vacuum distillation because it decomposes at its normal boiling point.</p>\n<p>B. Aniline can be purified by steam distillation as aniline is miscible in water.</p>\n<p>C. Ethanol can be separated from ethanol water mixture by azeotropic distillation because it forms azeotrope.</p>\n<p>D. An organic compound is pure, if mixed M.P. is remained same.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, C, D only\n",
      "B, C, D only\n",
      "A, B, D only\n",
      "A, B, C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-the-preparation-of-organic-and-inorganic-compounds",
    "solution": "A, C, D only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "xTN9Z6PmV9viFCY4Vf974",
    "question": "For standardizing NaOH solution, which of the following is used as a primary standard ? ",
    "options": [
      "Ferrous Ammonium Sulfate",
      "dil. HCl",
      "Oxalic acid ",
      "Sodium tetraborate "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-titrimetric-experiments",
    "solution": "Oxalic acid "
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f7i5x6",
    "question": "<p>In base vs. acid titration, at the end point methyl orange is present as</p>",
    "options": [
      "quinonoid form",
      "heterocyclic form",
      "phenolic form",
      "benzenoid form"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-titrimetric-experiments",
    "solution": "quinonoid form"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyh4w33",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Aqueous solution of K$$_2$$Cr$$_2$$O$$_7$$ is preferred as a primary standard in volumetric analysis over Na$$_2$$Cr$$_2$$O$$_7$$ aqueous solution.</p>\n<p>Statement II : K$$_2$$Cr$$_2$$O$$_7$$ has a higher solubility in water than Na$$_2$$Cr$$_2$$O$$_7$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-titrimetric-experiments",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgysk2xy",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Methyl orange is a weak acid.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The benzenoid form of methyl orange is more intense/deeply coloured than the quinonoid form.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statement, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement $$\\mathrm{I}$$ is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Both statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-titrimetric-experiments",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbm7sp8",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (I)</b> : Potassium hydrogen phthalate is a primary standard for standardisation of sodium hydroxide solution.\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement (II)</b> : In this titration phenolphthalein can be used as indicator.<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the <b>most appropriate</b> answer from the options given below :\n",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-titrimetric-experiments",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2uzox",
    "question": "<p>Identify the incorrect statements regarding primary standard of titrimetric analysis.</p>\n<p>(A) It should be purely available in dry form.</p>\n<p>(B) It should not undergo chemical change in air.</p>\n<p>(C) It should be hygroscopic and should react with another chemical instantaneously and stoichiometrically.</p>\n<p>(D) It should be readily soluble in water.</p>\n<p>(E) $$\\mathrm{KMnO}_4$$ &amp; $$\\mathrm{NaOH}$$ can be used as primary standard.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(C) and (E) only",
      "(A) and (B) only",
      "(B) and (E) only",
      "(C) and (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "chemistry-involved-in-titrimetric-experiments",
    "solution": "(C) and (E) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "RoaWGv7xoIOnOfUP",
    "question": "Which of the following reagents may be used to distinguish between phenol and benzoic acid ?",
    "options": [
      "Tollen’s reagent",
      "Molisch reagent",
      "Neutral FeCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "Aqueous NaOH "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "Neutral FeCl<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "5SZYObrM7c9kpKCGNPq1U",
    "question": "Sodium extract is heated with concentrated HNO<sub>3</sub> before testing for halogens because :\n",
    "options": [
      "Silver halides are totally insoluble in nitric acid.",
      "Ag<sub>2</sub>S and AgCN are soluble in acidic medium.",
      "S<sub>2</sub><sup>−</sup> and CN<sup>−</sup>, if present, are\ndecomposed by conc. HNO<sub>3</sub> and hence do not interfere in the test.\n",
      "Ag reacts faster with halides in acidic medium."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "S<sub>2</sub><sup>−</sup> and CN<sup>−</sup>, if present, are\ndecomposed by conc. HNO<sub>3</sub> and hence do not interfere in the test.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "zt1pSlBdnxcZnZhd8f84m",
    "question": "The correct match between item 'I' and item 'II' is : \n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-wrg0{font-size:22px;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-wv9z{font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-de48{font-weight:bold;font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-ujoh{font-weight:bold;font-size:22px;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-de48\" colspan=\"2\">Item 'I' (compound)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-ujoh\" colspan=\"2\">Item 'II' <br/>(reagent)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Lysine</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(P)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">1-naphthol</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Furfural</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(Q)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">ninhydrin</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">Benzylalcohol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(R)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">KMnO<sub>4</sub></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">Styrene</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">(S)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">Ceric ammonium<br/> nitrate</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "(A)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(Q);&nbsp;&nbsp;(B)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(R);&nbsp;&nbsp;(C)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(S);&nbsp;&nbsp;\n(D)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(P)",
      "(A)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(Q);&nbsp;&nbsp;(B)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(P);&nbsp;&nbsp;(C)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(S);&nbsp;&nbsp;\n(D)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(R)",
      "(A)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(R);&nbsp;&nbsp;(B)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(P);&nbsp;&nbsp;(C)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(Q);&nbsp;&nbsp;\n(D)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(S)",
      "(A)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(Q);&nbsp;&nbsp;(B)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(P);&nbsp;&nbsp;(C)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(R);&nbsp;&nbsp;\n(D)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(S)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "(A)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(Q);&nbsp;&nbsp;(B)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(P);&nbsp;&nbsp;(C)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(S);&nbsp;&nbsp;\n(D)&nbsp;&nbsp;$$ \\to $$&nbsp;&nbsp;(R)"
  },
  {
    "id": "8KDcveGMs0DDHM85kg7k9k2k5llhweq",
    "question": "A, B and C are three biomolecules. The results\nof the tests performed on them are given\nbelow:<br/><br/>\n$$\n\\begin{array}{|l|l|l|l|}\n\\hline &amp; \\begin{array}{l}\n\\text { Molisch's } \\\\\n\\text { Test }\n\\end{array} &amp; \\begin{array}{l}\n\\text { Barfoed } \\\\\n\\text { Test }\n\\end{array} &amp; \\begin{array}{l}\n\\text { Biuret } \\\\\n\\text { Test }\n\\end{array} \\\\\n\\hline \\text { A } &amp; \\text { Positive } &amp; \\text { Negative } &amp; \\text { Negative } \\\\\n\\hline \\text { B } &amp; \\text { Positive } &amp; \\text { Positive } &amp; \\text { Negative } \\\\\n\\hline \\text { C } &amp; \\text { Negative } &amp; \\text { Negative } &amp; \\text { Positive } \\\\\n\\hline\n\\end{array}\n$$\n<br/><br/>\nA, B and C are respectively :",
    "options": [
      "A = Lactose, B = Glucose, C = Albumin",
      "A = Lactose, B = Fructose, C = Alanine",
      "A = Lactose, B = Glucose, C = Alanine",
      "A = Glucose, B = Fructose, C = Albumin"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "A = Lactose, B = Glucose, C = Albumin"
  },
  {
    "id": "Vs7hwvcmskHCHu42F9jgy2xukg4m6vst",
    "question": "Match the following :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\"><b>Test/Method</b></th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\"><b>Reagent</b></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(i) Lucas Test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(a) C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>SO<sub>2</sub>Cl/\naq. KOH</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(ii) Dumas method</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(b) HNO<sub>3</sub>/\nAgNO<sub>3</sub></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(iii) Kjeldahl’s method</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(c) CuO/CO<sub>2</sub></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(iv) Hinsberg test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(d) Conc. HCl\nand ZnCl<sub>2</sub></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td 11<=\"\" class=\"tg-baqh\" td=\"\">\n</td><td class=\"tg-baqh\">(e) H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub></td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "(i)-(b), (ii)-(d), (iii)-(e), (iv)-(a)",
      "(i)-(d), (ii)-(c), (iii)-(e), (iv)-(a)",
      "(i)-(b), (ii)-(a), (iii)-(c), (iv)-(d)",
      "(i)-(d), (ii)-(c), (iii)-(b), (iv)-(e)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "(i)-(d), (ii)-(c), (iii)-(e), (iv)-(a)"
  },
  {
    "id": "u5GKPkAaQknjdjCcLb1kmlmfej6",
    "question": "Reagent, 1-napthylamine and sulphanilic acid in acetic acid is used for the detection of ",
    "options": [
      "N<sub>2</sub>O",
      "NO$$_3^ - $$",
      "NO",
      "NO$$_2^ - $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "NO$$_2^ - $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krrj9hoe",
    "question": "In Carius method, halogen containing organic compound is heated with fuming nitric acid in the presence of :",
    "options": [
      "HNO<sub>3</sub>",
      "AgNO<sub>3</sub>",
      "CuSO<sub>4</sub>",
      "BaSO<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "AgNO<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfskbwi",
    "question": "Which one of the following tests used for the identification of functional groups in organic compounds does not use copper reagent?",
    "options": [
      "Barfoed's test",
      "Seliwanoff's test",
      "Benedict's test",
      "Biuret test for peptide bond"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "Seliwanoff's test"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56bamt0",
    "question": "<p>The formula of the purple colour formed in Laissaigne's test for sulphur using sodium nitroprusside is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "NaFe[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]",
      "Na[Cr(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(NCS)<sub>4</sub>]",
      "Na<sub>2</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>5</sub>(NO)]",
      "Na<sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>5</sub>(NOS)]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "Na<sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>5</sub>(NOS)]"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58e0ehp",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : In 'Lassaigne's Test', when both nitrogen and sulphur are present in an organic compound, sodium thiocyanate is formed.</p>\n<p>Statement II : If both nitrogen and sulphur are present in an organic compound, then the excess of sodium used in sodium fusion will decompose the sodium thiocyanate formed to give NaCN and Na<sub>2</sub>S.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w6gv56",
    "question": "<p>The reagent neutral ferric chloride is used to detect the presence of ______________</p>",
    "options": [
      "sulphide ion and alcoholic $$-$$OH group.",
      "acetate ion and phenolic $$-$$OH group.",
      "sulphide ion and phenolic $$-$$OH group.",
      "acetate ion and alcoholic $$-$$OH group."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "acetate ion and phenolic $$-$$OH group."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldo20ob0",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Sulphanilic acid gives esterification test for carboxyl group.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Sulphanilic acid gives red colour in Lassigne's test for extra element detection.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo9h8z1",
    "question": "In Dumas method for the estimation of $\\mathrm{N}_{2}$, the sample is heated with copper oxide and the gas evolved is passed over :",
    "options": [
      "Copper oxide",
      "Copper gauze",
      "$\\mathrm{Pd}$",
      "$\\mathrm{Ni}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "Copper gauze"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsqs6x7",
    "question": "<p>Compound that will give positive Lassaigne's test for both nitrogen and halogen is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{NH_2OH.HCl}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{N_2H_4.HCl}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{CH_3NH_2.HCl}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{NH_4Cl}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{CH_3NH_2.HCl}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguzm6th",
    "question": "<p>When a solution of mixture having two inorganic salts was treated with freshly prepared ferrous sulphate in acidic medium, a dark brown ring was formed whereas on treatment with neutral $$\\mathrm{FeCl}_{3}$$, it gave deep red colour which disppeared on boiling and a brown red ppt was formed. The mixture contains :</p>",
    "options": [
      "SO$$_3^{2-}$$ & C$$_2$$O$$_4^{2-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{CH}_{3} \\mathrm{COO}^{-} \\& ~\\mathrm{NO}_{3}^{-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}{ }^{2-} \\& ~\\mathrm{NO}_{3}^{-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{SO}_{3}^{2-} \\& ~\\mathrm{CH}_{3} \\mathrm{COO}^{-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{CH}_{3} \\mathrm{COO}^{-} \\& ~\\mathrm{NO}_{3}^{-}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvuy2lf",
    "question": "<p>In Carius tube, an organic compound '$$\\mathrm{X}$$' is treated with sodium peroxide to form a mineral acid 'Y'.</p>\n<p>The solution of $$\\mathrm{BaCl}_{2}$$ is added to '$$\\mathrm{Y}$$' to form a precipitate 'Z'. 'Z' is used for the quantitative estimation of an extra element. '$$\\mathrm{X}$$' could be</p>",
    "options": [
      "Cytosine",
      "Methionine",
      "Chloroxylenol",
      "A nucleotide"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "Methionine"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyrwlgc",
    "question": "<p>A compound '$$\\mathrm{X}$$' when treated with phthalic anhydride in presence of concentrated $$\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$$ yields '$$\\mathrm{Y}$$'. '$$\\mathrm{Y}$$' is used as an acid/base indicator. '$$\\mathrm{X}$$' and '$$\\mathrm{Y}$$' are respectively</p>",
    "options": [
      "Toludine, Phenolphthalein",
      "Carbolic acid, Phenolphthalein",
      "Salicylaldehyde, Phenolphthalein",
      "Anisole, methyl orange"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "Carbolic acid, Phenolphthalein"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh29g8bx",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 616px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 258px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I <br/>Element detected</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II <br/>Reagent used / Product formed<br/></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Nitrogen</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Na_2[Fe(CN)_5NO]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Sulphur</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{AgNO_3}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Phosphorous</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Fe_4[Fe(CN)_6]_3}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Halogen</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{(NH_4)_2MoO_4}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-I, D-III",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh31sl33",
    "question": "<p>Formation of which complex, among the following, is not a confirmatory test of $$\\mathrm{Pb}^{2+}$$ ions :</p>",
    "options": [
      "lead chromate",
      "lead iodide",
      " lead sulphate",
      "lead nitrate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "lead nitrate"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3xmb2m",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 664px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 262px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Test)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Identification)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Bayer's test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Phenol</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ceric ammonium nitrate test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Aldehyde</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Phthalein dye test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Alcoholic-OH group</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Schiff's test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Unsaturation</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(III), (C)-(IV), (D)-(I)\n",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "detection-of-extra-elements-and-functional-groups",
    "solution": "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfmvcwt",
    "question": "<p>Chromatographic technique/s based on the principle of differential adsorption is / are</p>\n<p>A. Column chromatography</p>\n<p>B. Thin layer chromatography</p>\n<p>C. Paper chromatography</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "B only",
      "A only",
      "A & B only",
      "C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "experiments-involving-physical-chemistry",
    "solution": "A & B only"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29ww2",
    "question": "<p>The correct statement among the following, for a \"chromatography\" purification method is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{R}_f$$ of a polar compound is smaller than that of a non-polar compound.\n",
      "Non-polar compounds are retained at top and polar compounds come down in column chromatography.\n",
      "Organic compounds run faster than solvent in the thin layer chromatographic plate.\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{R}_f$$ is an integral value."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "experiments-involving-physical-chemistry",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{R}_f$$ of a polar compound is smaller than that of a non-polar compound.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "C3RKGJ2L0noPtzFd66Pjd",
    "question": "A solution containing a group-IV cation gives a precipitate on passing H<sub>2</sub>S. A solution of this precipitate in dil.HCl produces a white precipitate with NaOH solution and bluish-white precipitate with basic potassium ferrocyanide. The cation is :\n ",
    "options": [
      "Co<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Ni<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Mn<sup>2+</sup> ",
      "Zn<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "Zn<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "EyL2l4rWDa200xcC",
    "question": "Sodium salt of an organic acid ‘X’ produces effervescence with conc. H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. ‘X’ reacts with the acidified\naqueous CaCl<sub>2</sub> solution to give a white precipitate which decolourises acidic solution of KMnO<sub>4</sub>. ‘X’ is :",
    "options": [
      "CH<sub>3</sub>COONa",
      "Na<sub>2</sub>C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>COONa",
      "HCOONa"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "Na<sub>2</sub>C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Mj4iu7R0msrjkrddr57k9k2k5dyy2ep",
    "question": "A solution of m-chloronailimne, m-chlorophenol and m-chlorobenzoic acid in ethyal acetate was extracted initially with a saturated solution of NaHCO<sub>3</sub>\n to give fraction A. The left over organic phase\nwas extracted with dilute NaoH solution tio give fraction B. The final organiic layer was labelled as\nfraction C. Fractions A,B and C, contain respectively :",
    "options": [
      "m-chlorobenzoic acid, m-chloroaniline and m-chlorophenol.",
      "m-chlorobenzoic acid, m-chlorophenol and m-chloroaniline.",
      "m-chlorophenol, m-chlorobenzoic acid and m-chloronailine.",
      "m-chloroaniline m-chlorobenzoic acid and m-chlorophenol."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "m-chlorobenzoic acid, m-chlorophenol and m-chloroaniline."
  },
  {
    "id": "J5V2MxZKBw3M7JtYg81kltbjh7x",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : The identification of Ni<sup>2+</sup> is carried out by dimethyl glyoxime in the presence of NH<sub>4</sub>OH. <br/><br/>Statement II : The dimethyl glyoxime is a bidentate neutral ligand.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq5ta5x",
    "question": "An inorganic Compound 'X' on treatment with concentrated H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> produces brown fumes and gives dark brown ring with FeSO<sub>4</sub> in presence of concentrated H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. Also Compound 'X' gives precipitate 'Y', when its solution in dilute HCl is treated with H<sub>2</sub>S gas. The precipitate 'Y' on treatment with concentrated HNO<sub>3</sub> followed by excess of NH<sub>4</sub>OH further gives deep blue coloured solution, Compound 'X' is :",
    "options": [
      "Co(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Pb(NO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Cu(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Pb(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "Cu(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krrj1xj7",
    "question": "Cu<sup>2+</sup> salt reacts with potassium iodide to give",
    "options": [
      "Cu<sub>2</sub>I<sub>2</sub>",
      "Cu<sub>2</sub>I<sub>3</sub>",
      "Cul",
      "Cu(I<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "Cu<sub>2</sub>I<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt4otqi",
    "question": "When silver nitrate solution is added to potassium iodide solution then the sol produced is :",
    "options": [
      "AgI / I<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "AgI / Ag<sup>+</sup>",
      "KI / NO$$_3^ - $$",
      "AgNO<sub>3</sub> / NO$$_3^ - $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "AgI / I<sup>$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1hv0hx",
    "question": "To an aqueous solution containing ions such as Al<sup>3+</sup>, Zn<sup>2+</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Fe<sup>3+</sup>, Ni<sup>2+</sup>, Ba<sup>2+</sup> and Cu<sup>2+</sup> was added conc. HCl, followed by H<sub>2</sub>S.<br/><br/>The total number of cations precipitated during this reaction is/are :",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "3",
      "4",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54yynco",
    "question": "<p>A white precipitate was formed when BaCl<sub>2</sub> was added to water extract of an inorganic salt. Further, a gas 'X' with characteristic odour was released when the formed white precipitate was dissolved in dilute HCl. The anion present in the inorganic salt is</p>",
    "options": [
      "I<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "SO<sub>3</sub><sup>2$$-$$</sup>",
      "S<sup>2$$-$$</sup>",
      "NO<sub>2</sub><sup>$$-$$</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "SO<sub>3</sub><sup>2$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59r7vgr",
    "question": "<p>During halogen test, sodium fusion extract is boiled with concentrated HNO<sub>3</sub> to</p>",
    "options": [
      "remove unreacted sodium",
      "decompose cyanide or sulphide of sodium",
      "extract halogen from organic compound",
      "maintain the pH of extract."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "decompose cyanide or sulphide of sodium"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bdobmi",
    "question": "<p>In the flame test of a mixture of salts, a green flame with blue centre was observed. Which one of the following cations may be present?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Cu<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Sr<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Ba<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Ca<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "Cu<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c6zbel",
    "question": "<p>During the qualitative analysis of salt with cation y<sup>2+</sup>, addition of a reagent (X) to alkaline solution of the salt gives a bright red precipitate. The reagent (X) and the cation (y<sup>2+</sup>) present respectively are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Dimethylglyoxime and Ni<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Dimethylglyoxime and Co<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Nessler's reagent and Hg<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Nessler's reagent and Ni<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "Dimethylglyoxime and Ni<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr3f16z",
    "question": "<p>In the wet tests for identification of various cations by precipitation, which transition element cation doesn't belong to group IV in qualitative inorganic analysis?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Co<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Ni<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Zn<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Fe<sup>3+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "Fe<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldukk58a",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 668px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 248px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I<br/>Elements</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II<br/>Colour imparted to the flame</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">K</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Brick Red</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ca</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Violet</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Sr</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Apple Green</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ba</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Crimson Red</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-II, B-I, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldul7hx4",
    "question": "<p>Match the List-I with List-II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 668px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 248px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List-I<br/>Cations</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List-II<br/>Group reagents</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Pb^{2+},Cu^{2+}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">i)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{H_2S}$$ gas in presence of dilute HCl</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Al^{3+},Fe^{3+}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">ii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{(NH_4)_2CO_3}$$ in presence of $$\\mathrm{NH_4OH}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Co^{2+},Ni^{2+}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">iii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{NH_4OH}$$ in presence of $$\\mathrm{NH_4Cl}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Ba^{2+},Ca^{2+}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">iv)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">H<sub>2</sub>S in presence of NH<sub>4</sub>OH</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Correct match is -</p>",
    "options": [
      "A $$\\to$$ i, B $$\\to$$ iii, C $$\\to$$ iv, D $$\\to$$ ii",
      "A $$\\to$$ i, B $$\\to$$ iii, C $$\\to$$ ii, D $$\\to$$ iv",
      "A $$\\to$$ iii, B $$\\to$$ i, C $$\\to$$ iv, D $$\\to$$ ii",
      "A $$\\to$$ iv, B $$\\to$$ ii, C $$\\to$$ iii, D $$\\to$$ i"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "A $$\\to$$ i, B $$\\to$$ iii, C $$\\to$$ iv, D $$\\to$$ ii"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp2d0he",
    "question": "<p>In the wet tests for detection of various cations by precipitation, $$\\mathrm{Ba}^{2+}$$ cations are detected by obtaining precipitate of</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{BaSO}_{4}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ba}(\\mathrm{OAc})_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{BaCO}_{3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ba}(\\mathrm{ox})$$ : Barium oxalate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{BaCO}_{3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjhjvg",
    "question": "<p>In chromyl chloride test for confirmation of $$\\mathrm{Cl}^{-}$$ ion, a yellow solution is obtained. Acidification of the solution and addition of amyl alcohol and $$10 \\% \\mathrm{~H}_2 \\mathrm{O}_2$$ turns organic layer blue indicating formation of chromium pentoxide. The oxidation state of chromium in that is</p>",
    "options": [
      "+6",
      "+5",
      "+3",
      "+10"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "+6"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjwynb",
    "question": "<p>Appearance of blood red colour, on treatment of the sodium fusion extract of an organic compound with $$\\mathrm{FeSO}_4$$ in presence of concentrated $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{SO}_4$$ indicates the presence of element/s</p>",
    "options": [
      "Br",
      "S",
      "N and S",
      "N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "N and S"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vycfc",
    "question": "<p>In the precipitation of the iron group (III) in qualitative analysis, ammonium chloride is added before adding ammonium hydroxide to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "decrease concentration of $${ }^{-} \\mathrm{OH}$$ ions\n",
      "increase concentration of $$\\mathrm{Cl}^{-}$$ ions\n",
      "prevent interference by phosphate ions\n",
      "increase concentration of $$\\mathrm{NH}_4{ }^{+}$$ ions"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "decrease concentration of $${ }^{-} \\mathrm{OH}$$ ions\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gt1uq",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 776px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 374px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Name of the test)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Reaction sequence involved) [M is metal]</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Borax bead test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{MCO}_3 \\rightarrow \\mathrm{MO} \\xrightarrow[+\\Delta]{\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NO}_3\\right)_2} \\mathrm{CoO} \\cdot \\mathrm{MO}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Charcoal cavity test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{MCO}_3 \\rightarrow \\mathrm{MCl}_2 \\rightarrow \\mathrm{M}^{2+}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Cobalt nitrate test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{MSO}_4 \\xrightarrow[\\Delta]{\\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{~B}_4 \\mathrm{O}_7} \\mathrm{M}\\left(\\mathrm{BO}_2\\right)_2 \\rightarrow \\mathrm{MBO}_2 \\rightarrow \\mathrm{M}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Flame test</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{MSO}_4 \\xrightarrow[\\Delta]{\\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{CO}_3} \\mathrm{MCO}_3 \\rightarrow \\mathrm{MO} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{M}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II\n",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I\n",
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29j92",
    "question": "<p>During the detection of acidic radical present in a salt, a student gets a pale yellow precipitate soluble with difficulty in $$\\mathrm{NH}_4 \\mathrm{OH}$$ solution when sodium carbonate extract was first acidified with dil. $$\\mathrm{HNO}_3$$ and then $$\\mathrm{AgNO}_3$$ solution was added. This indicates presence of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{I}^{-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CO}_3{ }^{2-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Cl}^{-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{Br}^{-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Br}^{-}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc583co",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 690px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 239px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>(Precipitating reagent and conditions)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>(Cation)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{NH}_4 \\mathrm{Cl}+\\mathrm{NH}_4 \\mathrm{OH}<br/>$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Mn^{2+}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{NH}_4 \\mathrm{OH}+\\mathrm{Na}_2 \\mathrm{CO}_3<br/>$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Pb^{2+}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{NH}_4 \\mathrm{OH}+\\mathrm{NH}_4 \\mathrm{Cl}+\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{~S} \\text { gas }<br/>$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Al^{3+}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">dilute $$\\mathrm{HCl}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{Sr^{2+}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I\n",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I\n",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "practical-organic-chemistry",
    "topic": "qualitative-salt-analysis",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ee9Rx5oIInUG5CDx",
    "question": "Consider the following reaction:<br/><br/>\n$$xMnO_4^- + yC_2O_4^{2-}$$ + zH<sup>+</sup> $$\\to$$ xMn<sup>2+</sup> + 2yCO<sub>2</sub> + $${z \\over 2}{H_2}O$$<br/><br/>\nThe value's of x, y and z in the reaction are, respectively :",
    "options": [
      "5, 2 and 16",
      "2, 5 and 8",
      "2, 5 and 16",
      "5, 2 and 8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "balancing-of-redox-reactions",
    "solution": "2, 5 and 16"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh031a7t",
    "question": "<p>$$2 \\mathrm{IO}_{3}^{-}+x \\mathrm{I}^{-}+12 \\mathrm{H}^{+} \\rightarrow 6 \\mathrm{I}_{2}+6 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$</p>\n<p>What is the value of $$x$$ ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "10",
      "2",
      "12",
      "6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "balancing-of-redox-reactions",
    "solution": "10"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbmpghu",
    "question": "In acidic medium, $\\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7$ shows oxidising action as represented in the half reaction:<br/><br/>\n$$\n\\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_7{ }^{2-}+\\mathrm{XH}^{+}+\\mathrm{Ye}^{\\ominus} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{~A}+\\mathrm{ZH}_2 \\mathrm{O}\n$$<br/><br/>\n$\\mathrm{X}, \\mathrm{Y}, \\mathrm{Z}$ and $\\mathrm{A}$ are respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "$14,7,6$ and $\\mathrm{Cr}^{3+}$",
      "$14,6,7$ and $\\mathrm{Cr}^{3+}$",
      "$8,4,6$ and $\\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_3$",
      "$8,6,4$ and $\\mathrm{Cr}_2 \\mathrm{O}_3$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "balancing-of-redox-reactions",
    "solution": "$14,6,7$ and $\\mathrm{Cr}^{3+}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjgqcy",
    "question": "<p>Chlorine undergoes disproportionation in alkaline medium as shown below :</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{aCl}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}+\\mathrm{b} \\mathrm{OH}_{(\\mathrm{aq})}^{-} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{c} \\mathrm{ClO}_{(\\mathrm{aq)}}^{-}+\\mathrm{d} \\mathrm{Cl}_{(\\mathrm{aq})}^{-}+\\mathrm{e} \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}_{(\\mathrm{l})}$$</p>\n<p>The values of $$a, b, c$$ and $$d$$ in a balanced redox reaction are respectively :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3, 4, 4 and 2",
      "1, 2, 1 and 1",
      "2, 4, 1 and 3",
      "2, 2, 1 and 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "balancing-of-redox-reactions",
    "solution": "1, 2, 1 and 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "xhb2zKJH6wZKhIy422O3J",
    "question": "The volume of 0.1N dibasic acid sufficient to neutralize 1 g of a base that furnishes 0.04 mole of OH<sup>−</sup> in aqueous solution is :",
    "options": [
      "200 mL ",
      "400 mL",
      "600 mL",
      "800 mL"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "equivalence",
    "solution": "400 mL"
  },
  {
    "id": "NEBjQdkhzIAtJZVzgZxw9",
    "question": "The hardness of a water sample (in terms of equivalents of CaCO<sub>3</sub>) containing 10<sup>–3</sup> M CaSO<sub>4</sub> is (Molar mass of CaSO<sub>4</sub> = 136 g mol<sup>–1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "90 ppm",
      "100 ppm",
      "50 ppm",
      "10 ppm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "equivalence",
    "solution": "100 ppm"
  },
  {
    "id": "KAjBwzLqopJziWrx0DCek",
    "question": "In order to oxidise a mixture of one mole of each of FeC<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, Fe<sub>2</sub>(C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>, FeSO<sub>4</sub> and Fe<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub> in\nacidic medium, the number of moles of KMnO<sub>4</sub> required is :",
    "options": [
      "1.5",
      "3",
      "2",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "equivalence",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "bUz5bDaiqt75drYS",
    "question": "Which of the following is a redox reaction ?",
    "options": [
      "NaCl + KNO<sub>3</sub> $$\\to$$ NaNO<sub>3</sub> + KCl",
      "CaC<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> + 2HCl $$\\to$$ CaCl<sub>2</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>",
      "Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> + 2NH<sub>4</sub>Cl $$\\to$$ MgCl<sub>2</sub> + 2NH<sub>4</sub>OH",
      "Zn + 2AgCN  $$\\to$$ 2Ag+ Zn(CN)<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "Zn + 2AgCN  $$\\to$$ 2Ag+ Zn(CN)<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "vmryv46T98UL1Lk5",
    "question": "Which of the following chemical reactions depicts the oxidizing behaviour of H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>?",
    "options": [
      "NaCl + H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> $$\\to$$ NaHSO<sub>4</sub> + HCl",
      "2PCl<sub>5</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> $$\\to$$ 2POCl<sub>3</sub> + 2HCl + SO<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "2HI + H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> $$\\to$$ I<sub>2</sub> + SO<sub>2</sub> + 2H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> $$\\to$$ CaSO<sub>4</sub> + 2H<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "2HI + H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> $$\\to$$ I<sub>2</sub> + SO<sub>2</sub> + 2H<sub>2</sub>O"
  },
  {
    "id": "6gt8nqdfhZsoiXTH",
    "question": "In which of the following reactions H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> acts as a reducing agent?\n<br/>1. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> + 2H<sup>+</sup> + 2e<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$ 2H<sub>2</sub>O\n<br/>2. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> - 2e<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$ O<sub>2</sub> + 2H<sup>+</sup>\n<br/>3. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> + 2e<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$ 2OH<sup>-</sup>\n<br/>4. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> + 2OH<sup>-</sup> - 2e<sup>-</sup> $$\\to$$ O<sub>2</sub> +  2H<sub>2</sub>O",
    "options": [
      "1, 2",
      "3, 4",
      "1, 3",
      "2, 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "2, 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "AZIQSjpVsC1nOZTE",
    "question": "Which of the following reactions is an example of a redox reaction?",
    "options": [
      "$$Xe{F_6}$$ + H<sub>2</sub>O $$\\to$$ $$XeO{F_4}$$ + 2HF",
      "$$Xe{F_6}$$ + 2H<sub>2</sub>O $$\\to$$ $$XeO_2{F_2}$$ + 4HF",
      "$$Xe{F_4}$$ + O<sub>2</sub>F<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ $$Xe{F_6}$$ + O<sub>2</sub> ",
      "$$Xe{F_2}$$ + PF<sub>5</sub> $$\\to$$ $${\\left[ {XeF} \\right]^ + }PF_6^ - $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "$$Xe{F_4}$$ + O<sub>2</sub>F<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ $$Xe{F_6}$$ + O<sub>2</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "dJsK1dnG9eeuqU6h6B1v3",
    "question": "In the reaction of oxalate with permanganate in acidic medium, the number of electrons involved in producing one molecule of CO<sub>2</sub> is : ",
    "options": [
      "10",
      "2",
      "1",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "uOActAkQoaumecjQJo7k9k2k5epwqeu",
    "question": "The redox reaction among the following is :",
    "options": [
      "reaction of H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> with NaOH.",
      "formation of ozone form atmosphere oxygen in the presence of sunlight.",
      "combination of dinitrogen with dioxygen at 2000 K",
      "reaction of [Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>]Cl<sub>3</sub> With AgNO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "combination of dinitrogen with dioxygen at 2000 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "91lPBnmet4BGfbFKjY1kmiunroc",
    "question": "Statement I : Sodium hydride can be used as an oxidising agent.<br/><br/>Statement II : The lone pair of electrons on nitrogen in pyridine makes it basic.<br/><br/>Choose the CORRECT answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscrqpvw",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following cannot function as an oxidising agent?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{SO}_4^{2-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{MnO}_4^{-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{N}^{3-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{BrO}_3^{-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{N}^{3-}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjzybv",
    "question": "<p>In alkaline medium, $$\\mathrm{MnO}_4^{-}$$ oxidises $$\\mathrm{I}^{-}$$ to </p>",
    "options": [
      "$$I_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{IO}_3^{-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{IO}^{-}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{IO}_4^{-}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{IO}_3^{-}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2ers4s",
    "question": "<p>When $$\\mathrm{MnO}_2$$ and $$\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{SO}_4$$ is added to a salt $$(\\mathrm{A})$$, the greenish yellow gas liberated as salt (A) is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{NH}_4 \\mathrm{Cl}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CaI}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{KNO}_3$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{NaBr}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{NH}_4 \\mathrm{Cl}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gt1sb",
    "question": "<p>Thiosulphate reacts differently with iodine and bromine in the reactions given below:</p>\n<p>$$\\begin{aligned}\n&amp; 2 \\mathrm{~S}_2 \\mathrm{O}_3^{2-}+\\mathrm{I}_2 \\rightarrow \\mathrm{S}_4 \\mathrm{O}_6^{2-}+2 \\mathrm{I}^{-} \\\\\n&amp; \\mathrm{S}_2 \\mathrm{O}_3^{2-}+5 \\mathrm{Br}_2+5 \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{SO}_4^{2-}+4 \\mathrm{Br}^{-}+10 \\mathrm{H}^{+}\n\\end{aligned}$$</p>\n<p>Which of the following statement justifies the above dual behaviour of thiosulphate?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Thiosulphate undergoes oxidation by bromine and reduction by iodine in these reactions\n",
      "Bromine is a weaker oxidant than iodine\n",
      "Bromine is a stronger oxidant than iodine\n",
      "Bromine undergoes oxidation and iodine undergoes reduction in these reactions"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "Bromine is a stronger oxidant than iodine\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29icb",
    "question": "<p>The number of ions from the following that are expected to behave as oxidising agent is :</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{Sn}^{4+}, \\mathrm{Sn}^{2+}, \\mathrm{Pb}^{2+}, \\mathrm{Tl}^{3+}, \\mathrm{Pb}^{4+}, \\mathrm{Tl}^{+}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "4",
      "2",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-and-reduction-reactions",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "ILZMXBbS6Wf9jXCoyj6rP",
    "question": "The correct order of the oxidation states of\nnitrogen in NO, N<sub>2</sub>O, NO<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "NO<sub>2</sub> &lt; NO &lt; N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; N<sub>2</sub>O",
      "NO<sub>2</sub> &lt; N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; NO &lt; N<sub>2</sub>O",
      "N<sub>2</sub>O &lt; NO &lt; N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; NO<sub>2</sub>",
      "N<sub>2</sub>O &lt; N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; NO &lt; NO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-number",
    "solution": "N<sub>2</sub>O &lt; NO &lt; N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> &lt; NO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "sUGLsiqlV2h6S2Ps2z7k9k2k5dyph0k",
    "question": "Oxidation number of potassium in K<sub>2</sub>O. K<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and KO<sub>2</sub> respectively is :",
    "options": [
      "+1, +2 and + 4",
      "+1, +1 and + 1",
      "+2, +1 and $$ + {1 \\over 2}$$",
      "+1, +4, and +2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-number",
    "solution": "+1, +1 and + 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "vlhjHX6yKGZg6V7YU07k9k2k5idmyit",
    "question": "The compound that cannot act both as oxidising\nand reducing agent is :",
    "options": [
      "H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>",
      "H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>",
      "HNO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-number",
    "solution": "H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "9qj8Tm9aeBraxksqGm1kmm1cgbf",
    "question": "The oxidation states of nitrogen in NO, NO<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>O and NO$$_3^ - $$ are in the order of :",
    "options": [
      "N<sub>2</sub>O &gt; NO<sub>2</sub> &gt; NO &gt; NO$$_3^ - $$",
      "NO &gt; NO<sub>2</sub> &gt; N<sub>2</sub>O &gt; NO$$_3^ - $$",
      "NO<sub>2</sub> &gt; NO$$_3^ - $$ &gt; NO &gt; N<sub>2</sub>O",
      "NO$$_3^ - $$ &gt; NO<sub>2</sub> &gt; NO &gt; N<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-number",
    "solution": "NO$$_3^ - $$ &gt; NO<sub>2</sub> &gt; NO &gt; N<sub>2</sub>O"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krxb954p",
    "question": "Identify the process in which change in the oxidation state is five :",
    "options": [
      "$$C{r_2}O_7^{2 - } \\to 2C{r^{3 + }}$$",
      "$$MnO_4^ -  \\to M{n^{2 + }}$$",
      "$$CrO_4^{2 - } \\to C{r^{3 + }}$$",
      "$${C_2}O_4^{2 - } \\to 2C{O_2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-number",
    "solution": "$$MnO_4^ -  \\to M{n^{2 + }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz034xm",
    "question": "The oxidation states of 'P' in H<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>, H<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and H<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>6</sub>, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "7, 5 and 6",
      "5, 4 and 3",
      "5, 3 and 4",
      "6, 4 and 5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "oxidation-number",
    "solution": "5, 3 and 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "Nc3KC2d3VAtJyLmgZhERW",
    "question": "50 mL of 0.5 M oxalic acid is needed to neutralize 25 mL of sodium hydroxide solution. The amount of NaOH in 50 mL of the given sodium hydroxide solution is -",
    "options": [
      "20 g ",
      "4 g",
      "80 g",
      "10 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "redox-titration",
    "solution": "4 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "fJgmdZRvqRLiiFd7mUjgy2xukevksjwi",
    "question": "While titrating dilute HCl solution with aqueous\nNaOH, which of the following will not be\nrequired?",
    "options": [
      "Pipette and distilled water\n",
      "Clamp and phenolphthalein",
      "Burette and porcelain tile",
      "Bunsen burner and measuring cylinder"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "redox-titration",
    "solution": "Bunsen burner and measuring cylinder"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i5tubb",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$.</p>\n<p>Assertion A: Phenolphthalein is a $$\\mathrm{pH}$$ dependent indicator, remains colourless in acidic solution and gives pink colour in basic medium.</p>\n<p>Reason R: Phenolphthalein is a weak acid. It doesn't dissociate in basic medium.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$.",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$.",
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "redox-titration",
    "solution": "A is true but R is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rl5zgs",
    "question": "<p>A compound 'X' is a weak acid and it exhibits colour change at pH close to the equivalence point during neutralization of NaOH with $$\\mathrm{CH}_{3} \\mathrm{COOH}$$. Compound 'X' exists in ionized form in basic medium. The compound 'X' is</p>",
    "options": [
      "methyl orange",
      "methyl red",
      "phenolphthalein",
      "erichrome Black T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "redox-titration",
    "solution": "phenolphthalein"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgys8ty2",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : In redox titration, the indicators used are sensitive to change in $$\\mathrm{pH}$$ of the solution.</p>\n<p>Statement II : In acid-base titration, the indicators used are sensitive to change in oxidation potential.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "redox-titration",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "BsaVZ1wbbWcIJLZwfg3rsa0w2w9jx56tijx",
    "question": "An example of a disproportionation reaction is :",
    "options": [
      "2NaBr + Cl<sub>2</sub> $$ \\to $$ 2NaCl + Br<sub>2</sub>",
      "2KMnO<sub>4</sub> $$ \\to $$ 2KMnO<sub>4</sub> + MnO<sub>2</sub> + O<sub>2</sub>\n(3)  (4)\n",
      "2CuBr $$ \\to $$ CuBr<sub>2</sub> + Cu",
      "2MnO<sub>4</sub>\n + 10I<sup>–</sup>\n + 16H<sup>+</sup> $$ \\to $$ 2Mn<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup> + 5I<sub>2</sub> + 8H<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "types-of-redox-reactions",
    "solution": "2CuBr $$ \\to $$ CuBr<sub>2</sub> + Cu"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58jinm1",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following is an example of disproportionation reaction ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3MnO_4^{2 - } + 4{H^ + } \\to 2MnO_4^ -  + Mn{O_2} + 2{H_2}O$$",
      "$$MnO_4^ -  + 4{H^ + } + 4{e^ - } \\to Mn{O_2} + 2{H_2}O$$",
      "$$10{I^ - } + 2MnO_4^ -  + 16{H^ + } \\to 2M{n^{2 + }} + 8{H_2}O + 5{I_2}$$",
      "$$8MnO_4^ -  + 3{S_2}O_3^{2 - } + {H_2}O \\to 8Mn{O_2} + 6SO_4^{2 - } + 2O{H^ - }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "types-of-redox-reactions",
    "solution": "$$3MnO_4^{2 - } + 4{H^ + } \\to 2MnO_4^ -  + Mn{O_2} + 2{H_2}O$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gqai21",
    "question": "<p>Which of the given reactions is not an example of disproportionation reaction?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}+\\mathrm{O}_{2}$$",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{NO}_{2}+\\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{HNO}_{3}+\\mathrm{HNO}_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{MnO}_{4}^{-}+4 \\mathrm{H}^{+}+3 \\mathrm{e}^{-} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{MnO}_{2}+2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$",
      "$$3 \\mathrm{MnO}_{4}^{2-}+4 \\mathrm{H}^{+} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{MnO}_{4}^{-}+\\mathrm{MnO}_{2}+2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "types-of-redox-reactions",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{MnO}_{4}^{-}+4 \\mathrm{H}^{+}+3 \\mathrm{e}^{-} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{MnO}_{2}+2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh27pci2",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following options are correct for the reaction</p>\n<p>$$2\\left[\\mathrm{Au}(\\mathrm{CN})_{2}\\right]^{-}(\\mathrm{aq})+\\mathrm{Zn}(\\mathrm{s}) \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{Au}(\\mathrm{s})+\\left[\\mathrm{Zn}(\\mathrm{CN})_{4}\\right]^{2-}(\\mathrm{aq})$$</p>\n<p>A. Redox reaction</p>\n<p>B. Displacement reaction</p>\n<p>C. Decomposition reaction</p>\n<p>D. Combination reaction</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and B only",
      "C and D only",
      "A only",
      "A and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "types-of-redox-reactions",
    "solution": "A and B only"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsblv392",
    "question": "Which of the following reactions are disproportionation reactions?<br/><br/>\n(A) $\\mathrm{Cu}^{+} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{Cu}^{2+}+\\mathrm{Cu}$<br/><br/>\n(B) $3 \\mathrm{MnO}_4^{2-}+4 \\mathrm{H}^{+} \\longrightarrow 2 <br/><br/>\\mathrm{MnO}_4^{-}+\\mathrm{MnO}_2+2 \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}$<br/><br/>\n(C) $2 \\mathrm{KMnO}_4 \\longrightarrow \\mathrm{K}_2 \\mathrm{MnO}_4+\\mathrm{MnO}_2+\\mathrm{O}_2$<br/><br/>\n(D) $2 \\mathrm{MnO}_4^{-}+3 \\mathrm{Mn}^{2+}+2 \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O} \\longrightarrow 5 \\mathrm{MnO}_2+4 \\mathrm{H}^{+}$\n<br/><br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A), (B)",
      "(A), (D)",
      "(B), (C), (D)",
      "(A), (B), (C)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "types-of-redox-reactions",
    "solution": "(A), (B)"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29nmy",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 771px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 320px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>Reaction</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>Type of redox reaction</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{N}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}+\\mathrm{O}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{NO}_{(\\mathrm{g})}<br/>$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Decomposition</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>2 \\mathrm{~Pb}\\left(\\mathrm{NO}_3\\right)_{2(\\mathrm{~s})} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{PbO}_{(\\mathrm{s})}+4 \\mathrm{NO}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}+\\mathrm{O}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}<br/>$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Displacement</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>2 \\mathrm{Na}_{(\\mathrm{s})}+2 \\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}_{(\\mathrm{l})} \\rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{NaOH}_{(\\mathrm{aq} .)}+\\mathrm{H}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}<br/>$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Disproportionation</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>2 \\mathrm{NO}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}+2^{-} \\mathrm{OH}(\\text { aq. }) \\rightarrow \\mathrm{NO}_{2(\\mathrm{aq} .)}^{-}+\\mathrm{NO}_{3(\\text { aq. })}^{-}+\\mathrm{H}_2 \\mathrm{O}_{(\\mathrm{l})}<br/>$$<br/></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Combination</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)\n",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(II), (C)-(III), (D)-(IV)\n",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(III), (C)-(IV), (D)-(I)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(II), (C)-(I), (D)-(IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "redox-reactions",
    "topic": "types-of-redox-reactions",
    "solution": "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "nZxFpwa9Fg4z9Ugm",
    "question": "KO<sub>2</sub> (potassium super oxide) is used in oxygen cylinders in space and submarines because it :",
    "options": [
      "absorbs CO<sub>2</sub> and increases O<sub>2</sub> content",
      "eliminates moisture",
      "absorbs CO<sub>2</sub>",
      "produces ozone"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "absorbs CO<sub>2</sub> and increases O<sub>2</sub> content"
  },
  {
    "id": "Qx01cNZKLz1oysG1",
    "question": "Which of the following on thermal decomposition yields a basic as well as an acidic oxide?",
    "options": [
      "NaNO<sub>3</sub>",
      "KClO<sub>3</sub>",
      "CaCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "NH<sub>4</sub>NO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "CaCO<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "RLhIav4b1VFGw9o607ijK",
    "question": "A metal on combustion in excess air forms X. X upon hydrolysis with water yields H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> along with another product. The metal is :",
    "options": [
      "Rb",
      "Mg",
      "Na",
      "Li"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Rb"
  },
  {
    "id": "lGXfO6lCgykyXQyZzz3rsa0w2w9jx0w6xqr",
    "question": "A hydrated solid X on heating initially gives a monohydrated compound Y. Y upon heating above 373  K leads\nto an anhydrous white powder Z. X and Z, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "Baking soda and dead burnt plaster.\n",
      "Washing soda and soda ash",
      "Washing soda and dead burnt plaster.",
      "Baking soda and soda as. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Washing soda and soda ash"
  },
  {
    "id": "ypLFVreANPpXyt4Dh81kmkj79r8",
    "question": "One of the by-products formed during the recovery of NH<sub>3</sub> from Solvay process is :",
    "options": [
      "Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>",
      "NH<sub>4</sub>Cl",
      "NaHCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "CaCl<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "CaCl<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq5w35n",
    "question": "A s-block element (M) reacts with oxygen to form an oxide of the formula MO<sub>2</sub>. The oxide is pale yellow in colour and paramagnetic. The element (M) is :",
    "options": [
      "Mg",
      "Na",
      "Ca",
      "K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "K"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krx511ei",
    "question": "Match List I with List II :<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List-I<br/>Elements</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List-II<br/>Properties</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(a)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Li</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(i)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Poor water solubility of $${I^ - }$$ salt</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(b)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Na</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(ii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Most abundant element in cell fluid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(c)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">K</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(iii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Bicarbonate salt used in fire extinguisher</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(d)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Cs</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(iv)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Carbonate salt decomposes easily on heating</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iii), (d)-(iv)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1gxe6d",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II :<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(a)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Li</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(i)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">photoelectric cell</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(b)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Na</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(ii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">absorbent of $$C{O_2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(c)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">K</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(iii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">coolant in fast breeder nuclear reactor</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(d)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Cs</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(iv)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">treatment of cancer</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(v)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">bearings for motor engines</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a) - (v), (b) - (i), (c) - (ii), (d) - (iv)",
      "(a) - (v), (b) - (ii), (c) - (iv), (d) - (i)",
      "(a) - (iv), (b) - (iii), (c) - (i), (d) - (ii)",
      "(a) - (v), (b) - (iii), (c) - (ii), (d) - (i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "(a) - (v), (b) - (iii), (c) - (ii), (d) - (i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfrglym",
    "question": "Choose the correct statement from the following :",
    "options": [
      "The standard enthalpy of formation for alkali metal bromides becomes less negative on descending the group.",
      "The low solubility of CsI in water is due to its high lattice enthalpy.",
      "Among the alkali metal halides, LiF is least soluble in water.",
      "LiF has least negative standard enthalpy of formation among alkali metal fluorides."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Among the alkali metal halides, LiF is least soluble in water."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54ygmwk",
    "question": "<p>Amongst baking soda, caustic soda and washing soda, carbonate anion is present in :</p>",
    "options": [
      "washing soda only.",
      "washing soda and caustic soda only.",
      "washing soda and baking soda only.",
      "baking soda, caustic soda and washing soda. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "washing soda only."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bd8vjo",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following compounds is used as a chemical in certain type of fire extinguishers?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Baking soda",
      "Soda ash",
      "Washing soda",
      "Caustic soda"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Baking soda"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w5wxgq",
    "question": "<p>Correct statement about alkali metal oxides is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "peroxides are colored.",
      "superoxides are paramagnetic.",
      "oxides are paramagnetic.",
      "peroxides are both colored and paramagnetic."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "superoxides are paramagnetic."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i51di1",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A: $$\\mathrm{LiF}$$ is sparingly soluble in water.</p>\n<p>Reason R: The ionic radius of $$\\mathrm{Li}^{+}$$ ion is smallest among its group members, hence has least hydration enthalpy.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "A is true but R is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p75gxd",
    "question": "<p>Lithium nitrate and sodium nitrate, when heated separately, respectively, give :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{LiNO}_{2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{NaNO}_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Li}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Na}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Li}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$ and $$\\mathrm{NaNO}_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{LiNO}_{2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Na}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Li}_{2} \\mathrm{O}$$ and $$\\mathrm{NaNO}_{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldoi309o",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 581px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 223px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 263px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Slaked lime</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{NaOH}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Dead burnt plaster</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Ca(OH)_2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Caustic soda</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{Na_2CO_3\\cdot 10H_2O}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Washing soda</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{CaSO_4}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - III, (B) - IV, (C) - II, (D) - I",
      "(A) - III, (B) - II, (C) - IV, (D) - I",
      "(A) - II, (B) - IV, (C) - I, (D) - III",
      "(A) - I, (B) - IV, (C) - II, (D) - III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "(A) - II, (B) - IV, (C) - I, (D) - III"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqwpq9c",
    "question": "Which of the following reaction is correct?",
    "options": [
      "$4 \\mathrm{LiNO}_{3} \\stackrel{\\Delta}{\\longrightarrow} 2 \\mathrm{Li}_{2} \\mathrm{O}+4 \\mathrm{NO}_{2}+\\mathrm{O}_{2}$",
      "$2 \\mathrm{LiNO}_{3} \\longrightarrow 2 \\mathrm{Li}+2 \\mathrm{NO}_{2}+\\mathrm{O}_{2}$",
      "$4 \\mathrm{LiNO}_{3} \\stackrel{\\Delta}{\\longrightarrow} 2 \\mathrm{Li}_{2} \\mathrm{O}+2 \\mathrm{~N}_{2} \\mathrm{O}_{4}+\\mathrm{O}_{2}$",
      "$2 \\mathrm{LiNO}_{3} \\stackrel{\\Delta}{\\longrightarrow} 2 \\mathrm{NaNO}_{2}+\\mathrm{O}_{2}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "$4 \\mathrm{LiNO}_{3} \\stackrel{\\Delta}{\\longrightarrow} 2 \\mathrm{Li}_{2} \\mathrm{O}+4 \\mathrm{NO}_{2}+\\mathrm{O}_{2}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr4kfao",
    "question": "<p>Lithium aluminium hydride can be prepared from the reaction of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{LiCl}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Al_2H_6}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{LiH}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Al}(\\mathrm{OH})_{3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{LiH}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Al}_{2} \\mathrm{Cl}_{6}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{LiCl}, \\mathrm{Al}$$ and $$\\mathrm{H}_{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{LiH}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Al}_{2} \\mathrm{Cl}_{6}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp305w1",
    "question": "<p>Identify the correct order of standard enthalpy of formation of sodium halides :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{NaI}<\\mathrm{NaBr}<\\mathrm{NaCl}<\\mathrm{NaF}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{NaI}<\\mathrm{NaBr}<\\mathrm{NaF}<\\mathrm{NaCl}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{NaF}<\\mathrm{NaCl}<\\mathrm{NaBr}<\\mathrm{NaI}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{NaCl}<\\mathrm{NaF}<\\mathrm{NaBr}<\\mathrm{NaI}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{NaI}<\\mathrm{NaBr}<\\mathrm{NaCl}<\\mathrm{NaF}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguzqkuf",
    "question": "<p>Match List-I with List-II:</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 554px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 49px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 201px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 54px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 250px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">K</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">Thermonuclear reactions</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">KCl</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">Fertilizer</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">KOH</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">Sodium potassium pump</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">Li</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">Absorbent of CO$$_2$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II",
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvul4xb",
    "question": "<p>Number of water molecules in washing soda and soda ash respectively are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 and 0",
      "10 and 1",
      "1 and 10",
      "10 and 0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "10 and 0"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh321pgm",
    "question": "<p>The product, which is not obtained during the electrolysis of brine solution is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "NaOH",
      "Cl$$_2$$",
      "H$$_2$$",
      "HCl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "HCl"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgys9jsl",
    "question": "<p>For a good quality cement, the ratio of lime to the total of the oxides of $$\\mathrm{Si}, \\mathrm{Al}$$ and $\\mathrm{Fe}$ should be as close as to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "2",
      "1",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "compounds-of-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "xmLplKAoWrSvtU2v",
    "question": "The metallic sodium disolves in liquid ammonia to form a deep blue coloured solution. The deep blue colour is due to formation of :",
    "options": [
      "solvated electron, $$e(NH_3)^-_x$$",
      "solvated atomic sodium, Na(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>y</sub>",
      "(Na<sup>+</sup> + Na<sup>-</sup>)",
      "NaNH<sub>2</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "solvated electron, $$e(NH_3)^-_x$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "8uVfBltXqgGofLA4",
    "question": "Based on lattice energy and other considerations which one of the following alkali\nmetal chlorides is expected to have the highest melting point :",
    "options": [
      "LiCl",
      "NaCl ",
      "KCl",
      "RbCl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "NaCl "
  },
  {
    "id": "ug5xRqR2hbb6I9wg",
    "question": "The ionic mobility of alkali metal ions in aqueous solution is maximum for :",
    "options": [
      "K<sup>+</sup>",
      "Rb<sup>+</sup>",
      "Li<sup>+</sup>",
      "Na<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Rb<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1nwds6DFEkalJLKm",
    "question": "Which of the following atoms has the highest first ionization energy?",
    "options": [
      "Na ",
      "K",
      "Sc",
      "Rb"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Sc"
  },
  {
    "id": "nMDPHAX75JenhSDN",
    "question": "The main oxides formed on combustion of Li, Na and K in excess of air are, respectively :",
    "options": [
      "LiO<sub>2</sub>, Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and K<sub>2</sub>O",
      "Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and KO<sub>2</sub>",
      "Li<sub>2</sub>O, Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and KO<sub>2</sub>",
      "Li<sub>2</sub>O, Na<sub>2</sub>O and KO<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Li<sub>2</sub>O, Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and KO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "TgDdM2mmeRLD5wAgr65Ee",
    "question": "The metal that forms nitride by reacting directly with  N<sub>2</sub> of air, is :",
    "options": [
      "K",
      "Li",
      "Rb",
      "Cs"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Li"
  },
  {
    "id": "3fIvRcFOUr7RdzK3xtdhl",
    "question": "Sodium metal on dissolution in liquid ammonia gives a deep blue solution due to the formation of : ",
    "options": [
      "ammoniated electrons ",
      "sodamide \n",
      "sodium-ammonia complex ",
      "sodium ion-ammonia complex "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "ammoniated electrons "
  },
  {
    "id": "8pFtw7Curi3b8lhQbQxiK",
    "question": "The correct order of hydration enthapies of alkali metal ions is :",
    "options": [
      "Li<sup>+</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; Cs<sup>+</sup> &gt; Rb<sup>+</sup>",
      "Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; Li<sup>+</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Cs<sup>+</sup> &gt; Rb<sup>+</sup>",
      "Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; Li<sup>+</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Rb<sup>+</sup> &gt; Cs<sup>+</sup>",
      "Li<sup>+</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Rb<sup>+</sup> &gt; Cs<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Li<sup>+</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Rb<sup>+</sup> &gt; Cs<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Md7RnupcKQ9LHk4fmu3rsa0w2w9jx84cpe7",
    "question": "The INCORRECT statement is :",
    "options": [
      "Lithium is least reactive with water among the alkali metals",
      "LiCl crystallises from aqueous solution as LiCl.2H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "Lithium is the strongest reducing agent among the alkali metals",
      "LiNO<sub>3</sub> decomposes on heating to give LiNO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub>\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "LiNO<sub>3</sub> decomposes on heating to give LiNO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub>\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "l4SUsVe5rxzI6pqp4d7k9k2k5ll12c5",
    "question": "Among the statements (a)-(d) the correct ones\nare :<br/><br/>\n(a) Lithium has the highest hydration enthalpy\namong the alkali metals.<br/><br/>\n(b) Lithium chloride is insoluble in pyridine.<br/><br/>\n(c) Lithium cannot form ethynide upon its\nreaction with ethyne.<br/><br/>\n(d) Both lithium and magnesium react slowly\nwith H<sub>2</sub>O.",
    "options": [
      "(b) and (c) only",
      "(a) and (d) only",
      "(a), (b) and (d) only",
      "(a), (c) and (d) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "(a), (c) and (d) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "S59yV4Qjk0ZGs6Qcydjgy2xukevm4nda",
    "question": "The metal mainly used in devising\nphotoelectric cells is :",
    "options": [
      "Na",
      "Rb",
      "Li",
      "Cs"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Cs"
  },
  {
    "id": "GBtrSd5mNmaUxQgvgmjgy2xukf93jp12",
    "question": "On combustion of Li, Na and K in excess of air,\nthe major oxides formed, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "Li<sub>2</sub>O, Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and K<sub>2</sub>O",
      "Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and K<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>",
      "Li<sub>2</sub>O, Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and KO<sub>2</sub>",
      "Li<sub>2</sub>O, Na<sub>2</sub>O and K<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Li<sub>2</sub>O, Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and KO<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "xIPx14sHG4Sji3P5j81klrv0p7u",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List I (Salt)</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List II (Flame colour wavelength)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>LiCl</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>455.5 nm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>NaCl</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>670.8 nm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>RbCl</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>780.0 nm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>CsCl</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>589.2 nm</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(iii), (d)-(i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(iii), (d)-(i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "kG3tUlNLd1J8H7qs8S1kmj7fogs",
    "question": "The correct order of conductivity of ions in water is :",
    "options": [
      "K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; Cs<sup>+</sup> &gt; Rb<sup>+</sup>",
      "Cs<sup>+</sup> &gt; Rb<sup>+</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup>",
      "Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Rb<sup>+</sup> &gt; Cs<sup>+</sup>",
      "Rb<sup>+</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Li<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Cs<sup>+</sup> &gt; Rb<sup>+</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Na<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz1p5wh",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion A and the other labelled as Reason R.<br/><br/>Assertion A : Lithium halides are some what covalent in nature.<br/><br/>Reason R : Lithium posses high polarisation capability.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjvo52s",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R). <br/><br/>Assertion (A) : Lithium salts are hydrated.<br/><br/>Reason (R) : Lithium has higher polarising power than other alkali metal group members.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct.",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct.",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l548jryc",
    "question": "<p>Arrange the following in the decreasing order of their covalent character :</p>\n<p>(A) LiCl</p>\n<p>(B) NaCl</p>\n<p>(C) KCl</p>\n<p>(D) CsCl</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) > (C) > (B) > (D)",
      "(B) > (A) > (C) > (D)",
      "(A) > (B) > (C) > (D)",
      "(A) > (B) > (D) > (C)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "(A) > (B) > (C) > (D)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l549ceo4",
    "question": "<p>Match List-I with List-II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 404px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 43px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 104px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 205px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">List-I<br/>(Metal)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">List-II<br/>(Emitted light wavelength (nm))</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Li</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">670.8</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Na</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">589.2</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Rb</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">780.0</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Cs</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">455.5</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(II), (C)-(III), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(II), (C)-(I), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(II), (C)-(I), (D)-(III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "(A)-(I), (B)-(II), (C)-(III), (D)-(IV)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bd7ybh",
    "question": "<p>In the industrial production of which of the following, molecular hydrogen is obtained as a byproduct?</p>",
    "options": [
      "NaOH",
      "NaCl",
      "Na metal",
      "Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "NaOH"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c6ksxr",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following statements are correct?</p>\n<p>(A) Both LiCl and MgCl<sub>2</sub> are soluble in ethanol.</p>\n<p>(B) The oxides Li<sub>2</sub>O and MgO combine with excess of oxygen to give superoxide.</p>\n<p>(C) LiF is less soluble in water than other alkali metal fluorides.</p>\n<p>(D) Li<sub>2</sub>O is more soluble in water than other alkali metal oxides.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) and (C) only",
      "(A), (C) and (D) only",
      "(B) and (C) only",
      "(A) and (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "(A) and (C) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6e18lqx",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct order of density of the alkali metals :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Li < K < Na < Rb < Cs",
      "Li < Na < K < Rb < Cs",
      "Cs < Rb < K < Na < Li",
      "Li < Na < K < Cs < Rb"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Li < K < Na < Rb < Cs"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mcnw4r",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following statement is <b>incorrect</b>?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Low solubility of LiF in water is due to its small hydration enthalpy.",
      "$$\\mathrm{KO}_{2}$$ is paramagnetic.",
      "Solution of sodium in liquid ammonia is conducting in nature.",
      "Sodium metal has higher density than potassium metal."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Low solubility of LiF in water is due to its small hydration enthalpy."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu04kqa",
    "question": "<p>Which one among the following metals is the weakest reducing agent?</p>",
    "options": [
      "K",
      "Na",
      "Li",
      "Rb"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Na"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu1d2x5",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements, one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : The alkali metals and their salts impart characteristic colour to reducing flame.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Alkali metals can be detected using flame tests.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "A is not correct but R is correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwv6nx1",
    "question": "<p>Identify the correct statements about alkali metals.</p>\n<p>A. The order of standard reduction potential (M$$^+$$ \n | M) for alkali metal ions is Na &gt; Rb &gt; Li.</p>\n<p>B. CsI is highly soluble in water.</p>\n<p>C. Lithium carbonate is highly stable to heat.</p>\n<p>D. Potassium dissolved in concentrated liquid ammonia is blue in colour and paramagnetic.</p>\n<p>E. All the alkali metal hydrides are ionic solids.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "C and E only",
      "A and E only",
      "A, B, D only",
      "A, B and E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "A and E only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrk21qp",
    "question": "<p>The density of alkali metals is in the order :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Na}<\\mathrm{K}<\\mathrm{Cs}<\\mathrm{Rb}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}<\\mathrm{Na}<\\mathrm{Rb}<\\mathrm{Cs}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}<\\mathrm{Cs}<\\mathrm{Na}<\\mathrm{Rb}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Na}<\\mathrm{Rb}<\\mathrm{K}<\\mathrm{Cs}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{K}<\\mathrm{Na}<\\mathrm{Rb}<\\mathrm{Cs}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsxv5u7",
    "question": "<p>Alkali metal from the following with least melting point is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Rb}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Na}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Cs}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Cs}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyrlw06",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Sodium is about 30 times as abundant as potassium in the oceans.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Potassium is bigger in size than sodium.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkali-metals",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "m7DFC0V1q3ppedgi",
    "question": "A metal M readily forms its sulphate MSO<sub>4</sub>, which is water-soluble. It forms its oxide MO which becomes inert on heating. It forms an insoluble hydroxide M(OH)<sub>2</sub> which is soluble in NaOH solution. The M is :",
    "options": [
      "Mg",
      "Ba",
      "Ca",
      "Be"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Be"
  },
  {
    "id": "gi6L6SzhhKrLkdzi",
    "question": "The solubilities of carbonates decrease down the magnesium group due to a decrease in :",
    "options": [
      "hydration energy of cations",
      "inter-ionic attraction",
      "entropy of solution formation",
      "lattice energies of solids"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "hydration energy of cations"
  },
  {
    "id": "CkTPci39C0Xfl6Cj",
    "question": "One mole of magnesium nitride on the reaction with an excess of water gives :",
    "options": [
      "one mole of ammonia",
      "two moles of nitric acid ",
      "two moles of ammonia ",
      "one mole of nitric acid "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "two moles of ammonia "
  },
  {
    "id": "K4eHcbFTKpsFqwfS",
    "question": "The metal that cannot be obtained by electrolysis of an aqueous solution of its salts is :",
    "options": [
      "Cu",
      "Cr",
      "Ag",
      "Ca"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Ca"
  },
  {
    "id": "NXhbC551v5SSKO0F",
    "question": "Which one of the following alkaline earth metal sulphates has its hydration enthalpy greater than its lattice\nenthalpy?",
    "options": [
      "BeSO<sub>4</sub>",
      "BaSO<sub>4</sub>",
      "SrSO<sub>4</sub>",
      "CaSO<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "BeSO<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "6b7YOR8lcPINC5urSqZaJ",
    "question": "The correct order of the solubility of alkaline-earth metal sulphates in water is :",
    "options": [
      "Mg &lt; Ca &lt; Sr &lt; Ba",
      "Mg &lt; Sr &lt; Ca &lt; Ba",
      "Mg &gt; Sr &gt; Ca &gt; Ba",
      "Mg &gt; Ca &gt; Sr &gt; Ba"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Mg &gt; Ca &gt; Sr &gt; Ba"
  },
  {
    "id": "7OQbAyzGvzLVaGmi",
    "question": "Both lithium and magnesium display several similar properties due to the diagonal relationship; however,\nthe one which is incorrect, is :",
    "options": [
      "both form soluble bicarbonates",
      "both from nitrides\n",
      "nitrates of both Li and Mg yield NO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> on heating ",
      "both form basic carbonates "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "both form basic carbonates "
  },
  {
    "id": "FFHRLWOztKUFsTfFIm3rsa0w2w9jx4ybuyc",
    "question": "The correct sequence of thermal stability of the following carbonates is :",
    "options": [
      "BaCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; SrCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; CaCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; MgCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "MgCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; CaCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; SrCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; BaCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "BaCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; CaCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; SrCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; MgCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "MgCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; SrCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; CaCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; BaCO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "MgCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; CaCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; SrCO<sub>3</sub> &lt; BaCO<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "g3MNTjqnsbi5rUXXP13rsa0w2w9jwvclt5n",
    "question": "The alloy used in the construction of aircrafts is :",
    "options": [
      "Mg – Zn",
      "Mg – Al ",
      "Mg – Mn",
      "Mg – Sn"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Mg – Al "
  },
  {
    "id": "sgBTVoF0USOrMyGlhD6PY",
    "question": "The amphoteric hydroxide is :",
    "options": [
      "Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Be(OH)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Sr(OH)<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Be(OH)<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "UDmTrfxCRp1DXrXcHTbww",
    "question": "The metal used for marking X–ray tube window is : ",
    "options": [
      "Ca",
      "Na",
      "Mg",
      "Be"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Be"
  },
  {
    "id": "x8nHejYs6ywrEWJdhB3Ja",
    "question": "The alkaline earth metal nitrate that does not crystallise with water molecules, is  : ",
    "options": [
      "Mg(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Sr(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Ca(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Ba(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Ba(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "UZbRl56uOuvlI5bb6ojgy2xukey6nndt",
    "question": "Two elements A and B have similar chemical\nproperties. They don’t form solid\nhydrogencarbonates, but react with nitrogen to\nform nitrides. A and B, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "Li and Mg",
      "Cs and Ba",
      "Na and Rb",
      "Na and Ca"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Li and Mg"
  },
  {
    "id": "IHQJW0f6JG7mifzSAIjgy2xukfcedvk5",
    "question": "An alkaline earth metal ‘M’ readily forms water\nsoluble sulphate and water insoluble hydroxide.\nIts oxide MO is very stable to heat and does not\nhave rock-salt structure. M is :",
    "options": [
      "Ca",
      "Mg",
      "Sr",
      "Be"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Be"
  },
  {
    "id": "WsmnVOe6nwSecTM36Ujgy2xukftdeo7z",
    "question": "Among the sulphates of alkaline earth metals,\nthe solubilities of BeSO<sub>4</sub> and MgSO<sub>4</sub> in water,\nrespectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "poor and poor",
      "poor and high",
      "high and poor",
      "high and high"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "high and high"
  },
  {
    "id": "FBEC1Yigj9F7SXOolx1kmhtmrch",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : Both CaCl<sub>2</sub> . 6H<sub>2</sub>O and MgCl<sub>2</sub> . 8H<sub>2</sub>O undergo dehydration on heating.<br/><br/>Statement II : BeO is amphoteric whereas the oxides of other elements in the same group are acidic.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both statement I and statement II are false",
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Both statement I and statement II are false"
  },
  {
    "id": "6BsBWGWetlGz7d3oGa1kmki64va",
    "question": "The set of elements that differ in mutual relationship from those of the other sets is :",
    "options": [
      "Li - Na",
      "Be - Al",
      "B - Si",
      "Li - Mg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Li - Na"
  },
  {
    "id": "hjfXD01LasylIUjUMN1kmm0q9tf",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II :<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Be</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>treatment of cancer</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Mg</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>extraction of metals</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Ca</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>incendiary bombs and signals</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Ra</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>windows of X-ray tubes</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td></td>\n<td></td>\n<td>(v)</td>\n<td>bearings for motor engines</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the option given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(v), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(v)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq5d3mo",
    "question": "The set in which compounds have different nature is :",
    "options": [
      "B(OH)<sub>3</sub> and H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>3</sub>",
      "B(OH)<sub>3</sub> and Al(OH)<sub>3</sub>",
      "NaOH and Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>",
      "Be(OH)<sub>2</sub> and Al(OH)<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "B(OH)<sub>3</sub> and Al(OH)<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krussbkk",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : None of the alkaline earth metal hydroxides dissolve in alkali.<br/><br/>Statement II : Solubility of alkaline earth metal hydroxides in water increases down the group. <br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct.",
      "Statement I and Statement II both are incorrect.",
      "Statement I and Statement II both are correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58dt92f",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of melting point is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Be > Mg > Ca > Sr",
      "Sr > Ca > Mg > Be",
      "Be > Ca > Mg > Sr",
      "Be > Ca > Sr > Mg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Be > Ca > Sr > Mg"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58j110e",
    "question": "<p>s-block element which cannot be qualitatively confirmed by the flame test is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Li",
      "Na",
      "Rb",
      "Be"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Be"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5alvkoc",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following alkaline earth metal ions has the highest ionic mobility in its aqueous solution?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Be<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Mg<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Ca<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Sr<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Sr<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f6uoab",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of density is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Be > Mg > Ca > Sr",
      "Sr > Ca > Mg > Be",
      "Sr > Be > Mg > Ca",
      "Be > Sr > Mg > Ca"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Sr > Be > Mg > Ca"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i4sc3n",
    "question": "<p>The metal that has very low melting point and its periodic position is closer to a metalloid is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Al",
      "Ga",
      "Se",
      "In"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Ga"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kpeypx",
    "question": "<p>An element A of group 1 shows similarity to an element B belonging to group 2. If A has maximum hydration enthalpy in group 1 then B is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Mg",
      "Be",
      "Ca",
      "Sr"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Mg"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nuhhdy",
    "question": "<p>The correct decreasing order for metallic character is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Na > Mg > Be > Si > P",
      "P > Si > Be > Mg > Na",
      "Si > P > Be > Na > Mg",
      "Be > Na > Mg > Si > P"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Na > Mg > Be > Si > P"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nuyuiq",
    "question": "<p>Statement I : An alloy of lithium and magnesium is used to make aircraft plates.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The magnesium ions are important for cell-membrane integrity.</p>\n<p>In the light the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo8cwum",
    "question": "The element playing significant role in neuromuscular function and interneuronal transmission is :",
    "options": [
      "Be",
      "$\\mathrm{Ca}$",
      "$\\mathrm{Mg}$",
      "$\\mathrm{Li}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{Ca}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldoj5w8f",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct statement(s) :</p>\n<p>A. Beryllium oxide is purely acidic in nature.</p>\n<p>B. Beryllium carbonate is kept in the atmosphere of $$\\mathrm{CO_2}$$.</p>\n<p>C. Beryllium sulphate is readily soluble in water.</p>\n<p>D. Beryllium shows anomalous behaviour.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A only",
      "B, C and D only",
      "A, B and C only",
      "A and B only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "B, C and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqwnz40",
    "question": "Chlorides of which metal are soluble in organic solvents :",
    "options": [
      "K",
      "Be",
      "Ca",
      "Mg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Be"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr4n6j4",
    "question": "<p>The alkaline earth metal sulphate(s) which are readily soluble in water is/are :</p>\n<p>A. $$\\mathrm{BeSO}_{4}$$</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{MgSO}_{4}$$</p>\n<p>C. $$\\mathrm{CaSO}_{4}$$</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{SrSO}_{4}$$</p>\n<p>E. $$\\mathrm{BaSO}_{4}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and B",
      "B and C",
      "B only",
      "A only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "A and B"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsr0jvc",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of hydration enthalpies is</p>\n<p>(A) K$$^+$$</p>\n<p>(B) Rb$$^+$$</p>\n<p>(C) Mg$$^{2+}$$</p>\n<p>(D) Cs$$^+$$</p>\n<p>(E) Ca$$^{2+}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "E > C > A > B > D",
      "C > A > E > B > D",
      "C > E > A > D > B",
      "C > E > A > B > D"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "C > E > A > B > D"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu0yi9x",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following represents the correct order of metallic character of the given elements?</p>",
    "options": [
      "K < Mg < Be < Si",
      "Si < Be < Mg < K",
      "Be < Si < Mg < K",
      "Be < Si < K < Mg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Si < Be < Mg < K"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwum0sy",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements, one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Beryllium has less negative value of reduction potential compared to the other alkaline earth metals.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Beryllium has large hydration energy due to small size of Be$$^{2+}$$ but relatively large value of atomization enthalpy</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT  the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "A is not correct but R is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnzloa4",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R :\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Assertion (A)</b> : $\\mathrm{BeCl}_{2}$ and $\\mathrm{MgCl}_{2}$ produce characteristic flame<br/><br/>\n<b>Reason (R)</b> : The excitation energy is high in $\\mathrm{BeCl}_{2}$ and $\\mathrm{MgCl}_{2}$\n<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{(A)}$ is true but $(\\mathrm{R})$ is false",
      "Both (A) and $(\\mathrm{R})$ are true and $(\\mathrm{R})$ is the correct explanation of $(A)$",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true\n",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is NOT the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "(A) is false but (R) is true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvtszte",
    "question": "<p>The correct order of metallic character is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "K > Be > Ca",
      "Ca > K > Be",
      "K > Ca > Be",
      "Be > Ca > K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "K > Ca > Be"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh036qop",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Lithium and Magnesium do not form superoxide</p>\n<p>Statement II : The ionic radius of $$\\mathrm{Li}^{+}$$ is larger than ionic radius of $$\\mathrm{Mg}^{2+}$$</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer\n\nfrom the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh32h679",
    "question": "<p>Ion having highest hydration enthalpy among the given alkaline earth metal ions is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Sr}^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ca}^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Be}^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ba}^{2+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "s-block-elements",
    "topic": "physiochemical-trends-in-alkaline-earth-metals",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Be}^{2+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "K8VVFHuXtvdFkmGb",
    "question": "In a compound atoms of element Y from ccp lattice and those of element X occupy 2/3rd of tetrahedral\nvoids. The formula of the compound will be :",
    "options": [
      "X<sub>4</sub>Y<sub>3</sub>",
      "X<sub>2</sub>Y<sub>3</sub>",
      "X<sub>2</sub>Y",
      "X<sub>3</sub>Y<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "close-packing-in-crystals",
    "solution": "X<sub>4</sub>Y<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "6xBm9SOvpviBC90u",
    "question": "Percentages of free space in cubic close packed structure and in body centred packed structure are\nrespectively :",
    "options": [
      "30% and 26%",
      "26% and 32%",
      "32% and 48%",
      "48% and 26%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "close-packing-in-crystals",
    "solution": "26% and 32%"
  },
  {
    "id": "ya2QzB4oEpOwCfOkCxVnd",
    "question": "A compound of formula A<sub>2</sub>B<sub>3</sub> has the hcp lattice. Which atom forms the hcp lattice and what fraction of tetrahedral voids is occupied by the other atoms : ",
    "options": [
      "hcp lattice - A, $${1 \\over 3}$$ Tetrahedral voids-B",
      "hcp lattice - B, $${1 \\over 3}$$ Tetrahedral voids - A",
      "hcp lattice - A, $${2 \\over 3}$$ Tetrahedral voids - B",
      "hcp lattice - B, $${2 \\over 3}$$ Tetrahedral voids - A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "close-packing-in-crystals",
    "solution": "hcp lattice - B, $${1 \\over 3}$$ Tetrahedral voids - A"
  },
  {
    "id": "FdsRW5NnnN48Z4EMOp1kmlniank",
    "question": "In a binary compound, atoms of element A form a hcp structure and those of element M occupy 2/3 of the tetrahedral voids of the hcp structure. The formula of the binary compound is :",
    "options": [
      "M<sub>2</sub>A<sub>3</sub>",
      "M<sub>4</sub>A<sub>3</sub>",
      "M<sub>4</sub>A",
      "MA<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "close-packing-in-crystals",
    "solution": "M<sub>4</sub>A<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh29b0ej",
    "question": "<p>A compound is formed by two elements $$\\mathrm{X}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Y}$$. The element $$\\mathrm{Y}$$ forms cubic close packed arrangement and those of element $$\\mathrm{X}$$ occupy one third of the tetrahedral voids. What is the formula of the compound?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{XY}_{3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{X_3Y}_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{X_3Y}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{X_2Y}_{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "close-packing-in-crystals",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{X_2Y}_{3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "8Z5YSSag1cXd5PT9",
    "question": "Na and Mg crystallize in BCC and FCC type crystals respectively, then the number of atoms of\nNa and Mg present in the unit cell of their respective crystal is :",
    "options": [
      "4 and 2",
      "9 and 14",
      "14 and 9",
      "2 and 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "2 and 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "MnTPBx7eUUSPDHM9",
    "question": "Total volume of atoms present in a face-centre cubic unit cell of a metal is (r is atomic radius)  :",
    "options": [
      "20/3 $$\\pi r^3$$",
      "24/3 $$\\pi r^3$$",
      "16/3 $$\\pi r^3$$",
      "12/3 $$\\pi r^3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "16/3 $$\\pi r^3$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "UAswneTg9kihqAeF",
    "question": "Copper crystallizes in fcc with a unit cell length of 361 pm. What is the radius of copper atom?",
    "options": [
      "108 pm ",
      "127 pm",
      "157 pm",
      "181 pm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "127 pm"
  },
  {
    "id": "0uJERo1Cizf4UXUY",
    "question": "In a face centred cubic lattice, atom A occupies the corner positions and atom B occupies the face centre\npositions. If one atom of B is missing from one of the face centred points, the formula of the compound is :",
    "options": [
      "AB<sub>2</sub>",
      "A<sub>2</sub>B<sub>3</sub>",
      "A<sub>2</sub>B<sub>5</sub>",
      "A<sub>2</sub>B"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "A<sub>2</sub>B<sub>5</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "JT7oTToVenVGeBmt",
    "question": "Lithium forms body centred cubic structure. The length of the side of its unit cell is 351 pm. Atomic radius\nof the lithium will be :",
    "options": [
      "75 pm",
      "300 pm",
      "240 pm",
      "152 pm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "152 pm"
  },
  {
    "id": "ddTbKpnahDDxHBZC",
    "question": "Sodium metal crystallizes in a body centred cubic lattice with a unit cell edge of 4.29 Å . The radius of\nsodium atom is approximately :",
    "options": [
      "5.72 Å",
      "0.93 Å",
      "1.86 Å",
      "3.22 Å"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "1.86 Å"
  },
  {
    "id": "UfyqZXeWprXZYWjU",
    "question": "A metal crystallises in a face centred cubic structure. If the edge length of its unit cell is ‘a’, the closest\napproach between two atoms in metallic crystal will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\sqrt 2 a$$",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 a$$",
      "$${a \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "2a"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "$${a \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "DaSAsuPSM8VLjf3GVx95Q",
    "question": "All of the following share the same crystal structure except : ",
    "options": [
      "LiCl",
      "NaCl",
      "RbCl",
      "CsCl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "CsCl"
  },
  {
    "id": "9gLROTdBInaKJiqCLzlN7",
    "question": "At 100<sup>o</sup>C, copper (Cu) has FCC unit cell structure with cell edge length of x $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$. What is the approximate density of Cu (in g cm<sup>$$-$$3</sup>) at this temperature? \n<br/>[Atomic Mass of Cu = 63.55 u]",
    "options": [
      "$${{205} \\over {{x^3}}}$$",
      "$${{105} \\over {{x^3}}}$$",
      "$${{211} \\over {{x^3}}}$$",
      "$${{422} \\over {{x^3}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "$${{422} \\over {{x^3}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "k5eMabjmavRIn34ZJosBg",
    "question": "Which premitive unit cell has unequal edge lengths (a $$ \\ne $$ b $$ \\ne $$ c) and all axial angles different from 90<sup>o</sup>? ",
    "options": [
      "Hexagonal ",
      "Tetragonal ",
      "Triclinic",
      "Monoclinic "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "Triclinic"
  },
  {
    "id": "z1RrQq5oYGmRs6tW3kQxj",
    "question": "A solid having density of 9$$ \\times $$10<sup>3</sup> kg m<sup>–3</sup> forms face centred cubic crystals of edge length $$200\\sqrt 2 $$ pm. What is the molar mass of the solid? \n<br/>[Avogadro constant $$ \\cong $$ 6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>23</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>\n, $$\\pi $$ $$ \\cong $$ 3]",
    "options": [
      "0.0305 kg mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "0.4320 kg mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "0.0216 kg mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "0.0432 kg mol<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "0.0305 kg mol<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "OxpLwNaIXA2zsSLbSVUf3",
    "question": "The radius of the largest sphere which fits properly at the centre of the edge of a body centred cubic unit cell is : (Edge length is represented by 'a')\n",
    "options": [
      "0.134 a ",
      "0.067 a",
      "0.047 a",
      "0.027 a "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "0.067 a"
  },
  {
    "id": "wyh7G1a54VgL5bnYASuQ2",
    "question": "Element 'B' forms ccp structure and 'A' occupies half of the octahedral voids, while oxygen atoms\noccupy all the tetrahedral voids, The structure of bimetallic oxide is :",
    "options": [
      "AB<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>",
      "A<sub>2</sub>BO<sub>4</sub>",
      "A<sub>4</sub>B<sub>2</sub>O",
      "A<sub>2</sub>B<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "AB<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "MKcfd78ZBvcfhSe4eYcLR",
    "question": "10 mL of 1mM surfactant solution forms a\nmonolayer covering 0.24 cm<sup>2</sup> on a polar\nsubstrate. If the polar head is approximated as\ncube, what is its edge length?",
    "options": [
      "1.0 pm",
      "2.0 nm",
      "0.1 nm",
      "2.0 pm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "2.0 pm"
  },
  {
    "id": "0SqfYkLMHfhb6iOnRu3rsa0w2w9jx53m6jc",
    "question": "An element has a face-centred cubic (fcc) structure with a cell edge of $$a$$. The distance between the centres of\ntwo nearest tetrahedral voids in the lattice is :",
    "options": [
      "$$a$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}a$$",
      "$${a \\over 2}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 a$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "$${a \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZARaC3QCRDROhbCrYq3rsa0w2w9jx91dizy",
    "question": "The ratio of number of atoms present in a simple cubic, body centered cubic and face centered cubic\nstructure are, respectively :",
    "options": [
      "8 : 1 : 6",
      "4 : 2 : 1",
      "1 : 2 : 4",
      "4 : 2 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "1 : 2 : 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "qOMDyIOHIAUqZRTApCjgy2xukfjfltlj",
    "question": "A diatomic molecule X<sub>2</sub>\n has a body-centred cubic\n(bcc) structure with a cell edge of 300 pm. The\ndensity of the molecule is 6.17 g cm<sup>–3</sup>. The number\nof molecules present in 200 g of X<sub>2</sub>\n is :\n<br/>(Avogadro constant (N\n<sub>A</sub>) = 6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>23</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>\n)",
    "options": [
      "8 N<sub>A</sub>",
      "40 N<sub>A</sub>",
      "4 N<sub>A</sub>",
      "2 N<sub>A</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "4 N<sub>A</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kryzwoqh",
    "question": "The parameters of the unit cell of a substance are a = 2.5, b = 3.0, c = 4.0, $$\\alpha$$ = 90$$^\\circ$$, $$\\beta$$ = 120$$^\\circ$$, $$\\gamma$$ = 90$$^\\circ$$. The crystal system of the substance is :",
    "options": [
      "Hexagonal ",
      "Orthorhombic",
      "Monoclinic",
      "Triclinic"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "Monoclinic"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w5ekzw",
    "question": "<p>An element X has a body centred cubic (bcc) structure with a cell edge of 200 pm. The density of the element is 5 g cm<sup>$$-$$3</sup>. The number of atoms present in 300 g of the element X is _______________.</p>\n<p>Given : Avogadro constant, N<sub>A</sub> = 6.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>23</sup> mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>.</p>",
    "options": [
      "5 N<sub>A</sub>",
      "6 N<sub>A</sub>",
      "15 N<sub>A</sub>",
      "25 N<sub>A</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "25 N<sub>A</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldulfzjs",
    "question": "<p>A cubic solid is made up of two elements X and Y. Atoms of X are present on every alternate corner and one at the center of cube. Y is at $$\\frac{1}{3}^{\\mathrm{rd}}$$ of the total faces. The empirical formula of the compound is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{{X_2}{Y_{1.5}}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{{X_{3}}{Y_2}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{X{Y_{2.5}}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{{X_{2.5}}Y}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{{X_{3}}{Y_2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnzx8zu",
    "question": "Which of the following expressions is correct in case of a $\\mathrm{CsCl}$ unit cell (edge length 'a')?",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{Cs}^{+}}+\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{Cl}^{-}}=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2} \\mathrm{a}$",
      "$\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{Cs}^{+}}+\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{Cl}^{-}}=\\frac{\\mathrm{a}}{\\sqrt{2}}$",
      "$\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{Cs}^{+}}+\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{Cl}^{-}}=\\mathrm{a}$",
      "$\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{Cs}^{+}}+\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{Cl}^{-}}=\\frac{\\mathrm{a}}{2}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{Cs}^{+}}+\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{Cl}^{-}}=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2} \\mathrm{a}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvukbm1",
    "question": "<p>The correct relationships between unit cell edge length '$$a$$' and radius of sphere '$$r$$' for face-centred and body-centred cubic structures respectively are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$r=2 \\sqrt{2} a$$ and $$\\sqrt{3} r=4 a$$",
      "$$r=2 \\sqrt{2} a$$ and $$4 r=\\sqrt{3} a$$",
      "$$2 \\sqrt{2} r=a$$ and $$\\sqrt{3} r=4 a$$",
      "$$2 \\sqrt{2} r=a$$ and $$4 r=\\sqrt{3} a$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "crystal-structure-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$2 \\sqrt{2} r=a$$ and $$4 r=\\sqrt{3} a$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Da5zXaLzbA2k3L9X",
    "question": "Which type of ‘defect’ has the presence of cations in the interstitial sites?",
    "options": [
      "Metal deficiency defect",
      "Schottky defect",
      "Vacancy defect",
      "Frenkel defect "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "defects-in-crystal",
    "solution": "Frenkel defect "
  },
  {
    "id": "n8ZembVGSa1Dmj83VK7k9k2k5hlfh94",
    "question": "Which of the following compounds is likely to\nshow both Frenkel and Schottky defects in its\ncrystalline form?",
    "options": [
      "CsCl",
      "AgBr",
      "ZnS",
      "KBr"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "defects-in-crystal",
    "solution": "AgBr"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktb5km5o",
    "question": "Given below are two statements.<br/><br/>Statement I : Frenkel defects are vacancy as well as interstitial defects.<br/><br/>Statement II : Frenkel defect leads to colour in ionic solids due to presence of F-centres.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer for the statements from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "defects-in-crystal",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56ai7q7",
    "question": "<p>The incorrect statement about the imperfections in solids is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Schottky defect decreases the density of the substance.",
      "Interstitial defect increases the density of the substance.",
      "Frenkel defect does not alter the density of the substance.",
      "Vacancy defect increases the density of the substance."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "defects-in-crystal",
    "solution": "Vacancy defect increases the density of the substance."
  },
  {
    "id": "EECxyLQjIqV67Nd49Bjgy2xukfp2ui06",
    "question": "An element crystallises in a face-centred cubic (fcc) unit cell with cell edge $$a$$. The distance\nbetween the centres of two nearest octahedral voids in the crystal lattice is :",
    "options": [
      "$$a$$",
      "$${a \\over 2}$$",
      "$${a \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$${\\sqrt 2 a}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "interestitial-voids",
    "solution": "$${a \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "fiIOZ7DHwQC2oWOg",
    "question": "How many unit cells are present in a cubeshaped ideal crystal of NaCl of mass 1.00 g?\n[Atomic masses: Na = 23, Cl = 35.5]",
    "options": [
      "5.14 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>21</sup> unit cells",
      "1.28 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>21</sup> unit cells",
      "1.71 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>21</sup> unit cells",
      "2.57 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>21</sup> unit cells"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "structure-of-ionic-compounds",
    "solution": "2.57 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>21</sup> unit cells"
  },
  {
    "id": "3vtRG37cz0uIYRi9",
    "question": "An ionic compound has a unit cell consisting of A ions at the corners of a cube and B\nions on the centres of the faces of the cube. The empirical formula for this compound\nwould be :",
    "options": [
      "AB",
      "A<sub>2</sub>B ",
      "AB<sub>3 </sub>",
      "A<sub>3</sub>B"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "structure-of-ionic-compounds",
    "solution": "AB<sub>3 </sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "gb6ztaMssnxMD7Av",
    "question": "The edge length of a face centered cubic cell of an ionic substance is 508 pm. If the radius of the\ncation is 110 pm, the radius of the anion is :",
    "options": [
      "288 pm",
      "398 pm",
      "618 pm",
      "144 pm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "structure-of-ionic-compounds",
    "solution": "144 pm"
  },
  {
    "id": "dvTgtXlUwp2Xb8Am",
    "question": "CsCl crystallises in body centred cubic lattice. If ‘a’ is its edge length then which of the following\nexpressions is correct?",
    "options": [
      "$${r_{C{s^ + }}} + {r_{C{l^ - }}} = {{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}a$$",
      "$${r_{C{s^ + }}} + {r_{C{l^ - }}} = {3 \\over 2}a$$ ",
      "$${r_{C{s^ + }}} + {r_{C{l^ - }}} = \\sqrt 3 a$$",
      "$${r_{C{s^ + }}} + {r_{C{l^ - }}} = 3a$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "structure-of-ionic-compounds",
    "solution": "$${r_{C{s^ + }}} + {r_{C{l^ - }}} = {{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}a$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "TswPb2b7XZp6vKRqdxjgy2xukg3e6aw3",
    "question": "A crystal is made up of metal ions 'M<sub>1</sub>' and 'M<sub>2</sub>'\nand oxide ions. Oxide ions form a ccp lattice\nstructure. The cation 'M<sub>1</sub>' occupies 50% of\noctahedral voids and the cation 'M<sub>2</sub>' occupies\n12.5% of tetrahedral voids of oxide lattice. The\noxidation numbers of 'M<sub>1</sub>' and 'M<sub>2</sub>' are,\nrespectively :",
    "options": [
      "+ 3, + 1",
      "+ 4, + 2",
      "+ 1, + 3",
      "+ 2, + 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "structure-of-ionic-compounds",
    "solution": "+ 2, + 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "Q9p2CUSccdOnmyB2",
    "question": "Which of the following exists as covalent crystals in the solid state? ",
    "options": [
      "Silicon ",
      "Sulphur ",
      "Phosphorous ",
      "Iodine "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "type-of-solids-and-their-properties",
    "solution": "Silicon "
  },
  {
    "id": "IBuMPKx3rWORpIDf8hCvp",
    "question": "0.27 g of a long chain fatty acid was dissolved\nin 100 cm<sup>3</sup> of hexane. 10 mL of this solution\nwas added dropwise to the surface of water in\na round watch glass. Hexane evaporates and a\nmonolayer is formed. The distance from edge\nto centre of the watch glass is 10 cm. What is\nthe height of the monolayer?<br/>\n[Density of fatty acid = 0.9 g cm<sup>–3</sup>, $$\\pi $$ = 3]",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>–8</sup> m",
      "10<sup>–2</sup> m",
      "10<sup>–4</sup> m",
      "10<sup>–6</sup> m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "type-of-solids-and-their-properties",
    "solution": "10<sup>–6</sup> m"
  },
  {
    "id": "dqmI96SC2iDG6849831kmm0k74t",
    "question": "A hard substance melts at high temperature and is an insulator in both solid and in molten state. This solid is most likely to be a/an :",
    "options": [
      "Covalent solid",
      "Molecular solid",
      "Ionic solid",
      "Metallic solid"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "type-of-solids-and-their-properties",
    "solution": "Covalent solid"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq5ildk",
    "question": "Given below are two statements. One is labelled as Assertion A nd the other is labelled as Reason R.<br/><br/>Assertion A : Sharp glass edge becomes smooth on heating it upto its melting point.<br/><br/>Reason R : The viscosity of glass decreases on melting.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below. ",
    "options": [
      "A is true but R is false",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is false but R is true.",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "type-of-solids-and-their-properties",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1ihsr8",
    "question": "Select the correct statements<br/><br/>(A) Crystalline solids have long range order.<br/><br/>(B) Crystalline solids are isotropic<br/><br/>(C) Amorphous solid are sometimes called pseudo solids.<br/><br/>(D) Amorphous solids soften over a range of temperatures.<br/><br/>(E) Amorphous solids have a definite heat of fusion.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.",
    "options": [
      "(A), (B), (E) only",
      "(B), (D) only",
      "(C), (D) only",
      "(A), (C), (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solid-state",
    "topic": "type-of-solids-and-their-properties",
    "solution": "(A), (C), (D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "s5aaCHQtyDoQrezp",
    "question": "In a 0.2 molal aqueous solution of a weak acid HX the degree of ionization is 0.3. Taking k<sub>f</sub> for water as 1.85, the freezing point of the solution will be nearest to",
    "options": [
      "-0.360<sup>o</sup>C",
      "-0.260<sup>o</sup>C",
      "+0.480<sup>o</sup>C",
      "-0.480<sup>o</sup>C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "-0.480<sup>o</sup>C"
  },
  {
    "id": "PoXBfP93pWIo259f",
    "question": "If liquids A and B form an ideal solution",
    "options": [
      "the entropy of mixing is zero",
      "the free energy of mixing is zero",
      "the free energy as well as the entropy of mixing are each zero",
      "the enthalpy of mixing is zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "the enthalpy of mixing is zero"
  },
  {
    "id": "vfaGK6GR608F07PE",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is false?",
    "options": [
      "Raoult’s law states that the vapour pressure of a components over a solution is\nproportional to its mole fraction ",
      "Two sucrose solutions of same molality prepared in different solvents will have the same\nfreezing point depression  ",
      "The correct order of osmotic pressure for 0.01 M aqueous solution of each compound is\n BaCl<sub>2</sub> &gt; KCl &gt; CH<sub>3</sub>COOH &gt; sucrose",
      "The osmotic pressure ($$\\pi$$) = MRT, where M is the molarity of the solution "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "Two sucrose solutions of same molality prepared in different solvents will have the same\nfreezing point depression  "
  },
  {
    "id": "IW172Yn1md1CA1iy",
    "question": "Which one of the following aqueous solutions will exhibit highest boiling point? ",
    "options": [
      "0.01 M Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> ",
      "0.015 M glucose",
      "0.015 M urea ",
      "0.01 M KNO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "0.01 M Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "RI2Bv42Km2tBeFSQ",
    "question": "If $$\\alpha$$ is the degree of dissociation of Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, the vant Hoff’s factor (i) used for\ncalculating the molecular mass is :",
    "options": [
      "1 + $$\\alpha$$",
      "1 + $$2\\alpha$$",
      "1 - $$\\alpha$$",
      "1 - $$2\\alpha$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "1 + $$2\\alpha$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "gT9UW738T4wk2zvr",
    "question": "Among the following mixtures, dipole-dipole as the major interaction, is present in ",
    "options": [
      "benzene and ethanol",
      "acetonitrile and acetone ",
      "KCl and water",
      "benzene and carbon tetrachloride"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "acetonitrile and acetone "
  },
  {
    "id": "FNZbeT7PKHNHVm0r",
    "question": "If sodium sulphate is considered to be completely dissociated into cations and anions in aqueous\nsolution, the change in freezing point of water (∆T<sub>f</sub>), when 0.01 mol of sodium sulphate is dissolved\nin 1 kg of water, is (K<sub>f</sub> = 1.86 K kg mol<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "0.0372 K",
      "0.0558 K",
      "0.0744 K",
      "0.0186 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "0.0558 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "UxOAOLB0n6FCdGiW",
    "question": "The degree of dissociation ($$\\alpha$$ ) of a weak electrolyte, A<sub>x</sub>B<sub>y</sub> is related to van’t Hoff factor (i) by the expression :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\alpha  = {{i - 1} \\over {x + y + 1}}$$",
      "$$\\alpha  = {{x + y - 1} \\over {i - 1}}$$",
      "$$\\alpha  = {{x + y + 1} \\over {i - 1}}$$",
      "$$\\alpha  = {{i - 1} \\over {(x + y - 1)}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha  = {{i - 1} \\over {(x + y - 1)}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "9sphxFqRICC6zAqE",
    "question": "K<sub>f</sub> for water is 1.86K kg mol<sup>–1</sup>. If your automobile radiator holds 1.0 kg of water, how many grams of\nethylene glycol (C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) must you add to get the freezing point of the solution lowered to –2.8<sup>o</sup>C ?",
    "options": [
      "72 g",
      "93 g",
      "39 g",
      "27 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "93 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "kaDUZp1Vne9f6oX2",
    "question": "Consider separate solutions of 0.500 M C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH(aq), 0.100 M Mg<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(aq), 0.250 M KBr(aq) and 0.125\nM Na<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>(aq) at 25<sup>o</sup>C. Which statement is true about these solutions, assuming all salts to be strong electrolytes?",
    "options": [
      "0.125 M Na<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>(aq) has the highest osmotic pressure.",
      "0.500 M C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH(aq) has the highest osmotic pressure",
      "They all have the same osmotic pressure",
      "0.100 M Mg<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(aq) has the highest osmotic pressure."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "They all have the same osmotic pressure"
  },
  {
    "id": "mRK2n4zCCX5hpeq9yRRaF",
    "question": "An aqueous solution of a salt MX<sub>2</sub> at certain temperature has a van’t Hoff factor of 2. The degree of dissociation for this solution of the salt is :",
    "options": [
      "0.33",
      "0.50",
      "0.67",
      "0.80"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "0.50"
  },
  {
    "id": "0NrKLjtuON0zWg9M",
    "question": "The freezing point of benzene decreases by 0.45<sup>0</sup>C when 0.2 g of acetic acid is added to 20g of benzene. If\nacetic acid associates to form a dimer in benzene, percentage association of acetic acid in benzene will be:\n(K<sub>f</sub> for benzene = 5.12 K kg mol<sup>–1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "80.4 %",
      "74.6 %",
      "94.6 %",
      "64.6 %"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "94.6 %"
  },
  {
    "id": "H9JnV1FMWZHsTQX4Irz4X",
    "question": "5 g of Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>  was dissolved in x g of H<sub>2</sub>O. The change in freezing point was found to be \n3.82<sup>o</sup>C. If Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>  is 81.5% ionised,\nthe value of x\n<br/><br/>(K<sub>f</sub> for water=1.86<sup>o</sup>C kg mol<sup>−1</sup>) is approximately :\n<br/><br/>(molar mass of S = 32 g mol<sup>−1</sup>  and that of Na = 23 g mol<sup>−1</sup>)\n",
    "options": [
      "15 g",
      "25 g",
      "45 g",
      "65 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "45 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "fCjLdX3ZvP16d4k3",
    "question": "For 1 molal aqueous solution of the following compounds, which one will show the highest freezing\npoint?",
    "options": [
      "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>3</sub> Cl<sub>3</sub>].3H<sub>2</sub>O ",
      "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>] Cl<sub>3</sub>",
      "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>5</sub> Cl] Cl<sub>2</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O",
      "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>4</sub> Cl<sub>2</sub>] Cl.2H<sub>2</sub>O"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "[Co(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>3</sub> Cl<sub>3</sub>].3H<sub>2</sub>O "
  },
  {
    "id": "HCjxAsmCGrVE9z34BSAOB",
    "question": "Molecules of benzoic acid (C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>COOH) dimerise in benzene. 'w' g of the acid dissolved in 30 g of benzene shows a depression in freezing point equal to 2K. If the percentage association of the acid to form dimmer in the solution is 80, then w is – (Its given that K<sub>f</sub> = 5 K kg mol<sup>–1</sup>, Molar mass of benzoic acid = 122 g mol<sup>–1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "1.5 g",
      "1.8 g",
      "1.0 g",
      "2.4 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "2.4 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "vYAPREOHuQqFPnH4gftdv",
    "question": "Molal depression constant for a solvent is\n4.0 kg mol<sup>–1</sup>. The depression in the freezing\npoint of the solvent for 0.03 mol kg<sup>–1</sup> solution\nof K<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> is :<br/>\n(Assume complete dissociation of the\nelectrolyte)",
    "options": [
      "0.18 K",
      "0.24 K",
      "0.36 K",
      "0.12 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "0.36 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "b0PA5RHbPrV9ubW6zma8B",
    "question": "K<sub>2</sub>Hgl<sub>4</sub> is 40% ionised in aqueous solution. The value of its van't Hoff factor (i) is: ",
    "options": [
      "1.6",
      "2.2",
      "2.0",
      "1.8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "1.8"
  },
  {
    "id": "YK46Ml11TsVXbVtuDEFy2",
    "question": "The freezing point of a diluted milk sample is found to be –0.2<sup>o</sup>C, while it should have been –0.5<sup>o</sup>C for pure milk. How much water has been added to pure milk to make the diluted sample?",
    "options": [
      "1 cup of water to 2 cups of pure milk ",
      "2 cups of water to 3 cups of pure milk",
      "3 cups of water to 2 cups of pure milk",
      "1 cup of water to 3 cups of pure milk"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "3 cups of water to 2 cups of pure milk"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krt64s80",
    "question": "Which one of the following 0.06 M aqueous solutions has lowest freezing point?",
    "options": [
      "Al<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>12</sub>O<sub>6</sub>",
      "KI",
      "K<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "Al<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59qkfik",
    "question": "<p>Solute A associates in water. When 0.7 g of solute A is dissolved in 42.0 g of water, it depresses the freezing point by 0.2$$^\\circ$$C. The percentage association of solute A in water, is :</p>\n<p>[Given : Molar mass of A = 93 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. Molal depression constant of water is 1.86 K kg mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>.]</p>",
    "options": [
      "50%",
      "60%",
      "70%",
      "80%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "80%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6e0nxvl",
    "question": "<p>The depression in freezing point observed for a formic acid solution of concentration $$0.5 \\mathrm{~mL} \\mathrm{~L}^{-1}$$ is $$0.0405^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. Density of formic acid is $$1.05 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~mL}^{-1}$$. The Van't Hoff factor of the formic acid solution is nearly : (Given for water $$\\mathrm{k}_{\\mathrm{f}}=1.86\\, \\mathrm{k} \\,\\mathrm{kg}\\,\\mathrm{mol}^{-1}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.8",
      "1.1",
      "1.9",
      "2.4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "1.9"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f64rq1",
    "question": "<p>Two solutions A and B are prepared by dissolving 1 g of non-volatile solutes X and Y, respectively in 1 kg of water. The ratio of depression in freezing points for A and B is found to be 1 : 4. The ratio of molar masses of X and Y is</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 4",
      "1 : 0.25",
      "1 : 0.20",
      "1 : 5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "1 : 0.25"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo9dqg6",
    "question": "Evaluate the following statements for their correctness.\n<br/><br/>\nA. The elevation in boiling point temperature of water will be same for $0.1 \\mathrm{M} \\, \\mathrm{NaCl}$ and $0.1 \\mathrm{M}$ urea.\n<br/><br/>\nB. Azeotropic mixtures boil without change in their composition.\n<br/><br/>\nC. Osmosis always takes place from hypertonic to hypotonic solution.\n<br/><br/>\nD. The density of $32 \\% \\, \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$ solution having molarity $4.09 ~\\mathrm{M}$ is approximately $1.26 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~mL}^{-1}$\n<br/><br/>\nE. A negatively charged sol is obtained when KI solution is added to silver nitrate solution.\n<br/><br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "A, B and D only",
      "A and C only",
      "B and D only",
      "B, D and E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "B and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsd375e",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 607px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 263px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">van't Hoff factor, i</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Cryoscopic constant</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{k_f}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Isotonic solutions</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Solutions with same osmotic pressure</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{\\frac{Normal\\,molar\\,mass}{Abnormal\\,molar\\,mass}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Azeotropes</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Solutions with same composition of vapour above it</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-I, B-III, C-II, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbmfv5f",
    "question": "We have three aqueous solutions of $\\mathrm{NaCl}$ labelled as ' $\\mathrm{A}$ ', ' $\\mathrm{B}$ ' and ' $\\mathrm{C}$ ' with concentration $0.1 \\mathrm{M}$, $0.01 \\mathrm{M}$ and $0.001 \\mathrm{M}$, respectively. The value of van 't Hoff factor(i) for these solutions will be in the order :",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{A}}<\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{C}}<\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{B}}$",
      "$\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{A}}<\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{B}}<\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{C}}$",
      "$\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{A}}>\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{B}}>\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{C}}$",
      "$\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{A}}=\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{B}}=\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{C}}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "abnormal-colligative-property-and-van't-hoff-factor",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{A}}<\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{B}}<\\mathrm{i}_{\\mathrm{C}}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "A5qdxMcm7s6dPyHC",
    "question": "Freezing point of an aqueous solution is (-0.186)<sup>o</sup>C. Elevation of boiling point of the same solution is K<sub>b</sub> = 0.512 <sup>o</sup>C, K<sub>f</sub>  = 1.86 <sup>o</sup>C, find the increase in boiling point. ",
    "options": [
      "0.186 <sup>o</sup>C",
      "0.0512 <sup>o</sup>C",
      "0.092 <sup>o</sup>C",
      "0.2732 <sup>o</sup>C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "depression-in-freezing-point",
    "solution": "0.0512 <sup>o</sup>C"
  },
  {
    "id": "Raghw5Pv8ekP1S85",
    "question": "Equimolar solutions in the same solvent have",
    "options": [
      "Same boiling point but different freezing point",
      "Same freezing point but different boiling point ",
      "Same boiling and same freezing points ",
      "Different boiling and different freezing points"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "depression-in-freezing-point",
    "solution": "Same boiling and same freezing points "
  },
  {
    "id": "Ov2iNZd93pMjbXe6",
    "question": "Ethylene glycol is used as an antifreeze in a cold climate. Mass of ethylene glycol which should be\nadded to 4 kg of water to prevent it from freezing at −6<sup>o</sup>C will be :\n [K<sub>f</sub> for water = 1.86 K kg mol<sup>−1</sup> , and molar mass of ethylene glycol = 62 g mol<sup>−1</sup> )",
    "options": [
      "204.30 g",
      "400.00 g ",
      "304.60 g",
      "804.32 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "depression-in-freezing-point",
    "solution": "804.32 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "uPhJ9fJb3qbYEviqMUKWP",
    "question": "A solution containing 62 g ethylene glycol in 250 g water is cooled to $$-$$ 10<sup>o</sup>C. If K<sub>f</sub> for water is 1.86 K kg mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup> , the amount of water (in g) separated as ice is : ",
    "options": [
      "48",
      "32",
      "64",
      "16"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "depression-in-freezing-point",
    "solution": "64"
  },
  {
    "id": "cLJziJMbqdaggnBOU6H3u",
    "question": "Elevation in the boiling point for 1 molar solution of glucose is 2 K. The depression in the freezing point for 2 molal solution of glucose in the same solvent is 2 K. The relation between K<sub>b</sub> and K<sub>f</sub> is ",
    "options": [
      "K<sub>b</sub> = K<sub>f</sub>",
      "K<sub>b</sub> = 0.5&nbsp;K<sub>f</sub>",
      "K<sub>b</sub> = 1.5&nbsp;K<sub>f</sub>",
      "K<sub>b</sub> = 2&nbsp;K<sub>f</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "depression-in-freezing-point",
    "solution": "K<sub>b</sub> = 2&nbsp;K<sub>f</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "49J2TKThr2kEsCqY1QD6K",
    "question": "Freezing point of a 4% aqueous solution of X is equal to freezing point of 12% aqueous solution of Y. If molecular weight of X is A, then molecular weight of Y is - ",
    "options": [
      "4A",
      "2A",
      "3A",
      "A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "depression-in-freezing-point",
    "solution": "3A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktiereev",
    "question": "Which one of the following 0.10 M aqueous solutions will exhibit the largest freezing point depression?",
    "options": [
      "hydrazine",
      "glucose",
      "glycine",
      "KHSO<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "depression-in-freezing-point",
    "solution": "KHSO<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57r5qly",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : At 10$$^\\circ$$C, the density of a 5 M solution of KCl [atomic masses of K &amp; Cl are 39 &amp; 35.5 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup> respectively], is 'x' g ml<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. The solution is cooled to $$-$$21$$^\\circ$$C. The molality of the solution will remain unchanged.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : The molality of a solution does not change with temperature as mass remains unaffected with temperature.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A).",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false.",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "depression-in-freezing-point",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyg764k",
    "question": "<p>In the depression of freezing point experiment</p>\n<p>A. Vapour pressure of the solution is less than that of pure solvent</p>\n<p>B. Vapour pressure of the solution is more than that of pure solvent</p>\n<p>C. Only solute molecules solidify at the freezing point</p>\n<p>D. Only solvent molecules solidify at the freezing point</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and C only",
      "A only",
      "A and D only",
      "B and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "depression-in-freezing-point",
    "solution": "A and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg7dshs",
    "question": "<p>The solution from the following with highest depression in freezing point/lowest freezing point is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$180 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of acetic acid dissolved in benzene\n",
      "$$180 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of acetic acid dissolved in water\n",
      "$$180 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of benzoic acid dissolved in benzene\n",
      "$$180 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of glucose dissolved in water"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "depression-in-freezing-point",
    "solution": "$$180 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of acetic acid dissolved in water\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgxwd5m",
    "question": "<p>What happens to freezing point of benzene when small quantity of napthalene is added to benzene?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Increases\n",
      "Decreases\n",
      "Remains unchanged\n",
      "First decreases and then increases"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "depression-in-freezing-point",
    "solution": "Decreases\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "ypqtNICb6KEJG2M3",
    "question": "A pressure cooker reduces cooking time for food because",
    "options": [
      "boiling point of water involved in cooking is increased",
      "the higher pressure inside the cooker crushes the food material",
      "cooking involves chemical changes helped by a rise in temperature",
      "heat is more evenly distributed in the cooking space"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "elevation-in-boiling-point",
    "solution": "boiling point of water involved in cooking is increased"
  },
  {
    "id": "tDvmievhAkqfTYyd563rsa0w2w9jx0x7b9s",
    "question": "1 g of a non-volatile non-electrolyte solute is dissolved in 100 g of two different solvents A and B whose\nebullioscopic constants are in the ratio of 1 : 5. The ratio of the elevation in their boiling points, $${{\\Delta {T_b}(A)} \\over {\\Delta {T_b}(B)}}$$, is :",
    "options": [
      "5 : 1",
      "1 : 0.2",
      "10 : 1",
      "1 : 5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "elevation-in-boiling-point",
    "solution": "1 : 5"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jkm033",
    "question": "<p>Boiling point of a $$2 \\%$$ aqueous solution of a non-volatile solute A is equal to the boiling point of $$8 \\%$$ aqueous solution of a non-volatile solute B. The relation between molecular weights of A and B is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{M}_{\\mathrm{A}}=4 \\mathrm{M}_{\\mathrm{B}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{M}_{\\mathrm{B}}=4 \\mathrm{M}_{\\mathrm{A}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{M}_{\\mathrm{A}}=8 \\mathrm{M}_{\\mathrm{B}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{M}_{\\mathrm{B}}=8 \\mathrm{M}_{\\mathrm{A}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "elevation-in-boiling-point",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{M}_{\\mathrm{B}}=4 \\mathrm{M}_{\\mathrm{A}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc54900",
    "question": "<p>A solution of two miscible liquids showing negative deviation from Raoult's law will have :\n</p>",
    "options": [
      "increased vapour pressure, increased boiling point\n",
      "increased vapour pressure, decreased boiling point\n",
      "decreased vapour pressure, decreased boiling point\n",
      "decreased vapour pressure, increased boiling point"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "elevation-in-boiling-point",
    "solution": "decreased vapour pressure, increased boiling point"
  },
  {
    "id": "NRMtCtz0O5hwInS10dGrt",
    "question": "The solubility of N<sub>2</sub> in water at 300 K and 500 torr partial pressure is 0.01 g L<sup>−1</sup>. The solubility (in g L<sup>−1</sup>) at 750 torr partial pressure is :",
    "options": [
      "0.0075",
      "0.015",
      "0.02",
      "0.005"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "henry's-law",
    "solution": "0.015"
  },
  {
    "id": "Gajxr8SuOb34y0PbIcYsL",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements regarding  Henry's law is not correct ? ",
    "options": [
      "Higher the value of K<sub>H</sub> at a given pressure, higher is the solubility of the gas in the liquids",
      "Different gases have different K<sub>H</sub> (Henry's law constant) values at the same temperature.",
      "The partial pressure of the gas in vapour phase is proportional to the mole fraction of the gas in the solution. ",
      "The value of K<sub>H</sub> increases with increase of temperature and K<sub>H</sub> is function of the nature of the gas "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "henry's-law",
    "solution": "Higher the value of K<sub>H</sub> at a given pressure, higher is the solubility of the gas in the liquids"
  },
  {
    "id": "YQsS4xk8jVSK2VUq",
    "question": "A 5.25 % solution of a substance is isotonic with a 1.5% solution of urea (molar mass = 60 g mol<sup>−1</sup>) in\nthe same solvent. If the densities of both the solutions are assumed to be equal to 1.0 g cm<sup>−3</sup>, molar mass of the substance will be ",
    "options": [
      "90.0 g mol<sup>−1</sup>\n ",
      "115.0 g mol<sup>−1</sup>",
      "105.0 g mol<sup>−1</sup>\n ",
      "210.0 g mol<sup>−1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "osmotic-pressure",
    "solution": "210.0 g mol<sup>−1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "VK0aKjIWvKnvDc5DMPTLT",
    "question": "The osmotic pressure of a dilute solution of an\nionic compound XY in water is four times that\nof a solution of 0.01 M BaCl<sub>2</sub> in water.\nAssuming complete dissociation of the given\nionic compounds in water, the concentration of\nXY (in mol L<sup>–1</sup>) in solution is :",
    "options": [
      "4 × 10<sup>–4</sup>",
      "6 × 10<sup>–2</sup>",
      "4 × 10<sup>–2</sup>",
      "16 × 10<sup>–4</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "osmotic-pressure",
    "solution": "6 × 10<sup>–2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "tZRwmMZwPTq9I1Doun3rsa0w2w9jx8yalrl",
    "question": "A solution is prepared by dissolving 0.6 g of urea (molar mass = 60 g mol<sup>–1</sup>) and 1.8 g of glucose (molar\nmass = 180 g mol<sup>–1</sup>) in 100 mL of water at 27<sup>o</sup>C. The osmotic pressure of the solution is :\n<br/>(R = 0.08206 L atm K<sup>–1</sup>\n mol<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "8.2 atm",
      "2.46 atm",
      "4.92 atm",
      "1.64 atm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "osmotic-pressure",
    "solution": "4.92 atm"
  },
  {
    "id": "a74MKCDwo8d8xFT0j0jgy2xukeyapmgh",
    "question": "The size of a raw mango shrinks to a much\nsmaller size when kept in a concentrated salt\nsolution. Which one of the following processes\ncan explain this?",
    "options": [
      "Osmosis",
      "Reverse osmosis",
      "Diffusion",
      "Dialysis"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "osmotic-pressure",
    "solution": "Osmosis"
  },
  {
    "id": "tdNQsECygguVLg9X",
    "question": "In a mixture of A and B, components show negative deviation when :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta V_{mix}$$ &gt; 0, $$\\Delta S_{mix}$$ &gt; 0",
      "$$\\Delta V_{mix}$$ = 0, $$\\Delta S_{mix}$$ &gt; 0",
      "A - B interaction is weaker than A - A and B - B interaction",
      "A - B interaction is stronger than A - A and B - B interaction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "A - B interaction is stronger than A - A and B - B interaction"
  },
  {
    "id": "LWh53htJcfZZITWZ",
    "question": "Which of the following liquid pairs shows a positive deviation from Raoult’s law? ",
    "options": [
      "Water – hydrochloric acid ",
      "Acetone – chloroform",
      "Water – nitric acid ",
      "Benzene – methanol "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "Benzene – methanol "
  },
  {
    "id": "9yNGNtOML1UDdjFp",
    "question": "For which of the following parameters the structural isomers C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH and CH<sub>3</sub>OCH<sub>3</sub> would\nbe expected to have the same values? (Assume ideal behaviour) ",
    "options": [
      "Heat of vaporization ",
      "Gaseous densities at the same temperature and pressure",
      "Boiling points",
      "Vapour pressure at the same temperature "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "Gaseous densities at the same temperature and pressure"
  },
  {
    "id": "1u1t3ZHohgiyEWLX",
    "question": "Benzene and toluene form nearly ideal solutions. At 20 <sup>o</sup>C, the vapour pressure of\nbenzene is 75 torr and that of toluene is 22 torr. The partial vapour pressure of\nbenzene at 20 <sup>o</sup>C for a solution containing 78 g of benzene and 46 g of toluene in\ntorr is ",
    "options": [
      "50",
      "25",
      "53.5",
      "37.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "50"
  },
  {
    "id": "ATPma1d202y7MdTp",
    "question": "18 g of glucose (C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>12</sub>O<sub>6</sub>) is added to 178.2 g of water. The vapour pressure of water for this aqueous solution at 100<sup>o</sup>C is ",
    "options": [
      "759.00 Torr",
      "7.60 Torr",
      "76.00 Torr ",
      "752.40 Torr"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "752.40 Torr"
  },
  {
    "id": "kkM4jRkZl5GzAZIJ",
    "question": "A mixture of ethyl alcohol and propyl alcohol has a vapour pressure of 290 mm at 300 K. The vapour\npressure of propyl alcohol is 200 mm. If the mole fraction of ethyl alcohol is 0.6, its vapour pressure\n(in mm) at the same temperature will be ",
    "options": [
      "360",
      "350",
      "300",
      "700"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "350"
  },
  {
    "id": "ssn7tyGt7YEUBPqG",
    "question": "At 80<sup>o</sup>C, the vapour pressure of pure liquid ‘A’ is 520 mm Hg and that of pure liquid ‘B’ is 1000 mm Hg. If a mixture solution of ‘A’ and ‘B’ boils at 80<sup>o</sup>C and 1 atm pressure, the amount of ‘A’ in the mixture is (1 atm = 760 mm Hg)  ",
    "options": [
      "52 mol percent ",
      "34 mol percent ",
      "48 mol percent",
      "50 mol percent"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "50 mol percent"
  },
  {
    "id": "5uJrBAVb3j7ItlHp",
    "question": "The vapour pressure of water at 20<sup>o</sup>C is 17.5 mm Hg. If 18 g of glucose (C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>12</sub>O<sub>6</sub>) is added to 178.2 g of water at 20<sup>o</sup>C, the vapour pressure of the resulting solution will be ",
    "options": [
      "17.675 mm Hg ",
      "15.750 mm Hg ",
      "16.500 mm Hg ",
      "17.325 mm Hg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "17.325 mm Hg"
  },
  {
    "id": "ILX6KRkuWYKgMWov",
    "question": "A binary liquid solution is prepared by mixing n-heptane and ethanol. Which one of the following\nstatements is correct regarding the behaviour of the solution ? ",
    "options": [
      "The solution formed is an ideal solution ",
      "The solution is non-ideal, showing +ve deviation from Raoult’s law. ",
      "The solution is non-ideal, showing –ve deviation from Raoult’s law. ",
      "n-heptane shows +ve deviation while ethanol shows –ve deviation from Raoult’s law. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "The solution is non-ideal, showing +ve deviation from Raoult’s law. "
  },
  {
    "id": "MyqgZzr0SGZfhccA",
    "question": "Two liquids X and Y form an ideal solution. At 300K, vapour pressure of the solution containing 1 mol\nof X and 3 mol of Y is 550 mm Hg. At the same temperature, if 1 mol of Y is further added to this\nsolution, vapour pressure of the solution increases by 10 mm Hg. Vapour pressure (in mm Hg) of X\nand Y in their pure states will be, respectively : ",
    "options": [
      "200 and 300 ",
      "300 and 400",
      "400 and 600 ",
      "500 and 600 "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "400 and 600 "
  },
  {
    "id": "ixCL3HUWCKtYjHb6",
    "question": "On mixing, heptane and octane form an ideal solution. At 373 K, the vapour pressures of the two\nliquid components (heptane and octane) are 105 kPa and 45 kPa respectively. Vapour pressure of\nthe solution obtained by mixing 25.0g of heptane and 35 g of octane will be (molar mass of heptane = 100 g mol<sup>–1</sup> and of octane = 114 g mol<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "72.0 kPa",
      "36.1 kPa",
      "96.2 kPa",
      "144.5 kPa"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "72.0 kPa"
  },
  {
    "id": "1xgTTVc3tihLuKOr",
    "question": "The vapour pressure of acetone at 20<sup>o</sup>C is 185 torr. When 1.2 g of a non-volatile substance was dissolved in\n100 g of acetone at 20<sup>o</sup>C, its vapour pressure was 183 torr. The molar mass (g mol<sup>-1</sup>) of the substance is:",
    "options": [
      "64",
      "128",
      "488",
      "32"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "64"
  },
  {
    "id": "w3wJEpPsCM8YS4Ez",
    "question": "18 g glucose (C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>12</sub>O<sub>6</sub>) is added to 178.2 g water. The vapor pressure of water (in torr) for this aqueous solution is :",
    "options": [
      "76.0 ",
      "752.4",
      "759.0",
      "7.6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "752.4"
  },
  {
    "id": "RdC7mcDXSuzFMaYlE74U3",
    "question": "A solution is prepared by mixing 8.5 g of CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>  and 11.95 g of CHCl<sub>3</sub> . If vapour pressure of CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>\n and CHCl<sub>3</sub>  at 298 K are 415 and 200 mmHg respectively, the mole fraction of CHCl<sub>3</sub>  in vapour form is : (Molar mass of Cl = 35.5 g mol<sup>−1</sup>)\n",
    "options": [
      "0.162",
      "0.675",
      "0.325",
      "0.486"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "0.325"
  },
  {
    "id": "kN5RXVNCwkUaqSfOsf1BU",
    "question": "Two 5 molal solutions are prepared by dissolving a non-electrolyte non-volatile solute separately in the solvents X and Y. The molecular weights of the solvents are M<sub>x</sub> and M<sub>y</sub>, respectively where M<sub>x</sub> = $${3 \\over 4}$$ My. The relative lowering of vapor pressure of the solution in X is ''m'' times that of the solution in Y. Given that the number of moles of solute is very small in comparison to that of the solvent, the value of ''m'' is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${4 \\over 3}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 4}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "NWznHMOmrbIAE97rJtiNP",
    "question": "The mass of a non-volatile,  non-electrolyte solute (molar mass = 50 g mol<sup>-1</sup> ) needed to be dissolved in 114 g octane to reduce its vapour pressure to 75%, is : ",
    "options": [
      "37.5 g",
      "75 g",
      "150 g",
      "50 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "150 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "KWklP8kxZBhWq5Gzjo3rsa0w2w9jwvebznx",
    "question": "At room temperature, a dilute solution of urea is prepared by dissolving 0.60 of urea in 360 g of water. If the\nvapour pressure of pure water at this temperature is 35 mm Hg, lowering of vapour pressure will be.\n(molar mass of urea = 60 g mol<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "0.031 mmHg",
      "0.017 mmHg",
      "0.028 mmHg",
      "0.027 mmHg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "0.017 mmHg"
  },
  {
    "id": "mNXtgXuZtwdpSC1IG4MfD",
    "question": "Liquid 'M' and liquid 'N' form an ideal solution.\nThe vapour pressures of pure liquids 'M' and\n'N' are 450 and 700 mmHg, respectively, at the\nsame temperature. Then correct statement is:<br/>\n(x<sub>M</sub> = Mole fraction of 'M' in solution ;<br/>\nx<sub>N</sub> = Mole fraction of 'N' in solution ;<br/>\ny<sub>M</sub> = Mole fraction of 'M' in vapour phase ;<br/>\ny<sub>N</sub> = Mole fraction of 'N' in vapour phase)",
    "options": [
      "$${{{x_M}} \\over {{x_N}}} &lt; {{{y_N}} \\over {{y_N}}}$$",
      "(x<sub>M</sub> – y<sub>M</sub>) &lt; (x<sub>N</sub> – y<sub>N</sub>)",
      "$${{{x_M}} \\over {{x_N}}} = {{{y_N}} \\over {{y_N}}}$$",
      "$${{{x_M}} \\over {{x_N}}} &gt; {{{y_M}} \\over {{y_N}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "$${{{x_M}} \\over {{x_N}}} &gt; {{{y_M}} \\over {{y_N}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "adPGBqmHlWclT9dmmDRye",
    "question": "Liquids A and B form an ideal solution in the entire composition range. At 350 K, the vaapor pressures of pure A and pure B are 7 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup> Pa and 12 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup> Pa, respectively . The composition of the vapor in equilibriumwith a solution containing 40 mole percent of A at this temperature is : ",
    "options": [
      "x<sub>A</sub> = 0.76; x<sub>B</sub> = 0.24 ",
      "x<sub>A</sub> = 0.28; x<sub>B</sub> = 0.72",
      "x<sub>A</sub> = 0.4; x<sub>B</sub> = 0.6",
      "x<sub>A</sub> = 0.37; x<sub>B</sub> = 0.63 "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "x<sub>A</sub> = 0.28; x<sub>B</sub> = 0.72"
  },
  {
    "id": "68rmX1zOFSD9AgEzvQ0zB",
    "question": "The vapour pressures of pure liquids A and B are 400 and 600 mmHg, respectively at 298 K on\nmixing the two liquids, the sum of their initial volume is equal ot the volume of the final mixture.\nThe mole fraction of liquid B is 0.5 in the mixture, The vapour pressure of the final solution, the\nmole fractions of components A and B in vapour phase, respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "500 mmHg. 0.5,0.5",
      "500 mmHg, 0.4, 0.6",
      "450 mmHg, 0.4,0.6",
      "450 mmHg.0.5,0.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "500 mmHg, 0.4, 0.6"
  },
  {
    "id": "GBalW0AFVltmUIkzbr7k9k2k5dyrz4h",
    "question": "At 35<sup>o</sup>C, the vapour pressure of CS<sub>2</sub>\n is 512 mm. Hg and that of acetone is 344 mm Hg. A solution\nof CS<sub>2</sub>\n in acetone has a total vapour pressure of 600 mm Hg. The false statement amongst the\nfollowing is :",
    "options": [
      "CS<sub>2</sub> and acetone are less attracted to each other than to themselves.",
      "a mixture of 100 ml. CS<sub>2</sub> and 100 ml. acetone has a volume &lt; 200 ml.",
      "Heat must be absorved in order to produce the solution 35<sup>o</sup>C",
      "Raoult's law is not obeyed by this system."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "a mixture of 100 ml. CS<sub>2</sub> and 100 ml. acetone has a volume &lt; 200 ml."
  },
  {
    "id": "ScWeujDIfg1TcG9q6G7k9k2k5epvacb",
    "question": "Two open beakers one containing a solvent and the other containing a mixture of that solvent\nwith a non voltatile solute are together selated in a container. Over time :\n",
    "options": [
      "The volume of the solution increases and the volume of the solvent decreases.",
      "The volume of solution does not change and the volume of the solvent decreases.",
      "The volumer of the solution and the solvent does not change.",
      "The volume of the solution decreases and the volume of the solvent increases.\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "The volume of the solution increases and the volume of the solvent decreases."
  },
  {
    "id": "tTBo7z5xTZntIy4s7Hjgy2xukg3f2u1b",
    "question": "A set of solutions is prepared using 180 g of\nwater as a solvent and 10 g of different nonvolatile solutes A, B and C. The relative\nlowering of vapour pressure in the presence of\nthese solutes are in the order :<br/><br/>[Given, molar\nmass of A = 100 g mol<sup>–1</sup>; B = 200 g mol<sup>–1</sup>;\nC = 10,000 g mol<sup>–1</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "A &gt; C &gt; B",
      "C &gt; B &gt; A",
      "A &gt; B &gt; C",
      "B &gt; C &gt; A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "A &gt; B &gt; C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsygi7r",
    "question": "<p>What weight of glucose must be dissolved in $$100 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of water to lower the vapour pressure by $$0.20 \\mathrm{~mm} ~\\mathrm{Hg}$$ ?</p>\n<p>(Assume dilute solution is being formed)</p>\n<p>Given : Vapour pressure of pure water is $$54.2 \\mathrm{~mm} ~\\mathrm{Hg}$$ at room temperature. Molar mass of glucose is $$180 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "3.69 g",
      "2.59 g",
      "3.59 g",
      "4.69 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "3.69 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse76yow",
    "question": "<p>Identify the mixture that shows positive deviations from Raoult's Law</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left(\\mathrm{CH}_3\\right)_2 \\mathrm{CO}+\\mathrm{CS}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\mathrm{CH}_3\\right)_2 \\mathrm{CO}+\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_5 \\mathrm{NH}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CHCl}_3+\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_6$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{CHCl}_3+\\left(\\mathrm{CH}_3\\right)_2 \\mathrm{CO}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "solutions",
    "topic": "relative-lowering-of-vapour-pressure-and-roult’s-law",
    "solution": "$$\\left(\\mathrm{CH}_3\\right)_2 \\mathrm{CO}+\\mathrm{CS}_2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "4XWEvDZgov05rNf5",
    "question": "With increase of temperature, which of these changes?",
    "options": [
      "molality",
      "weight fraction of solute",
      "molarity",
      "mole fraction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "molarity"
  },
  {
    "id": "FxfDS88oxZ3iAqZ1",
    "question": "25 ml of a solution of barium hydroxide on titration with a 0.1 molar solution of hydrochloric acid gave a litre value of 35 ml. The molarity of barium hydroxide solution was",
    "options": [
      "0.14",
      "0.28",
      "0.35",
      "0.07"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "0.07"
  },
  {
    "id": "JLmhW0rwv9npaRo3",
    "question": "To neutralise completely 20 mL of 0.1 M aqueous solution of phosphorous acid (H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>3</sub>), the volume of 0.1 M aqueous KOH solution required is",
    "options": [
      "40 mL",
      "20 mL",
      "10 mL",
      "60 mL"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "40 mL"
  },
  {
    "id": "QjmzkdZvdbblx3Fb",
    "question": "6.02 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>20</sup> molecules of urea are present in 100 ml of its solution. The concentration of urea solution is <br/>(Avogadro constant, N<sub>A</sub> = 6.02 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>23</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "0.02 M",
      "0.01 M",
      "0.001 M",
      "0.1 M"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "0.01 M"
  },
  {
    "id": "QB3J5rvjWKHvWeza",
    "question": "Two solutions of a substance (non electrolyte) are mixed in the following manner. 480 ml of 1.5 M first solution + 520 ml of 1.2 M second solution. What is the molarity of the final mixture?",
    "options": [
      "2.70 M",
      "1.344 M",
      "1.50 M",
      "1.20 M"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "1.344 M"
  },
  {
    "id": "pWjKxtlz0I5ydHDJ",
    "question": "Density of a 2.05M solution of acetic acid in water is 1.02 g/mL The molality of the solution is",
    "options": [
      "2.28 mol kg<sup>-1</sup>",
      "0.44 mol kg<sup>-1</sup>",
      "1.14 mol kg<sup>-1</sup>",
      "3.28 mol kg<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "2.28 mol kg<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "844sUB4RFISSFOXR",
    "question": "The density (in g mL<sup>-1</sup>) of a 3.60 M sulphuric acid solution that is 29% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> (molar mass = 98 g mol<sup>-1</sup>) by mass will be",
    "options": [
      "1.45",
      "1.64",
      "1.88",
      "1.22"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "1.22"
  },
  {
    "id": "x4Gyy58dmTWLt229",
    "question": "A 5.2 molal aqueous solution of methyl alcohol, CH<sub>3</sub>OH, is supplied. What is the mole fraction of methyl\nalcohol in the solution ?",
    "options": [
      "0.190",
      "0.086",
      "0.050",
      "0.100"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "0.086"
  },
  {
    "id": "gxeMWkrz1ZAzgkNf",
    "question": "The density of a solution prepared by dissolving 120 g of urea (mol. Mass = 60 u ) in 1000g of water is\n1.15 g/mL. The molarity of this solution is :",
    "options": [
      "0.50 M",
      "1.78 M",
      "1.02 M",
      "2.05 M"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "2.05 M"
  },
  {
    "id": "3ERrWbhv3mTCxxp8",
    "question": "The molarity of a solution obtained by mixing 750 mL of 0.5 (M) HCl with 250 mL of 2(M) HCl will be: ",
    "options": [
      "1.00 M",
      "1. 75 M ",
      "0.975 M ",
      "0.875 M"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "0.875 M"
  },
  {
    "id": "PVKotErnxHw0lyKaAF2oI",
    "question": "Excess of NaOH (aq) was added to 100 mL of FeCl<sub>3</sub>  (aq) resulting into 2.14 g of Fe(OH)<sub>3</sub> . The molarity of FeCl<sub>3</sub> (aq) is :\n<br/><br/>(Given molar mass of Fe = 56 g mol<sup>−1</sup>  and molar mass of Cl = 35.5 g mol<sub>−1</sub>)\n",
    "options": [
      "0.2 M",
      "03 M",
      "0.6 M",
      "1.8 M"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "0.2 M"
  },
  {
    "id": "K9SYpSYXNXvIRgks",
    "question": "The ratio of mass percent of C and H of an organic compound (C<sub>X</sub>H<sub>Y</sub>O<sub>Z</sub>) is 6 : 1. If one molecule of the above compound (C<sub>X</sub>H<sub>Y</sub>O<sub>Z</sub>) contains half as much oxygen as required to burn one molecule of compound C<sub>X</sub>H<sub>Y</sub> completely to CO<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>O. The empirical formula of compound C<sub>X</sub>H<sub>Y</sub>O<sub>Z</sub> is ",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>6</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
      "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub>O",
      "C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>4</sub>O<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub>O<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Y43xWlFoQQdJAQFKzvGzu",
    "question": "A solution of sodium sulphate contains 92 g of Na<sup>+</sup> ions per kilogram of water. The molality of Na<sup>+</sup> ions in that solution in mol kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup> is : ",
    "options": [
      "12",
      "4",
      "8",
      "16"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "u0OEQcFRPlqr9tiY883rsa0w2w9jx4rwcfo",
    "question": "The mole fraction of a solvent in aqueous solution of a solute is 0.8. The molality (in mol kg<sup>–1</sup>\n) of the\naqueous solution is :",
    "options": [
      "13.88 × 10<sup>–1</sup>",
      "13.88 × 10<sup>–3</sup>",
      "13.88",
      "13.88 × 10<sup>–2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "13.88"
  },
  {
    "id": "ov1PKjoChpAPDQ3efSBqx",
    "question": "What would be the molality of 20% (mass/\nmass) aqueous solution of KI?<br/>\n(molar mass of KI = 166 g mol<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "1.51",
      "1.35",
      "1.08",
      "1.48"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "1.51"
  },
  {
    "id": "bKxsooNQMecIGrtOBKQyP",
    "question": "8 g of NaOH is dissolved in 18g of H<sub>2</sub>O. Mole fraction of NaOH in solution and molality (in mol kg<sup>–1</sup>) of the solution respectively are - ",
    "options": [
      "0.2, 11.11",
      "0.167, 22.20",
      "0.167, 11.11",
      "0.2, 22.20"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "0.167, 11.11"
  },
  {
    "id": "rlNzEv7uCwtb5vrmG7L1P",
    "question": "25 ml of the given HCl solution requires 30 mL of 0.1 M sodium carbonate solution. What is the volume of this HCl solution required to titrate 30 mL of 0.2 M aqueous NaOH solutions ?",
    "options": [
      "50 mL",
      "12.5 mL",
      "25 mL",
      "75 mL"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "25 mL"
  },
  {
    "id": "hFSv53q3s7OTcGsqIre6r",
    "question": "The amount of sugar (C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>22</sub>O<sub>11</sub>) required to prepare 2L of its 0.1 M aqueous solution is : ",
    "options": [
      "17.1 g",
      "34.2 g",
      "68.4 g",
      "136.8 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "68.4 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "z0nMxb9i873GWe6YLXjgy2xukft5pysc",
    "question": "A solution of two components containing\nn<sub>1</sub> moles of the 1<sup>st</sup> component and n<sub>2</sub> moles of\nthe 2<sup>nd</sup> component is prepared. M<sub>1</sub> and M<sub>2</sub> are\nthe molecular weights of component 1 and 2\nrespectively. If d is the density of the solution\nin g mL<sup>–1</sup>, C<sub>2</sub> is the molarity and x<sub>2</sub> is the mole\nfraction of the 2<sup>nd</sup> component, then C<sub>2</sub> can be\nexpressed as :",
    "options": [
      "$${C_2} = {{1000{x_2}} \\over {{M_1} + {x_2}\\left( {{M_2} - {M_1}} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${C_2} = {{1000d{x_2}} \\over {{M_1} + {x_2}\\left( {{M_2} - {M_1}} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${C_2} = {{d{x_2}} \\over {{M_1} + {x_2}\\left( {{M_2} - {M_1}} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${C_2} = {{d{x_1}} \\over {{M_1} + {x_2}\\left( {{M_2} - {M_1}} \\right)}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "$${C_2} = {{1000d{x_2}} \\over {{M_1} + {x_2}\\left( {{M_2} - {M_1}} \\right)}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "uD0F9CX0Jww3HxCYiLjgy2xukf3hha1o",
    "question": "The strengths of 5.6 volume hydrogen peroxide\n(of density 1 g/mL) in terms of mass percentage\nand molarity (M), respectively, are:\n(Take molar mass of hydrogen peroxide as\n34 g/mol)",
    "options": [
      "0.85 and 0.5",
      "0.85 and 0.25",
      "1.7 and 0.25",
      "1.7 and 0.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "1.7 and 0.5"
  },
  {
    "id": "LnmES6OKMekV2y3cOn1kmitgbw3",
    "question": "The exact volumes of 1 M NaOH solution required to neutralise 50 mL of 1 M H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>3</sub> solution and 100 mL of 2 M H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>2</sub> solution, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "100 mL and 50 mL",
      "100 mL and 200 mL",
      "100 mL and 100 mL",
      "50 mL and 50 mL"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "100 mL and 200 mL"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58da0zj",
    "question": "<p>A commercially sold conc. HCl is 35% HCl by mass. If the density of this commercial acid is 1.46 g/mL, the molarity of this solution is:</p>\n<p>(Atomic mass : Cl = 35.5 amu, H = 1 amu)</p>",
    "options": [
      "10.2 M",
      "12.5 M",
      "14.0 M",
      "18.2 M"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "14.0 M"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6e0ioba",
    "question": "<p>$$\\mathrm{SO}_{2} \\mathrm{Cl}_{2}$$ on reaction with excess of water results into acidic mixture</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{SO}_{2} \\mathrm{Cl}_{2}+2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}+2 \\mathrm{HCl}$$</p>\n<p>16 moles of $$\\mathrm{NaOH}$$ is required for the complete neutralisation of the resultant acidic mixture. The number of moles of $$\\mathrm{SO}_{2} \\mathrm{Cl}_{2}$$ used is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "16",
      "8",
      "4",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jk7xj0",
    "question": "<p>$$250 \\mathrm{~g}$$ solution of $$\\mathrm{D}$$-glucose in water contains $$10.8 \\%$$ of carbon by weight. The molality of the solution is nearest to</p>\n<p>(Given: Atomic Weights are, $$\\mathrm{H}, 1 \\,\\mathrm{u} ; \\mathrm{C}, 12 \\,\\mathrm{u} ; \\mathrm{O}, 16 \\,\\mathrm{u}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.03",
      "2.06",
      "3.09",
      "5.40"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "2.06"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqxivpf",
    "question": "$1 \\mathrm{~L}, 0.02 \\mathrm{M}$ solution of $\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{5} \\mathrm{SO}_{4}\\right]$ Br is mixed with $1 \\mathrm{~L}, 0.02 \\mathrm{M}$ solution of $\\left[\\mathrm{Co}\\left(\\mathrm{NH}_{3}\\right)_{5} \\mathrm{Br}\\right] \\mathrm{SO}_{4}$. The resulting solution is divided into two equal parts $(\\mathrm{X})$ and treated with excess of $\\mathrm{AgNO}_{3}$ solution and $\\mathrm{BaCl}_{2}$ solution respectively as shown below:\n<br/><br/>\n$1 \\mathrm{~L}$ Solution $(\\mathrm{X})+\\mathrm{AgNO}_{3}$ solution (excess) $\\longrightarrow \\mathrm{Y}$\n<br/><br/>\n$1 \\mathrm{~L}$ Solution $(\\mathrm{X})+\\mathrm{BaCl}_{2}$ solution (excess) $\\longrightarrow \\mathrm{Z}$\n<br/><br/>\nThe number of moles of $\\mathrm{Y}$ and $\\mathrm{Z}$ respectively are",
    "options": [
      "$0 .01,0.01$",
      "$0.01,0.02$",
      "$0.02,0.01$",
      "$0.02,0.02$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "$0 .01,0.01$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldu0fnza",
    "question": "<p>What is the mass ratio of ethylene glycol ($$\\mathrm{C_2H_6O_2}$$, molar mass = 62 g/mol) required for making 500 g of 0.25 molal aqueous solution and 250 mL of 0.25 molar aqueous solution?</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 2",
      "1 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "3 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldukrf6s",
    "question": "<p>'25 volume' hydrogen peroxide means</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 L marketed solution contains 75 g of H$$_2$$O$$_2$$.",
      "1 L marketed solution contains 250 g of H$$_2$$O$$_2$$.",
      "1 L marketed solution contains 25 g of H$$_2$$O$$_2$$.",
      "100 mL marketed solution contains 25 g of H$$_2$$O$$_2$$."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "1 L marketed solution contains 75 g of H$$_2$$O$$_2$$."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsyhrki",
    "question": "<p>A solution is prepared by adding $$2 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of \"$$\\mathrm{X}$$\" to 1 mole of water. Mass percent of \"$$\\mathrm{X}$$\" in the solution is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "20%",
      "10%",
      "2%",
      "5%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "10%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvu3ogf",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A : $$3.1500 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of hydrated oxalic acid dissolved in water to make $$250.0 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ solution will result in $$0.1 \\mathrm{~M}$$ oxalic acid solution.</p>\n<p>Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$ : Molar mass of hydrated oxalic acid is $$126 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is false but R is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh32l8lw",
    "question": "<p>The volume of $$0.02 ~\\mathrm{M}$$ aqueous $$\\mathrm{HBr}$$ required to neutralize $$10.0 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ of $$0.01 ~\\mathrm{M}$$ aqueous $$\\mathrm{Ba}(\\mathrm{OH})_{2}$$ is (Assume complete neutralization)</p>",
    "options": [
      "7.5 mL",
      "5.0 mL",
      "10.0 mL",
      "2.5 mL"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "10.0 mL"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscryk9k",
    "question": "<p>The quantity which changes with temperature is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Molality",
      "Molarity",
      "Mole fraction",
      "Mass percentage"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "Molarity"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg7jd5s",
    "question": "<p>If a substance '$$A$$' dissolves in solution of a mixture of '$$B$$' and '$$C$$' with their respective number of moles as $$\\mathrm{n}_{\\mathrm{A}}, \\mathrm{n}_{\\mathrm{B}}$$ and $$\\mathrm{n}_{\\mathrm{C}_3}$$. Mole fraction of $$\\mathrm{C}$$ in the solution is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{n_C}{n_A \\times n_B \\times n_C}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{n_B}{n_A+n_B}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{n_C}{n_A+n_B+n_C}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{n_C}{n_A-n_B-n_C}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{n_C}{n_A+n_B+n_C}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vyqoa",
    "question": "<p>The Molarity (M) of an aqueous solution containing $$5.85 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of $$\\mathrm{NaCl}$$ in $$500 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ water is : (Given : Molar Mass $$\\mathrm{Na}: 23$$ and $$\\mathrm{Cl}: 35.5 \\mathrm{~gmol}^{-1}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "20",
      "4",
      "2",
      "0.2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "0.2"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2a2bp",
    "question": "<p>Molality $$(\\mathrm{m})$$ of $$3 \\mathrm{M}$$ aqueous solution of $$\\mathrm{NaCl}$$ is :\n(Given : Density of solution $$=1.25 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~mL}^{-1}$$, Molar mass in $$\\mathrm{g} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}: \\mathrm{Na}-23, \\mathrm{Cl}-35.5$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.90 m",
      "3.85 m",
      "1.90 m",
      "2.79 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "2.79 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57i4m",
    "question": "<p>The density of '$$x$$' $$\\mathrm{M}$$ solution ('$$x$$' molar) of $$\\mathrm{NaOH}$$ is $$1.12 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~mL}^{-1}$$, while in molality, the concentration of the solution is $$3 \\mathrm{~m}$$ ( 3 molal). Then $$x$$ is</p>\n<p>(Given : Molar mass of $$\\mathrm{NaOH}$$ is $$40 \\mathrm{~g} / \\mathrm{mol}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "3.8",
      "3.0",
      "3.5",
      "2.8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "concentration-terms",
    "solution": "3.0"
  },
  {
    "id": "29zPo9XaMdIFlyBJ",
    "question": "What volume of hydrogen gas at 273 K and 1 atm pressure will be consumed in obtaining 21.6 g of elemental boron (atomic mass = 10.8) from the reduction of boron trichloride by hydrogen?",
    "options": [
      "67.2 L",
      "44.8 L",
      "22.4 L",
      "89.6 L"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "laws-of-chemical-combination",
    "solution": "67.2 L"
  },
  {
    "id": "scr2lDOm0WB6sdIf",
    "question": "The ammonia evolved from the treatment of 0.30 g of an organic compound for the estimation of nitrogen was passed in 100 mL of 0.1 M sulphuric acid. The excess of acid required 20 mL of 0.5 M sodium hydroxide solution for complete neutralization. The organic compound is",
    "options": [
      "urea",
      "benzamide",
      "acetamide",
      "thiourea"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "laws-of-chemical-combination",
    "solution": "urea"
  },
  {
    "id": "iFOCpvHDjmR9VR1X",
    "question": "The ratio of masses of oxygen and nitrogen in a particular gaseous mixture is 1 : 4. The ratio of number of\ntheir molecule is:",
    "options": [
      "1: 8",
      "3 : 16",
      "1 : 4",
      "7 : 32"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "laws-of-chemical-combination",
    "solution": "7 : 32"
  },
  {
    "id": "bdKhAnBfK4pYimHvgfLID",
    "question": "What quantity (in mL) of a 45% acid solution of a mono-protic strong acid must\nbe mixed with a 20% solution of the same acid to produce 800 mL of a 29.875% acid\nsolution ?\n",
    "options": [
      "320",
      "325",
      "316",
      "330"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "laws-of-chemical-combination",
    "solution": "316"
  },
  {
    "id": "IrGVkdxwdeaOjVy1IFsWX",
    "question": "A 10 mg effervescent tablet containing sodium bicarbonate and oxalic acid releases 0.25 ml of CO<sub>2</sub> at T = 298.15 K and p = 1 bar. If molar volume of CO<sub>2</sub> is 25.0 L under such condition, what is the percentage of sodium bicarbonate in each tablet ? \n<br/>[Molar mass of NaHCO<sub>3</sub> = 84 g mol<sup>–1</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "33.6",
      "0.84",
      "8.4",
      "16.8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "laws-of-chemical-combination",
    "solution": "8.4"
  },
  {
    "id": "Bd3kIn7RoGOVqmZN4C7k9k2k5dymla5",
    "question": "Amongst the following statements, that which was not proposed by Dalton was :",
    "options": [
      "Matter consists of indivisible atoms all the atoms of a given element have.",
      "Chemical reactions involve reorganization of atoms. These are neither created not destroyed in\na chemical reaction.",
      "When gases combine or reproduced in a chemical reactionn they do so in a simple ratio by\nvolume provided all gases are the same T &amp; P.",
      "Identical properties including identical mass. Atoms of differemt element differ in mass."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "laws-of-chemical-combination",
    "solution": "When gases combine or reproduced in a chemical reactionn they do so in a simple ratio by\nvolume provided all gases are the same T &amp; P."
  },
  {
    "id": "uJ7wL8tXgwpjQUwj",
    "question": "Number of atoms in 558.5 gram Fe (at. wt. of Fe = 55.85 g mol<sup>-1</sup>) is",
    "options": [
      "twice that in 60 g carbon",
      "6.023 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>22</sup>",
      "half that in 8 g He",
      "558.5 $$\\times$$ 6.023 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>23</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "twice that in 60 g carbon"
  },
  {
    "id": "QzGotHLXODpQD9r6",
    "question": "If we consider that 1/6, in place of 1/12, mass of carbon atom is taken to be the relative atomic mass unit, the mass of one mole of the substance will ",
    "options": [
      "be a function of the molecular mass of the substance",
      "remain unchanged",
      "increase two fold",
      "decrease twice"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "decrease twice"
  },
  {
    "id": "ml8U6CMJWDAl2xLH",
    "question": "How many moles of magnesium phosphate Mg<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub> will contain 0.25 mole of oxygen atoms?",
    "options": [
      "1.25 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup>",
      "2.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup>",
      "0.02",
      "3.125 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "3.125 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "2Gh7pyD2S4Crb8fq",
    "question": "In the reaction<br/><br/>\n2Al(s) + 6HCl(aq)  $$\\to$$ 2Al<sup>3+</sup> (aq) + 6Cl<sup>-</sup>(aq) + 3H<sub>2</sub>(g)",
    "options": [
      "11.2 L H<sub>2</sub>(g) at STP is produced for every mole HCl(aq)  consumed",
      "6 L HCl(aq) is consumed for every 3L H<sub>2</sub>(g) produced",
      "33.6 L H<sub>2</sub>(g) is produced regardless of temperature and pressure for every mole that reacts",
      "67.2 H<sub>2</sub>(g) at STP is produced for every mole Al that reacts"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "11.2 L H<sub>2</sub>(g) at STP is produced for every mole HCl(aq)  consumed"
  },
  {
    "id": "uFDqfbIrxOPsFFmR",
    "question": "The molecular formula of a commercial resin used for exchanging ions in water softening is\nC<sub>8</sub>H<sub>7</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>Na (Mol. Wt. 206). What would be the maximum uptake of Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions by the resin when expressed in mole per gram resin?",
    "options": [
      "2/309",
      "1/412",
      "1/103",
      "1/206"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "1/412"
  },
  {
    "id": "ywVAkLfCch5kY2EFQiWDH",
    "question": "The amount of arsenic pentasulphide that can be obtained when 35.5 g arsenic acid istreated with excess H<sub>2</sub>S in the presence of conc. HCl ( assuming 100% conversion) is :",
    "options": [
      "0.50 mol ",
      "0.25 mol",
      "0.125 mol",
      "0.333 mol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "0.125 mol"
  },
  {
    "id": "BqSFClk0IVTCYAg3sNptI",
    "question": "An organic compound contains C, H and S. The minimum molecular weight of the\ncompound containing 8% sulphur is : \n<br/><br/>(atomic weight of S = 32 amu)\n",
    "options": [
      "200 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "400 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "600 g mol<sup>−1</sup>",
      "300 g mol<sup>−1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "400 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "7CF58UDFv4yg0OcG",
    "question": "1 gram of a carbonate (M<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>) on treatment with excess HCl produces 0.01186 mole of CO<sub>2</sub>. The molar mass of M<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> in g mol<sup>–1</sup> is:",
    "options": [
      "84.3",
      "118.6",
      "11.86",
      "1186"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "84.3"
  },
  {
    "id": "c1FL4mkVPUwV7MZv",
    "question": "The most abundant elements by mass in the body of a healthy human adult are: Oxygen (61.4%); Carbon\n(22.9%), Hydrogen (10.0%); and Nitrogen (2.6%). The weight which a 75 kg person would gain if all\n<sup>1</sup>H atoms are replaced by <sup>2</sup>H atoms is: ",
    "options": [
      "37.5 kg",
      "7.5 kg",
      "10 kg",
      "15 kg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "7.5 kg"
  },
  {
    "id": "Rf6DaryHU6CH252RHY4bG",
    "question": "A sample of $$NaCl{O_3}$$ is converted by heat to $$NaCl$$ with a loss of $$0.16$$ $$g$$ of oxygen. The residue is dissolved in water and precipitated as $$AgCl.$$ The mass of $$AgCl$$ (in $$g$$) obtained will be : (Given : Molar mass of $$AgCl=143.5$$ $$g$$ $$mo{l^{ - 1}}$$)",
    "options": [
      "$$0.35$$ ",
      "$$0.41$$ ",
      "$$0.48$$ ",
      "$$0.54$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "$$0.48$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "4R8sj0h5Qd1wYZP3QAxlC",
    "question": "An organic compound is estimated through Duma's method and was found to evolve 6 moles of CO<sub>2</sub>. 4 moles of H<sub>2</sub>O and 1 mole of nitrogen gas. The formula of the compound is : ",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>8</sub>N",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>8</sub>N<sub>2</sub>",
      "C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>8</sub>N",
      "C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>8</sub>N<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>8</sub>N<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "qkiVs9dLdkXLEkkmNV3rsa0w2w9jx0xkpa8",
    "question": "The minimum amount of O<sub>2</sub>(g) consumed per gram of reactant is for the reaction : <br/>(Given atomic mass : Fe =\n56, O = 16, Mg = 24, P = 31, C = 12, H = 1)\n",
    "options": [
      "4Fe(s) + 3O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 2Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>(s)",
      "P<sub>4</sub>(s) + 5O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ P<sub>4</sub>O<sub>10</sub>(s)",
      "C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>8</sub>(g) + 5O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 3CO<sub>2</sub>(g) + 4H<sub>2</sub>O(l)",
      "2Mg(s) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 2MgO(s)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "4Fe(s) + 3O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 2Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>(s)"
  },
  {
    "id": "YaKfwPtJcpsSzoQMmN3rsa0w2w9jx55sska",
    "question": "5 moles of AB<sub>2</sub> weigh 125 × 10<sup>–3</sup>\n kg and 10 moles of A<sub>2</sub>B<sub>2</sub> weigh 300 × 10<sup>–3</sup>\n kg. The molar mass of A (M<sub>A</sub>)\nand molar mass of B (M<sub>B</sub>) in kg mol are:\n",
    "options": [
      "M<sub>A</sub> = 10 × 10<sup>–3</sup>\n and M<sub>B</sub> = 5 × 10<sup>–3</sup>",
      "M<sub>A</sub> = 25 × 10<sup>–3</sup>\n and M<sub>B</sub> = 50 × 10<sup>–3</sup>",
      "M<sub>A</sub> = 5 × 10<sup>–3</sup>\n and M<sub>B</sub> = 10 × 10<sup>–3</sup>",
      "M<sub>A</sub> = 50 × 10<sup>–3</sup>\n and M<sub>B</sub> = 25 × 10<sup>–3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "M<sub>A</sub> = 5 × 10<sup>–3</sup>\n and M<sub>B</sub> = 10 × 10<sup>–3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "7avp27bvbIPAKIwj1E3rsa0w2w9jx82nf67",
    "question": "25 g of an unknown hydrocarbon upon burning produces 88 g of CO<sub>2</sub> and 9 g of H<sub>2</sub>O. This unknown\nhydrocarbon contains :",
    "options": [
      "18 g of carbon and 7 g of hydrogen",
      "20 g of carbon and 5 g of hydrogen",
      "22 g of carbon and 3 g of hydrogen",
      "24 g of carbon and 1 g of hydrogen"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "24 g of carbon and 1 g of hydrogen"
  },
  {
    "id": "ytuTg6iZ987Ftn1rt6jgy2xukg3dv83p",
    "question": "The average molar mass of chlorine is\n35.5 g mol<sup>–1</sup>. The ratio of <sup>35</sup>Cl to <sup>37</sup>Cl in naturally\noccuring chlorine is close to :",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "3 : 1",
      "4 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "3 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i4ah7e",
    "question": "<p>Hemoglobin contains $$0.34 \\%$$ of iron by mass. The number of Fe atoms in $$3.3 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of hemoglobin is</p>\n<p>(Given: Atomic mass of Fe is $$56 \\,\\mathrm{u}, \\mathrm{N}_{\\mathrm{A}}=6.022 \\times 10^{23} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$.)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1.21 \\times 10^{5}$$",
      "$$12.0 \\times 10^{16}$$",
      "$$1.21 \\times 10^{20}$$",
      "$$3.4 \\times 10^{22}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "$$1.21 \\times 10^{20}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jm83xp",
    "question": "<p>In Carius method of estimation of halogen, $$0.45 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of an organic compound gave $$0.36 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of $$\\mathrm{AgBr}$$. Find out the percentage of bromine in the compound.</p>\n<p>(Molar masses : $$\\mathrm{AgBr}=188 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1} ; \\mathrm{Br}=80 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "34.04%",
      "40.04%",
      "36.03%",
      "38.04%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "34.04%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rj54no",
    "question": "<p>Consider the reaction</p>\n<p>$$4 \\mathrm{HNO}_{3}(1)+3 \\mathrm{KCl}(\\mathrm{s}) \\rightarrow \\mathrm{Cl}_{2}(\\mathrm{~g})+\\mathrm{NOCl}(\\mathrm{g})+2 \\mathrm{H}_{2} \\mathrm{O}(\\mathrm{g})+3 \\mathrm{KNO}_{3}(\\mathrm{~s})$$</p>\n<p>The amount of $$\\mathrm{HNO}_{3}$$ required to produce $$110.0 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of $$\\mathrm{KNO}_{3}$$ is</p>\n<p>(Given: Atomic masses of $$\\mathrm{H}, \\mathrm{O}, \\mathrm{N}$$ and $$\\mathrm{K}$$ are $$1,16,14$$ and 39, respectively.)</p>",
    "options": [
      "32.2 g",
      "69.4 g",
      "91.5 g",
      "162.5 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "91.5 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rjcjxd",
    "question": "<p>$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n&amp;\\mathrm{C}(\\mathrm{s})+\\mathrm{O}_{2}(\\mathrm{~g}) \\rightarrow \\mathrm{CO}_{2}(\\mathrm{~g})+400 \\mathrm{~kJ} \\\\\n&amp;\\mathrm{C}(\\mathrm{s})+\\frac{1}{2} \\mathrm{O}_{2}(\\mathrm{~g}) \\rightarrow \\mathrm{CO}(\\mathrm{g})+100 \\mathrm{~kJ}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$</p>\n<p>When coal of purity 60% is allowed to burn in presence of insufficient oxygen, 60% of carbon is converted into 'CO' and the remaining is converted into '$$\\mathrm{CO}_{2}$$'. The heat generated when $$0.6 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ of coal is burnt is _________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "1600 kJ",
      "3200 kJ",
      "4400 kJ",
      "6600 kJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "6600 kJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrkmdoz",
    "question": "<p>A metal chloride contains $$55.0 \\%$$ of chlorine by weight . $$100 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ vapours of the metal chloride at STP weigh $$0.57 \\mathrm{~g}$$. The molecular formula of the metal chloride is</p>\n<p>(Given: Atomic mass of chlorine is $$35.5 \\mathrm{u}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{MCl}_{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{MCl}_{4}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{MCl}_{3}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{MCl}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{MCl}_{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvv3573",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 554px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 49px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 201px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 54px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 250px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - II ($$\\Delta_0$$)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">16 g of $$\\mathrm{CH_4~(g)}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">Weighs 28 g</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">1 g of $$\\mathrm{H_2~(g)}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$$60.2\\times10^{23}$$ electrons</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">1 mole of $$\\mathrm{N_2~(g)}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">Weighs 32 g</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">0.5 mol of $$\\mathrm{SO_2~(g)}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">Occupies 11.4 L volume of STP</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III",
      "A-I, B-III, C-II, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyg3ikm",
    "question": "<p>The number of molecules and moles in 2.8375 litres of O$$_2$$ at STP are respectively</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.505 $$\\times$$ 10$$^{23}$$ and 0.250 mol",
      "7.527 $$\\times$$ 10$$^{22}$$ and 0.250 mol",
      "7.527 $$\\times$$ 10$$^{23}$$ and 0.125 mol",
      "7.527 $$\\times$$ 10$$^{22}$$ and 0.125 mol"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "7.527 $$\\times$$ 10$$^{22}$$ and 0.125 mol"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd9xf75",
    "question": "<p>A sample of $$\\mathrm{CaCO}_3$$ and $$\\mathrm{MgCO}_3$$ weighed $$2.21 \\mathrm{~g}$$ is ignited to constant weight of $$1.152 \\mathrm{~g}$$. The composition of mixture is :</p>\n<p>(Given molar mass in $$\\mathrm{g} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1} \\mathrm{CaCO}_3: 100, \\mathrm{MgCO}_3: 84$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1.187 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~CaCO}_3+1.187 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~MgCO}_3$$\n",
      "$$1.187 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~CaCO}_3+1.023 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~MgCO}_3$$\n",
      "$$1.023 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~CaCO}_3+1.187 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~MgCO}_3$$\n",
      "$$1.023 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~CaCO}_3+1.023 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~MgCO}_3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "$$1.187 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~CaCO}_3+1.023 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~MgCO}_3$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v49so",
    "question": "<p>An organic compound has $$42.1 \\%$$ carbon, $$6.4 \\%$$ hydrogen and remainder is oxygen. If its molecular weight is 342 , then its molecular formula is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{14} \\mathrm{H}_{20} \\mathrm{O}_{10}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{12} \\mathrm{H}_{22} \\mathrm{O}_{11}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{12} \\mathrm{H}_{20} \\mathrm{O}_{12}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{C}_{11} \\mathrm{H}_{18} \\mathrm{O}_{12}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{C}_{12} \\mathrm{H}_{22} \\mathrm{O}_{11}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s2psv",
    "question": "<p>The number of moles of methane required to produce $$11 \\mathrm{~g} \\mathrm{~CO}_2(\\mathrm{g})$$ after complete combustion is : (Given molar mass of methane in $$\\mathrm{g} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}: 16$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.35",
      "0.25",
      "0.5",
      "0.75"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "mole-concept",
    "solution": "0.25"
  },
  {
    "id": "cIb7tW44TFvHbqdR",
    "question": "In a compound C, H and N atoms are present in 9 : 1 : 3.5 by weight . Molecular weight of the compound is 108 g mol<sup>-1</sup> . Molecular formula of compound is",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>N<sub>2</sub>",
      "C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>4</sub>N",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>8</sub>N<sub>2</sub>",
      "C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>12</sub>N<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>8</sub>N<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "KAOBLLxcrPv5D22n",
    "question": "A gaseous hydrocarbon gives upon combustion 0.72 g of water and 3.08 g of CO<sub>2</sub>. The empirical formula of the hydrocarbon is",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub> ",
      "C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>4</sub> ",
      "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub> ",
      "C<sub>7</sub>H<sub>8</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "C<sub>7</sub>H<sub>8</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "sEZTscq20HMkpB6y",
    "question": "Experimentally it was found that a metal oxide has formula M<sub>0.98</sub>O. Metal M, present as M<sup>2+</sup> and M<sup>3+</sup> in its oxide. Fraction of the metal which exists as M<sup>3+</sup> would be",
    "options": [
      "7.01%",
      "4.08%",
      "6.05%",
      "5.08%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "4.08%"
  },
  {
    "id": "TCaSdKbhIoD0kroGtcBCk",
    "question": "For per gram of reactant, the maximum quantity of N<sub>2</sub> gas is produced in which of the following thermal decomposition reactions ? \n<br/>(Given : Atomic wt. - Cr = 52 u, Ba = 137 u)",
    "options": [
      "(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>(s) $$ \\to $$ N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 4H<sub>2</sub>O(g) + Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>(s)",
      "2NH<sub>4</sub>NO<sub>3</sub>(s) $$ \\to $$ 2 N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 4H<sub>2</sub>O(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g)",
      "Ba(N<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(s) $$ \\to $$ Ba(s) + 3N<sub>2</sub>(g)",
      "2NH<sub>3</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub>(g)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "2NH<sub>3</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub>(g)"
  },
  {
    "id": "7PYAO24NRxqfwJqtl1cLV",
    "question": "An unknown chlorohydrocarbon has 3.55% of chlorine. If each molecule of the hydrocarbon has one chlorine atom only; chlorine atoms present in 1 g of chlorohydrocarbon are : \n<br/>(Atomic wt. of Cl = 35.5 u; Avogadro constant  = 6.023 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>23</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "6.023 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>20</sup>",
      "6.023 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>9</sup>",
      "6.023 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>21</sup>",
      "6.023 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>23</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "6.023 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>20</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "CkBn6GigLOINxu289eUJw",
    "question": "For the following reaction, in the mass of water produced from 445 g of C<sub>57</sub>H<sub>110</sub>O<sub>6</sub> is :\n<br/><br/>2C<sub>57</sub>H<sub>110</sub>O<sub>6</sub>(s) + 163 O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 114 CO<sub>2</sub>(g) + 110 H<sub>2</sub>O(l)",
    "options": [
      "490 g",
      "445 g",
      "495 g",
      "890 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "495 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "ONW35xpuIRSPOh7QHLB8P",
    "question": "The percentage composition of carbon by mole\nin methane is :",
    "options": [
      "80%",
      "20%",
      "75%",
      "25%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "20%"
  },
  {
    "id": "jQKxqaRxKFIDz7odUcYCv",
    "question": "For a reaction,<br/>\nN<sub>2</sub>(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 2NH<sub>3</sub>(g) ;<br/>\nidentify dihydrogen (H<sub>2</sub>) as a limiting reagent\nin the following reaction mixtures.",
    "options": [
      "56g of N<sub>2</sub> + 10g of H<sub>2</sub>",
      "14g of N<sub>2</sub> + 4g of H<sub>2</sub>",
      "28g of N<sub>2</sub> + 6g of H<sub>2</sub>",
      "35g of N<sub>2</sub> + 8g of H<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "56g of N<sub>2</sub> + 10g of H<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "AXCOjxNdF33tuo0kru3rsa0w2w9jwvdnuf1",
    "question": "At 300 K and 1 atmospheric pressure, 10 mL of a hydrocarbon required 55 mL of O<sub>2</sub> for complete\ncombustion, and 40 mL of CO<sub>2</sub> is formed. The formula of the hydrocarbon is : \n",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>7</sub>Cl",
      "C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>6</sub>",
      "C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>8</sub>",
      "C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>10</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>6</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "DTWK2nLaP9vnWQSvio3rsa0w2w9jx83otga",
    "question": "Thermal decomposition of a Mn compound (X) at 513 K results in compound Y, MnO<sub>2</sub> and gaseous product.\nMnO<sub>2</sub> reacts with NaCl and concentrated H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> to give a pungent gas Z. X, Y and Z, respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "KMnO<sub>4</sub>, K<sub>2</sub>MnO<sub>4</sub> and Cl<sub>2</sub>\n",
      "K<sub>2</sub>MnO<sub>4</sub>, KMnO<sub>4</sub> and SO<sub>2</sub>",
      "K<sub>3</sub>MnO<sub>4</sub>, K<sub>2</sub>MnO<sub>4</sub> and Cl<sub>2</sub>",
      "K<sub>2</sub>MnO<sub>4</sub>, KMnO<sub>4</sub> and Cl<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "KMnO<sub>4</sub>, K<sub>2</sub>MnO<sub>4</sub> and Cl<sub>2</sub>\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "uH6OTxcnskcV4S7LCI7k9k2k5eq1zyk",
    "question": "The ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>) released on quantitative reaction of 0.6 g urea (NH<sub>2</sub>CONH<sub>2</sub>) with sodium hydroxide (NaOH) can be neutralized by :",
    "options": [
      "200 ml of 0.02 N HCl",
      "100 ml of 0.2 N HCl ",
      "100 ml of 0.1 HCl",
      "200 ml of 0.4 N HCl"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "100 ml of 0.2 N HCl "
  },
  {
    "id": "9My0R4yfuhcONDZEm31kls94pra",
    "question": "Complete combustion of 1.80 g of an oxygen containing compound (C<sub>x</sub>H<sub>y</sub>O<sub>z</sub>) gave 2.64 g of CO<sub>2</sub> and 1.08 g of H<sub>2</sub>O. The percentage of oxygen in the organic compound is :",
    "options": [
      "51.63",
      "50.33",
      "63.53",
      "53.33"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "53.33"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l548f6vq",
    "question": "<p>Production of iron in blast furnace follows the following equation</p>\n<p>Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>(s) + 4CO(g) $$\\to$$ 3Fe(l) + 4CO<sub>2</sub>(g)</p>\n<p>when 4.640 kg of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> and 2.520 kg of CO are allowed to react then the amount of iron (in g) produced is :</p>\n<p>[Given : Molar Atomic mass (g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>) : Fe = 56, Molar Atomic mass (g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>) : O \n = 16, Molar Atomic mass (g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>) : C = 12]</p>",
    "options": [
      "1400",
      "2200",
      "3360",
      "4200"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "3360"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55mqyve",
    "question": "<p>Compound A contains 8.7% Hydrogen, 74% Carbon and 17.3% Nitrogen. The molecular formula of the compound is,</p>\n<p>Given : Atomic masses of C, H and N are 12, 1 and 14 amu respectively.</p>\n<p>The molar mass of the compound A is 162 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>.</p>",
    "options": [
      "C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>6</sub>N<sub>2</sub>",
      "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>3</sub>N",
      "C<sub>5</sub>H<sub>7</sub>N",
      "C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>14</sub>N<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>14</sub>N<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bcrmoo",
    "question": "<p>120 g of an organic compound that contains only carbon and hydrogen gives 330 g of CO<sub>2</sub> and 270 g of water on complete combustion. The percentage of carbon and hydrogen, respectively are</p>",
    "options": [
      "25 and 75",
      "40 and 60",
      "60 and 40",
      "75 and 25"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "75 and 25"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c4yhkb",
    "question": "<p>If a rocket runs on a fuel (C<sub>15</sub>H<sub>30</sub>) and liquid oxygen, the weight of oxygen required and CO<sub>2</sub> released for every litre of fuel respectively are :</p>\n<p>(Given : density of the fuel is 0.756 g/mL)</p>",
    "options": [
      "1188 g and 1296 g",
      "2376 g and 2592 g",
      "2592 g and 2376 g",
      "3429 g and 3142 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "2592 g and 2376 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p6u769",
    "question": "<p>$$\n\\mathrm{N}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})}+3 \\mathrm{H}_{2(\\mathrm{~g})} \\rightleftharpoons 2 \\mathrm{NH}_{3(\\mathrm{~g})}\n$$</p>\n<p>$$20 \\mathrm{~g} \\quad ~~~5 \\mathrm{~g}$$</p>\n<p>Consider the above reaction, the limiting reagent of the reaction and number of moles of $$\\mathrm{NH}_{3}$$ formed respectively are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{H}_{2}, 1.42$$ moles",
      "$$\\mathrm{H}_{2}, 0.71$$ moles",
      "$$\\mathrm{N}_{2}, 1.42$$ moles",
      "$$\\mathrm{N}_{2}, 0.71$$ moles"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{N}_{2}, 1.42$$ moles"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo82s11",
    "question": "When a hydrocarbon A undergoes complete combustion it requires 11 equivalents of oxygen and produces 4 equivalents of water. What is the molecular formula of $A$ ?",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{C}_{9} \\mathrm{H}_{8}$",
      "$\\mathrm{C}_{5} \\mathrm{H}_{8}$",
      "$\\mathrm{C}_{11} \\mathrm{H}_{4}$",
      "$\\mathrm{C}_{11} \\mathrm{H}_{8}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{C}_{9} \\mathrm{H}_{8}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsch1gp",
    "question": "<p>When a hydrocarbon A undergoes combustion in the presence of air, it requires 9.5 equivalents of oxygen and produces 3 equivalents of water. What is the molecular formula of A?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{C_9H_6}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{C_6H_6}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{C_8H_6}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{C_9H_9}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{C_8H_6}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gsy0w",
    "question": "<p>Combustion of glucose $$(\\mathrm{C}_6 \\mathrm{H}_{12} \\mathrm{O}_6)$$ produces $$\\mathrm{CO}_2$$ and water. The amount of oxygen (in $$\\mathrm{g}$$) required for the complete combustion of $$900 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of glucose is :</p>\n<p>[Molar mass of glucose in $$\\mathrm{g} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}=180$$]</p>",
    "options": [
      "32",
      "480",
      "800",
      "960"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "quantitative-measures-in-chemical-equations",
    "solution": "960"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54xxyaf",
    "question": "<p>Using the rules for significant figures, the correct answer for the expression $${{0.02858 \\times 0.112} \\over {0.5702}}$$ will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.005613",
      "0.00561",
      "0.0056",
      "0.006"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "significant-figures",
    "solution": "0.00561"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyrudyw",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following have same number of significant figures?</p>\n<p>A. 0.00253</p>\n<p>B. 1.0003</p>\n<p>C. 15.0</p>\n<p>D. 163</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, C and D only",
      "B and C only",
      "A, B and C only",
      "C and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "some-basic-concepts-of-chemistry",
    "topic": "significant-figures",
    "solution": "A, C and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "ymXe0k7U7wjsSKup",
    "question": "In a hydrogen atom, if energy of an electron in ground state is -13.6 eV, then that in the 2<sup>nd</sup> excited state is",
    "options": [
      "-1.51 eV",
      "-3.4 eV",
      "-6.04 eV",
      "-13.6 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "-1.51 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "YfCCyH3qbhXF71wz",
    "question": "In Bohr series of lines of hydrogen spectrum, the third line from the red end corresponds to which one of the following inter-orbit jumps of the electron for Bohr orbits in an atom of hydrogen",
    "options": [
      "5 $$\\to$$ 2",
      "4 $$\\to$$ 1",
      "2 $$\\to$$ 5",
      "3 $$\\to$$ 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "5 $$\\to$$ 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "fN8JlmJoUrdP6sZC",
    "question": "According to Bohr's theory, the angular momentum of an electron in 5<sup>th</sup> orbit is",
    "options": [
      "10 $$h/\\pi$$",
      "2.5 $$h/\\pi$$",
      "25 $$h/\\pi$$",
      "1.0 $$h/\\pi$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "2.5 $$h/\\pi$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "41Mk8gx8RiId53bS",
    "question": "Ionisation energy of He<sup>+</sup> is 19.6 x 10<sup>–18</sup> J atom<sup>–1</sup>. The energy of the first stationary state (n = 1) of Li<sup>2+</sup> is",
    "options": [
      "4.41 x 10<sup>–16</sup> J atom<sup>–1</sup>",
      "-4.41 x 10<sup>–17</sup> J atom<sup>–1</sup>",
      "-2.2 x 10<sup>–15</sup> J atom<sup>–1</sup>",
      "8.82 x 10<sup>–17</sup> J atom<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "-4.41 x 10<sup>–17</sup> J atom<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "vIlUiuau2OiTPDR4",
    "question": "Which of the following is the energy of a possible excited state of hydrogen?",
    "options": [
      "–6.8 eV",
      "–3.4 eV",
      "+6.8 eV",
      "+13.6 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "–3.4 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "SFHuJUfQ4CoAgsX9",
    "question": "The radius of the second Bohr orbit for hydrogen atom is:<br/>\n(Planck’s Const. h = 6.6262 × 10<sup>-34</sup> Js; mass of electron = 9.1091 × 10<sup>-31</sup> kg; charge of electron (e) = 1.60210 × 10<sup>-19</sup> C; permittivity of vacuum ($${\\varepsilon _0}$$) = 8.854185 × 10<sup>-12</sup> kg<sup>-1</sup> m<sup>-3</sup> A<sup>2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "4.76 $$\\mathop {\\rm A}\\limits^o $$",
      "2.12 $$\\mathop {\\rm A}\\limits^o $$",
      "0.529 $$\\mathop {\\rm A}\\limits^o $$",
      "1.65 $$\\mathop {\\rm A}\\limits^o $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "2.12 $$\\mathop {\\rm A}\\limits^o $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "TLXQBgxVy537DaLdQpWjW",
    "question": "The de-Broglie's wavelength of electron present in first Bohr orbit of 'H' atom is : ",
    "options": [
      "0.529 $$\\mathop {\\rm A}\\limits^ \\circ  $$",
      "2$$\\pi $$ $$ \\times $$ 0.529 $$\\mathop {\\rm A}\\limits^ \\circ  $$",
      "$${{0.529} \\over {2\\pi }}$$ $$\\mathop {\\rm A}\\limits^ \\circ  $$",
      "4 $$ \\times $$ 0.529 $$\\mathop {\\rm A}\\limits^ \\circ  $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "2$$\\pi $$ $$ \\times $$ 0.529 $$\\mathop {\\rm A}\\limits^ \\circ  $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "YFCJMi4HwnR7wlzI5D7k9k2k5hlkh7l",
    "question": "The radius of the second Bohr orbit, in terms\nof the Bohr radius, a<sub>0</sub>, in Li<sup>2+</sup> is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2{a_0}} \\over 9}$$",
      "$${{2{a_0}} \\over 3}$$",
      "$${{4{a_0}} \\over 9}$$",
      "$${{4{a_0}} \\over 3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "$${{4{a_0}} \\over 3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "3VRO6j8pYWnflYX7SB7k9k2k5idnuac",
    "question": "The de Broglie wavelength of an electron in the\n4th Bohr orbit is :",
    "options": [
      "2$$\\pi $$a<sub>0</sub>",
      "6$$\\pi $$a<sub>0</sub>",
      "8$$\\pi $$a<sub>0</sub>",
      "4$$\\pi $$a<sub>0</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "8$$\\pi $$a<sub>0</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "5JTV2rvdK5v9A1jdrBjgy2xukfjbcfrs",
    "question": "The difference between the radii of 3<sup>rd</sup> and 4<sup>th</sup>\n<br/>orbits of Li<sup>2+</sup> is R<sub>1</sub>\n. The difference between the\n<br/>radii of 3<sup>rd</sup> and 4<sup>th</sup> orbits of He<sup>+</sup> is\n$$\\Delta $$R<sub>2</sub>  \n. <br/>Ratio $$\\Delta $$R<sub>1</sub> : $$\\Delta $$R<sub>2</sub> is :\n",
    "options": [
      "8 : 3",
      "3 : 2",
      "2 : 3",
      "3 : 8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "2 : 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "2TIo7Ul2JGlOG2qGN41klru1lo0",
    "question": "According to Bohr's atomic theory :<br/><br/>(A) Kinetic energy of electron is $$ \\propto {{{Z^2}} \\over {{n^2}}}$$.<br/><br/>(B) The product of velocity (v) of electron and principal quantum number (n), $$'vn' \\propto {Z^2}$$.<br/><br/>(C) Frequency of revolution of electron in an orbit is $$ \\propto {{{Z^3}} \\over {{n^3}}}$$.<br/><br/>(D) Coulombic force of attraction on the electron is $$ \\propto {{{Z^3}} \\over {{n^4}}}$$.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A), (C) and (D) only",
      "(A) only",
      "(C) only",
      "(A) and (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "(A) and (D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "vDX7OsXHrWn9ljlgAM1klurwqgo",
    "question": "Which of the following forms of hydrogen emits low energy $$\\beta$$<sup>-</sup> particles?",
    "options": [
      "Tritium $$_1^3$$H",
      "Proton H<sup>+</sup>",
      "Protium $$_1^1$$H",
      "Deuterium $$_1^2$$H"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "Tritium $$_1^3$$H"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5Bovq3AsJnnksFw01kmm1a72t",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : Bohr's theory accounts for the stability and line spectrum of Li<sup>+</sup> ion.<br/><br/>Statement II : Bohr's theory was unable to explain the splitting of spectral lines in the presence of a magnetic field.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true.",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true.",
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false.",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but statement II is true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktb5a0k2",
    "question": "Given below are two statements.<br/><br/>Statement I : According to Bohr's model of an atom, qualitatively the magnitude of velocity of electron increases with decrease in positive charges on the nucleus as there is no strong hold on the electron by the nucleus.<br/><br/>Statement II : According to Bohr's model of an atom, qualitatively the magnitude of velocity of electron increases with decrease in principal quantum number.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58ddlxi",
    "question": "<p>If the radius of the 3<sup>rd</sup> Bohr's orbit of hydrogen atom is r<sub>3</sub> and the radius of 4<sup>th</sup> Bohr's orbit is r<sub>4</sub>. Then :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${r_4} = {9 \\over {16}}{r_3}$$",
      "$${r_4} = {16 \\over {9}}{r_3}$$",
      "$${r_4} = {3 \\over {4}}{r_3}$$",
      "$${r_4} = {4 \\over {3}}{r_3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "$${r_4} = {16 \\over {9}}{r_3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jkf94j",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements. One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A: Energy of $$2 \\mathrm{s}$$ orbital of hydrogen atom is greater than that of $$2 \\mathrm{s}$$ orbital of lithium.</p>\n<p>Reason R: Energies of the orbitals in the same subshell decrease with increase in the atomic number.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mbuost",
    "question": "<p>Identify the incorrect statement from the following.</p>",
    "options": [
      "A circular path around the nucleus in which an electron moves is proposed as Bohr's orbit.",
      "An orbital is the one electron wave function $$(\\psi)$$ in an atom.",
      "The existence of Bohr's orbits is supported by hydrogen spectrum.",
      "Atomic orbital is characterised by the quantum numbers $$\\mathrm{n}$$ and $$l$$ only."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "Atomic orbital is characterised by the quantum numbers $$\\mathrm{n}$$ and $$l$$ only."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduktq2c",
    "question": "<p>The radius of the $$\\mathrm{2^{nd}}$$ orbit of $$\\mathrm{Li^{2+}}$$ is $$x$$. The expected radius of the $$\\mathrm{3^{rd}}$$ orbit of $$\\mathrm{Be^{3+}}$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{16}{27}x$$",
      "$$\\frac{4}{9}x$$",
      "$$\\frac{9}{4}x$$",
      "$$\\frac{27}{16}x$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{27}{16}x$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnzntql",
    "question": "Given below are two statements:\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement I</b> : According to Bohr's model of hydrogen atom, the angular momentum of an electron in a given stationary state is quantised.\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement II</b> : The concept of electron in Bohr's orbit, violates the Heisenberg uncertainty principle.\n<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:\n",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq4ogs9",
    "question": "<p>The energy of an electron in the first Bohr orbit of hydrogen atom is $$-2.18 \\times 10^{-18} \\mathrm{~J}$$. Its energy in the third Bohr orbit is ____________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "One third of this value",
      "Three times of this value",
      "$$\\frac{1}{9}$$ th of this value",
      "$$\\frac{1}{27}$$ of this value"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-for-hydrogen-atom",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{9}$$ th of this value"
  },
  {
    "id": "2T7T88kQq4wEOAoG",
    "question": "The de Broglie wavelength of a tennis ball of mass 60 g moving with a velocity of 10 meters per second is approximately",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>-31</sup> meters",
      "10<sup>-16</sup> meters",
      "10<sup>-25</sup> meters",
      "10<sup>-33</sup> meters"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "de-broglie-hypothesis",
    "solution": "10<sup>-33</sup> meters"
  },
  {
    "id": "YIwlTjMeeNfhreFp",
    "question": "Calculate the wavelength (in nanometer) associated with a proton moving at 1.0 x 10<sup>3</sup> ms<sup>−1</sup>\n (Mass of proton = 1.67 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-27</sup> kg and h =  6.63 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-34</sup> Js) : ",
    "options": [
      "0.40 nm",
      "2.5 nm",
      "14.0 nm",
      "0.32 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "de-broglie-hypothesis",
    "solution": "0.40 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "pcBY2JhSGlhpg3gN",
    "question": "The energy required to break one mole of Cl–Cl bonds in Cl<sub>2</sub> is 242 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>. The longest\nwavelength of light capable of breaking a single Cl – Cl bond is<br/>\n(c = 3 x 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>–1</sup> and N<sub>A</sub> = 6.02 x 10<sup>23</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "594 nm",
      "640 nm",
      "700 nm",
      "494 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "de-broglie-hypothesis",
    "solution": "494 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "3ael0UfsR1e2ZRaI",
    "question": "A stream of electrons from a heated filament was passed between two charged plates kept at a potential\ndifference V esu. If e and m are charge and mass of an electron, respectively, then the value of h / $$\\lambda $$ (where\n$$\\lambda $$ is wavelength associated with electron wave) is given by :",
    "options": [
      "2meV ",
      "$$\\sqrt {meV} $$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt {2meV} $$ ",
      "meV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "de-broglie-hypothesis",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {2meV} $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "RSUl17B4KTBkfgsW",
    "question": "Which one of the following groupings represents a collection of isoelectronic species? (At. nos. : Cs : 55, Br : 35)",
    "options": [
      "N<sup>3-</sup>, F<sup>-</sup>, Na<sup>+</sup>",
      "Be, Al<sup>3+</sup>, Cl<sup>-</sup>",
      "Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Cs<sup>+</sup>, Br ",
      "Na<sup>+</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "N<sup>3-</sup>, F<sup>-</sup>, Na<sup>+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "pUvquwVZbI1KCOD2",
    "question": "Which one of the following sets of ions represents the collection of isoelectronic species? (Atomic nos. : F = 9, Cl = 17, Na = 11, Mg = 12, Al = 13, K = 19, Ca = 20, Sc = 21)",
    "options": [
      "K<sup>+</sup>, Cl<sup>-</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>, Sc<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Na<sup>+</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Sc<sup>3+</sup>, F<sup>-</sup>",
      "K<sup>+</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Sc<sup>3+</sup>, Cl<sup>-</sup>",
      "Na<sup>+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>, Al<sup>3+</sup>, Cl<sup>-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "K<sup>+</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Sc<sup>3+</sup>, Cl<sup>-</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "bH46VJtbNLYxFGQo",
    "question": "Of the following sets which one does NOT contain isoelectronic species?",
    "options": [
      "$$BO_3^{3 - }$$, $$CO_3^{2 - }$$, $$NO_3^{- }$$",
      "$$SO_3^{2 - }$$, $$CO_3^{2 - }$$, $$NO_3^{-}$$",
      "$$CN^{- }$$, $$N_2$$, $$C_2^{2 - }$$",
      "$$PO_4^{3 - }$$, $$SO_4^{2 - }$$, $$ClO_4^{ - }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "$$SO_3^{2 - }$$, $$CO_3^{2 - }$$, $$NO_3^{-}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "fYZaue5XeCAA7xbI",
    "question": "Pick out the isoelectronic structure from the following : \n<br/><br/>$$\\eqalign{\n  &amp; \\left( i \\right)\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,C{H_3}^ +   \\cr \n  &amp; \\left( {ii} \\right)\\,\\,\\,\\,{H_3}{O^ + }  \\cr \n  &amp; \\left( {iii} \\right)\\,\\,\\,N{H_3}  \\cr \n  &amp; \\left( {iv} \\right)\\,\\,\\,\\,C{H_3}^ -  \\cr} $$ ",
    "options": [
      "$$(i)$$ and $$(ii)$$ ",
      "$$(iii)$$ and $$(iv)$$ ",
      "$$(i)$$ and $$(iii)$$ ",
      "$$(ii), (iii)$$ and $$(iv)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "$$(ii), (iii)$$ and $$(iv)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "b03gVgWuXmI3qC22",
    "question": "Which of the following sets of ions represents a collection of isoelectronic species?",
    "options": [
      "N<sup>3-</sup>, O<sup>2-</sup>, F<sup>-</sup>, S<sup>2-</sup>",
      "Li<sup>+</sup>, Na<sup>+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>",
      "K<sup>+</sup>, Cl<sup>-</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Sc<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Ba<sup>2+</sup>, Sr<sup>2+</sup>, K<sup>+</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "K<sup>+</sup>, Cl<sup>-</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Sc<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "o6mA6AxOKuOKG4zP",
    "question": "Which one of the following constitutes a group of the isoelectronic species? ",
    "options": [
      "$$C_2^{2 - }$$, $$O_2^{-}$$, CO, NO",
      "$$NO^{+}$$, $$C_2^{2 - }$$, CN<sup>-</sup>, $$N_2$$",
      "CN<sup>-</sup>, $$N_2$$, $$O_2^{2-}$$, $$C_2^{2 - }$$",
      "$$N_2$$, $$O_2^{-}$$, $$NO^{+}$$, CO"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "$$NO^{+}$$, $$C_2^{2 - }$$, CN<sup>-</sup>, $$N_2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1y8wmTsiXqZGmJIS",
    "question": "The group having isoelectronic species is:",
    "options": [
      "O<sup>2-</sup> , F<sup>-</sup> , Na<sup>+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>",
      "O<sup>2-</sup> , F<sup>-</sup> , Na, Mg<sup>2+</sup>",
      "O<sup>-</sup> , F<sup>-</sup> , Na<sup>+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>",
      "O<sup>-</sup> , F<sup>-</sup> , Na, Mg<sup>+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "O<sup>2-</sup> , F<sup>-</sup> , Na<sup>+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1t8KnCesGIAARFRIeC3rsa0w2w9jwup40cd",
    "question": "The isoelectronic set of ions is :",
    "options": [
      "F<sup>–</sup>, Li<sup>+</sup>, Na<sup>+</sup> and Mg<sup>2+ </sup>",
      "Li<sup>+</sup>, Na<sup>+</sup>, O<sup>2-</sup> and F<sup>- </sup>",
      "N<sup>3–</sup>, O<sup>2-</sup>, F<sup>-</sup> and Na<sup>+ </sup>",
      "N<sup>3–</sup>, Li<sup>+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup> and O<sup>2-</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "N<sup>3–</sup>, O<sup>2-</sup>, F<sup>-</sup> and Na<sup>+ </sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "SeaEfsy2zg9A1eKiRe3rsa0w2w9jx55b0hl",
    "question": "The group number, number of valence electrons, and valency of an element with atomic number 15,\nrespectively, are:",
    "options": [
      "16, 6 and 3\n",
      "15, 6 and 12",
      "16, 5 and 2",
      "15, 5 and 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "15, 5 and 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "S92kk16mmQYeosX0RP7k9k2k5hltccg",
    "question": "Hydrogen has three isotopes (A), (B) and (C).\nIf the number of neutron(s) in (A), (B) and (C)\nrespectively, are (x), (y) and (z), the sum of (x),\n(y) an (z) is :",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "1",
      "4",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "LJ3LhuwhcNFrYDYDsE1klue0c5x",
    "question": "The orbital having two radial as well as two angular nodes is :",
    "options": [
      "3p",
      "5d",
      "4d",
      "4f"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "5d"
  },
  {
    "id": "3zMNrAgCzdvti0g1yJ1kmln1oy5",
    "question": "A certain orbital has no angular nodes and two radial nodes. The orbital is :",
    "options": [
      "2s",
      "3s",
      "3p",
      "2p"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "3s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krrhsppx",
    "question": "Outermost electronic configuration of a group 13 element, E, is 4s<sup>2</sup>, 4p<sup>1</sup>. The electronic configuration of an element of p-block period-five placed diagonally to element, E is :",
    "options": [
      "[Kr] 3d<sup>10</sup> 4s<sup>2</sup> 4p<sup>2</sup>",
      "[Ar] 3d<sup>10</sup> 4s<sup>2</sup> 4p<sup>2</sup>",
      "[Xe] 5d<sup>10</sup> 6s<sup>2</sup> 6p<sup>2</sup>",
      "[Kr] 4d<sup>10</sup> 5s<sup>2</sup> 5p<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "[Kr] 4d<sup>10</sup> 5s<sup>2</sup> 5p<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58iscjf",
    "question": "<p>The number of radial and angular nodes in 4d orbital are, respectively</p>",
    "options": [
      " 1 and 2",
      "3 and 2",
      "1 and 0",
      "2 and 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": " 1 and 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5alobsw",
    "question": "<p>The pair, in which ions are isoelectronic with AI<sup>3+</sup> is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Br<sup>$$-$$</sup> and Be<sup>2+</sup>",
      "Cl<sup>$$-$$</sup> and Li<sup>+</sup>",
      "S<sup>2$$-$$</sup> and K<sup>+</sup>",
      "O<sup>2$$-$$</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "O<sup>2$$-$$</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kpdcns",
    "question": "<p>Outermost electronic configurations of four elements A, B, C, D are given below :</p>\n<p>(A) $$3 s^{2}$$</p>\n<p>(B) $$3 s^{2} 3 p^{1}$$</p>\n<p>(C) $$3 s^{2} 3 p^{3}$$</p>\n<p>(D) $$3 s^{2} 3 p^{4}$$</p>\n<p>The correct order of first ionization enthalpy for them is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) < (B) < (C) < (D)",
      "(B) < (A) < (D) < (C)",
      "(B) < (D) < (A) < (C)",
      "(B) < (A) < (C) < (D)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "(B) < (A) < (D) < (C)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldo2n8em",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following sets of ions represents a collection of isoelectronic species?</p>\n<p>(Given : Atomic Number : $$\\mathrm{F:9,Cl:17,Na=11,Mg=12,Al=13,K=19,Ca=20,Sc=21}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{N}^{3-}, \\mathrm{O}^{2-}, \\mathrm{F}^{-}, \\mathrm{S}^{2-}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Ba}^{2+}, \\mathrm{Sr}^{2+}, \\mathrm{K}^{+}, \\mathrm{Ca}^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Li}^{+}, \\mathrm{Na}^{+}, \\mathrm{Mg}^{2+}, \\mathrm{Ca}^{2+}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}^{+}, \\mathrm{Cl}^{-}, \\mathrm{Ca}^{2+}, \\mathrm{Sc}^{3+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{K}^{+}, \\mathrm{Cl}^{-}, \\mathrm{Ca}^{2+}, \\mathrm{Sc}^{3+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwschva",
    "question": "<p>The number of s-electrons present in an ion with 55 protons in its unipositive state is</p>",
    "options": [
      "10",
      "9",
      "12",
      "8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "10"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsaotnb3",
    "question": "The number of radial node/s for $3 p$ orbital is :",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "2",
      "1",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "electronic-configuration-and-nodes",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "YisqRgD5VJowdT8d",
    "question": "Uncertainty in position of a minute particle of mass 25 g in space is 10<sup>-5</sup> m. What is the uncertainty in its velocity (in ms<sup>-1</sup>) (h = 6.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-34</sup> Js)",
    "options": [
      "2.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-34</sup>",
      "0.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-34</sup>",
      "2.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-28</sup>",
      "0.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-23</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "heisenberg-uncertainty-principle",
    "solution": "2.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-28</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "5KsHu1M3tbccJ0lG",
    "question": "Uncertainty in the position of an electron (mass = 9.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-31</sup> kg) moving with a velocity 300 ms<sup>-1</sup>, accurate upto 0.001% will be (h = 6.63 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-34</sup> Js)",
    "options": [
      "1.92 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> m",
      "3.84 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> m",
      "19.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> m",
      "5.76 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "heisenberg-uncertainty-principle",
    "solution": "1.92 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> m"
  },
  {
    "id": "EfIY5anToRCUDjzF",
    "question": "In an atom, an electron is moving with a speed of 600 m/s with an accuracy of 0.005%. Certainity\nwith which the position of the electron can be located is (h = 6.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-34</sup> kg m<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup>, mass of electron, e<sub>m</sub> = 9.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-31</sup> kg) ",
    "options": [
      "5.10 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-3</sup> m",
      "1.92 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-3</sup> m",
      "3.84 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-3</sup> m",
      "1.52 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-4</sup> m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "heisenberg-uncertainty-principle",
    "solution": "1.92 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-3</sup> m"
  },
  {
    "id": "k09CJFg6NGiaTv7E",
    "question": "The wavelength of the radiation emitted when in a hydrogen atom electron falls from infinity to stationary state 1, would be (Rydberg constant  = 1.097 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> m<sup>-1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "406 nm",
      "192 nm",
      "91 nm",
      "9.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-8</sup> nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "91 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "sZWnnkK82yYmQY9U",
    "question": "The ionization enthalpy of hydrogen atom is 1.312 × 10<sup>6</sup> J mol<sup>−1</sup>. The energy required to excite the\nelectron in the atom from n = 1 to n = 2 is ",
    "options": [
      "8.51 × 10<sup>5</sup> J mol<sup>−1</sup>",
      "6.56 × 10<sup>5</sup> J mol<sup>−1</sup>",
      "7.56 × 10<sup>5</sup> J mol<sup>−1</sup>",
      "9.84 × 10<sup>5</sup> J mol<sup>−1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "9.84 × 10<sup>5</sup> J mol<sup>−1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "EJfaZP3w13VOJxuS",
    "question": "Energy of an electron is given by $$E =  - 2.178 \\times {10^{ - 18}}J\\left( {{{{Z^2}} \\over {{n^2}}}} \\right)$$. Wavelength of light required to excite an\nelectron in an hydrogen atom from level n = 1 to n = 2 will be<br/>\n (h = 6.62 × 10<sup>−34</sup> Js and c = 3.0 × 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>−1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "2.816 × 10<sup>−7</sup> m ",
      "6.500 × 10<sup>−7</sup> m",
      "8.500 × 10<sup>−7</sup> m",
      "1.214 × 10<sup>−7</sup> m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "1.214 × 10<sup>−7</sup> m"
  },
  {
    "id": "YOSc4PhWSUSbPu2OX8wQV",
    "question": "If the shortest wavelength in Lyman series of hydrogen atom is A, then the longestwavelength in Paschen series of He<sup>+</sup> is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{5A} \\over 9}$$",
      "$${{9A} \\over 5}$$",
      "$${{36A} \\over 5}$$",
      "$${{36A} \\over 7}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${{36A} \\over 7}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "3kSEPthQdGxIdpC6YFNq7",
    "question": "The electron in the hydrogen atom undergoes transition from higher orbitals\nto orbital of radius 211.6 pm. This transition is associated with :",
    "options": [
      "Lyman series",
      "Balmer series",
      "Paschen series",
      "Brackett series"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "Balmer series"
  },
  {
    "id": "U946F4N0kaJUMwhd46fSu",
    "question": "For emission line of atomic hydrogen from n<sub>i</sub> = 8 to n<sub>f</sub> = n, the plot of wave number $$\\left( {\\overline v } \\right)$$ against $$\\left( {{1 \\over {{n^2}}}} \\right)$$ will be (The Rydberg constant, R<sub>H</sub> is in wave number unit)",
    "options": [
      "Linear with intercept $$-$$R<sub>H</sub>",
      "Non linear ",
      "Linear with slope R<sub>H</sub>",
      "Linear with slope $$-$$R<sub>H</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "Linear with slope R<sub>H</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "9se8wYIKEPrvyjqeqlSv2",
    "question": "The ground state energy of hydrogen atom is – 13.6 eV. The energy of second excited state of He<sup>+</sup> ion in eV is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$ 6.04",
      "$$-$$ 54.4",
      "$$-$$ 27.2",
      "$$-$$ 3.4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$-$$ 6.04"
  },
  {
    "id": "QvCzsZ8ob1PHF1Ojjy15Q",
    "question": "Heat treatment of muscular pain involves radiation of wavelength of about 900 nm. Which spectral line of H atom is suitable for this purpose?\n<br/><br/>[R<sub>H</sub> = 1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup> cm<sup>–1</sup>, h = 6.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–34</sup> Js, c = 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>–1</sup>]\n",
    "options": [
      "Balmer, $$\\infty $$ $$ \\to $$ 2 ",
      "Paschen, 5 $$ \\to $$ 3 ",
      "Paschen, $$\\infty $$ $$ \\to $$ 3",
      "Lyman, $$\\infty $$ $$ \\to $$ 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "Paschen, $$\\infty $$ $$ \\to $$ 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "Gv2q1O0hzNqS4xOrX48Dz",
    "question": "For any given series of spectral lines of atomic\nhydrogen, let $$\\Delta \\mathop v\\limits^\\_  = $$ $$\\Delta {\\overline v _{\\max }} - \\Delta {\\overline v _{\\min }}$$ be the difference\nin maximum and minimum frequencies in\ncm<sup>–1</sup>. The ratio Lyman Balmer $${{\\Delta {{\\overline v }_{Lyman}}} \\over {\\Delta {{\\overline v }_{Balmer}}}}$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "9 : 4",
      "4 : 1",
      "27 : 5",
      "5 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "9 : 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "NmFzi45N1bd5Rwlmme3rsa0w2w9jx0wvawz",
    "question": "The ratio of the shortest wavelength of two spectral series of hydrogen spectrum is found to be about 9. The\nspectral series are :",
    "options": [
      "Paschen and Pfund",
      "Balmer and Brackett",
      "Lyman and Paschen",
      "Brackett and Pfund"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "Lyman and Paschen"
  },
  {
    "id": "nHiB0rxXmLUhyOHZVe7k9k2k5h626lr",
    "question": "For the Balmer series in the spectrum of H atom,\n<br/>$$\\overline \\nu   = {R_H}\\left\\{ {{1 \\over {n_1^2}} - {1 \\over {n_2^2}}} \\right\\}$$, the correct statements among (I) to (IV)\nare :\n<br/>(I) As wavelength decreases, the lines in the series converge\n<br/>(II) The integer n<sub>1</sub> is equal to 2\n<br/>(III) The lines of longest wavelength corresponds to n<sub>2</sub> = 3\n<br/>(IV) The ionization energy of hydrogen can be calculated from wave number of these lines",
    "options": [
      "(II), (III), (IV)",
      "(I), (II), (III)",
      "(I), (III), (IV)",
      "(I), (II), (IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "(I), (II), (III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "fTRDvW7BzAYr0TJ9DNjgy2xukfcegnyw",
    "question": "The shortest wavelength of H atom in the\nLyman series is $$\\lambda $$<sub>1</sub>. The longest wavelength in\nthe Balmar series of He<sup>+</sup> is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{5{\\lambda _1}} \\over 9}$$",
      "$${{36{\\lambda _1}} \\over 5}$$",
      "$${{27{\\lambda _1}} \\over 5}$$",
      "$${{9{\\lambda _1}} \\over 5}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${{9{\\lambda _1}} \\over 5}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "kJgtQcrQQjJh5krB8Djgy2xukf93lzve",
    "question": "The region in the electromagnetic spectrum\nwhere the Balmar series lines appear is :",
    "options": [
      "Microwave",
      "Ultraviolet",
      "Visible",
      "Infrared"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "Visible"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpoziwp",
    "question": "<p>Which transition in the hydrogen spectrum would have the same wavelength as the Balmer type transition from $$\\mathrm{n=4}$$ to $$\\mathrm{n}=2$$ of $$\\mathrm{He}^{+}$$ spectrum</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{n}=3$$ to $$\\mathrm{n}=4$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{n}=2$$ to $$\\mathrm{n}=1$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{n}=1$$ to $$\\mathrm{n}=2$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{n}=1$$ to $$\\mathrm{n}=3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{n}=2$$ to $$\\mathrm{n}=1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsrgqai",
    "question": "<p>The shortest wavelength of hydrogen atom in Lyman series is $$\\lambda$$. The longest wavelength is Balmer series of He$$^+$$ is </p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{36\\lambda}{5}$$",
      "$$\\frac{5}{9\\lambda}$$",
      "$$\\frac{9\\lambda}{5}$$",
      "$$\\frac{5\\lambda}{9}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{9\\lambda}{5}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfmnzhl",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 523px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 70px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 184px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 94px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 175px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - I<br/>(Spectral Series for Hydrogen)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - II<br/>(Spectral Region/Higher Energy State)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Lyman</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Infrared region</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Balmer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">UV region</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Paschen</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Infrared region</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Pfund</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Visible region</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I\n",
      "A-I, B-III, C-II, D-IV\n",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV\n",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2a7vy",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 690px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 239px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>Alkali Metal</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>Emission Wavelength in nm</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Li</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">589.2</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Na</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">455.5</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Rb</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">670.8</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Cs</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">780.0</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(IV), (C)-(III), (D)-(I)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(IV), (C)-(III), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(II), (C)-(I), (D)-(III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "xOzKpr8XmbTNXmji",
    "question": "A gas absorbs a photon of 355 nm and emits at two wavelengths. If one of the emissions is at\n 680 nm, the other is at :",
    "options": [
      "325 nm ",
      "743 nm ",
      "518 nm",
      "1035 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "743 nm "
  },
  {
    "id": "HqyOr7yIZjbwsK73rBKuD",
    "question": "Ejection of the photoelectron from metal in the photoelectric experiment can be stopped by applying 0.5 V when the radiation of 250 nm is used. The work function of the metal is : ",
    "options": [
      "4 eV",
      "4.5 eV",
      "5 eV",
      "5.5 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "4.5 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "HJ6RKzhE1DmEBo3FpEwJo",
    "question": "The de Broglie wavelength ($$\\lambda $$) associated with a photoelectron varies with the frequency (v) of the incident radiation as, [v<sub>0</sub> is threshold frequency] : ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda \\,\\infty \\,{1 \\over {{{\\left( {v - {v_0}} \\right)}^{{3 \\over 2}}}}}$$",
      "$$\\lambda \\,\\infty \\,{1 \\over {{{\\left( {v - {v_0}} \\right)}^{{1 \\over 4}}}}}$$",
      "$$\\lambda \\,\\infty \\,{1 \\over {\\left( {v - {v_0}} \\right)}}$$",
      "$$\\lambda \\,\\infty \\,{1 \\over {{{\\left( {v - {v_0}} \\right)}^{{1 \\over 2}}}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda \\,\\infty \\,{1 \\over {{{\\left( {v - {v_0}} \\right)}^{{1 \\over 2}}}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "6SUkkVQp6A51tmJMhTdmX",
    "question": "What is the work function of the metal if the light of wavelength 4000$$\\mathop A\\limits^ \\circ  $$ generates photoelectrons of velocity 6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup>  ms<sup>–1</sup> from it ? \n<br/>(Mass of electron = 9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–31</sup> kg;\n<br/>Velocity of light = 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>\n<br/>Plank's constant = 6.626 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–34</sup> Js; \n<br/>Charge of electron = 1.6 $$ \\times $$10<sup>–19</sup> JeV<sup>–1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "4.0 eV",
      "0.9 eV ",
      "2.1 eV ",
      "3.1 eV "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "2.1 eV "
  },
  {
    "id": "o9xcMFaHXOBYV1WoL3hoH",
    "question": "The upper stratosphere consisting of the ozone layer protects us from sun's radiation that falls in the wavelength region of - ",
    "options": [
      "200-315 nm ",
      "400-550 nm ",
      "0.8-1.5 nm",
      "600-750 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "200-315 nm "
  },
  {
    "id": "afkxwx7CCiYvJbEhj8JOn",
    "question": "If p is the momentum of the fastest electron\nejected from a metal surface after the irradiation\nof light having wavelength $$\\lambda $$, then for 1.5 p\nmomentum of the photoelectron, the\nwavelength of the light should be:\n(Assume kinetic energy of ejected\nphotoelectron to be very high in comparison\nto work function)",
    "options": [
      "1/2 $$\\lambda $$",
      "3/4 $$\\lambda $$",
      "4/9 $$\\lambda $$",
      "2/3 $$\\lambda $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "4/9 $$\\lambda $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59qewbw",
    "question": "<p>The minimum energy that must be possessed by photons in order to produce the photoelectric effect with platinum metal is :</p>\n<p>[Given : The threshold frequency of platinum is 1.3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup> s<sup>$$-$$1</sup> and h = 6.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> J s.]</p>",
    "options": [
      "3.21 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$14</sup> J",
      "6.24 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$16</sup> J",
      "8.58 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$19</sup> J",
      "9.76 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$20</sup> J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "8.58 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$19</sup> J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguza9op",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R :</p>\n<p>Assertion A : In the photoelectric effect, the electrons are ejected from the metal surface as soon as the beam of light of frequency greater than threshold frequency strikes the surface.</p>\n<p>Reason R : When the photon of any energy strikes an electron in the atom, transfer of energy from the photon to the electron takes place.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the  correct explanation of A",
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "A is correct but R is not correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxzq9as",
    "question": "<p>The candela is the luminous intensity, in a given direction, of a source that emits monochromatic radiation of frequency '$$A$$' $$\\times 10^{12}$$ hertz and that has a radiant intensity in that direction of $$\\frac{1}{{ 'B'}}$$, watt per steradian.\n'$$A$$' and '$$B$$' are respectively</p>",
    "options": [
      "450 and 683\n",
      "540 and $$\\frac{1}{683}$$\n",
      "540 and 683\n",
      "450 and $$\\frac{1}{683}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "540 and 683\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "bROozFyhm5jkbwI4fvbGs",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is <b>false</b> ?",
    "options": [
      "Photon has momentum as well as wavelength. ",
      "Splitting of spectral lines in electrical field is called Stark effect. ",
      "Rydberg constant has unit of energy. ",
      "Frequency of emitted radiation from a black body goes from a lower wavelength to higher wavelength as  the temperature increases. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-mechanical-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "Frequency of emitted radiation from a black body goes from a lower wavelength to higher wavelength as  the temperature increases. "
  },
  {
    "id": "WuxX0SVyhNlwREz1yOcAy",
    "question": "If the de Broglie wavelength of the electron in n<sup>th</sup> Bohr orbit in a hydrogenic atom is equal to 1.5 $$\\pi $$a<sub>0</sub> (a<sub>0</sub> is Bohr radius), then the value of n/z is - ",
    "options": [
      "0.75",
      "0.40",
      "1.50",
      "1.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-mechanical-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "0.75"
  },
  {
    "id": "XaEFXP0Tja2lYqx59Lvx2",
    "question": "Which one of the following about an electron\noccupying the 1s orbital in a hydrogen atom is\nincorrect ?<br/><br/> (The Bohr radius is represented\nby a<sub>0</sub>)",
    "options": [
      "The probability density of finding the\nelectron is maximum at the nucleus.",
      "The electron can be found at a distance 2a<sub>0</sub>\nfrom the nucleus",
      "The total energy of the electron is maximum\nwhen it is at a distance a<sub>0</sub> from the nucleus.",
      "The magnitude of potential energy is\ndouble that of its kinetic energy on an\naverage."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-mechanical-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "The total energy of the electron is maximum\nwhen it is at a distance a<sub>0</sub> from the nucleus."
  },
  {
    "id": "qsZP0WPT9wfLCKwnyxjgy2xukfouqx0h",
    "question": "The correct statement about probability density (except at infinite distance from nucleus) is :",
    "options": [
      "It can be zero for 1s orbital",
      "It can be zero for 3p orbital",
      "It can never be zero for 2s orbital",
      "It can negative for 2p orbital"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-mechanical-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "It can be zero for 3p orbital"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bcu17r",
    "question": "<p>The energy of one mole of photons of radiation of wavelength 300 nm is<br/><br/> (Given : h = 6.63 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> J s, N<sub>A</sub> = 6.02 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>23</sup> mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, c = 3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> m s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "235 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "325 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "399 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "435 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-mechanical-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "399 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqxknea",
    "question": "The wave function $(\\Psi)$ of $2 \\mathrm{~s}$ is given by<br/><br/>\n$$\n\\Psi_{2 \\mathrm{~s}}=\\frac{1}{2 \\sqrt{2 \\pi}}\\left(\\frac{1}{a_0}\\right)^{1 / 2}\\left(2-\\frac{r}{a_0}\\right) e^{-r / 2 a_0}\n$$<br/><br/>\nAt $r=r_0$, radial node is formed. Thus, $r_0$ in terms of $a_0$",
    "options": [
      "$r_0=a_0$",
      "$r_0=4 a_0$",
      "$r_0=2 a_0$",
      "$r_0=\\frac{a_0}{2}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-mechanical-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "$r_0=2 a_0$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh320r86",
    "question": "<p>If the radius of the first orbit of hydrogen atom is $$\\alpha_{0}$$, then de Broglie's wavelength of electron in $$3^{\\text {rd }}$$ orbit is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\pi \\alpha^{3}}{6}$$",
      "$$3\\pi\\alpha_0$$",
      "$$6\\pi\\alpha_0$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi \\alpha^{3}}{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-mechanical-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "$$6\\pi\\alpha_0$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbm99de",
    "question": "In case of isoelectronic species the size of $\\mathrm{F}^{-}, \\mathrm{Ne}$ and $\\mathrm{Na}^{+}$is affected by :",
    "options": [
      "Nuclear charge $(\\mathrm{z})$",
      "None of the factors because their size is the same",
      "Electron-electron interaction in the outer orbitals",
      "Principal quantum number (n)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-mechanical-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "Nuclear charge $(\\mathrm{z})$"
  },
  {
    "id": "kn7jsYYGSQqucQDd",
    "question": "The orbital angular momentum for an electron revolving in an orbit is given by $$\\sqrt {l(l + 1)} {h \\over {2\\pi }}$$. This momentum for an s-electron will be given by",
    "options": [
      "zero",
      "$${h \\over {2\\pi }}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 {h \\over {2\\pi }}$$",
      "$$ + {1 \\over 2}{h \\over {2\\pi }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "zero"
  },
  {
    "id": "1tx8tYJ1jHptsti0",
    "question": "Which of the following sets of quantum numbers is correct for an electron in 4f orbital?",
    "options": [
      "n = 4, l = 3, m = +1, s = + 1/2",
      "n = 4, l = 4, m = -4, s = - 1/2",
      "n = 4, l = 3, m = +4, s = + 1/2",
      "n = 3, l = 2, m = -2, s = + 1/2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "n = 4, l = 3, m = +1, s = + 1/2"
  },
  {
    "id": "OfWe1r8mlv35VE0s",
    "question": "Consider the ground state of Cr atom (Z = 24). The number of electrons with the azimuthal quantum numbers, l = 1 and 2 are respectively",
    "options": [
      "16 and 4",
      "12 and 5",
      "12 and 4",
      "16 and 5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "12 and 5"
  },
  {
    "id": "AU3WplgNeEgPJaPK",
    "question": "In a multi-electron atom, which of the following orbitals described by the three quantum members will have the same energy in the absence of magnetic and electric fields?<br/>\n<b>(A)</b> n = 1, l = 0, m = 0<br/>\n<b>(B)</b> n = 2, l = 0, m = 0<br/>\n<b>(C)</b> n = 2, l = 1, m = 1<br/>\n<b>(D)</b> n = 3, l = 2, m = 1<br/>\n<b>(E)</b> n = 3, l = 2, m = 0<br/>",
    "options": [
      "(D) and (E)",
      "(C) and (D)",
      "(B) and (C)",
      "(A) and (B)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "(D) and (E)"
  },
  {
    "id": "ELLdcc63i6nzceU7",
    "question": "Which of the following sets of quantum numbers represents the highest energy of an atom?",
    "options": [
      "n = 3, l = 0, m = 0, s = +1/ 2",
      "n = 3, l = 1, m = 1, s = +1/ 2",
      "n = 3, l = 2, m = 1, s = +1/ 2",
      "n = 4, l = 0, m = 0, s = +1/ 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "n = 3, l = 2, m = 1, s = +1/ 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "kuUs7Pzl8TLEZHtZ",
    "question": "The electrons identified by quantum numbers n and l :<br/>\n(a) n = 4, $$l$$ = 1<br/>\n(b) n = 4, $$ l$$ = 0<br/>\n(c) n = 3, $$l$$ = 2<br/>\n(d) n = 3, $$l$$ = 1<br/>\nCan be placed in order of increasing energy as :",
    "options": [
      "(c) &lt; (d) &lt; (b) &lt; (a)",
      "(d) &lt; (b) &lt; (c) &lt; (a)",
      "(b) &lt; (d) &lt; (a) &lt; (c)",
      "(a) &lt; (c) &lt; (b) &lt; (d)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "(d) &lt; (b) &lt; (c) &lt; (a)"
  },
  {
    "id": "2Dl5N3E8p9oof6za",
    "question": "The correct set of four quantum numbers for the valence elections of rubidium atom (Z= 37) is:",
    "options": [
      "5, 1, 1, + 1/2",
      "5, 1, 0, + 1/2",
      "5, 0, 0, + 1/2",
      "5, 0, 1, + 1/2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "5, 0, 0, + 1/2"
  },
  {
    "id": "uZKcj9ZVstfKbQckfQORm",
    "question": "The total number of orbitals associated with the principal quantum number 5 is :",
    "options": [
      "5",
      "10",
      "20",
      "25"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "25"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZJwfAyrNkLLSdcdVLlB31",
    "question": "The highest value of the calculated spin only  magnetic moment  (in BM) among all the transition metal complexes is : ",
    "options": [
      "5.92",
      "6.93",
      "3.87",
      "4.90"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "5.92"
  },
  {
    "id": "YI1qnu75AyGwhM6uNfioM",
    "question": "Which of the following combination of statements is true regarding the interpretation of the atomic orbitals ? <br/><br/>\n(a) An electron in an orbital of high angular momentum stays away from the nucleus than an electron in the orbital of lower angular momentum. <br/><br/>\n(b) For a given value of the principal quantum number, the size of the orbit is inversely proportional to the azimuthal quantum number. <br/><br/>\n(c) According to wave mechanics, the ground state angular momentum is equal to $${h \\over {2\\pi }}$$.<br/><br/>\n(d) The plot of $$\\psi $$ vs r for various azimuthal quantum numbers, shows peak shifting towards higher r value. ",
    "options": [
      "(a), (b)",
      "(a), (d)",
      "(b), (c)",
      "(a), (c)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "(a), (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": "FD5WMRAgscXSkzRrqWAsl",
    "question": "The quantum number of four electrons are given below :<br/>\nn = 4, l = 2, m<sub>l</sub> =–2, m<sub>s</sub> = –1/2<br/>\nn = 3, l = 2, m<sub>l</sub> = 1, m<sub>s</sub> = +1/2<br/>\nn = 4, l = 1, m<sub>l</sub> = 0, m<sub>s</sub> = +1/2<br/>\nn = 3, l = 1, m<sub>l</sub> = 1, m<sub>s</sub> = –1/2<br/>\nThe correct order of their increasing enegies will be :",
    "options": [
      "IV &lt; II &lt; III &lt; I",
      "I &lt; III &lt; II &lt; IV",
      "IV &lt; III &lt; II &lt; I",
      "I &lt; II &lt; III &lt; IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "IV &lt; II &lt; III &lt; I"
  },
  {
    "id": "fNVB1JjmQVWjETZenV7k9k2k5dzy7mo",
    "question": "The number of orbitals associated with quantum number n = 5, m<sub>s</sub> = +$${1 \\over 2}$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "11",
      "25",
      "15",
      "50"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "25"
  },
  {
    "id": "Txt0uLrhcklmhRd7XJjgy2xukf3hktvy",
    "question": "Consider the hypothetical situation where the\nazimuthal quantum number,\n$$l$$, takes values 0,\n1, 2, ....., n + 1, where n is the principal\nquantum number. Then, the element with\natomic number :",
    "options": [
      "13 has a half-filled valence subshell",
      "9 is the first alkali metal",
      "8 is the first noble gas",
      "6 has a 2p-valence subshell"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "13 has a half-filled valence subshell"
  },
  {
    "id": "l90OnnrzB5z7lw0oLOjgy2xukey6zsg9",
    "question": "The number of subshells associated with n = 4\nand m = –2 quantum numbers is",
    "options": [
      "8",
      "2",
      "16",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l548hspn",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following statements are correct?</p>\n<p>(A) The electronic configuration of Cr is [Ar] 3d<sup>5</sup> 4s<sup>1</sup>.</p>\n<p>(B) The magnetic quantum number may have a negative value.</p>\n<p>(C) In the ground state of an atom, the orbitals are filled in order of their increasing energies.</p>\n<p>(D) The total number of nodes are given by n $$-$$ 2.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A), (C) and (D) only",
      "(A) and (B) only",
      "(A) and (C) only",
      "(A), (B) and (C) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "(A), (B) and (C) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55mu84s",
    "question": "<p>Consider the following statements :</p>\n<p>(A) The principal quantum number 'n' is a positive integer with values of 'n' = 1, 2, 3, ...</p>\n<p>(B) The azimuthal quantum number 'l' for a given 'n' (principal quantum number) can have values as 'l' = 0, 1, 2, ...... n</p>\n<p>(C) Magnetic orbital quantum number 'm<sub>l</sub>' for a particular 'l' (azimuthal quantum number) has (2l + 1) values.</p>\n<p>(D) $$\\pm$$ 1/2 are the two possible orientations of electron spin.</p>\n<p>(E) For l = 5, there will be a total of 9 orbital</p>\n<p>Which of the above statements are correct?</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A), (B) and (C)",
      "(A), (C), (D) and (E)",
      "(A), (C) and (D)",
      "(A), (B), (C) and (D)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "(A), (C) and (D)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c5zysg",
    "question": "<p>Consider the following pairs of electrons</p>\n<p>(A) (a) n = 3, $$l$$ = 1, m<sub>1</sub> = 1, m<sub>s</sub> = + $${1 \\over 2}$$</p>\n<p>      (b) n = 3, 1 = 2, m<sub>1</sub> = 1, m<sub>s</sub> = + $${1 \\over 2}$$</p>\n<p>(B) (a) n = 3, $$l$$ = 2, m<sub>1</sub> = $$-$$2, m<sub>s</sub> = $$-$$$${1 \\over 2}$$</p>\n<p>      (b) n = 3, $$l$$ = 2, m<sub>1</sub> = $$-$$1, m<sub>s</sub> = $$-$$$${1 \\over 2}$$</p>\n<p>(C) (a) n = 4, $$l$$ = 2, m<sub>1</sub> = 2, m<sub>s</sub> = + $${1 \\over 2}$$</p>\n<p>      (b) n = 3, $$l$$ = 2, m<sub>1</sub> = 2, m<sub>s</sub> = + $${1 \\over 2}$$</p>\n<p>The pairs of electrons present in degenerate orbitals is/are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Only (A)",
      "Only (B)",
      "Only (C)",
      "(B) and (C)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "Only (B)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w5fan6",
    "question": "<p>The number of radial nodes and total number of nodes in 4p orbital respectively are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 and 3",
      "2 and 2",
      "3 and 4",
      "4 and 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "2 and 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6e0k8m9",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following sets of quantum numbers is not allowed?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\n\\mathrm{n}=3,1=2, \\mathrm{~m}_{\\mathrm{l}}=0, \\mathrm{~s}=+\\frac{1}{2}\n$$",
      "$$\n\\mathrm{n}=3, \\mathrm{l}=2, \\mathrm{~m}_{\\mathrm{l}}=-2, \\mathrm{~s}=+\\frac{1}{2}\n$$",
      "$$\n\\mathrm{n}=3, \\mathrm{l}=3, \\mathrm{~m}_{\\mathrm{l}}=-3, \\mathrm{~s}=-\\frac{1}{2}\n$$",
      "$$\n\\mathrm{n}=3, \\mathrm{l}=0, \\mathrm{~m}_{1}=0, \\mathrm{~s}=-\\frac{1}{2}\n$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "$$\n\\mathrm{n}=3, \\mathrm{l}=3, \\mathrm{~m}_{\\mathrm{l}}=-3, \\mathrm{~s}=-\\frac{1}{2}\n$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kov76x",
    "question": "<p>The correct decreasing order of energy for the orbitals having, following set of quantum numbers :</p>\n<p>(A) n = 3, l = 0, m = 0</p>\n<p>(B) n = 4, l = 0, m = 0</p>\n<p>(C) n = 3, l = 1, m = 0</p>\n<p>(D) n = 3, l = 2, m = 1</p>\n<p>is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(D) > (B) > (C) > (A)",
      "(B) > (D) > (C) > (A)",
      "(C) > (B) > (D) > (A)",
      "(B) > (C) > (D) > (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "(D) > (B) > (C) > (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nughc7",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ : Zero orbital overlap is an out of phase overlap.</p>\n<p>Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$ : It results due to different orientation / direction of approach of orbitals.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rj8621",
    "question": "<p>Given below are the quantum numbers for 4 electrons.</p>\n<p>A. $$\\mathrm{n}=3,l=2, \\mathrm{~m}_{1}=1, \\mathrm{~m}_{\\mathrm{s}}=+1 / 2$$</p>\n<p>B. $$\\mathrm{n}=4,l=1, \\mathrm{~m}_{1}=0, \\mathrm{~m}_{\\mathrm{s}}=+1 / 2$$</p>\n<p>C. $$\\mathrm{n}=4,l=2, \\mathrm{~m}_{1}=-2, \\mathrm{~m}_{\\mathrm{s}}=-1 / 2$$</p>\n<p>D. $$\\mathrm{n}=3,l=1, \\mathrm{~m}_{1}=-1, \\mathrm{~m}_{\\mathrm{s}}=+1 / 2$$</p>\n<p>The correct order of increasing energy is</p>",
    "options": [
      "D < B < A < C",
      "D < A < B < C",
      "B < D < A < C",
      "B < D < C < A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "D < A < B < C"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo9gadb",
    "question": "Arrange the following orbitals in decreasing order of energy.<br/><br/>\nA. $\\mathrm{n}=3, \\mathrm{l}=0, \\mathrm{~m}=0$<br/><br/>\nB. $\\mathrm{n}=4, \\mathrm{l}=0, \\mathrm{~m}=0$<br/><br/>\nC. $\\mathrm{n}=3, \\mathrm{l}=1, \\mathrm{~m}=0$<br/><br/>\nD. $\\mathrm{n}=3, \\mathrm{l}=2, \\mathrm{~m}=1$\n<br/><br/>\nThe correct option for the order is :",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{D}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{A}$",
      "$\\mathrm{A}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{D}$",
      "$\\mathrm{D}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{A}>\\mathrm{C}$",
      "$\\mathrm{D}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{A}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{D}>\\mathrm{B}>\\mathrm{C}>\\mathrm{A}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqxaaeh",
    "question": "Maximum number of electrons that can be accommodated in shell with $n=4$ are:",
    "options": [
      "50",
      "32",
      "72",
      "16"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "32"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyg36lx",
    "question": "<p>The magnetic moment of a transition metal compound has been calculated to be 3.87 B.M. The metal ion is</p>",
    "options": [
      "Ti$$^{2+}$$",
      "V$$^{2+}$$",
      "Cr$$^{2+}$$",
      "Mn$$^{2+}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "V$$^{2+}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd9bc2m",
    "question": "<p>The four quantum numbers for the electron in the outer most orbital of potassium (atomic no. 19) are</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{n}=3, l=0, \\mathrm{~m}=1, \\mathrm{~s}=+\\frac{1}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{n}=4, l=0, \\mathrm{~m}=0, s=+\\frac{1}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{n}=2, l=0, \\mathrm{~m}=0, s=+\\frac{1}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{n}=4, l=2, \\mathrm{~m}=-1, s=+\\frac{1}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{n}=4, l=0, \\mathrm{~m}=0, s=+\\frac{1}{2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjl0qx",
    "question": "<p>The correct set of four quantum numbers for the valence electron of rubidium atom $$(\\mathrm{Z}=37)$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$5,1,1,+\\frac{1}{2}$$\n",
      "$$5,0,0,+\\frac{1}{2}$$\n",
      "$$5,0,1,+\\frac{1}{2}$$\n",
      "$$5,1,0,+\\frac{1}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "$$5,0,0,+\\frac{1}{2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgy7zzo",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : The orbitals having same energy are called as degenerate orbitals.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : In hydrogen atom, 3p and 3d orbitals are not degenerate orbitals.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2un1m",
    "question": "<p>Compare the energies of following sets of quantum numbers for multielectron system.</p>\n<p>(A) $$\\mathrm{n}=4,1=1$$</p>\n<p>(B) $$\\mathrm{n}=4,1=2$$</p>\n<p>(C) $$\\mathrm{n}=3, \\mathrm{l}=1$$</p>\n<p>(D) $$\\mathrm{n}=3,1=2$$</p>\n<p>(E) $$\\mathrm{n}=4,1=0$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\n(\\mathrm{E})>(\\mathrm{C})>(\\mathrm{A})>(\\mathrm{D})>(\\mathrm{B})\n$$",
      "$$\n(\\mathrm{B})>(\\mathrm{A})>(\\mathrm{C})>(\\mathrm{E})>(\\mathrm{D})\n$$",
      "$$\n(\\mathrm{C})<(\\mathrm{E})<(\\mathrm{D})<(\\mathrm{A})<(\\mathrm{B})\n$$",
      "$$\n(\\mathrm{E})<(\\mathrm{C})<(\\mathrm{D})<(\\mathrm{A})<(\\mathrm{B})\n$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "quantum-numbers-and-orbitals",
    "solution": "$$\n(\\mathrm{C})<(\\mathrm{E})<(\\mathrm{D})<(\\mathrm{A})<(\\mathrm{B})\n$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krz0qljv",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : Rutherford's gold foil experiment cannot explain the line spectrum of hydrogen atom.<br/><br/>Statement II : Bohr's model of hydrogen atom contradicts Heisenberg' uncertainty principle.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true.",
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false.",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false.",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "thomson's-model-and-rutherford's-model",
    "solution": "Both statement I and statement II are true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1id595",
    "question": "If the Thompson model of the atom was correct, then the result of Rutherford's gold foil experiment would have been :",
    "options": [
      "All of the $$\\alpha$$-particles pass through the gold foil without decrease in speed.",
      "$$\\alpha$$-particles are deflected over a wide range of angles.",
      "All $$\\alpha$$-particles get bounced back by 180$$^\\circ$$",
      "$$\\alpha$$-particles pass through the gold foil deflected by small angles and with reduced speed."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "thomson's-model-and-rutherford's-model",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha$$-particles pass through the gold foil deflected by small angles and with reduced speed."
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erjgk",
    "question": "<p>Choose the Incorrect Statement about Dalton's Atomic Theory</p>",
    "options": [
      "Compounds are formed when atoms of different elements combine in any ratio.\n",
      "Matter consists of indivisible atoms.\n",
      "chemical reactions involve reorganization of atoms\n",
      "All the atoms of a given element have identical properties including identical mass."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "thomson's-model-and-rutherford's-model",
    "solution": "Compounds are formed when atoms of different elements combine in any ratio.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3tzr",
    "question": "<p>The incorrect postulates of the Dalton's atomic theory are :</p>\n<p>(A) Atoms of different elements differ in mass.</p>\n<p>(B) Matter consists of divisible atoms.</p>\n<p>(C) Compounds are formed when atoms of different element combine in a fixed ratio.</p>\n<p>(D) All the atoms of given element have different properties including mass.</p>\n<p>(E) Chemical reactions involve reorganisation of atoms.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(B), (D) only\n",
      "(A), (B), (D) only\n",
      "(B), (D), (E) only\n",
      "(C), (D), (E) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "structure-of-atom",
    "topic": "thomson's-model-and-rutherford's-model",
    "solution": "(B), (D) only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse7p62x",
    "question": "<p>'Adsorption' principle is used for which of the following purification method?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Chromatography\n",
      "Sublimation\n",
      "Distillation\n",
      "Extraction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "adsorption",
    "solution": "Chromatography\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2es2sk",
    "question": "<p>The adsorbent used in adsorption chromatography is/are -</p>\n<p>A. silica gel</p>\n<p>B. alumina</p>\n<p>C. quick lime</p>\n<p>D. magnesia</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "C and D only\n",
      "A only\n",
      "B only\n",
      "A and B only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "adsorption",
    "solution": "A and B only"
  },
  {
    "id": "aZF2dryeJYL0x8nUshhoN",
    "question": "Which of the following is not an example of heterogenous catalytic reaction?",
    "options": [
      "Ostwald's process ",
      "Combustion of coal ",
      "Hydrogenation of vegetable oils ",
      "Haber's process "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "catalysis",
    "solution": "Combustion of coal "
  },
  {
    "id": "qmJpQFnpbWjVANadlI886",
    "question": "Match the catalysts <b>(Column I)</b> with products\n<b>(Column II)</b>.<br/><br/>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-s6z2{text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-hgcj{font-weight:bold;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-hgcj\">Column I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-hgcj\">Column II</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(A) V<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(i) Polyethylene</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(B) TiCl<sub>4</sub>/Al(Me)<sub>3</sub></td>\n<td class=\"tg-s6z2\">(ii) ethanal</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(C) PdCl<sub>2</sub></td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(iii) H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub></td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(D) Iron Oxide</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(iv) NH<sub>3</sub></td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(iii); (B)-(i); (C)-(ii); (D)-(iv)",
      "(A)-(ii); (B)-(iii); (C)-(i); (D)-(iv)",
      "(A)-(iii); (B)-(iv); (C)-(i); (D)-(ii)",
      "(A)-(iv); (B)-(iii); (C)-(ii); (D)-(i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "catalysis",
    "solution": "(A)-(iii); (B)-(i); (C)-(ii); (D)-(iv)"
  },
  {
    "id": "KxcP4BNmWppLIR0e7m7k9k2k5hlv6y6",
    "question": "For the following Assertion and Reason, the\ncorrect option is<br/>\n<b>Assertion </b>: For hydrogenation reactions, the\ncatalytic activity increases from Group 5 to\nGroup 11 metals with maximum activity shown\nby Group 7-9 elements.<br/>\n<b>Reason</b> : The reactants are most strongly\nadsorbed on group 7-9 elements.",
    "options": [
      "Both assertion and reason are true and\nthe reason is the correct explanation for\nthe assertion.",
      "The assertion is true, but the reason is false.",
      "Both assertion and reason are true but the\nreason is not the correct explanation for the\nassertion.",
      "Both assertion and reason are false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "catalysis",
    "solution": "The assertion is true, but the reason is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mcfm48",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-fymr{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"table-layout: fixed; width: 805px;overflow-x:auto;\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 588px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 34px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 135px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-fymr\">List - I<br/>Reaction</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-fymr\">List - II<br/>Catalyst</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$4N{H_3}(g) + 5{O_2}(g) \\to 4NO(g) + 6{H_2}O(g)$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$NO(g)$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${N_2}(g) + 3{H_2}(g) \\to 2N{H_3}(g)$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${H_2}S{O_4}(l)$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${C_{12}}{H_{22}}{O_{11}}(aq) + {H_2}O(l) \\to \\mathop {{C_6}{H_{12}}{O_6}}\\limits_{Glu\\cos e}  + \\mathop {{C_6}{H_{12}}{O_6}}\\limits_{Fructose} $$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$Pt(s)$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$2S{O_2}(g) + {O_2}(g) \\to 2S{O_3}(g)$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$Fe(s)$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{I}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{IV})$$",
      "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{I})$$",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (II), (C) - (IV), (D) - (I)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "catalysis",
    "solution": "$$(\\mathrm{A})-(\\mathrm{III}),(\\mathrm{B})-(\\mathrm{IV}),(\\mathrm{C})-(\\mathrm{II}),(\\mathrm{D})-(\\mathrm{I})$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "VlRpNsphLZ69vv6c",
    "question": "Alum helps in purifying water by :",
    "options": [
      "forming Si complex with clay particles",
      "sulphate part which combines with the dirt and removes it",
      "coagulating the mud particles",
      "making mud water soluble"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "coagulating the mud particles"
  },
  {
    "id": "gosQcP9CLd5jF8tK",
    "question": "The disperse phase in colloidal iron (III) hydroxide and colloidal gold is positively and\nnegatively charged, respectively, which of the following statements is NOT correct?",
    "options": [
      "magnesium chloride solution coagulates, the gold sol more readily than the iron\n(III) hydroxide sol. ",
      "sodium sulphate solution causes coagulation in both sols",
      "mixing the sols has no effect",
      "coagulation in both sols can be brought about by electrophoresis "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "mixing the sols has no effect"
  },
  {
    "id": "y7j8Q8O1fYzk2rhH",
    "question": "The volume of a colloidal particle, V<sub>C</sub> as compared to the volume of a solute particle\nin a true solution V<sub>S</sub>, could be ",
    "options": [
      "$${V_C \\over V_S } \\simeq 1$$",
      "$${V_C \\over V_S } \\simeq 10^{-3}$$",
      "$${V_C \\over V_S } \\simeq 10^3$$",
      "$${V_C \\over V_S } \\simeq 10^{23}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "$${V_C \\over V_S } \\simeq 10^3$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "pEeegZrKsKEzGaE8",
    "question": "Gold numbers of protective colloids A, B, C and D are 0.50, 0.01, 0.10 and 0.005, respectively. The\ncorrect order of their protective powers is",
    "options": [
      "D &lt; A &lt; C &lt; B",
      "C &lt; B &lt; D &lt; A ",
      "A &lt; C &lt; B &lt; D",
      "B &lt; D &lt; A &lt; C "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "A &lt; C &lt; B &lt; D"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ql4OXRsAXcqFDiN5",
    "question": "The coagulating power of electrolytes having ions Na<sup>+</sup>, Al<sup>3+</sup> and Ba<sup>2+</sup> for arsenic sulphide sol increases in the order: ",
    "options": [
      "Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; Ba<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Al<sup>3+</sup>",
      "Al<sup>3+</sup> &lt; Ba<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> ",
      "Ba<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt;  Al<sup>3+</sup>   ",
      "Al<sup>3+</sup>    &lt; Na<sup>+</sup> &lt;  Ba<sup>2+</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; Ba<sup>2+</sup> &lt; Al<sup>3+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "4r0je9s1CICt1J5Q3fcK0",
    "question": "The most appropriate method of making egg-albumin sol is :\n",
    "options": [
      "Break an egg carefully and transfer the transparent part of the content to 100 mL of 5% w/V saline solution and stir well",
      "Break an egg carefully and transfer only the yellow part of the content to 100 mL of 5% w/V saline solution and stir well.",
      "Keep the egg in boiling water for 10 minutes. After removing the shell, transfer the white part of the content to 100 mL of 5% w/V saline solution and homogenize with a mechanical shaker.",
      "Keep the egg in boiling water for 10 minutes. After removing the shell, transfer the yellow part of the content to 100 mL of 5% w/V saline solutionand homogenize with a mechanical shaker."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Break an egg carefully and transfer the transparent part of the content to 100 mL of 5% w/V saline solution and stir well"
  },
  {
    "id": "T4yATZAcxd3GO3S6eezAn",
    "question": "Gold numbers of some colloids are : Gelatin : 0.005 - 0.01, Gum Arabic : 0.15 - 0.25; Oleate : 0.04 - 1.0; Starch : 15 - 25. Which among these is a\nbetter protective colloid ?",
    "options": [
      "Gelatin",
      "Gum Arabic",
      "Oleate",
      "Starch"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Gelatin"
  },
  {
    "id": "fRCyhch2Z1CLXq2A",
    "question": "The Tyndall effect is observed only when following conditions are satisfied:<br/>\n(a) The diameter of the dispersed particles is much smaller than the wavelength of the light used.<br/>\n(b) The diameter of the dispersed particle is not much smaller than the wavelength of the light used.<br/>\n(c) The refractive indices of the dispersed phase and dispersion medium are almost similar in magnitude.<br/>\n(d) The refractive indices of the dispersed phase and dispersion medium differ greatly in magnitude. ",
    "options": [
      "(b) and (d)",
      "(a) and (c)",
      "(b) and (c)",
      "(a) and (d)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "(b) and (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": "VVuTz7zOVa1BI6sbMl6AV",
    "question": "Among the following, correct statement is :",
    "options": [
      "Brownian movement is more pronounced for smaller particles than for bigger–particles",
      "Sols of metal sulphides are lyophilic.",
      "Hardy Schulze law states that bigger the size of the ions, the greater is its\ncoagulating power.",
      "One would expect charcoal to adsorb chlorine more than hydrogen sulphide."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "One would expect charcoal to adsorb chlorine more than hydrogen sulphide."
  },
  {
    "id": "7QMYW58iC205VnmxBxLr7",
    "question": "Which of the following statements about colloids is <b>False </b>?",
    "options": [
      "Freezing point of colloidal solution is lower than true solution at same concentration of a solute. ",
      "Colloidal particles can pass through ordinary filter paper.",
      "When silver nitrate solution is added to potassium iodide solution, a negatively charged colloidal solution is formed. ",
      "When excess of electolyte is added to colloidal solution, colloidal particle will be precipitated."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Freezing point of colloidal solution is lower than true solution at same concentration of a solute. "
  },
  {
    "id": "YCDBZD9RuHNJOecoH7dUZ",
    "question": "Among the colloids cheese (C), milk (M), and smoke (S), the correct combination of the dispersed phase and dispersion medium, respectively is : ",
    "options": [
      "C : liquid in solid ; M : liquid in liquid ; S : solid in gas ",
      "C : liquid in solid ; M : liquid in solid ; S : solid in gas",
      "C : solid in liquid ; M : liquid in liquid ; S : gas in solid ",
      "C : solid in liqid ; M : solid in liquid ; S : solid in gas \n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "C : liquid in solid ; M : liquid in liquid ; S : solid in gas "
  },
  {
    "id": "qzWni6Pu21YFK21OQb3rsa0w2w9jx7vzvnw",
    "question": "Among the following, the INCORRECT statement about colloids is :\n",
    "options": [
      "The range of diameters of colloidal particles is between 1 and to 1000 nm",
      "they are larger than small molecules and have high molar mass",
      "They can scatter light",
      "The osmotic pressure of a colloidal solution is of higher order than the true solution at the same\nconcentration."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "The osmotic pressure of a colloidal solution is of higher order than the true solution at the same\nconcentration."
  },
  {
    "id": "c5ed5JYlxACfvwUrVV3rsa0w2w9jx4z1vgb",
    "question": "Peptization is a :",
    "options": [
      "process of converting soluble particles to form colloidal solution",
      "process of converting precipitate into colloidal solution",
      "process of bringing colloidal molecule into solution",
      "process of converting a colloidal solution into precipitate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "process of converting precipitate into colloidal solution"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ay5VmT5sAvYMA4FHDM3rsa0w2w9jx0ufiqs",
    "question": "The correct option among the following is :",
    "options": [
      "Addition of alum to water makes it unfit for drinking.",
      "Colloidal medicines are more effective because they have small surface area.",
      "Colloidal paraticles in lyophobic sols can be precipitated by electrophoresis.",
      "Brownian motion in colloidal solution is faster if the viscosity of the solution is very high."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Colloidal paraticles in lyophobic sols can be precipitated by electrophoresis."
  },
  {
    "id": "e1dslVlbtOrGXTTCJif1g",
    "question": "The aerosol is a kind of colloid in which :",
    "options": [
      "solid is dispersed in gas",
      "gas is dispersed in solid",
      "gas is dispersed in liquid",
      "liquid is dispersed in water"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "solid is dispersed in gas"
  },
  {
    "id": "fh7FvpbAwAgAAkX8hEf91",
    "question": "Among the following the false statement is -",
    "options": [
      "Lyophilic sol can be coagulated by adding an electrote ",
      "Tyndall effect can be used to distinguish between a colloidal solution and a true solution ",
      "It is possible to cause artificial rain by throwing electrified sand carrying charge opposite to the one on clouds from an aeroplane",
      "Latex is a colloidal solution of rubber particles which are positively charged "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Latex is a colloidal solution of rubber particles which are positively charged "
  },
  {
    "id": "BfpVOfAr1z4BJ7Kp4vA0h",
    "question": "An example of solid sol is : ",
    "options": [
      "Butter",
      "Hair cream",
      "Gem stones",
      "Paint"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Gem stones"
  },
  {
    "id": "FZLerdAfYNiY5LAZXus5Z",
    "question": "Haemoglobin and gold sol are examples of : ",
    "options": [
      "positively charged sols",
      "negatively charged sols",
      "Positively and negatively charged sols, respectively \n",
      "negatively and positively charged sols, respectively "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Positively and negatively charged sols, respectively \n"
  },
  {
    "id": "miMFHPOgfCgdem6M1qFFF",
    "question": "For coagulation of arsenious sulphate sol, which one of the following salt solution will be most effective ? ",
    "options": [
      "BaCl<sub>2</sub>",
      "AlCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "NaCl",
      "Na<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "AlCl<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "o77BKzl7ctMOI0a2fI7k9k2k5h2wthc",
    "question": "As per Hardy-Schulze formulation, the flocculation values of the following for ferric hydroxide sol are in the\norder :",
    "options": [
      "AICl<sub>3</sub> &gt; K<sub>3</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>] &gt; K<sub>2</sub>CrO<sub>4</sub> &gt; KBr = KNO<sub>3</sub>",
      "K<sub>3</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>] &lt; K<sub>2</sub>CrO<sub>4</sub> &lt; KBr = KNO<sub>3</sub> = AlCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "K<sub>3</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>] &lt; K<sub>2</sub>CrO<sub>4</sub> &lt; AlCl<sub>3</sub> &lt; KBr &lt; KNO<sub>3</sub>",
      "K<sub>3</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>] &gt; AlCl<sub>3</sub> &gt; K<sub>2</sub>CrO<sub>4</sub> &gt; KBr &gt; KNO<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "K<sub>3</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>] &lt; K<sub>2</sub>CrO<sub>4</sub> &lt; KBr = KNO<sub>3</sub> = AlCl<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "bMfP4Y4lJQ1dG1YCvTjgy2xukft6yw4a",
    "question": "Kraft temperature is the temperature :",
    "options": [
      "below which the aqueous solution of\ndetergents starts freezing.",
      "above which the formation of micelles takes\nplace.",
      "below which the formation of micelles takes\nplace.",
      "above which the aqueous solution of\ndetergents starts boiling."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "above which the formation of micelles takes\nplace."
  },
  {
    "id": "PJE05lWLOtmyrfjGG1jgy2xukfcfcxjw",
    "question": "A sample of red ink (a colloidal suspension) is\nprepared by mixing eosin dye, egg white, HCHO\nand water. The component which ensures\nstability of the ink sample is :",
    "options": [
      "HCHO",
      "Water",
      "Eosin dye",
      "Egg white"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Egg white"
  },
  {
    "id": "iNc6gYDQGEIb1ueWhUjgy2xukf925i6p",
    "question": "Match the following :<br/><br/>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">(i) Foam</th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\"> (a) smoke</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(ii) Gel</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(b) cell fluid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(iii) Aerosol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\"> (c) jellies</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(iv) Emulsion</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\"> (d) rubber\n</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(e) froth</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(f) Milk</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "(i)-(e), (ii)-(c), (iii)-(a), (iv)-(f)",
      "(i)-(d), (ii)-(b), (iii)-(a), (iv)-(e)",
      "(i)-(d), (ii)-(b), (iii)-(e), (iv)-(f)",
      "(i)-(b), (ii)-(c), (iii)-(e), (iv)-(d)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "(i)-(e), (ii)-(c), (iii)-(a), (iv)-(f)"
  },
  {
    "id": "T60hgImpCTj8NHN886jgy2xukf2cbbyu",
    "question": "Tyndall effect is observed when:",
    "options": [
      "The diameter of dispersed particles is similar to the wavelenght of light used.",
      "The diameter of dispersed particles is much smaller than the wavelength of light used.",
      "The diameter of dispersed particles is much larger than the wavelength of light used.",
      "The refractive index of dispersed phase is greater than that of the dispersion medium."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "The diameter of dispersed particles is similar to the wavelenght of light used."
  },
  {
    "id": "7DVTTROmCYXe7I0Gi6jgy2xukevl5bks",
    "question": "Which of the following is used for the\npreparation of colloids?",
    "options": [
      "Van Arkel Method",
      "Bredig’s Arc Method",
      "Mond Process",
      "Ostwald Process"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Bredig’s Arc Method"
  },
  {
    "id": "oySEhgMuf9YRMrlRC31klru2w4a",
    "question": "Most suitable salt which can be used for efficient clotting of blood will be :",
    "options": [
      "Mg(HCO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
      "NaHCO<sub>3</sub>",
      "FeCl<sub>3</sub>",
      "FeSO<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "FeCl<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "sRuYxv4jRM0DXJwAAV1kltbl31l",
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is FALSE for hydrophilic sols?",
    "options": [
      "They do not require electrolytes for stability.",
      "The sols cannot be easily coagulated.",
      "These sols are reversible in nature.",
      "Their viscosity is of the order of that of H<sub>2</sub>O."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Their viscosity is of the order of that of H<sub>2</sub>O."
  },
  {
    "id": "af4bXu3X9nuI2j0NTU1klusgkob",
    "question": "The nature of charge on resulting colloidal particles when FeCl<sub>3</sub> is added to excess of hot water is :",
    "options": [
      "neutral",
      "sometimes positive and sometimes negative",
      "positive",
      "negative"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "positive"
  },
  {
    "id": "soDvuluFNOQSeYyXKi1kmiuhemi",
    "question": "The INCORRECT statements below regarding colloidal solutions is :",
    "options": [
      "The flocculating power of Al<sup>3+</sup> is more than that of Na<sup>+</sup>.",
      "A colloidal solutions shows Brownian motion of colloidal particles.",
      "An ordinary filter paper can stop the flow of colloidal particles.",
      "A colloidal solutions shows colligative properties."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "An ordinary filter paper can stop the flow of colloidal particles."
  },
  {
    "id": "tHwCMwnxJyXFfhTw3M1kmj7b19z",
    "question": "A colloidal system consisting of a gas dispersed in a solid is called a/an :",
    "options": [
      "foam",
      "aerosol",
      "solid sol",
      "gel"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "solid sol"
  },
  {
    "id": "6KLlwLujiAQmCK4Uom1kmkiqkyg",
    "question": "For the coagulation of a negative sol, the species below, that has the highest flocculating power is :",
    "options": [
      "Na<sup>+</sup>",
      "Ba<sup>2+</sup>",
      "PO$$_4^{3 - }$$",
      "SO$$_4^{2 - }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Ba<sup>2+</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "FsBMJfDtfmE4LUKVhF1kmm0giya",
    "question": "The charges on the colloidal CdS sol and TiO<sub>2</sub> sol are, respectively :",
    "options": [
      "positive and positive",
      "positive and negative",
      "negative and negative",
      "negative and positive"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "negative and positive"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krq67ahw",
    "question": "The conditions given below are in the context of observing Tyndall effect in colloidal solutions :<br/><br/>(A) The diameter of the colloidal particles is comparable to the wavelength of light used.<br/><br/>(B) The diameter of the colloidal particles is much smaller than the wavelength of light used.<br/><br/>(C) The diameter of the colloidal particles is much larger than the wavelength of light used.<br/><br/>(D) The refractive indices of the dispersed phase and the dispersion medium are comparable.<br/><br/>(E) The dispersed phase has a very different refractive index from the dispersion medium.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate conditions from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A) and (E) only",
      "(C) and (D) only",
      "(A) and (D) only",
      "(B) and (E) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "(A) and (E) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krxb2oy9",
    "question": "Match List I with List II :<br/><br/><table style=\"width:  100%\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th>List-I<br/>Example of colloids</th>\n<th>List - II<br/>Classification</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a) Cheese</td>\n<td>(i) dispersion of liquid in liquid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b) Pumice stone</td>\n<td>(ii) dispersion of liquid in gas</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c) Hair cream</td>\n<td>(iii) dispersion of gas in solid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d) Cloud</td>\n<td>(iv) dispersion of liquid in solid</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below ",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(i), (c)-(iii), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktcp1mny",
    "question": "The sol given below with negatively charged colloidal particles is :",
    "options": [
      "FeCl<sub>3</sub> added to hot water",
      "KI added to AgNO<sub>3</sub> solution",
      "AgNO<sub>3</sub> added to KI solution",
      "Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.xH<sub>2</sub>O in water"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "AgNO<sub>3</sub> added to KI solution"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktecswl2",
    "question": "Tyndall effect is more effectively shown by : ",
    "options": [
      "true solution",
      "lyophilic colloid",
      "lyophobic colloid",
      "suspension"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "lyophobic colloid"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfsenzv",
    "question": "Lyophilic sols are more stable than lyophobic sols because :",
    "options": [
      "there is a strong electrostatic repulsion between the negatively charged colloidal particles.",
      "the colloidal particles have positive charge.",
      "the colloidal particles have no charge.",
      "the colloidal particles are solvated."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "the colloidal particles are solvated."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l548mlm8",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following is a correct statement?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Brownian motion destabilises sols.",
      "Any amount of dispersed phase can added to emulsion without destablising it.",
      "Mixing two oppositely charged sols in equal amount neutralises charges and stabilises colloids. ",
      "Presence of equal and similar charges on colloidal particles provides stability to the colloidal solution."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Presence of equal and similar charges on colloidal particles provides stability to the colloidal solution."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54y6j4t",
    "question": "<p>A 42.12% (w/v) solution of NaCl causes precipitation of a certain sol in 10 hours. The coagulating value of NaCl for the sol in 2 hours is :</p>\n<p>[Given : Molar mass : Na = 23.0 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup> ; Cl = 35.5 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]</p>",
    "options": [
      "36 m mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "36 mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "1440 mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "1440 m mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "1440 m mol L<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55n3hj5",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 478px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 43px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 178px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 205px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">negatively charged sol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$F{e_2}{O_3}\\,.\\,x{H_2}O$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">macromolecular colloid</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">CdS sol</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">positively charged sol</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Starch</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Cheese</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">a gel</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (III), (C) - (IV), (D) - (I)",
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (I), (C) - (III), (D) - (IV)",
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (III), (C) - (I), (D) - (IV)",
      "(A) - (I), (B) - (III), (C) - (II), (D) - (IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "(A) - (II), (B) - (III), (C) - (I), (D) - (IV)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56aj493",
    "question": "<p>The Zeta potential is related to which property of colloids?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Colour",
      "Tyndall effect",
      "Charge on the surface of colloidal particles",
      "Brownian movement"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Charge on the surface of colloidal particles"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57rl0bt",
    "question": "<p>Match List-I with List-II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 716px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 44px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 313px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 42px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 317px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Lyophilic colloid</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Liquid-liquid colloid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Emulsion</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Protective colloid</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Positively charged colloid</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">FeCl$$_3$$ + NaOH</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Negatively charged colloid</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">FeCl$$_3$$ + hot water</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (I), (C) - (IV), (D) - (III)",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (I), (C) - (IV), (D) - (II)",
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (I), (C) - (III), (D) - (IV)",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (II), (C) - (I), (D) - (IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "(A) - (II), (B) - (I), (C) - (IV), (D) - (III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5almtuu",
    "question": "<p>Incorrect statement for Tyndall effect is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "The refractive indices of the dispersed phase and the dispersion medium differ greatly in magnitude.",
      "The diameter of the dispersed particles is much smaller than the wavelength of the light used.",
      "During projection of movies in the cinemas hall, Tyndall effect is noticed.",
      "It is used to distinguish a true solution from a colloidal solution."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "The diameter of the dispersed particles is much smaller than the wavelength of the light used."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5ama29a",
    "question": "<p>Using very little soap while washing clothes, does not serve the purpose of cleaning of clothes, because :</p>",
    "options": [
      "soap particles remain floating in water as ions.",
      "the hydrophobic part of soap is not able to take away grease.",
      "the micelles are not formed due to concentration of soap, below its CMC value.",
      "colloidal structure of soap in water is completely disturbed."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "the micelles are not formed due to concentration of soap, below its CMC value."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c6bsns",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Emulsions of oil in water are unstable and sometimes they separate into two layers on standing.</p>\n<p>Statement II : For stabilisation of an emulsion, excess of electrolyte is added.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w66f9j",
    "question": "<p>TLC analysis of a mixture having 3 components (A, B, C) using silica gel as the stationary phase gave following R<sub>f</sub> values; for A = 0.72, B = 0.48, C = 0.20.</p>\n<p>Regarding the above observations, which one of the following statements is not correct for column chromatography of the mixture?</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is the most non-polar component",
      "C is the most soluble component in mobile phase",
      "A will be eluted first",
      "C is the most strongly absorbed component"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "C is the most soluble component in mobile phase"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f6o6hn",
    "question": "<p>For micelle formation, which of the following statements are correct?</p>\n<p>A. Micelle formation is an exothermic process.</p>\n<p>B. Micelle formation is an endothermic process.</p>\n<p>C. The entropy change is positive.</p>\n<p>D. The entropy change is negative.</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and D only",
      "A and C only",
      "B and C only",
      "B and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "B and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i4qvph",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Finest gold is red in colour, as the size of the particles increases, it appears purple then blue and finally gold.</p>\n<p>Reason R : The colour of the colloidal solution depends on the wavelength of light scattered by the dispersed particles.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kpa2gm",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : Dissolved substances can be removed from a colloidal solution by diffusion through a parchment paper.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Particles in a true solution cannot pass through parchment paper but the colloidal particles can pass through the parchment paper.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p6wgu2",
    "question": "<p>$$100 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ of $$5 \\%\\,(\\mathrm{w} / \\mathrm{v})$$ solution of $$\\mathrm{NaCl}$$ in water was prepared in $$250 \\mathrm{~mL}$$ beaker. Albumin from the egg was poured into $$\\mathrm{NaCl}$$ solution and stirred well. This resulted in a/an :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Lyophilic sol",
      "Lyophobic sol",
      "Emulsion",
      "Precipitate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Lyophilic sol"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr4e1fd",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : In expensive scientific instruments, silica gel is kept in watch-glasses or in semipermeable membrane bags.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Silica gel adsorbs moisture from air via adsorption, thus protects the instrument from water corrosion (rusting) and / or prevents malfunctioning.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldscohtd",
    "question": "<p>Match List I and List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 607px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 263px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Osmosis</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Solvent molecules pass through semi permeable membrane towards solvent side.</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Reverse osmosis</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Movement of charged colloidal particles under the influence of applied electric potential towards oppositely charged electrodes.</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Electro osmosis</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Solvent molecules pass through semi permeable membrane towards solution side.</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Electrophoresis</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Dispersion medium moves in an electric field.</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV",
      "A-I, B-III, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-I, B-III, C-II, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-IV, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldss2vd1",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following salt solutions would coagulate the colloid solution formed when $$\\mathrm{FeCl_3}$$ is added to $$\\mathrm{NaOH}$$ solution, at the fastest rate?</p>",
    "options": [
      "10 mL of 0.15 mol dm$$^{-3}$$ CaCl$$_2$$",
      "10 mL of 0.2 mol dm$$^{-3}$$ AlCl$$_3$$",
      "10 mL of 0.1 mol dm$$^{-3}$$ Na$$_2$$SO$$_4$$",
      "10 mL of 0.1 mol dm$$^{-3}$$ Ca$$_3$$(PO$$_4$$)$$_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "10 mL of 0.2 mol dm$$^{-3}$$ AlCl$$_3$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyfpgfp",
    "question": "<p>Statement I : For colloidal particles, the values of colligative properties are of small order as compared to values shown by true solutions at same concentration.</p>\n<p>Statement II : For colloidal particles, the potential difference between the fixed layer and the diffused layer of same charges is called the electrokinetic potential or zeta potential.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true and Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Statement I is true and Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp2rny4",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements, one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : The diameter of colloidal particles in solution should not be much smaller than wavelength of light to show Tyndall effect.</p>\n<p>Reason R : The light scatters in all directions when the size of particles is large enough.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is false but R is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq4128q",
    "question": "<p>What happens when a lyophilic sol is added to a lyophobic sol?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Film of lyophobic sol is formed over lyophilic sol.",
      "Lyophilic sol is dispersed in lyophobic sol.",
      "Film of lyophilic sol is formed over lyophobic sol.",
      "Lyophobic sol is coagulated"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "Film of lyophilic sol is formed over lyophobic sol."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvtv38n",
    "question": "<p>Ferric chloride is applied to stop bleeding because -</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{FeCl}_{3}$$ reacts with the constituents of blood which is a positively charged sol.",
      "Blood absorbs $$\\mathrm{FeCl}_{3}$$ and forms a complex.",
      "$$\\mathrm{Cl}^{-}$$ ions cause coagulation of blood.",
      "$$\\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}$$ ions coagulate blood which is a negatively charged sol."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "surface-chemistry",
    "topic": "colloids",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Fe}^{3+}$$ ions coagulate blood which is a negatively charged sol."
  },
  {
    "id": "phalQRQ972Brggx5",
    "question": "If an endothermic reaction is non-spontaneous at freezing point of water and becomes feasible at its boiling point, then :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta H$$ is -ve, $$\\Delta S$$ is +ve",
      "$$\\Delta H$$ and $$\\Delta S$$ are both +ve",
      "$$\\Delta H$$ and $$\\Delta S$$ are both -ve",
      "$$\\Delta H$$ is +ve, $$\\Delta S$$ is -ve"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta H$$ and $$\\Delta S$$ are both +ve"
  },
  {
    "id": "sPSvpoqLxuJ2aurO",
    "question": "In an irreversible process taking place at constant T and P and in which only pressure-volume work is being done, the change in Gibbs free energy (dG) and change in entropy (dS), satisfy the criteria :",
    "options": [
      "(dS)<sub>V, E</sub> &gt; 0, (dG)<sub>T, P</sub> &lt; 0",
      "(dS)<sub>V, E</sub> = 0, (dG)<sub>T, P</sub> = 0",
      "(dS)<sub>V, E</sub> = 0, (dG)<sub>T, P</sub> &gt; 0",
      "(dS)<sub>V, E</sub> &lt; 0, (dG)<sub>T, P</sub> &lt; 0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "(dS)<sub>V, E</sub> &gt; 0, (dG)<sub>T, P</sub> &lt; 0"
  },
  {
    "id": "sHDrywGF2oZGYLEv",
    "question": "The correct relationship between free energy change in a reaction and the corresponding equilibrium constant K<sub>c</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "- $$\\Delta G$$ = RT ln K<sub>c</sub>",
      "$$\\Delta G^o$$ = RT ln K<sub>c</sub>",
      "- $$\\Delta G^o$$ = RT ln K<sub>c</sub>",
      "$$\\Delta G$$ = RT ln K<sub>c</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "- $$\\Delta G^o$$ = RT ln K<sub>c</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "QIZvwTiW2R9ZxNa5",
    "question": "In conversion of lime-stone to lime, <br/>\nCaCO<sub>3</sub>(s) $$\\to$$ CaO(s) + CO<sub>2</sub> (g) the vales of ∆H° and ∆S° are +179.1 kJ mol−1\n and 160.2 J/K respectively at 298 K and 1 bar.\nAssuming that ∆H° do not change with temperature, temperature above which conversion of\nlimestone to lime will be spontaneous is :",
    "options": [
      "1008 K ",
      "1200 ",
      "845 K",
      "1118 K "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "1118 K "
  },
  {
    "id": "6wcnWh2dejd5kT3l",
    "question": "Standard entropy of X<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub> and XY<sub>3</sub> are 60, 40 and 50 JK<sup>−1</sup>\nmol<sup>−1</sup> , respectively. For the reaction,  <br/>\n$${1 \\over 2} X_2$$ + $${3 \\over 2} Y_2 \\to$$ XY<sub>3</sub>, $$\\Delta H$$ = -30 kJ, to be at equilibrium, the temperature will be :",
    "options": [
      "1250 K",
      "500 K",
      "750 K",
      "1000 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "750 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "8YOhXpsnxnaq1ymO",
    "question": "For a particular reversible reaction at temperature T, ∆H and ∆S were found to be both +ve. If T<sub>e</sub> is\nthe temperature at equilibrium, the reaction would be spontaneous when :",
    "options": [
      "T<sub>e</sub> &gt; T",
      "T &gt; T<sub>e</sub>",
      "T<sub>e</sub> is 5 times T",
      "T = T<sub>e</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "T &gt; T<sub>e</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "BcphWoKO63fYQVqB",
    "question": "The entropy change involved in the isothermal reversible expansion of 2 moles of an ideal gas from a\nvolume of 10 dm<sup>3</sup> to a volume of 100 dm<sup>3</sup> at 27<sup>o</sup>C is :",
    "options": [
      "35.8 J mol<sup>-1</sup> K<sup>−1</sup> ",
      "32.3 J mol<sup>-1</sup> K<sup>−1</sup> ",
      "42.3 J mol<sup>-1</sup> K<sup>−1</sup> ",
      "38.3 J mol<sup>-1</sup> K<sup>−1</sup> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "38.3 J mol<sup>-1</sup> K<sup>−1</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "eaqqbvY65NgoNa5n",
    "question": "The incorrect expression among the following is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\Delta {G_{system}}} \\over {\\Delta {S_{total}}}} =  - T$$ ",
      "In isothermal process $${w_{reversible}}$$ = $$ - nRT\\,\\ln \\,{{{V_f}} \\over {{V_i}}}$$",
      "In $$K\\, = {{\\Delta {H^o} - T\\Delta {S^o}} \\over {RT}}$$",
      "$$K\\, = \\,{e^{ - \\Delta {G^o}/RT}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "In $$K\\, = {{\\Delta {H^o} - T\\Delta {S^o}} \\over {RT}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "abw0HPkOJTHzb9O6",
    "question": "The following reaction is performed at 298 K<br/>\n2NO(g) +  O<sub>2</sub> (g) $$\\leftrightharpoons$$ 2NO<sub>2</sub> (g)<br/> \nThe standard free energy of formation of NO(g) is 86.6 kJ/mol at 298 K. What is the standard free energy\nof formation of NO<sub>2</sub>(g) at 298 K? (KP = 1.6 × 10<sup>12</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "86600 + R(298) ln(1.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>12</sup>)",
      "86600 - $$ln (1.6 \\times 10^{12}) \\over R (298)$$",
      "0.5[2×86,600 – R(298) ln(1.6×10<sup>12</sup>)] ",
      "R(298) ln(1.6×10<sup>12</sup>) – 86600"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "0.5[2×86,600 – R(298) ln(1.6×10<sup>12</sup>)] "
  },
  {
    "id": "QV1uDvUN2q3sFjXdOuRMm",
    "question": "A reaction at 1 bar is non-spontaneous at low temperature but becomes spontaneous\nat high temperature. Identify the correct statement about the reaction among the\nfollowing :",
    "options": [
      "Both $$\\Delta $$H and $$\\Delta $$S are negative.",
      "Both $$\\Delta $$H and $$\\Delta $$S are positive.",
      "$$\\Delta $$H is positive while $$\\Delta $$S is negative.",
      "$$\\Delta $$H is negative while $$\\Delta $$S is positive."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "Both $$\\Delta $$H and $$\\Delta $$S are positive."
  },
  {
    "id": "iaIfEPNoZEMepV4TiITWS",
    "question": "For the reaction,\n<br/>A(g) + B(g) $$ \\to $$ C(g) + D(g),  $$\\Delta $$H<sup>o</sup> and $$\\Delta $$S<sup>o</sup>  are, respectively, − 29.8 kJ mol<sup>−1</sup> and −0.100 kJ K<sup>−1</sup> mol<sup>−1</sup> at 298 K. The equilibrium constant for the reaction at 298 K is :",
    "options": [
      "1.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$10</sup>",
      "1.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>10</sup>",
      "10",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "3oMCAaXlAkKhZuVDEwROx",
    "question": "At 320 K, a gas A<sub>2</sub> is 20% dissociated to A(g). The standard free energy change at 320 K and 1 atm in J mol<sup>-1</sup> is approximately : (R = 8.314 JK<sup>-1</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup>; ln2 = 0.693; ln 3 = 1.098)",
    "options": [
      "4763",
      "2068",
      "1844",
      "4281"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "4281"
  },
  {
    "id": "QRNOQ7ZCfVfwo5d0EfXXZ",
    "question": "For which of the following processes,  $$\\Delta $$S is negative ? ",
    "options": [
      "H<sub>2</sub>(g)  $$ \\to $$  2H(g)",
      "N<sub>2</sub>(g, 1 atm)  $$ \\to $$  N<sub>2</sub>(g, 5 atm)",
      "C(diamond)  $$ \\to $$  C(graphite)",
      "N<sub>2</sub>(g, 273 K) $$ \\to $$ N<sub>2</sub>(g, 300 K)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "N<sub>2</sub>(g, 1 atm)  $$ \\to $$  N<sub>2</sub>(g, 5 atm)"
  },
  {
    "id": "nF98raqXNVt1Pqygegj2P",
    "question": "Given\n<br/><br/>(i)   2Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>(s) $$ \\to $$ 4Fe(s) + 3O<sub>2</sub>(g); \n<br/><br/>$$\\Delta $$<sub>r</sub>G<sup>o</sup> = + 1487.0 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>\n<br/><br/>(ii)   2CO(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 2CO<sub>2</sub>(g); \n<br/><br/>$$\\Delta $$<sub>r</sub>G<sup>o</sup> = $$-$$ 514.4 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>\n<br/><br/>Free energy change, $$\\Delta $$<sub>r</sub>G<sup>o</sup> for the reaction <br/><br/>2Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>(s) + 6CO(g) $$ \\to $$ 4Fe(s) + 6CO<sub>2</sub>(g) will be :\n",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$ 112.4 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>",
      "$$-$$ 56.2 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>",
      "$$-$$ 168.2 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>",
      "$$-$$ 208.0 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "$$-$$ 56.2 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "7tRDrgv30LYuVdZQ9HiRw",
    "question": "$$\\Delta $$<sub>f</sub>G<sup>o</sup> at 500 K for substance 'S' in liquid state and gaseous state are +100.7 kcl mol-<sup>1</sup> and +103 kcal mol<sup>-1</sup>, respectively. Vapour pressure of liquid 'S' at 500 K is approximately equal to : ( R = 2 cal K<sup>-1</sup> mol<sup>-1</sup> )",
    "options": [
      "0.1 atm",
      "1 atm",
      "10 atm",
      "100 atm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "0.1 atm"
  },
  {
    "id": "qIUwi5Ml0Y7LZ3CDQH4tg",
    "question": "A process has $$\\Delta $$H = 200 J mol<sup>–1</sup> and $$\\Delta $$S = 40 JK<sup>–1</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>. Out of the values given below, choose the minimum temperature above which the process will be spontaneous :",
    "options": [
      "4 K",
      "20 K",
      "5 K",
      "12 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "5 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "qsZnQyDcywbXiTgy82w2w",
    "question": "For the chemical reaction X $$\\rightleftharpoons$$ Y,   the standard reaction Gibbs energy depends on temperature T (in K) as\n$$\\Delta $$<sub>r</sub>G<sup>o</sup> (in kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>) = 120 $$ - {3 \\over 8}$$ T. \n<br/><br/>The major component of the reaction mixture at T is : \n",
    "options": [
      "Y if T = 300 K",
      "Y if T = 280 K ",
      "X if T = 350 K",
      "X if T = 315 K "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "X if T = 315 K "
  },
  {
    "id": "vF0WDAdMB1lFuJfkX8Nux",
    "question": "For the equilibrium,  \n<br/>2H<sub>2</sub>O $$\\rightleftharpoons$$  H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup> + OH<sup>$$-$$</sup>, the value of $$\\Delta $$G<sup>o</sup> at 298 K is approximately : ",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$ 80 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "100 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "$$-$$ 100 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "80 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "80 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "FNrh0oUQDHdLKsjYPZlmH",
    "question": "The reaction, MgO(s) + C(s) $$ \\to $$ Mg(s) + CO(g), for which $$\\Delta $$<sub>r</sub>H<sup>o</sup> + 491.1 kJ mol<sup><sup>–1</sup></sup> and $$\\Delta $$<sub>r</sub>S<sup>o</sup> = 198.0 JK<sup>–1</sup>  mol<sup>–1</sup>, is not feasible at 298 K. Temperature above which reaciton will be feasible is : \n",
    "options": [
      "2480.3 K ",
      "2040.5 K ",
      "2380.5 K",
      "1890.0 K "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "2480.3 K "
  },
  {
    "id": "DpOlHQlGxtzkv6YpGBuZW",
    "question": "The standard reaction Gibbs energy for a chemical reaction at an absolute temperature T is given by\n$$\\Delta $$<sub>r</sub>G<sup>o</sup> = A – BT\n<br/><br/>Where A and B are non-zero constants. Which of the following is TRUE about this reaction?",
    "options": [
      "Exothermic if B &lt; 0 ",
      "Endothermic if A &gt; 0",
      "Exothermic if A &gt; 0 and B &lt; 0",
      "Endothermic if A &lt; 0 and B &gt; 0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "Endothermic if A &gt; 0"
  },
  {
    "id": "yRVnKS7DGpKkm4pcsf3rsa0w2w9jwvd58pi",
    "question": "A process will be spontaneous at all temperatures if :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta $$H &lt; 0 and $$\\Delta $$S &gt; 0",
      "$$\\Delta $$H &lt; 0 and $$\\Delta $$S &lt; 0",
      "$$\\Delta $$H &gt; 0 and $$\\Delta $$S &lt; 0",
      "$$\\Delta $$H &gt; 0 and $$\\Delta $$S &gt; 0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta $$H &lt; 0 and $$\\Delta $$S &gt; 0"
  },
  {
    "id": "SKCkG6ju71QEK14WQEjgy2xukg3eriam",
    "question": "For a reaction,\n<br/>4M(s) + nO<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 2M<sub>2</sub>O<sub>n</sub>(s)\n<br/>the free energy change is plotted as a function\nof temperature. The temperature below which\nthe oxide is stable could be inferred from the\nplot as the point at which :",
    "options": [
      "the free energy change shows a change\nfrom negative to positive value",
      "the slope changes from positive to negative",
      "the slope changes from negative to positive",
      "the slope changes from positive to zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "the free energy change shows a change\nfrom negative to positive value"
  },
  {
    "id": "iUKFSnX9wqPPtSnJG21kmkinzyu",
    "question": "During which of the following processes, does entropy decrease?<br/><br/>(A) Freezing of water to ice at 0$$^\\circ$$C<br/><br/>(B) Freezing of water to ice at $$-$$10$$^\\circ$$C<br/><br/>(C) N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 2NH<sub>3</sub>(g)<br/><br/>(D) Adsorption of CO(g) on lead surface.<br/><br/>(E) Dissolution of NaCl in water<br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A), (C) and (E) only",
      "(B) and (C) only",
      "(A), (B), (C) and (D) only",
      "(A) and (E) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "(A), (B), (C) and (D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjvsvso",
    "question": "The incorrect expression among the following is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\Delta {G_{System}}} \\over {\\Delta {S_{Total}}}} =  - T$$ (at constant P)",
      "$$K = {{\\Delta H^\\circ  - T\\Delta S^\\circ } \\over {RT}}$$",
      "$$K = {e^{ - \\Delta G^\\circ /RT}}$$",
      "For isothermal process $${w_{reversible}} =  - nRT\\ln {{{V_f}} \\over {{V_i}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "$$K = {{\\Delta H^\\circ  - T\\Delta S^\\circ } \\over {RT}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nunztx",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A : The reduction of a metal oxide is easier if the metal formed is in liquid state than solid state.</p>\n<p>Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$ : The value of $$\\Delta G ^\\Theta$$ becomes more on negative side as entropy is higher in liquid state than solid state.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "A is not correct but R is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfjpymm",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following is not correct?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta \\mathrm{G}$$ is positive for a spontaneous reaction\n",
      "$$\\Delta \\mathrm{G}$$ is positive for a non-spontaneous reaction\n",
      "$$\\Delta \\mathrm{G}$$ is zero for a reversible reaction\n",
      "$$\\Delta \\mathrm{G}$$ is negative for a spontaneous reaction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "entropy,-free-energy-change-and-spontaneity",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta \\mathrm{G}$$ is positive for a spontaneous reaction\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "98FjQESVhnjwpe5h",
    "question": "A heat engine absorbs heat Q<sub>1</sub> at temperature T<sub>1</sub> and heat Q<sub>2</sub> at temperature T<sub>2</sub>. Work done by the engine is J (Q<sub>1</sub> + Q<sub>2</sub>). This data :",
    "options": [
      "violates 1<sup>st</sup> law of thermodynamics",
      "violates 1<sup>st</sup> law of thermodynamics if Q<sub>1</sub> is +ve",
      "violates 1<sup>st</sup> law of thermodynamics if Q<sub>1</sub> is -ve",
      "does not violates 1<sup>st</sup> law of thermodynamics"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "violates 1<sup>st</sup> law of thermodynamics"
  },
  {
    "id": "CtnAEjRAXdaaaS5f",
    "question": "The internal energy change when a system goes from state A to B is 40 kJ/mole. If the system goes from A to B by a reversible  path and returns to state A by an irreversible path what would be the net change in internal energy?",
    "options": [
      "&gt; 40 kJ",
      "&lt; 40 kJ",
      "Zero",
      "40 kJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "Zero"
  },
  {
    "id": "T1yyrnlbg8okisHc",
    "question": "An ideal gas expands in volume from 1$$\\times$$10<sup>-3</sup> m<sup>3</sup> to 1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> m<sup>3</sup> at 300 K against a constant pressure of 1$$\\times$$10<sup>5</sup> Nm<sup>-2</sup>. The work done is :",
    "options": [
      "-900 J ",
      "900 kJ ",
      "270 kJ ",
      "-900 kJ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "-900 J "
  },
  {
    "id": "X7Qpe69FCzAaaTrM",
    "question": "An ideal gas is allowed to expand both reversibly and irreversibly in an isolated system. If T<sub>i</sub> is the\ninitial temperature and T<sub>f</sub> is the final temperature, which of the following statements is correct?",
    "options": [
      "(T<sub>f</sub>)<sub>irrev</sub> &gt; (T<sub>f</sub>)<sub>rev</sub>",
      "(T<sub>f</sub>)<sub>rev</sub> = (T<sub>f</sub>)<sub>irrev</sub>",
      "T<sub>f</sub> &gt; T<sub>i</sub>\n for reversible process but T<sub>f</sub> = T<sub>i</sub>\n for irreversible process ",
      "T<sub>f</sub> = T<sub>i</sub> for both reversible and irreversible processes "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "(T<sub>f</sub>)<sub>irrev</sub> &gt; (T<sub>f</sub>)<sub>rev</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "5pH25xJQ6F1NJ5Kz",
    "question": "A piston filled with 0.04 mol of an ideal gas expands reversibly from 50.0 mL to 375 mL at a constant\ntemperature of 37.0<sup>o</sup>C. As it does so, it absorbs 208J of heat. The values of q and w for the process will be :<br/>\n(R = 8.314 J/mol K) ( l n 7.5 = 2.01)",
    "options": [
      "q = – 208 J, w = – 208 J ",
      "q = – 208 J, w = + 208 J",
      "q = + 208 J, w = + 208 J",
      "q = + 208 J, w = – 208 J "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "q = + 208 J, w = – 208 J "
  },
  {
    "id": "FLF00zYKOUeO5QsyAig0F",
    "question": "If 100 mole of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> decompose at 1 bar and 300 K, the work done (kJ) by one mole of O<sub>2</sub>(g) as it expands against 1 bar pressure is :\n<br/><br/>2H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>(l)    $$\\rightleftharpoons$$    2H<sub>2</sub>O(l) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) \n<br/><br/>(R = 8.3 J K <sup>$$-$$1</sup> mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "62.25",
      "124.50",
      "249.00",
      "498.00"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "249.00"
  },
  {
    "id": "jsgorkZ6BUuFnGFy",
    "question": "$$\\Delta $$U is equal to :",
    "options": [
      "Isobaric work",
      "Adiabatic work ",
      "Isothermal work ",
      "Isochoric work "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "Adiabatic work "
  },
  {
    "id": "g9p0EYnRxA9Rv09nJWZHu",
    "question": "A gas undergoes change from state A to state B. In this process, the heat absorbed\nand work done by the gas is 5 J and 8 J, respectively. Now gas is brought back to\nA by another process during which 3 J of heat is evolved. In this reverse process of\nB to A :",
    "options": [
      "10 J of the work will be done by the gas. ",
      "6 J of the work will be done by the gas.",
      "10 J of the work will be done by the surrounding on gas.\n",
      "6 J of the work will be done by the surrounding on gas."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "6 J of the work will be done by the surrounding on gas."
  },
  {
    "id": "u2tCpn0kWEsKdZBzxVhRC",
    "question": "5 moles of an ideal gas at 100 K are allowed\nto undergo reversible compression till its\ntemperature becomes 200 K.\nIf C<sub>V</sub> = 28 JK<sup>–1</sup>mol<sup>–1</sup>, calculate $$\\Delta $$U and $$\\Delta $$pV for\nthis process. (R = 8.0 JK<sup>–1</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta $$U = 14 kJ; $$\\Delta $$(pV) = 4 kJ",
      "$$\\Delta $$U = 2.8 kJ; $$\\Delta $$(pV) = 0.8 kJ",
      "$$\\Delta $$U = 14 kJ; $$\\Delta $$(pV) = 18 kJ",
      "$$\\Delta $$U = 14 kJ; $$\\Delta $$(pV) = 0.8 kJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta $$U = 14 kJ; $$\\Delta $$(pV) = 4 kJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "R8RsT9JfEu81Ll7rYC3rsa0w2w9jx534wt1",
    "question": "An ideal gas is allowed to expand form 1 L to 10 L against a constant external pressure of I bar. The work\ndone in kJ is :",
    "options": [
      "+10.0",
      "–0.9",
      "– 2.0",
      "– 9.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "–0.9"
  },
  {
    "id": "T4IWm6qbVm6MnVRfq3V1L",
    "question": "During compression of a spring the work done\nis 10kJ and 2kJ escaped to the surroundings as\nheat. The change in internal energy, $$\\Delta $$U(inkJ)\nis :",
    "options": [
      "- 12",
      "8",
      "- 8",
      "12"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "8"
  },
  {
    "id": "9r1FdNeqctnkk3jpF52GU",
    "question": "Which one of the following equations does not correctly represent the first law of thermodynamics\nfor the given processes involving an ideal gas? (Assume non-expansion work is zero)",
    "options": [
      "Adiabatic process : $$\\Delta $$U= – w",
      "Cyclic process : q = –w",
      "Isochoric process : $$\\Delta $$U= q",
      "Isothermal process : q = – w"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "Adiabatic process : $$\\Delta $$U= – w"
  },
  {
    "id": "uZvgJnxKsRyuimysh3fCg",
    "question": "An ideal gas undergoes isothermal compression from 5m<sup>3</sup> to 1 m<sup>3</sup>  against a constant external pressure of 4 Nm<sup>–2</sup>. Heat released in this process is used to increase the temperature of 1 mole of Al. If molar heat capacity of Al is 24 J mol<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>, the temperature of Al increases by :",
    "options": [
      "$${2 \\over 3}K$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}K$$",
      "1 K",
      "2 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over 3}K$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "agnOphGtqdEAlBmEV0jgy2xukfcepdd9",
    "question": "Five moles of an ideal gas at 1 bar and 298 K\nis expanded into vacuum to double the volume.\nThe work done is :",
    "options": [
      "Zero",
      "-RT $$\\ln {{{V_2}} \\over {{V_1}}}$$",
      "C<sub>V</sub> (T<sub>2</sub> – T<sub>1</sub>)",
      "– RT (V<sub>2</sub> – V<sub>1</sub>)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "Zero"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsblx2nm",
    "question": "Choose the correct option for free expansion of an ideal gas under adiabatic condition from the following :",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{q}=0, \\Delta \\mathrm{T}=0, \\mathrm{w}=0$",
      "$\\mathrm{q}=0, \\Delta \\mathrm{T} \\neq 0, \\mathrm{w}=0$",
      "$\\mathrm{q} \\neq 0, \\Delta \\mathrm{T}=0, \\mathrm{w}=0$",
      "$\\mathrm{q}=0, \\Delta \\mathrm{T}<0, \\mathrm{w} \\neq 0$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{q}=0, \\Delta \\mathrm{T}=0, \\mathrm{w}=0$"
  },
  {
    "id": "IvJk60A3K13igIgC",
    "question": "The heat required to raise the temperature of body by 1 K is called :",
    "options": [
      "specific heat",
      "thermal capacity",
      "water equivalent",
      "none of these"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "fundamentals-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "thermal capacity"
  },
  {
    "id": "geVNizGmSr5wzrQTu1BCR",
    "question": "An ideal gas undergoes isothermal expansion at constant pressure. During\nthe process :",
    "options": [
      "enthalpy increases but entropy decreases.",
      "enthalpy remains constant but entropy increases.",
      "enthalpy decreases but entropy increases.",
      "Both enthalpy and entropy remain constant.\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "fundamentals-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "enthalpy remains constant but entropy increases."
  },
  {
    "id": "AIptkfEbUM5X7S2PuA8A1",
    "question": "Among the following, the set of parameters that\nrepresents path function, is :<br/>\n(A) q + w<br/>\n(B) q<br/>\n(C) w<br/>\n(D) H–TS<br/>",
    "options": [
      "(B) and (C)",
      "(A) and (D)",
      "(B), (C) and (D)",
      "(A), (B) and (C)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "fundamentals-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "(B) and (C)"
  },
  {
    "id": "dKxseaqgpKvic9iQK0jgy2xukf7tfwiq",
    "question": "For one mole of an ideal gas, which of these\nstatements must be true?\n<br/>(a) U and H each depends only on temperature\n<br/>(b) Compressibility factor z is not equal to 1\n<br/>(c) C<sub>P, m</sub> – C<sub>V, m</sub> = R\n<br/>(d) dU = C<sub>V</sub>dT for any process<br/>",
    "options": [
      "(a), (c) and (d)",
      "(a) and (c)",
      "(c) and (d)",
      "(b), (c) and (d)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "fundamentals-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "(a), (c) and (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57rgtgz",
    "question": "<p>Match List-I with List-II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 716px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 44px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 313px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 42px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 317px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Spontaneous process</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\Delta H &lt; 0$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Process with $$\\Delta P = 0$$, $$\\Delta T = 0$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\Delta {G_{T,P}} &lt; 0$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\Delta {H_{reaction}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Isothermal and isobaric process</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Exothermic Process</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">[Bond energies of molecules in reactants] $$ - $$ [Bond energies of product molecules</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (II), (C) - (IV), (D) - (I)",
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (III), (C) - (IV), (D) - (I)",
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (III), (C) - (I), (D) - (IV)",
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (I), (C) - (III), (D) - (IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "fundamentals-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "(A) - (II), (B) - (III), (C) - (IV), (D) - (I)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mbw6fr",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following relation is not correct?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta \\mathrm{H}=\\Delta \\mathrm{U}-\\mathrm{P} \\Delta \\mathrm{V}$$",
      "$$\\Delta \\mathrm{U}=\\mathrm{q}+\\mathrm{W}$$",
      "$$\\Delta \\mathrm{S}_{\\text {sys }}+\\Delta \\mathrm{S}_{\\text {surr }} \\geqslant 0$$",
      "$$\\Delta \\mathrm{G}=\\Delta \\mathrm{H}-\\mathrm{T} \\Delta \\mathrm{S}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "fundamentals-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta \\mathrm{H}=\\Delta \\mathrm{U}-\\mathrm{P} \\Delta \\mathrm{V}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsc8dmu",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following relations are correct?</p>\n<p>(A) $$\\mathrm{\\Delta U=q+p\\Delta V}$$</p>\n<p>(B) $$\\mathrm{\\Delta G=\\Delta H-T\\Delta S}$$</p>\n<p>(C) $$\\Delta \\mathrm{S}=\\frac{q_{rev}}{T}$$</p>\n<p>(D) $$\\mathrm{\\Delta H=\\Delta U-\\Delta nRT}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and B only",
      "B and C only",
      "C and D only",
      "B and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "fundamentals-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "B and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "96sFRl1xHh7Lww4E",
    "question": "For the reactions<br/>\n2C + O<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ 2CO<sub>2</sub>; $$\\Delta H$$ = -393 J<br/>\n2Zn + O<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ 2ZnO; $$\\Delta H$$ = -412 J",
    "options": [
      "carbon can oxidise Zn",
      "oxidation of carbon is not feasible",
      "oxidation of Zn is not feasible",
      "Zn can oxidise carbon"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "Zn can oxidise carbon"
  },
  {
    "id": "1XMTpaNC2M3DXEaK",
    "question": "If at 298 K the bond energies of C - H, C - C, C = C and H - H bonds are respectively 414, 347, 615 and 435 kJ/mol, the value of enthalpy change for the reaction<br/>\nH<sub>2</sub>C = CH<sub>2</sub>(g) + H<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\to$$ H<sub>3</sub>C - CH<sub>3</sub>(g) at 298 K will be :",
    "options": [
      "- 250 kJ",
      "+ 125 kJ",
      "- 125 kJ",
      "+ 250 kJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "- 125 kJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "nthNWg6NbhKkFNtk",
    "question": "The enthalpy change for a reaction does not depend upon :",
    "options": [
      "use of different reactants for the same product",
      "the nature of intermediate reaction steps",
      "the differences in initial or final temperature of involved substances",
      "the physical states of reactants and products"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "the nature of intermediate reaction steps"
  },
  {
    "id": "yAuIYD3VZdr8bSk4",
    "question": "The enthalpies of combustion of carbon and carbon monoxide are -393.5 and -283 kJ mol-1\nrespectively. The enthalpy of formation of carbon monoxide per mole is :",
    "options": [
      "110.5 kJ",
      "-110.5 kJ",
      "-676.5 kJ",
      "676.5 kJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "-110.5 kJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "H0gde6CcofVD3KwM",
    "question": "Consider an endothermic reaction, X $$\\to$$ Y with the activation energies E<sub>b</sub> and E<sub>f</sub>\nfor the backward and forward reactions, respectively. In general :",
    "options": [
      "E<sub>b</sub> &lt; E<sub>f</sub>",
      "E<sub>b</sub> &gt; E<sub>f</sub>",
      "E<sub>b</sub> = E<sub>f</sub>",
      "There is no definite relation between E<sub>b</sub> and E<sub>f</sub> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "E<sub>b</sub> &lt; E<sub>f</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "28ftA6VnOxdFyHH4",
    "question": "Consider the reaction: N<sub>2</sub> + 3H<sub>2</sub> $$\\to$$ 2NH<sub>3</sub> carried out at constant temperature and\npressure. If $$\\Delta H$$ and $$\\Delta U$$ are the enthalpy and internal energy changes for the\nreaction, which of the following expressions is true? ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta H$$ &gt; $$\\Delta U$$",
      "$$\\Delta H$$ &lt; $$\\Delta U$$",
      "$$\\Delta H$$ = $$\\Delta U$$",
      "$$\\Delta H$$ = 0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta H$$ &lt; $$\\Delta U$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "J24XjW5J82brwjD0",
    "question": "If the bond dissociation energies of XY, X<sub>2</sub> and Y<sub>2</sub> (all diatomic molecules) are in the ratio of 1:1:0.5 and $$\\Delta H_f$$ for the formation of XY is -200 kJ mole<sup>-1</sup>. The bond\ndissociation energy of X<sub>2</sub> will be :",
    "options": [
      "100 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup> ",
      "200 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>",
      "300 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup> ",
      "800 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "800 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "U3iyY5LnDKq3TzEE",
    "question": "($$\\Delta H - \\Delta U$$) for the formation of carbon monoxide (CO) from its elements at 298 K is : (R = 8.314 J K<sup>–1</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "–1238.78 J mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "1238.78 J mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "–2477.57 J mol<sup>–1</sup> ",
      "2477.57 J mol<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "1238.78 J mol<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "8gNZYH52f4fjzzVb",
    "question": "The standard enthalpy of formation $$\\Delta _fH^o$$ at 298 K for methane, CH<sub>4</sub>(g), is –74.8 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>. The additional information required to determine the average energy for C – H bond formation would be :",
    "options": [
      "the dissociation energy of H<sub>2</sub> and enthalpy of sublimation of carbon",
      "latent heat of vapourization of methane ",
      "the first four ionization energies of carbon and electron gain enthalpy of hydrogen",
      "the dissociation energy of hydrogen molecule, H<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "the dissociation energy of H<sub>2</sub> and enthalpy of sublimation of carbon"
  },
  {
    "id": "W9PpzCB9wILwglIR",
    "question": "The enthalpy changes for the following processes are listed below : <br/><br/>\nCl<sub>2</sub>(g) = 2Cl(g),  242.3 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup><br/>\nI<sub>2</sub>(g) = 2I(g), 151.0 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup> <br/>\nICl(g) = I(g) + Cl(g), 211.3 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup><br/>\nI<sub>2</sub>(s) = I<sub>2</sub>(g), 62.76 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup> <br/><br/>\nGiven that the standard states for iodine and chlorine are I<sub>2</sub>(s) and Cl<sub>2</sub>(g), the standard enthalpy of\nformation for ICl(g) is :",
    "options": [
      "–14.6 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup> ",
      "–16.8 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "+16.8 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "+244.8 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "+16.8 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "nwZbzAAAv8f0WATD",
    "question": "Assuming that water vapour is an ideal gas, the internal energy change $$\\left( {\\Delta U} \\right)$$ when $$1$$ mol of water is vapourised at $$1$$ bar pressure and $${100^ \\circ }C$$ (Given : molar enthalpy of vapourisation of water at $$1$$ bar and $$373$$ $$K$$ $$ = 41\\,kJ\\,mo{l^{ - 1}}\\,$$ \n<br/>and $$R = 8.3\\,J\\,mo{l^{ - 1}}\\,{K^{ - 1}}$$ )",
    "options": [
      "$$41.00\\,kJ\\,mo{l^{ - 1}}$$ ",
      "$$4.100\\,kJ\\,mo{l^{ - 1}}$$ ",
      "$$3.7904\\,kJ\\,mo{l^{ - 1}}$$ ",
      "$$37.904\\,kJ\\,mo{l^{ - 1}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "$$37.904\\,kJ\\,mo{l^{ - 1}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "8RPGAzlQzMaIOhtP",
    "question": "Oxidising power of chlorine in aqueous solution can be determined by the parameters indicated\nbelow: <br/>\n$${1 \\over 2}C{l_2}(g)$$ $$\\buildrel {{1 \\over 2}{\\Delta _{diss}}{H^\\Theta }} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ $$Cl(g)$$ $$\\buildrel {{\\Delta _{eg}}{H^\\Theta }} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ $$C{l^ - }(g)$$ $$\\buildrel {{\\Delta _{Hyd}}{H^\\Theta }} \\over\n \\longrightarrow $$ $$C{l^ - }(aq)$$<br/>\n(Using the data, $${\\Delta _{diss}}H_{C{l_2}}^\\Theta $$ = 240 kJ/mol, $${\\Delta _{eg}}H_{Cl}^\\Theta $$ = -349 kJ/mol, $${\\Delta _{hyd}}H_{C{l^ - }}^\\Theta $$ = - 381 kJ/mol) will be :",
    "options": [
      "+152 kJ mol<sup>−1</sup>",
      "−610 kJ mol<sup>−1</sup>",
      "−850 kJ mol<sup>−1</sup>",
      "+120 kJ mol<sup>−1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "−610 kJ mol<sup>−1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "KYX8L2SMD3SvNEjD",
    "question": "On the basis of the following thermochemical data : <br/>($$\\Delta _fG^oH^+_{(aq)}$$ = 0)<br/><br/>\n\nH<sub>2</sub>O(l) $$\\to$$ H<sup>+</sup>(aq) + OH<sup>-</sup>(aq); $$\\Delta H$$ = 57.32 kJ<br/>\nH<sub>2</sub>(g) + $${1 \\over 2} O_2(g) \\to$$ H<sub>2</sub>O(l); $$\\Delta H$$ = -286.20 kJ<br/><br/>\nThe value of enthalpy of formation of OH<sup>−</sup> ion at 25<sup>o</sup>C is :",
    "options": [
      "-22.88 kJ ",
      "-228.88 kJ ",
      "+228.88 kJ ",
      "-343.52 kJ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "-228.88 kJ "
  },
  {
    "id": "cTIvQgMIyWL58Sob",
    "question": "The standard enthalpy of formation of NH<sub>3</sub> is –46.0 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>. If the enthalpy of formation of H<sub>2</sub> from its atoms is –436 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup> and that of N2 is –712 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>, the average bond enthalpy of N–H bond in NH<sub>3</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "–964 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "+352 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "+ 1056 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "–1102 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "+352 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "C5MHaVAVVbr2QtiD",
    "question": "For complete combustion of ethanol, C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH(l) +  3O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\to$$ 2CO<sub>2</sub>(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub>O(l) the amount of heat\nproduced as measured in bomb calorimeter, is 1364.47 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup> at 25<sup>o</sup>C. Assuming ideality the Enthalpy of combustion, $$\\Delta _CH$$, for the reaction will be : (R = 8.314 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "–1460.50 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "– 1350.50 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "– 1366.95 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "– 1361.95 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "– 1366.95 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "kq7naEdLF4URf35Q",
    "question": "The heats of combustion of carbon and carbon monoxide are –393.5 and –283.5 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>, respectively. The\nheat of formation (in kJ) of carbon monoxide per mole is :",
    "options": [
      "676.5",
      "-676.5",
      "–110",
      "110.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "–110"
  },
  {
    "id": "HdfgVo1LFVAsMcvNSJCYP",
    "question": "For a reaction,  A(g) $$ \\to $$ A($$\\ell $$); $$\\Delta $$H= $$-$$ 3RT.\n<br/>The <b>correct</b> statement for the reaction is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta $$H = $$\\Delta $$U $$ \\ne $$ O",
      "$$\\Delta $$H = $$\\Delta $$U = O",
      "$$\\left| {} \\right.$$$$\\Delta $$H$$\\left| {} \\right.$$ &lt; $$\\left| {} \\right.$$$$\\Delta $$U$$\\left| {} \\right.$$",
      "$$\\left| {} \\right.$$$$\\Delta $$H$$\\left| {} \\right.$$ &gt; $$\\left| {} \\right.$$$$\\Delta $$U$$\\left| {} \\right.$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "$$\\left| {} \\right.$$$$\\Delta $$H$$\\left| {} \\right.$$ &gt; $$\\left| {} \\right.$$$$\\Delta $$U$$\\left| {} \\right.$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "05Qs43IOtj8tZgN5ztCTj",
    "question": "The enthalpy change on freezing of 1 mol of water at 5<sup>o</sup>C to ice at −5<sup>o</sup>C is :\n<br/><br/>(Given $$\\Delta $$<sub>fus</sub>H = 6 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup> at 0<sup>o</sup>C, \n<br/>C<sub>p</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O, $$\\ell $$ = 75.3J mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup> K<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)\n<br/>C<sub>p</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O s) =36.8 J mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup> K<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "5.44 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "5.81 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "6.56 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "6.00 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "6.56 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "9z1xsGvNOMCeubLi",
    "question": "Given, $${C_{(graphite)}} + {O_2} \\to C{O_2}(g)$$;<br/><br>\n$${\\Delta _r}{H^o}$$ = - 393.5 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup><br/><br>\n$${{\\rm H}_2}(g)$$ + $${1 \\over 2}{O_2}(g)$$$$\\to {{\\rm H}_2}{\\rm O}(l)$$<br/><br>\n$${\\Delta _r}{H^o}$$ = - 285.8 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup><br/><br>\n$$C{O_2}(g)$$ + $$2{{\\rm H}_2}{\\rm O}(l) \\to$$  $$C{H_4}(g)$$ + $$2{O_2}(g)$$<br/><br>\n$${\\Delta _r}{H^o}$$ = + 890.3 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup><br/><br>\nBased on the above thermochemical equations, the value of $${\\Delta _r}{H^o}$$  at 298 K for the reaction<br/><br/>\n$${C_{(graphite)}}$$ + $$2{{\\rm H}_2}(g) \\to$$ $$C{H_4}(g)$$ will be :</br></br></br></br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "+144.0 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "– 74.8 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "-144.0 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "+ 74.8 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "– 74.8 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Xt4C2Fl0OwalJsTp",
    "question": "The combustion of benzene(l) gives CO<sub>2</sub>(g) and H<sub>2</sub>O(l). Given that heat of combustion of benzene at constant volume is –3263.9 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup> at 25<sup>o</sup>C; heat of combustion (in kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>) of benzene at constant pressure will be :<br/>\n(R = 8.314 JK<sup>–1</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "–3267.6",
      "4152.6",
      "–452.46",
      "3260"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "–3267.6"
  },
  {
    "id": "4IHDNNQSZPLQjgvdk7u1S",
    "question": "For which of the following reactions, $$\\Delta $$H is equal to $$\\Delta $$U?",
    "options": [
      "N<sub>2</sub>(g) + 3H<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 2NH<sub>3</sub>(g)",
      "2HI(g) $$ \\to $$ H<sub>2</sub>(g) + I<sub>2</sub>(g)",
      "2NO<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>(g)",
      "2SO<sub>2</sub>(g) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ 2SO<sub>3</sub>(g)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "2HI(g) $$ \\to $$ H<sub>2</sub>(g) + I<sub>2</sub>(g)"
  },
  {
    "id": "6orHD6VOmxopDeO891jVu",
    "question": "Given \n<br/><br/>(i)  C (graphite) + O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ CO<sub>2</sub>(g); $$\\Delta $$rH$$^\\Theta $$ = x kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>\n<br/><br/>(ii)  C(graphite) + $${1 \\over 2}$$O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ CO(g); $$\\Delta $$rH$$^\\Theta $$ = y kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>\n<br/><br/>(iii)  CO(g) + $${1 \\over 2}$$ O<sub>2</sub>(g) $$ \\to $$ CO<sub>2</sub>(g);  $$\\Delta $$rH$$^\\Theta $$ = z kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>\n<br/><br/>Based on the above thermochemical equations, find out which one of the following algebraic relationships is correct?",
    "options": [
      "z = x + y ",
      "x = y + z ",
      "x = y – z ",
      "y = 2z – x"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "x = y + z "
  },
  {
    "id": "uNXhBdsR5e8WMjmcMen8X",
    "question": "For silver, C<sub>p</sub>(J K<sup>–1</sup> mol<sup>–1</sup>) = 23 +0.01 T. If the temperature (T) of 3 moles of silver is raised from 300\nK to 1000 K at 1 atm pressure, the value of $$\\Delta H$$ will be close to :",
    "options": [
      "62 KJ",
      "16 KJ",
      "13 KJ",
      "21 KJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "62 KJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "rXXFZN7gz7QMbQrDjk3rsa0w2w9jx0xcvqr",
    "question": "The difference between $$\\Delta $$H and $$\\Delta $$U ($$\\Delta $$H – $$\\Delta $$U), when the combustion of one mole of heptane(l) is carried\nout at a temperature T, is equal to :",
    "options": [
      "– 4 RT",
      "3 RT",
      "– 3 RT",
      "4 RT"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "– 4 RT"
  },
  {
    "id": "58s60SB4MZNQOIUzzy3rsa0w2w9jx4z5p33",
    "question": "Enthalpy of sublimation of iodine is 24 cal g<sup>–1\n</sup> at 200 <sup>o</sup>C. If specific heat of I<sub>2</sub>(s) and l<sub>2</sub> (vap) are 0.055 and\n0.031 cal g<sup>–1</sup>K\n<sup>–1</sup>\nrespectively, then enthalpy of sublimation of iodine at 250 <sup>o</sup>C in cal g<sup>–1</sup>\n is :",
    "options": [
      "2.85",
      "22.8",
      "11.4",
      "5.7"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "22.8"
  },
  {
    "id": "uUBameTGHZjPdkQgNjjgy2xukfp1w2mk",
    "question": "Lattice enthalpy and enthalpy of solution of NaCl are 788 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>, and 4 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>, respectively.\n<br/>The hydration enthalpy of NaCl is :",
    "options": [
      "–780 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "–784 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "780 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>",
      "784 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "–784 kJ mol<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "eXcTwCrf4G9XSwsCSmjgy2xukfc82l0k",
    "question": "The process that is NOT endothermic in nature\nis :",
    "options": [
      "Ar(g) + e<sup>-</sup> $$ \\to $$ Ar<sup>-</sup>(g)",
      "H(g) + e<sup>-</sup> $$ \\to $$ H<sup>-</sup>(g)",
      "Na(g) $$ \\to $$ Na<sup>+</sup>(g) + e<sup>-</sup>",
      "O<sup>-</sup>(g) + e<sup>-</sup> $$ \\to $$ O<sup>2-</sup>(g)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "H(g) + e<sup>-</sup> $$ \\to $$ H<sup>-</sup>(g)"
  },
  {
    "id": "fEIDA08mB1iW9zxyLf7k9k2k5icl3zo",
    "question": "If enthalpy of atomisation for Br<sub>2(1)</sub> is x kJ/mol\nand bond enthalpy for Br<sub>2</sub> is y kJ/mol, the\nrelation between them :",
    "options": [
      "does not exist",
      "is x &lt; y",
      "is x &gt; y",
      "is x = y"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "is x &gt; y"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59qhjvo",
    "question": "<p>At 25$$^\\circ$$C and 1 atm pressure, the enthalpy of combustion of benzene (I) and acetylene (g) are $$-$$ 3268 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup> and $$-$$1300 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, respectively. The change in enthalpy for the reaction 3 C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>2</sub>(g) $$\\to$$ C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>6</sub> (I), is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "+324 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "+632 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "$$-$$ 632 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "$$-$$ 732 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "$$-$$ 632 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bd221s",
    "question": "<p>At 25$$^\\circ$$C and 1 atm pressure, the enthalpies of combustion are as given below :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 527px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 171px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 115px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 112px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 129px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">Substance</th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">$${H_2}$$</th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">C (graphite)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">$${C_2}{H_6}(g)$$</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$${{{\\Delta _c}{H^\\Theta }} \\over {kJ\\,mo{l^{ - 1}}}}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$ - 286.0$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$ - 394.0$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">$$ - 1560.0$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>The enthalpy of formation of ethane is</p>",
    "options": [
      "+54.0 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "$$-$$68.0 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "$$-$$86.0 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "+97.0 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "$$-$$86.0 kJ mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgygw4e4",
    "question": "<p>Given</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 683px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 43px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 327px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 104px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 209px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\">(A)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{2CO(g)+O_2(g)\\to 2CO_2(g)}$$</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{\\Delta H_1^0=-x~kJ~mol^{-1}}$$</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{C(graphite)+O_2(g)\\to CO_2(g)}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\"></td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{\\Delta H_2^0=-y~kJ~mol^{-1}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{\\Delta H^0}$$ for the reaction</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{C(graphite)+\\frac{1}{2}O_2(g)\\to CO(g)}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{x-2y}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{x+2y}{2}$$",
      "$$2y-x$$",
      "$$\\frac{2x-y}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{x-2y}{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v4hc8",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R)</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : Enthalpy of neutralisation of strong monobasic acid with strong monoacidic base is always $$-57 \\mathrm{~kJ} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Enthalpy of neutralisation is the amount of heat liberated when one mole of $$\\mathrm{H}^{+}$$ ions furnished by acid combine with one mole of $${ }^{-} \\mathrm{OH}$$ ions furnished by base to form one mole of water.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "reactions-related-to-enthalpies-and-hess's-law",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "NrUdplY76GSyd3Yg",
    "question": "Identify the correct statement regarding a spontaneous process :",
    "options": [
      "For a spontaneous process in an isolated system, the change in entropy is positive",
      "Endothermic processes are never spontaneous",
      "Exothermic processes are always spontaneous ",
      "Lowering of energy in the reaction process is the only criterion for spontaneity "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "second-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "For a spontaneous process in an isolated system, the change in entropy is positive"
  },
  {
    "id": "71VojfDQdmqJuDEV9LITB",
    "question": "The entropy change associated with the conversion of 1 kg of ice at 273 K to water vapours at 383 K is : \n<br/><br/>(Specific heat of water liquid and water vapour are 4.2 kJ K<sup>$$-$$1</sup> kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup> and 2.0 kJ K<sup>$$-$$1</sup> kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup>; heat of liquid fusion and vapourisation of water are 334 kJ<sup>$$-$$1</sup> and 2491 kJ kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, respectively). (log 273 = 2.436, log 373 = 2.572, log 383 = 2.583)",
    "options": [
      "7.90 kJ kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup>  K<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "2.64 kJ kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup>  K<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "8.49 kJ kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup>  K<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "9.26 kJ kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup>  K<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "second-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "9.26 kJ kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup>  K<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "FHaRGtPUM79cCTPFIEGf5",
    "question": "The process with negative entropy change is :",
    "options": [
      "Dissociation of CaSO<sub>4</sub> (s) to CaO(s) and SO<sub>3</sub>(g) ",
      "Dissolution of iodine in water",
      "Synthesis of ammonia from N<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>",
      "Sublimation of dry ice "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "second-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "Synthesis of ammonia from N<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "J3nQebb8KPSS3bvn4VTDj",
    "question": "Two blocks of the same metal having same mass and at temperature T<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>2</sub>, respectively, are brought in contact with each other and allowed to attain thermal equilibrium at constant pressure. The change in entropy, $$\\Delta $$S, for this process is : ",
    "options": [
      "2C<sub>p</sub> In $$\\left[ {{{{{\\left( {{T_1} + {T_2}} \\right)}^{{1 \\over 2}}}} \\over {{T_1}{T_2}}}} \\right]$$",
      "2C<sub>p</sub> In $$\\left[ {{{\\left( {{T_1} + {T_2}} \\right)} \\over {2{T_1}{T_2}}}} \\right]$$",
      "C<sub>p</sub> In $$\\left[ {{{{{\\left( {{T_1} + {T_2}} \\right)}^2}} \\over {4{T_1}{T_2}}}} \\right]$$",
      "2C<sub>p</sub> In $$\\left[ {{{\\left( {{T_1} + {T_2}} \\right)} \\over {4{T_1}{T_2}}}} \\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "second-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "C<sub>p</sub> In $$\\left[ {{{{{\\left( {{T_1} + {T_2}} \\right)}^2}} \\over {4{T_1}{T_2}}}} \\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "d3f4lJ3VjKthAZZtmx7k9k2k5llm4zr",
    "question": "The true statement amongst the following is :",
    "options": [
      "S is a function of temperature but $$\\Delta $$S is not\na function of temperature.",
      "Both S and $$\\Delta $$S are not functions of\ntemperature.",
      "Both $$\\Delta $$S and S are functions of temperature.",
      "S is not a function of temperature but $$\\Delta $$S is\na function of temperature."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "thermodynamics",
    "topic": "second-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "Both $$\\Delta $$S and S are functions of temperature."
  }
]